<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051155</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ankle-brachial index to detect peripheral arterial disease: concordance and validation study between Doppler and an oscillometric device</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To evaluate the sensitivity and specificity of ankle-brachial index (ABI) determined by oscillometry, using a Doppler ultrasound probe as a gold standard. We also aimed to evaluate the agreement between both methods. Patients and method: Right and left ABI measurements (ABIr,ABIl) with oscillometric (OMRON-705-CP) and Doppler (DIADOP-50) devices in hypertensive patients without peripheral arterial disease. Results: One hundred patients, 61 women, 66.4 (SD 10.9) year-old, smokers 16%, diabetics 38%. Oscillometric and doppler ABI could be calculated in 83% and 93% of patients, respectively. Oscillometric ABIr and ABIl measurements were &lt; 0.9 in 9.6% (CI 95%, 4.2-18.1) and 8.4% (CI 95%, 3.4-16.6), respectively, and Doppler measurements were 10.8% (CI 95%, 5.3-18.9) and 15.4% (CI 95%, 8.7-24.5) respectively. The oscillometric ABIr and ABIl sensitivity was 37.5% (CI 95%, 13.7-69.4) and 20.0% (CI 95%, 5.7-51.0) respectively, and the specificity was 93.0% (CI 95%, 84.6-97.8) and 97.1% (CI 95%, 89.9-99.2), respectively. The intraclass correlation (index Doppler/oscillometric device) was 0.64 (CI 95%, 0.44-0.77) for ABIr and 0.62 (CI 95%, 0.41-0.76) for ABIl. Conclusions: About 8.4-15.4% of hypertensive patients attended have an abnormal Doppler ABI measurement. There is not a good concordance between Doppler and oscillometric ABI measurements. This oscillometric device does not seem useful as an ABI screening method</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vinyoles, Ernest</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casermeiro, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jabalera, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado, Cristina de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salido, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Estimar la sensibilidad y la especificidad del índice tobillo-brazo (ITB) determinado oscilométricamente respecto al Doppler y la concordancia entre ambas técnicas. Pacientes y método: Cálculo del ITB derecho (ITBd) e izquierdo (ITBi) mediante oscilometría (OMRON 705-CP) y Doppler (DIADOP-50) en pacientes hipertensos sin arteriopatía periférica. Resultados: Se incluyó a 100 pacientes hipertensos, 61 mujeres, con una media (DE) de edad de 66,4 (10,9) años. Un 16% eran fumadores y un 38%, diabéticos. Fue posible calcular el ITB en el 83 y el 93% de los pacientes mediante oscilometría y Doppler, respectivamente. Los ITBd e ITBi calculados oscilométricamente eran &lt; 0,9 en el 9,6% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 4,2-18,1) y el 8,4% (IC del 95%, 3,4-16,6), respectivamente, y mediante Doppler en el 10,8% (IC del 95%, 5,3-18,9) y el 15,4% (IC del 95%, 8,7-24,5), respectivamente. Las sensibilidades del ITBd y el ITBi determinados oscilométricamente fueron del 37,5% (IC del 95%, 13,7-69,4) y el 20,0% (IC del 95%, 5,7-51,0) respectivamente, y las especificidades, del 93,0% (IC del 95%, 84,6-97,8) y el 97,1% (IC del 95%, 89,9-99,2), respectivamente. El índice de correlación intraclase Doppler/oscilometría para ITBd e ITBi fue 0,64 (IC del 95%, 0,44-0,77) y 0,62 (IC del 95%, 0,41-0,76), respectivamente. Conclusiones: Entre el 8,4 y el 15,4% de los pacientes hipertensos presentan ITB patológico según Doppler, el cual no tiene buena concordancia con la oscilometría. El equipo oscilométrico evaluado no parece útil para el cribado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(3): 92-94, ene. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Índice tobillo-brazo en la detección de arteriopatía periférica: estudio de validez y concordancia entre Doppler y método oscilométrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14864</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10168^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
