<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113695</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors associated to dysfunctions of an arteriovenous fistula in patients with chronic renal disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Renal disease has become a chronic disease of high prevalence in industrialized countries. A form of renal replacement therapy is hemodialysis, which is essential to have a vascular access. As vascular access of choice preferable to central venous catheter is arteriovenous fistula for showing fewer complications. However, it is not without risks and problems as related to vascular access are the leading cause of morbidity and hospitalization, we intended to study the risk factors that influencing arteriovenous fistulas dysfunction. Methods This is a case-control design in which we compared the group with some fistula dysfunction, either autologous or prosthetic, with which presented no dysfunction to analyze the differences between both. The variables were grouped into three sections defined to organize the results and stratified by gender, age and having suffered or not fistula dysfunction. Results Age and gender do not influence fistula dysfunction but has more influence dyslipidemia, having started hemodialysis, type of fistula and have carried central venous catheter. Discussion Unlike studies published, in our population did not find fistula dysfunction differences in age and gender. However, it is seen that there is less risk of dysfunction in patients with dyslipidemia, wherein the fistula is autologous and the hemodialysis have not started or have done on a scheduled start and, therefore, they have not carried central venous catheters(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez González, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad renal se ha convertido en una patología crónica de gran prevalencia en los países industrializados. Una modalidad de tratamiento sustitutivo renal es la hemodiálisis, para la cual es imprescindible tener un acceso vascular. Como acceso vascular de elección preferible al catéter venoso central, está la fístula arteriovenosa por haber demostrado menos complicaciones. Sin embargo, no está exenta de riesgos y dado que los problemas relacionados con el acceso vascular constituyen la primera causa de morbilidad y hospitalización, se pretendió estudiar aquellos factores de riesgo que influyen en la disfunción de las fístulas arteriovenosas. Material y métodos: Se trata de un diseño de caso-control en el que se comparó el grupo que presentó alguna disfunción de su fístula, ya fuera autóloga o protésica, con el que no presentó ninguna disfunción para analizar las diferencias entre ambos. Las variables se agruparon en tres apartados definidos para organizar los resultados y se estratificó por sexo, edad y por haber padecido o no disfunción de la fístula. Resultados: La edad y el sexo no influyen en padecer disfunción de la fístula sino que tiene más influencia la dislipemia, el haber comenzado tratamiento con hemodiálisis, el tipo de fístula y el haber portado catéter venoso central. Discusión: A diferencia de estudios publicados, en nuestra población no se han encontrado diferencias de disfunción de fístula en cuanto a edad y sexo. Sin embargo, se ha visto que hay menos riesgo de disfunción en aquellos pacientes con dislipemia, en los que su fístula es autóloga y en los que no han iniciado hemodiálisis o lo han hecho de manera programada y, por tanto, no han portado catéteres venosos centrales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;16(2): 104-114, abr.-jun.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113695</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo asociados a la disfunción de una fístula arteriovenosa en pacientescon enfermedad renal crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
