<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164364</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When and which employees feel obliged: a personality perspective of how organizational identification develops</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper examines the indirect effect of interpersonal and informational justice on organizational identification through psychological contract fulfillment across different levels of equity sensitivity. The data were collected using self-reported measures from 656 permanent employees working in five commercial banks in Pakistan. The statistical results of the study confirmed that the indirect effect of interpersonal and informational justice on organizational identification through psychological contract fulfillment is significant. However, the statistical results of the study also demonstrated that the indirect effect of interpersonal and informational justice does not differ across different levels of equity sensitivity. This study offers some implications for managers to maintain an effective employment relationship with the employees inside the organizations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arain, Ghulam Ali</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asadullah, Muhammad Ali</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Imran, Hameed</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akram, Ammara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo analiza el efecto indirecto de la justicia interpersonal e informativa en la identificación con la organización a través del cumplimiento del contrato psicológico en los diferentes niveles de sensibilidad a la equidad. Por medio de medidas de autoinforme se recogieron datos de 656 empleados fijos de cinco bancos comerciales de Paquistán. Los resultados estadísticos del estudio confirman que es significativo el efecto indirecto de la justicia interpersonal e informativa en la identificación con la organización a través del cumplimiento del contrato psicológico. No obstante, dichos resultados demuestran también que el efecto indirecto de la justicia interpersonal e informativa no es distinto en los distintos niveles de sensibilidad a la equidad. El estudio propone algunas implicaciones para que los directivos mantengan una relación eficaz de empleo con los empleados en el seno de las organizaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);33(2): 125-135, ago. 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuándo están agradecidos los empleados y a qué aspectos: el desarrollo de la identificación con la organización desde la perspectiva de la personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35647</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3303^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3303^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
