<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127336</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genital-urinary rhabdomyosarcoma in childhood: our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Rhabdomyosarcoma (RSM) becomes the most common tumour of the soft tissues during the paediatric age. It represents among 2-3% of child tumours. The genital-urinary location is the second most common location, only after head and neck. The treatment is usually medical, being the surgery a mere contribution, except for the cases in which the situation is not under control, when very aggressive surgery is necessary. The aim of this study is to analyse the cases of genial-urinary RMS that have been treated in our centre and the role that surgery has in their treatment. Material and methods. Retrospective study of 20 patient (7 girls and 13 boys) with a median age of 24 months (range from 1 month to 12 years) with RMS in the aurochs-genial tract who have been treated in our hospital from 1990 to 2012. The variables described are demographic, location of the primary tumour, state at diagnosis, received treatment, both medical and surgical, with greater emphasis on the kind of surgery applied and monitoring in terms of survival. Results. The location of the primary tumour was: bladder (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Vázquez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Zegarra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Herrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fraile, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aransay Bramtot, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tordable Ojeda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezalí Barbanco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morante Valverde, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El rabdomiosarcoma (RMS) constituye el tumor de tejidos blandos más frecuente en la edad pediátrica, representando el 2-3% de los tumores infantiles. La localización genitourinaria es la segunda en frecuencia tras la cabeza y cuello. El tratamiento suele ser médico, quedando la cirugía como coadyuvante, excepto en casos no controlados en que se precisan cirugías muy agresivas. El objetivo del estudio es analizar los casos de RMS de localización genitourinaria tratados en nuestro Centro y el papel que la cirugía tiene en su tratamiento. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 20 pacientes (7 niñas y 13 niños) con una mediana de edad de 24 meses (rango de 1 mes a 12 años) con RMS del tracto urogenital tratados en nuestro Hospital desde 1990 hasta 2012. Se describen variables demográficas, localización del tumor primario, estadio al diagnóstico, tratamiento recibido, tanto (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;27(2): 53-56, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rabdomiosarcoma genitourinario en la infancia,  nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29574^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12619^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
