<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83216</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the use of medication for diabetic patients in the province of Pontevedra</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: a) To determine the demographic features and profile of use ofmedicines by the population who takes hypoglycemic agents in the provinceof Pontevedra, and b) to analyze any differences in the use of these drugs accordingto age, sex and residence (interior or coast). A retrospective descriptivestudy of consumption of hypoglycemic agents in community pharmaciesfrom Pontevedra during 2007. Analysed variables: The daily dose per thousandin habitants and the number of prescriptions per patients. Results:41,202 patients (4.35% of total population, to over 20% for aged 80):51.67% were women. More consumed hypoglycemic groups were: amonginsulins, the premixed insulins: 40.36%, and among the oral hypoglycaemicagents: biguanides 51.61% and sulfonylureas 29.52%. Glibenclamide wasused to a greater extent by pensioners than by nonpensioners (17.88 vs13.88%; p= 0.07). The use of hypoglycemic agents, angiotensin-convertingenzymeinhibitors/angiotensin II receptor antagonists, antiagreggants and statinsare not consistent with the recommendations of current treatment guidelines.Among women, the consumption of anxiolytics and antidepressants wasstatistically significant. Hypoglycemic drugs consumption per patient is higheramong residents on the coast(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fornos Pérez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cordeiro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Añón, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Iglesias, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Rodríguez, N. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: a) Determinar las características demográfi cas y el perfi l de utilizaciónde los medicamentos de la población usuaria de hipoglucemiantes en la provincia dePontevedra, y b) analizar las eventuales diferencias en la utilización de esos medicamentosen función de la edad, el sexo y la residencia de los pacientes (interior ocosta). Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de consumo (dispensación) de hipoglucemiantesen las ofi cinas de farmacia de la provincia de Pontevedra durante 2007.Variables analizadas: Dosis diaria por 1.000 habitantes y número de recetas porpaciente. Resultados: Se estudió a un total de 41.202 pacientes (un 4,35% de lapoblación total, que llega al 20% a partir de 80 años); un 51,67% eran mujeres.Los grupos de hipoglucemiantes más consumidos fueron, entre las insulinas, lasmixtas (40,36%), y entre los hipoglucemiantes orales las biguanidas (51,61%) y lassulfonilureas (29,52%). La glibenclamida la utilizan en mayor medida los pensionistasque los no pensionistas (el 17,88 frente al 13,88%; p= 0,07). La utilización dehipoglucemiantes, inhibidores de la enzima conversora de la angiotensina/antagonistasdel receptor de la angiotensina II, antiagregantes y estatinas no se ajusta a lasrecomendaciones de las guías terapéuticas actuales. El mayor consumo de ansiolíticosy antidepresivos en las mujeres es estadísticamente signifi cativo. El consumode hipoglucemiantes por paciente es mayor entre los residentes en la costa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(1): 47-52, ene.-feb. 2010. graf, ^gtab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83216</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la utilización de medicamentos por pacientes diabéticos en la provincia de Pontevedra</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
