<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115686</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethics and prevention of medicalization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Society has shifted issues of subjective and social reality of the population into the medical field, with the obsession with perfect health becoming a predominant pathogenic factor in the increase in the number of diseases and patients, while the level of health in the population is improving. The power of medicine has made the idea of «medicalising» various aspects of life that can be perceived as medical problems as attractive even when it is not the case. Living entails times of unhappiness and anguish but, should we treat these episodes? We are in the health culture of «everything, here and now». In this article, the ethical implications of unnecessary interventions are analysed, along with the different alternatives that the professionals involved may perform to redirect this situation. It is reflected if we want a world where we all risk wearing labels for this or that disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tovar-Bobo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozadilla-Arias, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerecedo-Pérez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sociedad ha desplazado al campo médico problemas de la realidad subjetiva y social de las personas, y la obsesión por una salud perfecta se ha convertido en un factor patógeno predominante existiendo un aumento del número de enfermedades y enfermos, a la vez que mejora el nivel de salud de la población. El poder de la medicina ha hecho atractiva la idea de «medicalizar» aspectos de la vida que se pueden percibir como problemas médicos aun sin serlo. Vivir conlleva momentos de infelicidad y de angustia, pero ¿deberíamos tratar dichos momentos? Estamos en la cultura sanitaria del «todo, aquí y ahora». En este artículo se analizan las implicaciones éticas de las intervenciones innecesarias y se plantean distintas alternativas que pueden realizar los profesionales implicados para reconducir dicha situación; reflexionamos si queremos un mundo donde todos llevemos etiquetas de riesgo de presentar esta o aquella enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(7): 376-381, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ética y prevención de la medicalización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55124^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55124^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55124^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55124^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
