<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116297</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical stages of patients with Alzheimer disease treated in specialist clinics in Spain. The EACE study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The diagnostic paradigm of Alzheimer disease (AD) is changing; there is a trend toward diagnosing the disease in its early stages, even before the complete syndrome of dementia is apparent. The clinical stage at which AD is usually diagnosed in our area is unknown. Therefore, the purpose of this study is to describe the clinical stages of AD patients at time of diagnosis. Methods: Multicentre, observational and cross-sectional study. Patients with probable AD according to NINCDS-ARDRA criteria, attended in specialist clinics in Spain, were included in the study. We recorded the symptom onset to evaluation and symptom onset to diagnosis intervals and clinical status of AD (based on MMSE, NPI questionnaire, and CDR scale). Results: Participants in this study included 437 specialists representing all of Spain&#146;s autonomous communities and a total of 1,707 patients, of whom 1,694 were included in the analysis. Mean MMSE score was 17.6±4.8 (95% CI: 17.4-17.9). Moderate cognitive impairment (MMSE between 10 and 20) was detected in 64% of the patients, and severe cognitive impairment (MMSE&lt;10) in 6%. The mean interval between symptom onset and the initial primary care visit was 10.9±17.2 months (95% CI: 9.9-11.8), and the interval between symptom onset and diagnosis with AD was 28.4±21.3 months. Conclusions: Results from the EACE show that most AD patients in our are area have reached a moderate clinical stage by the time they are evaluated in a specialist clinic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alom Poveda, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Adalid Guerreiro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Estamos asistiendo a un cambio en el paradigma del diagnóstico de la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA), de modo que tiende a realizarse en fases más precoces de la evolución, incluso antes de la aparición del síndrome completo de demencia. En nuestro entorno no se conoce en qué situación clínica se está realizando el diagnóstico de la EA. Por ese motivo, se ha llevado a cabo este estudio, para describir el estadio evolutivo de los pacientes con EA en el momento del diagnóstico. Métodos: Estudio multicéntrico, observacional y transversal. Se incluyeron pacientes que cumplían criterios NINCDS-ARDRA de EA probable, atendidos en consultas de Atención Especializada en España. Se recogieron los datos sobre los tiempos asistenciales y de evolución de la EA según el MMSE, el cuestionario NPI y la escala CDR. Resultados: Participaron 437 especialistas de todas las Comunidades Autónomas, que incluyeron un total de 1.707 pacientes, de los cuales 1.694 fueron incluidos en el análisis. La puntuación media del MMSE fue de 17,6±4,8 (IC 95%: 17,4-17,9). El 64% de los pacientes presentaban deterioro cognitivo moderado (MMSE entre 10 y 20) y el 6% grave (MMSE &lt; 10). El tiempo medio desde los primeros síntomas hasta la primera consulta a Atención Primaria fue de 10,9±17,2 meses (IC 95%: 9,9-11,8), y hasta el diagnóstico de la EA fue de 28,4±21,3 meses. Conclusiones: Los resultados del EACE ponen de manifiesto que en nuestro entorno la mayor parte de los pacientes con EA acuden a Atención especializada en un estado evolutivo moderado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(8): 477-487, oct. 2013. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estadio evolutivo de los pacientes con enfermedad de Alzheimer que acuden a la consulta especializada en España. Estudio EACE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
