<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159427</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive value of cerebellar growth and general movements assessments for neurodevelopment of very preterm infants at 18-24 months&#146; corrected age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Fidgety movements assessments is very sensitive predicting long-term outcome or cerebral palsy of preterm, disrupted cerebellar growth has been reported in these patients. Aim. To compare the predictive value of cerebellar ultrasound growth and fidgety movements assessments, for neurodevelopment outcome of very preterm at 18-24 month&#146;s corrected age (CA). Subjects and methods. Prospective study of 88 infants cohort (&amp;#8804; 32 weeks&#146; gestation), transverse cerebellar diameter was obtained by ultrasound via mastoid fontanel, in a weekly basis, until 40 weeks CA. Fidgety movements were assessed at 3 months CA. Neurodevelopment outcome at 18-24 month&#146;s CA was evaluated in 68 using Schedule of Growing Skills II Scale (SGS-II) and Amiel-Tison Neurologic Assessment (ATNA). Results. At term age, cerebellar growth was under 3rd percentile in 11 (10.3%). Fidgety movements were normal in 42 (61.8%) and abnormal or absent in 7 (10.3%). At 18-24 months CA, 54 (79.4%) were normal by the SGS-II and in 6 (8.8%) ATNA classified as cerebral palsy. Cerebellar diameter under 3rd percentile at term was associated with abnormal motor outcome and normal fidgety movements correlated with normal neurodevelopment. Conclusion. Ultrasound cerebellar measurements and functional examinations (fidgety movements) have important complementary roles in predicting neurodevelopment of very preterm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Correa, Flávia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueiredo, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso, Rosalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cunha, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreiro, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadete, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valério, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La evaluación de los movimientos de ajetreo es sumamente sensible a la hora de predecir el desenlace a largo plazo o la parálisis cerebral del neonato prematuro, un tipo de paciente en el que se ha descrito el crecimiento anómalo del cerebelo. Objetivo. Comparar el valor pronóstico de la determinación ecográfica del crecimiento anómalo del cerebelo y el de la evaluación de los movimientos de ajetreo en el neurodesarrollo de grandes prematuros a los 18-24 meses de edad corregida. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio prospectivo con una cohorte de 88 neonatos (32 semanas o menos de gestación) en que se analizó el diámetro transversal del cerebelo por medio de una ecografía semanal hasta las 40 semanas de edad corregida. Los movimientos de ajetreo se evaluaron a los tres meses de edad corregida. El estado de maduración neurológica a los 18-24 meses de edad corregida se evaluó en 68 neonatos con la escala de evaluación de las competencias en el desarrollo infantil (SGS-II) y la escala de evaluación neurológica de Amiel-Tison (ATNA). Resultados. En la edad a término, el crecimiento del cerebelo fue inferior al tercer percentil en 11 neonatos (10,3%). Los movimientos de ajetreo eran normales en 42 (61,8%), y anormales o ausentes, en 7 (10,3%). A los 18-24 meses de edad corregida, 54 (79,4%) mostraron resultados normales en la SGS-II y 6 (8,8%) fueron calificados como afectados por parálisis cerebral según la ATNA. El diámetro cerebelar inferior al tercer percentil a término estuvo asociado con un desenlace motor anómalo y los movimientos de ajetreo normales se correlacionaron con el neurodesarrollo normal. Conclusión. La estimación del tamaño del cerebelo y las exploraciones funcionales (movimientos de ajetreo) poseen un importante papel complementario en el pronóstico del desarrollo nervioso en el gran prematuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(2): 63-69, 16 ene., 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159427</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de las evaluaciones del crecimiento cerebelar y de los movimientos generales para el neurodesarrollo del gran prematuro entre los 18 y 24 meses de edad corregida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2568^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
