<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82378</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Image fusion of gated-SPECT and CT angiography in coronary artery disease. Importance of anatomic-functional correlation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 77-year old patient was admitted for acute coronary syndrome without ST elevation. His risk was stratified using the myocardial perfusion gated SPECT, mild inferior ischemia being observed. Thus, medical therapy was optimized and the patient was discharged. He continued with exertional dyspnea so a coronary CT angiography was performed. It revealed severe lesions in the proximal RCA. SPECT-CT fusion images correlated the myocardial perfusion defect with a posterior descending artery from the RCA, in a co-dominant coronary area. Subsequently, cardiac catheterism was indicated for his treatment. The current use of image fusion studies is limited to patients in whom it is difficult to attribute a perfusion defect to a specific coronary artery. In our patient, the fusion images helped to distinguish between the RCA and the circumflex artery as the culprit artery of ischemia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nazarena Pizzi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Candell Riera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguadé Bruix, s</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuéllar Calabria, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliaga, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente de 77 años de edad ingresado por un síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST. Se estratificó su riesgo mediante gated-SPECT de perfusión miocárdica, evidenciándose una ligera isquemia inferior, por lo cual se optimizó el tratamiento médico y recibió el alta hospitalaria. El paciente continuó con disnea de esfuerzo, y se le realizó una angiotomografía computarizada coronaria que mostró lesiones intensas en la arteria coronaria derecha (CD) proximal. La fusión SPECT-tomografía computarizada correlacionó el defecto de perfusión miocárdica con la arteria descendente posterior proveniente de la arteria CD en un territorio de irrigación codominante. Posteriormente se indicó un cateterismo cardiaco para su tratamiento. El uso actual de los estudios de fusión de imágenes se limita a pacientes en los cuales es difícil la asignación de un defecto de perfusión a una determinada arteria coronaria. En nuestro paciente, las imágenes de fusión contribuyeron a discernir la arteria responsable del territorio isquémico entre la arteria CD y la arteria circunfleja(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;29(6): 299-303, nov.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82378</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fusión de imágenes de gated-SPECT y angiotomografía computarizada en la enfermedad coronaria. Importancia de la correlación anatomicofuncional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
