<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167520</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bariatric surgery has become the most efficient technique in the treatment of morbid obesity. The goal of this study was to analyze the differences between a bariatric surgery candidates group and a control sample in the variables attachment, rumination, and referential thinking. The design of this study is ex post facto prospective. From the 285 subjects who participated in the study, 162 were bariatric surgery candidates. The other 123 participants were individuals from the general population selected by convenience. For data collection was used the Cuestionario de Apego Adulto (Adult Attachment Questionnaire), the Escala de Pensamiento Referencial (Referential Thinking Scale) and the Escala de Respuestas Rumiativas (Ruminative Responses Scale). We conclude there is a larger prevalence of concerned attachment in the group of candidates not suitable for bariatric surgery, as well as a greater presence of both referential and ruminative thinking in the same group comparing to the other two groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez Hernández, Mª del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Testal, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado Siles, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Budía, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borda Mas, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía bariátrica se ha erigido como la técnica más potente en el tratamiento de la obesidad mórbida. El objetivo de este estudio era estudiar las diferencias existentes entre un grupo de candidatos a cirugía bariátrica y una muestra control en las variables apego, pensamiento rumiativo y referencial. El diseño del estudio es ex post facto prospectivo. De los 285 sujetos que participaron en el estudio, 162 eran pacientes candidatos a cirugía bariátrica. Los 123 participantes restantes eran individuos de la población general seleccionados por conveniencia. Se emplearon: Cuestionario de Apego Adulto, Escala de Pensamiento Referencial y Escala de Respuestas Rumiativas. A partir de los resultados del estudio, se concluye que existe una mayor prevalencia de apego preocupado en el grupo no apto para la cirugía bariátrica, al igual que mayor presencia, tanto de pensamiento referencial como pensamiento rumiativo en ese mismo grupo conforme a los otros dos grupos de comparación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;35(1): 73-79, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apego preocupado, pensamiento rumiativo y pensamiento referencial en candidatos a cirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
