<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141921</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health needs of the elderly woman in the context of primary health care: integrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To identify scientific production on health needs of the elderly woman in the context of primary care and analyze what aspects are addressed as the health needs of the elderly woman in the context of primary care. Method: Integrative review search question: What are the concepts addressed in the literature on the theme health needs of the elderly woman in the context of primary care? The search occurred in LILACS and MEDLINE databases, in March 2014. Inclusion criteria: article in its entirety; Portuguese, English or Spanish and Brazilian reality. Results: The sample of five articles points care needs of women in the reproductive cycle supported in PNAISM perspective. It is noteworthy that the health-disease process is a socially conditioned phenomenon and not just biological. Conclusions: On the importance of moving towards new health care approaches, giving reasons for professional practice focused on comprehensive care to women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tocantins Romijn, Florence</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza da Silva, Luana Christina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cunha Passos, Lidiane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvalho Mendes, Simone</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Identificar producciones científicas sobre necesidades de salud de la mujer mayor en el contexto de la atención primaria y analizar qué aspectos se tratan en cuanto a las necesidades de salud de la mujer de edad avanzada en el contexto de la atención primaria. Método: Revisión integral con la cuestión de la búsqueda: ¿Cuáles son los conceptos tratados en la literatura sobre el tema de las necesidades de salud de la mujer mayor en el contexto de la atención primaria? La búsqueda se produjo en bases de datos LILACS y MEDline, en marzo de 2015. Criterios de inclusión: artículo en su totalidad; portugués, inglés o español y realidad brasileña. Resultados: La muestra de cinco artículos apunta necesidades asistenciales de la mujer en el ciclo reproductivo apoyado en perspectiva PNAISM. Es de destacar que el proceso salud-enfermedad es un fenómeno socialmente condicionado y no sólo biológico. Conclusiones: La importancia de avanzar hacia nuevos enfoques para el cuidado de la salud, explicando los motivos de la práctica profesional centrada en la atención integral a la mujer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;14(40): 375-387, oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades de salud de la mujer mayor en el contexto de la atención primaria de salud: revisión integral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5527^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
