<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101022</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of an integrated programme of Mindfulness and Emotional Intelligence on cognitive strategies of emotional regulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract: A group (n=27) of students took part in an eight week Emotional Intelligence (EI) training course, on the basis of Mayer y Salovey (1997) model of EI, which included Mindfulness training that conformed to the recommendations proposed by Kabat-Zinns´(1990) Stress Reduction Programme. The purpose of this study was to test the effectiveness of an integrated programme. In contrast with the control group (n=22), the experimental group showed decreased levels of anxiety and significant changes in their use of cognitive strategies of emotional regulation using the Cognitive Emotion Regulation (CERQ; Garmefski, Kraaij &amp; Spinhoven, 2001). Un particular, participants demonstrated a decreased tendency to blame themselves and others for life´s difficulties, and an increase in the use of planning strategies and a increase in their capacity to appreciate positive aspects of their life. In addition, participants showed a reduced number of intrusive thoughts concerning personal problems. The inclusion of Mindfulness training within Emotional Intelligence programmes leads to significant improvements over a short period of time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanca, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Natalia S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Sandra M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un grupo de estudiantes (n=27) formaron parte de un entrenamiento en Inteligencia Emocional (IE) de ocho semanas de duración, basado en el modelo propuesto por Mayer y Salovey (1997), que integraba la práctica de Conciencia Plena (Mindfulness) siguiendo las pautas recomendadas en el programa de reducción del estrés de Kabat-Zinn (1990). El propósito de este estudio era comprobar la eficacia de este programa integrado. En comparación mostró un decremento en los niveles de ansiedad y experimentaron cambios significativos en el uso de estrategias cognitivas de regulación emocional usando el Cuestionario de Regulación Emocional Cognitiva (CERQ; Garnefski, Kraaji &amp; Spinhove, 2001). Los participantes de este programa mostraron una menor tendencia a culparse a sí msimos y a otros de sus dificultades y una mayor planificación frente a los problemas cotidianos así como una mayor capacidad de apreciar lo positivo. Por otra parte, estos individuos evidenciaron un menor número de intrusiones relacionadas con sus dificultades cotidianas. Incluir mindfulness en los programas de Inteligencia Emocional conlleva beneficios emocionales a corto plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;15(2/3): 207-216, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de un programa integrado de mindfulness e inteligencia emocional sobre las estrategias cognitivas de regulación emocional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
