<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79462</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measles outbreak in Campo de Gibraltar, Cadiz, Spain, during the period February-July 2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: On the 4th of February 2008, 2 cases of measles,epidemiologically linked (2 members of the crew of the Fast-FerryJaime I from the company Balearia, which performs the route Algeciras- Tangier), were notified to the Epidemiological SurveillanceNetwork in Andalusia (SVEA). The aim of this paper is to epidemiologicallycharacterize this population level outbreak detected inthe area of Campo de Gibraltar, the vaccine effectiveness and thecontrol measures implemented.Methods: Descriptive observational study of reported cases.We have analysed the following variables: age, sex, municipality ofresidence, onset date, virus genotype, groups involved, previousimmunization status, interventions, vaccine effectiveness. Informationsources are SVEA records, vaccination program and individualdigital story (Diraya). Rates 105 were calculated according to agegroup and frequency measurements. To compare vaccine effectiveness,the Chi2 test was used.Results: We confirmed 155 cases of measles, 88.4% by laboratorytechniques. Most affected age groups under 2 years (19%) andfrom 21 to 40 (51%). The 54.2% male. The 72,14% were not vaccinated.Virus was isolated from imported measles genotype D4. Thevaccine efficacy was greater than 99%.Conclusions: The outbreak of the imported measles virus wasconfirmed. More than half of the cases were not vaccinated. Thedecrease in the incidence in vaccinated individuals recommends thenecessity of carrying out Catch-Up campaigns to increase the coveragetherefore avoiding the appearance of these outbreaks(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masa Calles, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Vera, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral Cortes, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Gutiérrez, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Benjumeda, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El 4 de febrero de 2008 se notificó a la Red de VigilanciaEpidemiológica de Andalucía (SVEA), 2 casos de sarampiónvinculados epidemiológicamente, 2 tripulantes del Fast-Ferry Jaime Ide la Compañía Balearia, que realiza la línea de Algeciras - Tánger. Elobjetivo de este trabajo es caracterizar epidemiológicamente el brote deámbito poblacional detectado en la Comarca Campo de Gibraltar, lasmedidas de control implementadas y la efectividad vacunal.Método: Estudio observacional descriptivo de casos notificados.Se analizan las variables edad, sexo, municipio de residencia,sintomatología, fecha de inicio, colectivos implicados, estado vacunalprevio, intervenciones realizadas, genotipo del virus, y efectividadvacunal. Fuentes de información los registros del SVEA, programade vacunas e historia digital individual (Diraya). Se calcularontasas x 105 por grupo de edad y medidas de frecuencia. Para comparaciónde efectividad vacunal se utilizó test Chi2.Resultados: Se confirmaron 155 casos de sarampión, 88.4%por laboratorio. Grupos de edad mas afectados menores de 2 años(19%) y de 21 a 40 (51%). El 54.2% varones. El 72,14% no estabanvacunados. Se aisló virus sarampión Genotipo D4 importado. Laefectividad vacunal era superior al 99%.Conclusiones: Se confirma un brote por virus del sarampiónimportado. Mas de la mitad de los casos no estaban vacunados. Ladisminución de la incidencia en vacunados hace necesario recomendarcampañas de Cacht - Up que aumenten las coberturas para evitarla aparición de estos brotes vacunales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;84(2): 203-214, mar.-abr.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de sarampión en Campo de Gibraltar, Cádiz, durante el período febrero- julio 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23113^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
