<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97560</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Perioperative anaphylaxis may be a life threatening clinical condition and is typically a results of drugs used for anesthesia. After anaphylaxis, allergologic assessment is essential to identify the offending agent and prevent recurrences. The overall incidence is estimated at 1 in 10,000-20,000 anesthetic procedures. The most commonly involved agents are neuromuscular blocking agents, latex and antibiotics. The initial diagnosis is presumptive, including clinical signs. Adrenalin is the treatment of choice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diz Gómez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doniz Campos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bevilacqua Alén, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Bravo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilas Otero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anafilaxia perioperatoria puede ser una un cuadro clínico que amenaza la vida del paciente, producido por los fármacos o sustancias usadas en la anestesia. Después de una anafilaxia, debe realizarse un estudio alergológico para identificar el agente responsable y prevenir recurrencias. La incidencia global es de 1 entre 10.000-20.000 anestesias. Los agentes más frecuentemente implicados son los bloqueantes neuromusculares, látex y antibióticos. El diagnóstico inicial es mediante la clínica. En el tratamiento es esencial la adrenalina(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;21(1): 18-25, ene.-mar. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97560</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anafilaxia perioperatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52246^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33776^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
