<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89842</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and validation of a Spanish version of the Athletic Coping Skills Inventory, ACSI-28</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study involved the translation, cultural adaptation and validation of the Athletic Coping Skills Inventory (ACSI-28) for a Spanish-speaking sport environment. The sample was made up of 1,253 Spanish athletes, 967 males and 286 females. Confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) showed that the 7-factor structure found in the English version was replicated in the Spanish translation in both males and females. Likewise, the reliability coefficients were similar to those of the English version, with values exceeding .80 for the total score. Several of the subscales correlated positively with sports experience and performance level. The Spanish version of the ACSI-28 thus maintains the factor structure of the original and exhibits similar psychometric properties. Consequently, it can reliably be applied to Spanish-speaking athletes for research and evaluation purposes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Smith, Ronald E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graupera Sanz, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Pérez, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Coll, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha realizado la traducción, adaptación cultural y validación del Inventario de Habilidades Deportivas de Afrontamiento (ACSI-28) en el ámbito deportivo de habla hispana. Se ha contado con una muestra de 1.253 deportistas españoles, 967 hombres y 286 mujeres. Se ha comprobado mediante análisis factorial confirmatorio que la estructura de siete factores del test original presenta un buen ajuste en la muestra española, tanto en los hombres como en las mujeres. Los coeficientes de fiabilidad obtenidos fueron semejantes a los de la versión inglesa y superiores a .80 en la escala total del test. Varias de las escalas del test se relacionaron positivamente con la experiencia deportiva y el nivel de rendimiento. En conclusión, la versión española del ACSI-28 mantiene la estructura factorial del original y tiene unas propiedades psicométricas semejantes. Por lo tanto, puede resultar aplicable y útil para la evaluación de los deportistas del ámbito cultural de habla hispana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(3): 495-502, jul.-sept. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89842</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo y validación de la versión española del Inventario de Habilidades Deportivas de Afrontamiento, ACSI-28</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54366^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54366^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
