<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119165</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of infected diabetic foot ulcers clinical effectiveness of a dressing of alginate and hydrocolloid, with silver fiber. Analysis of results of a series of cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: High levels of bacterial load have shown a deleterious influence on wound healing. Using antimicrobial dressings can control ulcers&#146; bioburden. The aim of our study was to evaluate the improving of infected diabetic foot ulcers due an alginate&#146;s fiber and hydrocolloid silver dressing. Material and Methods: We analysed a case series of 6 patients with diabetic foot ulcers without peripheral vascular disease and diagnosed from critical colonization and / or local infection according the presence of inflammation clinical signs. Patients were treated for a minimum period of two weeks. We analysed the percentage reduction in ulcer area from the day of enrolment to antimicrobial dressing removal. Results: The duration of treatment had a median of 5 weeks with a minimum of 2 weeks and up to 6. The median percentage of area reduction of the wounds was 47.7% (range: 0.5%-90%). The mean percentage reduction on the lesion was 58% from 2 weeks and 67.14% at 3 weeks. All patients had reduced significantly their size at 3 weeks from beginning of treatment (p&lt;0.05). Conclusion: The use of an alginate&#146;s fiber and hydrocolloid silver dressing promotes healing on diabetic foot ulcers with local infection, reducing the inflammatory clinical signs significantly over a period of three weeks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Álvarez, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cecilia-Matilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Morales, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvaro-Afonso, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragón-Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro-Martínez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Niveles altos de carga bacteriana han demostrado una influencia negativa en la cicatrización de las úlceras. El uso de apósitos antimicrobianos con plata puede controlar el nivel de carga bacteriana de las heridas. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la respuesta terapéutica de un apósito de fibra de alginato e hidrocoloide, con plata, en úlceras infectadas de pie diabético. Material y métodos. Se analizó una serie de casos de 6 pacientes con úlceras de pie diabético, sin enfermedad vascular periférica y diagnosticadas de colonización crítica y/o infección local mediante la recogida de signos clínicos inflamatorios. Los pacientes fueron tratados durante un período mínimo de 2 semanas. Se analizó el porcentaje de reducción del área de la úlcera desde el día de la inclusión hasta la retirada del apósito antimicrobiano.  Resultados. El tratamiento tuvo una mediana de 5 semanas con una duración mínima de 2 y máxima de 6. La mediana del porcentaje de reducción de la superficie de las heridas fue de 47,7% (rango: 0,5%-90%). La media del porcentaje de reducción de la lesión a las 2 semanas fue del 58% y a la tercera semana del 67,14%. Todos los pacientes habían disminuido sus dimensiones a las 3 semanas de tratamiento de forma significativa (p&lt;0,05). Conclusión. El uso de un apósito de fibra de alginato e hidrocoloide, con plata, favorece la cicatrización de las úlceras de pie diabético con infección local, reduciendo los signos clínicos inflamatorios de forma significativa en un período de 3 semanas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(11): 741-746, nov. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de úlceras infectadas de pie diabético. Efectividad clínica de un apósito de fibra de alginato e hidrocoloide, con plata. Análisis de resultados de una serie de casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d467^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31043^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30097^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15344^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38828^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
