<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115648</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic impact of the resolution of drug related problems in an Emergency Department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Determine the economic impact of avoided cost in hospital stays by preventing drug-related problems. Method: Prospective observational study of six months in the emergency department. We included patients admitted for observation and preadmission beds. A pharmacist was integrated into the healthcare team to validate / reconcile pharmacotherapy. Severity was associated DRPs detected / resolved with the risk increasing the stay of patients admitted to a clinical unit, estimating the potential cost avoided. Results: El 32,5% of patients required intervention and were intercepted 444 drug-related problems, resolving 85.5%. Serious problems serious / significant unresolved affected 130 patients who were admitted, with an estimated avoided cost about 60,000 &#128;. It was noted that serious problems and oral cytostatics, insulin and diabetes were the groups associated with a higher average cost avoided (p &lt;0.05). Conclusion: The integration of the pharmacist in the emergency team to intercept medication problems, reducing the risk of stay and increase healthcare costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pichel-Loureiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ucha-Samartín, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-López de Castro, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Parente, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Payero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar el impacto económico del coste evitado en estancias hospitalarias a través de la prevención de problemas relacionados con los medicamentos. Método: Estudio observacional prospectivo de seis meses en un Servicio de Urgencias. Se incluyeron a pacientes hospitalizados en camas de observación y preingreso. Un farmacéutico se integró en el equipo asistencial para validar/ conciliar la farmacoterapia. Se asoció la gravedad de los PRM detectados/ resueltos con el riesgo incrementar la estancia de los pacientes que ingresaron en una unidad clínica, estimando el coste potencialmente evitado. Resultados: El 32,5% de los pacientes requirieron intervención y se interceptaron 444 problemas relacionados con medicamentos, resolviéndose el 85,5%. Problemas de gravedad seria/ significativa resueltos afectaron a 130 pacientes que ingresaron, estimándose un coste evitado de unos 60.000 &#128;. Se observó que los problemas serios y los citostáticos orales, insulinas y antidiabéticos fueron los grupos asociados a un coste medio evitado mayor (p&lt;0,05). Conclusión: La integración del farmacéutico en el equipo de Urgencias permite interceptar problemas de medicación, reduciéndose el riesgo de incrementar la estancia y los costes sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(1): 59-64, ene.-feb. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto económico de la resolución de problemas relacionados con medicamentos en un servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
