<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045690</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recurrent aseptic meningitis secondary to taking ibuprofen and ketorolac</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Aseptic meningitis is a process that is characterised by an inflammatory reaction of the meninges thatis not due to any infectious agent. Its aetiology is varied and is most frequently caused by rheumatologic and/or autoimmuneprocesses, chemical or medication-induced meningitis, the most notable drugs involved being antibiotics and non-steroidalanti-inflammatory drugs (NSAI). Case report. We report the case of a 70-year-old male, with no relevant history, who wasadmitted to hospital five times over a period of 16 months because of acute meningitis with polymorphonuclear pleocytosis,high protein levels in cerebrospinal fluid and normal glucose in cerebrospinal fluid. No evidence of an infectious causation,chemical meningitis, carcinomatosis or autoimmune disease was found and the patient was diagnosed with recurrent asepticmeningitis. It was found that the patient had taken ibuprofen or ketorolac on several occasions, a few hours before theappearance of symptoms. These episodes were quickly resolved after withdrawal of this medication. Conclusions. A number ofNSAI have been reported as inducers of aseptic meningitis, one of the most notable being ibuprofen. We report the case of apatient who, as a consequence of taking ibuprofen and ketorolac, presented episodes of recurrent aseptic meningitis. To ourknowledge this side effect of ketorolac has not been reported before. Its clinical features are impossible to differentiate fromthose of infectious meningitis. Diagnosis is reached by exclusion and a careful pharmacological study, including over-thecounterdrugs like some of the NSAI, must be performed in patients with this condition, since it is a problem that can easily besolved by withdrawing the drug that causes it</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Vargas-Machuca, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mondéjar-Marín, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Molina, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Muñoz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Robres, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Tejerina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La meningitis aséptica es un proceso quese caracteriza por una reacción inflamatoria meníngea no causadapor ningún agente infeccioso. Su etiología es variada, y la más frecuentees la secundaria a procesos reumatológicos y/o autoinmunes,meningitis química e inducida por fármacos, entre los que destacanlos antibióticos y los antiinflamatorios no esteroideos(AINE). Caso clínico. Varón de 70 años de edad, sin antecedentesrelevantes, que en el período de 16 meses ingresó en cinco ocasionespor meningitis aguda con pleocitosis polimorfonuclear, hiperproteinorraquiay glucosa normal en el líquido cefalorraquídeo, enlas que se descartó una etiología infecciosa, meningitis química,carcinomatosis o enfermedad autoinmune y se le diagnosticó meningitisaséptica recurrente. Se comprobó la toma de ibuprofeno oketorolaco en distintas ocasiones, unas pocas horas antes de laaparición de la clínica. Estos episodios se resolvieron rápidamentetras la retirada de dicha medicación. Conclusiones. Se han implicadovarios AINE como inductores de meningitis aséptica, entre losque destaca el ibuprofeno. Presentamos un paciente que, como consecuenciade la toma de ibuprofeno y ketorolaco, sufrió episodiosde meningitis recurrente aséptica. En nuestro conocimiento no seha comunicado previamente este efecto secundario con el ketorolaco.Su clínica es indistinguible de la meningitis infecciosa; el diagnósticose efectúa por exclusión, y debe realizarse una cuidadosahistoria farmacológica, que incluya fármacos de libre dispensacióncomo algunos AINE, en pacientes con esta patología, puesto que setrata de un problema fácilmente solucionable con la retirada de lamedicación que lo causa</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(4): 217-219, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045690</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningitis recurrente aséptica secundaria a toma de ibuprofeno y ketorolaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34399^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34399^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
