<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038532</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ancient urology in Galicia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Although Urology is a recent branch of medical science and practice, it is not a contradiction to talk about ancient Urology, as a reflection on the ways of getting sick and treating genitourinary diseases in past times, sufferings that are recognized if compared to the present-day ones. This paper takes into account the social view of the history of medicine and tries to reject either the intention to create a mythic past for urology or to underestimate the ancient practices because of irrational or not scientific. Material y Method: Review based on primary and secondary sources, with reference to the medicine and surgery of the urinary tract and genitalia in Galicia (Spain) and the Iberian peninsula, from the ancient and medieval periods, to the appearance of modern, anatomo-clinic medicine in the XVIII th century. Results: Because of the pilgrimage through the Way of Saint James to Santiago de Compostela, many centers of great importance for the attention of sick people rose up in Galicia, like the Monastery of Saint Martin Pinario and the Hospital of the Catholic Kings, where traditional European standars of patient care and use of medicinal plants were followed in. Ancient medicine and surgery of the urinary tract and genitalia had in Galicia, characters of great interest, such as doctor Romano, instructor of Galician practitioners in catheterisation and urethral dilatation, and important thinkers such as the physician- philosopher Francisco Sanchez and the erudite monks Sarmiento and Feijoo, whom, without being doctors, may be considered as pioneers of modern evidenced- based medicine. Comments: The importance that the Galician hospitals had in past times and the works of several characters related to Galician country, had a distinguished place in the ancient history of the medicine and surgery of the urinary tract and genitalia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fariña Pérez, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Aunque la Urología es una rama reciente de la ciencia y práctica médica, no resulta contradictorio hablar de Urología antigua, como una reflexión sobre las formas de enfermar y de tratar en épocas pasadas las enfermedades genitourinarias, padecimientos que son reconocibles al compararlos con las actuales. En este trabajo se tiene presente la visión de la historia de la medicina desde el punto de vista social y se procura dejar a un lado la pretensión de crear un pasado mítico para la urología o de subestimar las prácticas antiguas por irracionales o acientíficas. Material y Método: Revisión basada en fuentes primarias y sobre todo secundarias, referidas a la medicina y cirugía de las vías urinarias y genitales en Galicia y en la península ibérica, durante la época antigua y medieval y hasta la aparición de la medicina anatomo-clínica en el siglo XVIII. Resultado: La peregrinación por el Camino de Santiago hizo surgir en Galicia centros de gran importancia para la atención a los enfermos, como el Monasterio de San Martín Pinario y el Hospital de los Reyes Católicos, en los que se siguen las pautas tradicionales en Europa, de cuidados y uso de plantas medicinales. La medicina y cirugía antiguas de las vías urinarias y genitales tiene en Galicia personajes de gran interés, como el doctor Romano, que fue instructor de médicos gallegos en el sondaje y la dilatación uretral, e importantes pensadores como el médico filósofo Francisco Sánchez y los frailes ilustrados Sarmiento y Feijóo, quienes sin ser médicos, pueden ser considerados como precursores de la medicina basada en pruebas. Comentarios: La importancia que en su tiempo tuvieron los hospitales gallegos y las obras de varios personajes relacionados con Galicia, ocupan un lugar destacado en la historia antigua de la cirugía de las vías urinarias y genitales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(2): 121-130, feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Urología antigua en Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38879</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38875</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
