<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72245</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7961</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebrovascular accident: Nutrition as a pathogenic and preventive factor. Post-CVA Nutritional support</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this review we will approach the topic in four stages: 1) Primary prevention Non-modifiable risk factors: 1) Age, 2) Gender, 3) Low birth weight, 4) Ethnicity, 5) Genetic factors. Modifiable risk factors: 1) Atherosclerotic disease, 2) Arterial hypertension, 3) Diabetes mellitus, 4) Dyslipidemia, 5) Cigarette smoking, 6) Alcohol abuse, 7) Physical activity, 8) Diet and nutrition: the scientific societies recommend the DASH diet (fruits, vegetables, and low in total fat and saturated fat) in order to reduce the blood pressure. The diet rich only in fruits and vegetables may decrease the risk of ictus. Reduction in sodium intake (£ 2.3 g or 100 mmol/day) and increase of potassium (4.7 g or 120 mmol/day) are recommended to reduce arterial blood pressure. 9) Obesity and distribution of body fat, 10) Hyperhomocysteinemia. 2) Managing the acute phase The incidence of malnourishment ranges 7%-15% at admission. After the CVA the nutritional status worsens, generally due to dysphagia and motor deficits that impair autonomous feeding, 22%-35% of the patients being already malnourished. The presence of malnourishment in these patients unfavourably affects their prognosis. In the case of having some difficulty for normal feeding and whenever the risk for aspiration is low, modifying the texture of the diet is indicated. If the patient presents fatigue or early satiety, having small but frequent intakes will be useful. It is common to encounter dysphagia for liquids so that beverages should be thicken with enteral nutrition products such as thickeners. In patients with a deficient nutritional status or not meeting the nutritional requirements with an oral diet, the enteral nutrition supplements are an effective resource. In patients with persistent dysphagia, the most common routes for administrating enteral nutrition are the nasogastric tube (NGT) and percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG). The first choice formula should be polymeric, normo-proteinic and normocaloric, with fibre, unless the recommendation is changed by some other condition. In the case of patients with hyponutrition at admission or with decubitus ulcers a hyperproteinic diet is recommended. Stress-induced hyperglycaemia is common, which may be controlled with specific diabetes mellitus formulas without needing pharmacological therapy for lowering glucose levels or intensive glycemic monitoring. 3) Care at discharge The development of malnourishment in this group of patients may be very common and is due to multiple factors. If dysphagia ensues, the occurrence of aspiration induced infections is facilitated. A nutritional follow-up should be done in the patients having required nutritional support during the acute phase of a CVA until complete recovery and appropriate nutrients intake are achieved. Home-based enteral nutrition has been shown to be cost effective in this group of patients. 4) Secondary prevention. Optimal management of vascular risk factors: 1) Arterial hypertension, 2) Diabetes mellitus, 3) Dyslipidemia, 4) Cigarette smoking, 5) Overweight, 6) Vitamins (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ballano, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Paris, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albero Gamboa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lofablos Callau, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diego Garcia, P de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta revisión valoraremos el tema en cuatro fases: 1) Prevención primaria Factores de riesgo no modificables: 1) Edad, 2) Sexo, 3) Bajo peso al nacer, 4) Raza, 5) Factores genéticos. Factores de riesgo modificables: 1) Enfermedad aterosclerótica, 2) Hipertensión arterial, 3) Diabetes mellitus, 4) Dislipemia, 5) Hábito tabáquico, 6) Consumo abusivo de alcohol, 7) Actividad física, 8) Dieta y nutrición: Las sociedades científicas recomiendan la dieta DASH (fruta, vegetales, pobre en grasas totales y saturadas) para reducir la presión arterial. La dieta rica solamente en fruta y vegetales puede disminuir el riesgo de ictus. Se recomienda reducir el consumo de sodio (&amp;#8804; 2,3 g 100 mmol/día) y aumentar el de potasio (&amp;#8805; 4,7 g . 120 mmol/día). para reducir la presión arterial. 9) Obesidad y distribución de la grasa corporal, 10) Hiperhomocisteinemia. 2) Tratamiento de la fase aguda La incidencia de malnutrición varían entre un 7-15% al ingreso. Después del ictus el estado nutricional se deteriora, generalmente por disfagia y déficit motores que dificultan la alimentación autónoma estando ya desnutridos el 22-35%. La presencia de malnutrición en estos pacientes condiciona de forma desfavorable su pronóstico. En caso de presentar alguna dificultad para la ingesta normal y siempre que el riesgo de aspiración sea mínimo, estar. indicado realizar modificaciones en la textura de la dieta. Si el paciente presenta fatiga o saciedad precoz será útil hacer tomas de poca cantidad pero muy frecuentes. Con mucha frecuencia nos encontramos disfagia para líquidos y deberemos espesar éstos con productos de nutrición enteral como los módulos de espesante. En pacientes con un estado nutricional deficitario o que no cubren sus requerimientos nutricionales con dieta oral los suplementos de nutrición enteral son un recurso eficaz. En pacientes con disfagia persistente, las vías para la administración de nutrición enteral m.s frecuentes son la sonda nasogástrica (SNG) y la gastrostomía endoscópica percutánea (PEG). La fórmula de elección es una polimérica, normoproteica y normocalórica y con fibra, salvo que alguna otra situación haga recomendable otro tipo diferente. En los casos de pacientes con desnutrición al ingreso o con úlceras de decúbito se recomienda una fórmula hiperprotéica. Es frecuente la hiperglucemia de estrés, que con fórmulas específicas para la diabetes mellitus se consigue controlar sin requerir tratamiento farmacológico hipoglucemiante ni control glucémico intensivo. 3) Cuidados tras el alta El desarrollo de malnutrición en este grupo de pacientes puede ser muy frecuente y se debe a míltiples factores. Si aparece disfagia, se favorece el desarrollo de infecciones por aspiración. Se debe realizar un seguimiento nutricional de los pacientes que han requerido soporte nutricional durante la fase aguda del ictus hasta su completa recuperación y un aporte de nutrientes adecuado. La nutrición enteral domiciliaria ha demostrado ser coste efectiva en este grupo de pacientes. 4) Prevención secundaria. Manejo óptimo de los factores de riesgo vascular: 1) Hipertensión arterial, 2) Diabetes mellitus, 3) Dislipemia, 4) Hábito tabáquico, 5) Sobrepeso, 6) Vitaminas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;2(supl.2): 38-55, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72245</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accidente cerebrovascular: la nutricion como factor patogenico y preventivo. Soporte nutricional post ACV</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16556</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
