<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045407</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Children of psychotic patients in the SASPE projects: research for a future of commitment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To contribute to the knowledge of the fertility and fecundity of an urban sample of patients diagnosed with schizophrenic disorder or «other psychoses»    (SASPE study), as well as of the offspring's psychopathology. Design: A retrospective study based in the computer treatment of the data of Project    SASPE, in the casting of clinical histories of five Units of Community Mental Health closely linked with the Primary Health CaTe (PHC) and in interviews with patients,    patient's offspring and professionals of the PHC and of Pediatrics of PHC. Location of the Project: Mental Health Unir (USM) of Sant Martí -The Mine, five Basic    Health Areas of Barcelona and Sant Adria (Barcelona), besides the Functional Unir of Attention to the Early Childhood of Sant Martí (Catalan lnstitute of Health).    Participants: 838 schizophrenic patients and with «delirant psychoses» detected by the    USM. 917 descendants of the same ones. Staff of the USM, 5 Basic Health Areas and of the Functional Unir of Attention to the Early Childhood (UFAPI). Children with    alert signs detected in the diverse Centers of the USM, and children with signs of alert or factors of risk detected in the PHC Teams and Pediatrics PHC teams.    Methodology and instruments: Diagnoses DSM-IV. Structured'interview ERIE-lRAOS. Screening for childhood mental health ARBB-ADBB, CBCL and LISMEP. Informatized    Data Base USM-SASPE</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parra, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalá, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrando, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tizón, Jorge L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pareja, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sorribes, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigue, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Conxita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Contribuir al conocimientod e la fertilidad y la fecundidad de una muestra urbana de pacientes diagnosticados bajo los rótulos de «trastorno esquizofrénico» y «otras psicosis» (estudio SASPE), así como de la psicopatología de su descendencia. Diseño:Estudio retrospectivo fundamentado  en el procesamiento informático de los datos del Proyecto SASPE, en el vaciado de historias clínicas de cinco Equipos deSalud Mental Comunitaria estrechamente vinculada con la Atención Primaria a la Salud (APS) y en entrevistas con pacientes, hijos de pacientes y profesionales de losEquipos de Atención Primaria (EAP) y de Pediatría de AP. Emplazamiento del Proyecto: Unitat de Salut Mental (USM) de Sant Martí-La Mina, cinco Áreas Básicas de Salud (ABS) de Barcelona y Sant Adria (provincia de Barcelona),además de la Unidad Funcional de Atención a la Primera Infancia de Sant Martí(Institut Catalá de la Salut).Sujetos: 838 pacientes esquizofrénicos y con «otras psicosis» detectados por la USM. 917 descendientedse los mismos. Personal asistencial de la USM,5 ABS y de la Unidad Funcional de Atención a la Primera Infancia ( UFAP1).N iños con señalesd e alerta detectadase n los diversosC entrosd e la USM,y niños con señalesd e alerta o factoresd    e riesgo detectadose n los EAP y en los Equiposd e Pediatríad e APS.    Metodologíae instrumentos:D iagnósticosD SM-1V.E ntrevistase structuradasE RIElRAOS.    E scalaso sistemasd e cribado en la infancia: cribadosA RBB-ADBB,C BCL y    USMEP. Based e datos informatizadosd e la USM-SASPE</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;69(1): 47-68, ene.-mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045407</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hijos de pacientes psicóticos en el proyecto SASPE: investigar para cuidar un futuro comprometido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d389^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d389^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
