<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045215</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness and efficacy of self-measurement of capillary blood glucose in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The efficacy of self-measurement of capillary blood glucose (SMBG) in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus is not fully established. The objectives of the study were: a) to verify the efficacy of the SMBG in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus in the primary care set; b) to investigate the possible causes that explain the lack of effectiveness of the method, in their case, and c) to deduce the predictive variables that permit to select good utilizador of the SMBG. Patients and method: Clinical trial controlled and randomized carried out in the environment of the primary care, on type 2 diabetic patients. The patients were assigned, of random form and stratified, according to the type of treatment for diabetes that received, in 2 groups: SMBG group (SMBG-G) and control group (CG). The period of monitoring was of 12 months. The efficacy of the SMBG was analyzed, and also its effectiveness. Results: 100 patients were included in the study. Out of them, 51 were assigned to SMBG-G and 49 to CG. The SMBG was efficient in the 21.6% of SMBG-G and in 14.3% patients of the CG (p = 0.44). The SMBG efficacy was greater in patients with combined treatment and in those who received only insulin (50% in both cases). No improvement was observed in patients on treatment with diet (p = 0.006). The effectiveness for the cut off from value the HbA1c was of 59.2% and of 29.58% for the totality of the European criteria of metabolic control. The independent predictor variables of the SMBG efficacy were: the evolution years number of the diabetes mellitus and a deficient control of the illness at the start of the study. The global precision of the mathematical model obtained was of 88.24% with sensibility of 54.5%, especificity of 97.5%, positive predictor value of 85.7% and negative predictive value of 11.4% (p &lt; 0.001). The area under the ROC curve was of 89.9% (p &lt; 0.001) (95% confidence interval, 81.2-98.5%). According to the ROC curve, the point of cut that better the SMBG efficacy discriminated was that of 74% (sensibility: 72.7%; especificity: 77.5%). Conclusions: SMBG is a tool that, although can improve the metabolic control of type 2 diabetes, requires a careful selection of patients and, therefore, cannot be utilized in an indiscriminate way. The time of evolution of the illness and fundamentally, the presence of a deficient metabolic control of the disease should be the factors that determine a good selection. Therefore, its extended use among the type 2 diabetic population, without a prior selection, does not seem to be justified</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero-Pérez, F. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna-Morales, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Guijo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oria-Pino, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo-Vázquez, Paloma del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La eficacia del autoanálisis (AA) de la glucemia capilar en los pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 no está plenamente establecida. Los objetivos del presente estudio han sido: a) comprobar la eficacia del AA en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 en el ámbito de la atención primaria; b) indagar las posibles causas que expliquen la falta de efectividad del método, en su caso, y c) deducir los factores predictivos que permitan seleccionar al buen utilizador del AA. Pacientes y método: Se trata de un ensayo clínico controlado y aleatorizado realizado en el ámbito de la atención primaria, en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Éstos se asignaron, de forma aleatoria y estratificada, según el tipo de tratamiento antidiabético que recibían, en 2 grupos: grupo de autoanálisis (GAA) y grupo control (GC). El período de seguimiento fue de 12 meses. Se analizaron la eficacia del AA y su efectividad. Resultados: De los 100 pacientes incluidos en el estudio, 51 fueron asignados al GAA y 49 al GC. El AA fue eficaz en el 21,6% de los pacientes del GAA frente al 14,3% en el GC (p = 0,44). La eficacia del AA fue mayor en los grupos de pacientes con tratamiento combinado y con tratamiento exclusivamente insulínico (un 50% en ambos casos), sin observarse mejoría en el grupo de tratamiento exclusivo con dieta (p = 0,006). La efectividad para el valor aislado de la hemoglobina glucosilada fue del 59,2%, y del 29,58% para la totalidad de los criterios europeos de control metabólico. Las variables predictoras independientes de la eficacia del AA fueron el número de años de evolución de la diabetes mellitus y un control deficiente de la enfermedad al inicio del estudio. La precisión global del modelo matemático obtenido fue del 88,24%, con una sensibilidad del 54,5%, especificidad del 97,5%, valor predictivo positivo del 85,7% y valor predictivo negativo del 11,4% (p &lt; 0,001). El área bajo la curva de eficacia diagnóstica fue del 89,9% (p &lt; 0,001) (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 81,2-98,5%). El punto de corte que, según la curva de eficacia diagnóstica, mejor discriminó la eficacia del AA fue el 74% (sensibilidad del 72,7% y especificidad del 77,5%). Conclusiones: El AA de la glucemia capilar es una herramienta que, aunque puede mejorar el control metabólico de la diabetes tipo 2, requiere una cuidadosa selección de pacientes y, por tanto, no puede utilizarse de manera indiscriminada. El tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad y, fundamentalmente, la presencia de un deficiente control metabólico de ésta deben ser los factores que determinen dicha selección. Por consiguiente, su extendido uso entre la población con diabetes tipo 2 sin una selección previa no parece estar justificada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(19): 728-735, mayo 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045215</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad y eficacia del autoanálisis de la glucemia capilar en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29116^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23570^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
