<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14717</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aetiopathogenic factors in colorectal cancer. Genetic and clinical aspects (part one of two)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Colorectal Cancer (CRC) is the second cause of death in Spain, reaching the first place in nonsmoking population. It is also the tumour with the greatest one-year incidence. The last few years some reduction in its incidence along with a greater 5-year average survival has been observed. Pathogenesis: Most CRCs develop from benign polyps. Vogelstein&#146;s hypothesis suggests an orderly progression from normal mucosa, to a small polyp, to a large polyp and finally to a CRC. In this progression transforming cells will be increasingly charged with molecular alterations. Genetic Factors: 20% of CRCs have a genetic background although only a fourth of these are genetically based. The APC (or FAP) gene mutation is one of the earlier events that can be seen in tumour progression. When this mutation appears in the germ line it renders Familial Adenomatose Polyposis Syndrome (that evolves to CRC in a 100% of cases) or to the Gardner Syndrome (if it has extracolonic expressions). The p53 mutation is a late event in cellular transformation but it makes a rapid accumulation of mutations an easier process and it confers advantages for survival of the tumour cells. Mutations in the genes implicated in microsatelite instability are related to DNA error repair; their clinical correlates are the Lynch I and II syndromes. Other important genes related to CRC are DCC and ras. Clinical Factors: Inflammatory Bowel Disease (particularly Crohn&#146;s disease) is the most important clinical factor, it may enhance basal risk 30 times. Other risk factors are: previous malignant conditions, pelvic irradiation and previous surgery (cholecystectomy and ureterosigmoidostomy). The endocrinologic factors have a rising importance and so hormonal substitution therapy for menopause and multiparity can provide some protection. The use of NSAIDs can also be protective (specially COX-2 inhibitors). Conclusions: It is important that people who are identified as having a high risk for developing a CRC are subjected to a strict clinical and endoscopic follow-up in order to be able to identify an incipient tumour or to practice prophylactic surgery. The use of hormonal substitution therapy or anti COX-2 NSAIDs can be future useful chemoprophylactic agents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cáncer colorrectal (CCR) es la segunda causa de muerte por cáncer en España, alcanzando el primer puesto entre la población sin hábito tabáquico. Es también el tumor que presenta una mayor incidencia a un año. En los últimos años se aprecia una cierta disminución de su incidencia, así como un aumento importante en la supervivencia media a 5 años. Patogenia: La mayoría de los CCR se desarrollan a partir de pólipos benignos. La hipótesis de Vogelstein sugiere una progresión ordenada desde una mucosa normal a un pólipo pequeño, a un pólipo grande y, finalmente a un CCR. En este proceso, las células que se transforman se irían cargando de alteraciones moleculares. Factores genéticos: El 20 por ciento de los CCR tienen un trasfondo genético, aunque de éstos en sólo una cuarta parte tiene una importancia fundamental. La mutación en el gen APC (o FAP) es uno de los eventos genéticos más tempranos que pueden apreciarse en la progresión tumoral. Cuando esta mutación aparece en la línea germinal, da lugar a la poliposis adenomatosa familiar (que evoluciona a CCR en el 100 por ciento de los casos) o al s. de Gardner (si presenta alteraciones extracolónicas). La mutación del gen de la p53 es un evento tardío en la transformación celular, pero facilita la acumulación rápida de mutaciones y confiere ventaja en la supervivencia de las células tumorales. Las mutaciones en los genes implicados en la inestabilidad microsatélite están relacionados con la presencia de defectos en la reparación de errores en el ADN; su correlato clínico son los síndromes de Lynch tipo I y II. Otros genes importantes relacionados con el CCR son: DCC y ras. Factores clínicos: La enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (particularmente, la enfermedad de Crohn) es el factor clínico más importante, pudiendo llegar a multiplicar por 30 el riesgo basal. Otros factores de riesgo son: enfermedad maligna previa, irradiación pélvica y cirugía previa (colecistectomía y ureterosigmoidostomía). A los factores endocrinológicos se les confiere cada vez una mayor importancia. Así, el tratamiento hormonal sustitutorio en la menopausia y la multiparidad pueden conferir protección. El uso de AINE puede ser también protector (especialmente inhibidores de la COX-2). Conclusiones: Es importante que las personas que se identifiquen como de alto riesgo para desarrollar un CCR se sometan a un seguimiento clínico y endoscópico estricto para identificar precozmente un tumor o realizar una cirugía profiláctica. El uso de tratamiento hormonal sustitutorio o AINE anti-COX-2 pueden ser en el futuro productos quimioprofilácticos eficaces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;17(2): 63-71, mar. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores etiopatogénicos en el cáncer colorrectal. Aspectos genéticos y clínicos (primera de dos partes)</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Casimiro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14717</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
