<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047458</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health condition in a group of chronic boarding schizophrenic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The schizophrenic patients have high rates of morbility of other diseases, in particular: obesity, diabetes, hipertensión, drugs abuse, specially nicotina, etc. Likewise they present a more pasive behaviour, social isolation, and deficient contacts with the sanitary services. Objective: To study the comorbidity and the health behaviour in a group of chronic schizophrenic patients patients with long internment. Material and method: Population: 66 patients diagnosed of schizophrenia according to Cie-10. With an average age of 57.85 years, and with an average time of internment of 27.3 years. Material: data taken from medical history and we used the EEAG scale of evaluation of a global activity the IAE accumulative of disease index, and as well the Cgi scale of global clinical impression. Method: cross-sectional study of descrptive character. Results: the average the EEAG is 34.24 and according to the GGI a 89.4% of the patients are severely or extremely ill. The IAE show an average of the total the category of the 3.6 for patient, the index of severity for patients is the 1.9. The more usualy disease are of the cardiac, vascular and endocrine-metabolic systems. Teh demand of attendances is high. Teh behaviour id very damaged, there is an important number of patients that not receives visits, or not go out into the street, or not are participants into therapeutic programes. Conclusions: Our patients have a high rate of the other medical disease, obesity, hypertension, diabetes, tobacco consuncion. Anyway a very passive an damaged behaviour</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Calle, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanguino Andrés, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Pablos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso del Teso, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los pacientes esquizofrénicos presentan una tasa elñevada de morbilidad de otras enfermedades médicas, particularmente: obesidad, diabetes, hipertensión, consumo de tabaco y otras sustancias, etc. Así mismo, presentan una conducta más pasiva, aislamiento social y contactos deficientes con los servicios sanitarios. Objetivos: Estudiar la comorbilidad y la conducta de salud de un grupo de pacientes esquiénicos, crónicas e institucionalizados. Material y método: - Población: 66 pacientes diagnosticadas de esquizofrenia según CIE-10. Con una edad media de 57,85 años y con un tiempo medio de internamiento de 27,3 años. Material: se recogieron datos de la historia clínica y como instrumento evaluativo de la salud física usamos el Índice Acumulativo de Enfermedad (IAE). Se utilizó también la Escala de Evaluación de la Actividad Global (EEAG) y la escala de Impresión Clínica Global (CGI). Método: estudio transversal de carácter descriptivo. Resultados: La puntuación media dela EEAG es de 34,24 y según la CGI es de 89,4% de las pacientes son severa o extremadamente enfermas. Según el IAE, el total del número de categorías incluidas arroja una media de 3,36 por paciente, con un índice de gravedad medio por paciente de 1,9. En cuanto a las enfermedades más habituales destacan las de sistemas: cardíaco, vascular y endocrinometabólico. La demanda de asistencia sanitaria está elevada. La conducta es muy deteriorada, con un número importante de pacientes que no reciben visitas, o no salen, o no participan en programas terapéuticos. Conclusiones: Nuestras pacientes presentan una elevada tasa de otras enfermedades médicas: obesidad, hipertensión, diabetes, consumo de tabaco. Así como una conducta muy pasiva y deteriorada</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;22(3): 102-110, mayo-jun.2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047458</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado de salud de un grupo de pacientes esquizofrénicas crónicas internadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28071^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28071^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28071^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
