<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147982</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adequacy of hospital admissions according to the type of physician who performs the indication for admission to an emergency room with a model of non-pyramidal supervision</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. A hospital admission adequacy warrants sustainability of a healthcare system and contributes increasing patients&#146; safety. Teaching hospitals must assure that pedagogic exercise with residents do not affect the adequacy of hospital admissions. Aim. To determine if our resident supervision model, known as non-pyramidal, warrants and homogeneous proportion of hospital admissions from the emergency department with independence of the different kind of physician who performs the instruction of hospital admission. Subjects and methods. A validated international protocol of hospital admission adequacy was applied to a randomized group of registries of hospital admissions which was used in a study of prevalence of adequate hospital admissions performed previously. The proportion of adequate hospital admission was compared according to who was who ordered the admission: a urgency physician staff, a first year resident under staff supervision and a second or third year resident. Results. The hospital admissions from the emergency department ordered by a staff physician, a first year resident and a second or third year resident were 125, 93 and 78 respectively. In those three groups, hospital admissions considered inadequate were 4 (3.2%), 5 (5.4%) and 4 (5.1%), respectively. There was no statistically significant difference among those proportions. Conclusions. In all groups, proportion of inadequate hospital admissions was less than those found in national reports. We believe that our non-pyramidal supervision model assures sustainability of the healthcare system saving costs of inadequate hospital admissions and contributes to warrant patients&#146; safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carballo-Cardona, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Egido, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Astete, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La adecuación de ingresos hospitalarios garantiza la sostenibilidad del sistema sanitario y contribuye a incrementar la seguridad de los pacientes. Los hospitales universitarios deben tener como prioridad que el ejercicio de la docencia no repercuta en detrimento de la adecuación de los ingresos hospitalarios. Objetivo. Determinar si nuestro modelo de supervisión de residentes, conocido como no piramidal, garantiza una homogénea proporción de ingresos hospitalarios adecuados desde el servicio de urgencias con independencia de la situación de supervisión que tenga el médico responsable del ingreso. Sujetos y métodos. Se aplicó el protocolo de adecuación de ingresos hospitalarios a un registro aleatorizado obtenido para un estudio previamente realizado sobre prevalencia de adecuación de los ingresos hospitalarios. La proporción de ingresos hospitalarios adecuados se comparó en función de quién había realizado la indicación del ingreso: un facultativo especialista, un residente de primer año bajo supervisión facultativa o un residente de segundo o tercer año. Resultados. Los ingresos hospitalarios indicados por un facultativo especialista, por un residente de primer año bajo supervisión de un facultativo especialista y por un residente de segundo o tercer año fueron 125, 93 y 78, respectivamente. En estos tres grupos, los ingresos hospitalarios considerados inadecuados fueron 4 (3,2%), 5 (5,4%), y 4 (5,1%), respectivamente, sin identificarse diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Conclusiones. En todos los grupos, la proporción de ingresos inadecuados fue inferior a la comunicada en estudios nacionales previos. Creemos que nuestro modelo de supervisión no piramidal garantiza una sostenibilidad del sistema sanitario al ahorrar costes de ingresos inadecuados y contribuye a aumentar la seguridad de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);18(6): 405-409, nov.-dic. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147982</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de los ingresos hospitalarios en función del personal sanitario facultativo responsable bajo un modelo de supervisión no piramidal de médicos residentes en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7471^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
