<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116668</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient with testosterone deficit syndrome and dyslipemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We define dyslipemia as the abnormally elevated presence of lipids in the blood. The main ones are hypercholesterolemia (cholesterol over 240 mg/dl), hypertrigliceridemia (triglicerides level over 200 mg/dl) and hipo-alphalipoproteinemia (High density lipoproteins, also called HDL Cholesterol, below 40 mg/dl). The presence of excessive lipids contributes to arteriosclerosis and they are an independent cardiovascular risk factor (1) (Table I).It may be primary, if they have genetic origin and they are not associated with other diseases, but in most cases they are secondary to other pathological entities such as diabetes, hypothyroidism, obesity and metabolic syndrome (MS). In our current society, sedentary lifestyle and unadequatelly hypercaloric diets are making obesity and MS prevalences grow, and their relation to dyslipemias has become tighter. Obesity is related with all the criteria for MS. But obesity is not at all synonymous of MS. On the one hand neither fat distribution is the same in all individualas nor confers the same risk. Accordingly, we know that abdominal localization of fat is related to higher intensity of insulin resistance (IR) and MS. On the other hand, it seems that certain components of MS are determined by genetic factors, since there are morbid obese persons that are metabolically healthy and other patients develop insulin resistance without obesity. So that, it seems that the excess in visceral adiposity in the presence of certain genetic factors would be the most related cause of the appearance of peripheral insulin resistance and diabetes mellitus, hyperlipidemia (increase of very low density pipoproteins (VLDL)), decrease of highdensity lipoproteins (HDL), arterial hypertension, and hypogonadotropic hypogonadism, composing what we call metabolic syndrome. In this scenario, we urologists are being first-hand witnesses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llorente Abarca, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, Borja</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola Galarza, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad se relaciona con todos los criterios de síndrome metabólico (SM). Pero obesidad no es ni mucho menos sinónimo de síndrome metabólico. Por una parte la distribución de grasa no es igual en todos los individuos ni confiere el mismo riesgo. En este sentido sabemos que la localización abdominal de la grasa, se relaciona con mayor intensidad con la resistencia a la insulina (RI) y el SM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(7): 752-759, sept. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116668</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente con SDT y dislipemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
