<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80618</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">To get the adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To let the intellectually hadicapped people to ge tinto the society and become parto f it, they need to have a life Project, a concepto f themselves, and a clear identity. It will make possible to accept the difficulties, to discover their potentials and reinforce their autoestime. Building the identity does not ends-up in the adolescence, it lasts for the whole life. Adulthood has more external needs, more if the person is working in ordinary jobs, and gets less internal support. In adulthood, persons with intellectual handicaps still need knowing themselves, to be satisfied with what they are doing, to be able to choose, and feel socially valuated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garvía Peñuelas, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para que las personas con discapacidad intelectual (DI) se incorporen a la sociedad y formen parte de ella necesitan tener un proyecto de vida, un concepto de sí mismas y una identidad clara que posibilite la aceptación de las dificultades, el descubrimiento de sus potencialidades y el reforzamiento de su autoestima. La construcción de la identidad no acaba en la adolescencia, sino que continúa a lo largo de la vida. Sin embargo, la etapa adulta es la de mayor exigencia externa &#150;sobre todo cuando la persona está integrada en el mundo laboral ordinario&#150; pero, la que menos apoyo recibe a nivel interno. Y la persona con DI sigue necesitando, en la edad adulta, conocerse, saber lo que desea, sentirse satisfecha de lo que hace, superarse, elegir y sentirse apoyada y reconocida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);11(2): 30-32, jul. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80618</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Para llegar a ser adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4581^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33554^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33554^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4581^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
