<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112114</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Critical analysis of positivist paradigm and its influence in knowledge development of nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper aims to analyze the influence of positivist paradigm in nursing. This thought tendency is described in terms of history and characteristics and nursing view under the reactive or particular - deterministic vision. Afterwards, it deepens over some positivism elements which are present in nursing area, such as: sanitary assistance, training nurses, and research care management. It is concluded that being able to visualize named areas under a holistic view, which is given by other paradigms as well as the observation of benefits comprehensively and transpersonal care by users, health team and society, a change in the value placed on nursing discipline can be reached (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paula Ceballos, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizet Veliz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivia Sanhueza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandra Valenzuela, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo tiene como propósito analizar la influencia del paradigma positivista en Enfermería. Se describen las características de esta corriente de pensamiento y la mirada de Enfermería a través de la visión reactiva o particular-determinística. Se profundiza sobre algunos elementos del positivismo presentes en los ámbitos de desempeño, como: asistencia sanitaria, formación, investigación y gestión. Se concluye que visibilizando dichos ámbitos desde una mirada holística, a la que se accede desde otros paradigmas, y la reflexión de los beneficios del cuidado integral y transpersonal por parte de los usuarios, del equipo de salud y de la sociedad, se puede contribuir para cambiar la valoración que tiene la sociedad de la disciplina de enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;21(4): 224-228, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis crítico del paradigma positivista y su influencia en el desarrollo de la enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23782</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
