<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131042</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of the neuropsychologist in neurology services: a descriptive study of the users of the specialised neurological assessment unit of the Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra during its first year in service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. A large number of neurological diseases course with impairment of higher cognitive functions, their evaluation being important for diagnostic, prognostic and therapeutic purposes. The main purpose of neuropsychological assessment s to identify behavioral, emotional and cognitive consequences of brain dysfunction. The neuropsychologist&#146;s figure was included in Navarra&#146;s Hospital Neurology Service in February 2013 through a specialized practice in neuropsychological assessment. Aim. To describe the sociodemographic and clinical profile of all patients referred to the same from March 2013 to March 2014. Patients and methods. A total of 511 people have been treated in this practice. Results. 73.2% are more than 55 years old and the most frequent reason of referral is to characterize the neuropsychological profile to detect and discriminate mild cognitive impairment and dementia, as well as the type of dementia. In younger adults (&lt; 55 years old) the most prevalent cognitive deficit is memory impairment. Conclusions. The expert neuropsychologist performs thorough neuropsychological evaluations from an interpretative approach. The results of this study suggest the importance of this figures role in neurology services and point out future aims (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carnés Vendrell, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna Lario, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seijs Gómez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Un gran número de patologías neurológicas cursa con afectación de las funciones cognitivas superiores, y su valoración es importante con fines diagnósticos, pronósticos y terapéuticos. El principal objetivo de la evaluación neuropsicológica es identificar las consecuencias conductuales, emocionales y cognitivas de la disfunción cerebral. La figura del neuropsicólogo se incluyó en el servicio de neurología del Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra en febrero de 2013 a través de una consulta especializada de evaluación neuropsicológica. Objetivo. Describir el perfil sociodemográfico y clínico del total de pacientes derivados a consulta de marzo de 2013 a marzo de 2014. Pacientes y métodos. Se ha atendido a un total de 511 personas en esta consulta. Resultados. El 73,2% tiene más de 55 años y el motivo de derivación más frecuente es la caracterización del perfil neuropsicológico para detectar y discriminar deterioro cognitivo leve y demencia, así como el tipo de demencia. En los adultos jóvenes (&lt; 55 años), el déficit cognitivo más prevalente es la afectación de la memoria. Conclusiones. El neuropsicólogo experto realiza evaluaciones neuropsicológicas exhaustivas desde un enfoque interpretativo. Los resultados de este estudio apuntan la relevancia de su función en los servicios de neurología y descubre objetivos futuros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(12): 529-536, dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131042</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel del neuropsicólogo en los servicios de neurología: estudio descriptivo de los usuarios de la consulta especializada de evaluación neuropsicológica del Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra en su primer año de funcionamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54753^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
