<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93944</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress and recovery in athletes and their relationship to mood state disturbances and coping strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to assess situations related to overtraining within the context of sport (RESTQ-Sport, Kellmann and Kallus, 2001; González-Boto et al., 2008c) and identify its temporal relationship with mood state disturbances (POMS, McNair et al., 1971; Balaguer et al., 1993) and its possible influence on the appearance of imbalances between stress and recovery according to the coping strategies used to deal with stress (ISCCS, Gaudreau and Blondin, 2002; Molinero et al., 2006, 2008, 2009). A total of 167 athletes (62.5% men, and 36.9% women) ranging in age from 18 to 28 years old in 11 sport modalities participated in the study. The results showed that modifications took place during the three measurements made of the levels of general stress (p = .027*), conflict/ pressure (p = .000**), fatigue (p = .000**), general wellbeing (p = .022*), burnout/ emotional fatigue (p = .009**), physical fitness/ injuries (p = .000**), burnout/ personal accomplishment (p = .000**), self-regulation (p = .000**), non-sport stress (p = .006**), sport stress (p = .001**), sport recovery (p = .000**), and total stress (p = .001**), which had changed compared with the main indices assessed by the RESTQ Sport. At the emotional level, we observed changes in the levels of depression (p = .040*), anger, (p = .006**), confusion (p = 036*) and total mood disturbance (p = .041*). We did not find any changes in the coping strategies used. According to these results, it is necessary to pay more attention to temporal changes during recovery, because they may lead to positive adaptations after overtraining periods and their relationship to athletes&#146; mood states, which have usually been used as fatigue indicators (González-Boto et al., 2009; Kellmann et al., 2001; Rietjens et al., 2005). Athletes use a number of coping strategies that may lead in different ways to the balance between stress and recovery and therefore, the possible triggering of overtraining (Márquez, 2006; González Boto et al., 2006, 2008a, 2009). This research project was supported by the Ministry of Science and Innovation (R+D Plan 008-2011) (Spain) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molinero, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es evaluar situaciones relacionadas con el sobreentrenamiento (RESTQ-Sport, Kellmann y Kallus, 2001; González- Boto et al., 2008c) en el contexto deportivo, e identificar su relación temporal con las modificaciones en los estados de ánimo (POMS, McNair y cols., 1971; Balaguer et al. 1993) y la posible influencia en la aparición de desequilibrios entre estrés y recuperación en función del tipo de estrategias de afrontamiento utilizadas (ISCCS, Gaudreau y Blondin, 2002; Molinero et al., 2006, 2008, 2009). Han participado 167 deportistas (62.5% hombres y 36.9% mujeres) entre 18 y 24 años pertenecientes a 11 modalidades deportivas. Los resultados muestran que se producen modificaciones a los largo de las tres tomas realizadas en los niveles de estrés general (p = .027*), conflictospresión (p = .000**), fatiga (p = .000**), bienestar general (p = .022*), burnout-fatiga emocional (p = .009**), forma física-lesiones (p = .000**), burnout- realización personal (p = .000**), autorregulación (p = .000**), Estrés no deportivo (p = .006**), Estrés y recuperación deportiva (p = .001**; p = .000**), Estrés Total (p = .001**) en relación a los índices medidos por el RESTQ Sport. A nivel emocional observamos cambios en los niveles de depresión (p = .040*), cólera, (p = .006**), confusión (p = 036*) y Alteración Emocional Total (p = .041*), y no se producen cambios en el uso de las distintas estrategias de afrontamiento. Es necesario prestar más atención a los cambios temporales durante la recuperación, que pueden inducir adaptaciones positivas tras periodos de sobreentrenamiento, y su relación con los estados de ánimo de los deportistas, que han sido utilizados habitualmente como indicadores de fatiga (González- Boto et al., 2009; Kellmann et al., 2001; Rietjens et al., 2005). Los deportistas utilizan una serie de estrategias de afrontamiento que podrían condicionar de forma diversa el balance entre estrés y recuperación y, por tanto, el posible desencadenamiento de situaciones de sobreentrenamiento (Márquez, 2006; González Boto et al., 2006, 2008a, 2009) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(1): 163-170, ene.-jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés-recuperación en deportistas y su relación con los estados de ánimo y las estrategias de afrontamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9316^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12485^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
