<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71242</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Six medical competences with 27 components were defined for the undergraduate medical program in2005. Aims. To evaluate the learning assessment tools that are used through the program, to develop faculty for working out and using reliable and valid assessment tools, in order to control medical competences, and to formulate learning assessment criteria. Materials and methods. In a descriptive, quali-quantitative study, a sample of 17modules, belonging to four different groups of courses was chosen. Samples of different evaluation tools of those modules were collected and analyzed in terms of validity, reliability and capability to evaluate medical competences. After given back the data to faculty and developed a training program for four modules&#146; teaching teams, their assessment system considerably improved. Five general criteria were developed to design a valid and reliable system of medical competences assessment. Results and conclusions. a)Many of the learning assessment tools that are used in the program are nor valid neither reliable, particularly those used in clerkships; b) even though many faculty members were part of the medical competences drafting process, a few competences&#146; compounds are effectively assessed; c) training faculty is enough to have them build up valid, reliable and competence oriented assessment tools; d) the Medical School should set up faculty development programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reta-De Rosas, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montbrun, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En 2005 se definieron y difundieron seis competencias con 27 componentes para la carrera de medicina. Objetivos. Evaluar los instrumentos de evaluación de los aprendizajes que se utilizan durante la carrera, formar docentes en la elaboración y uso de instrumentos adecuados, válidos y fiables con el fin de evaluar competencias médicas, y formular criterios generales para la evaluación de los aprendizajes. Materiales y métodos. Se trabajó sobre una muestra de 17 asignaturas, pertenecientes a cuatro grupos. Se recogieron muestras de sus instrumentos de evaluación, que se analizaron según su validez, fiabilidad y capacidad de evaluar competencias médicas, en un estudio descriptivo y cuali-cuantitativo. Varios instrumentos de evaluación de las asignaturas no resultaron válidos ni fiables. Pocos evaluaban las competencias médicas. Se devolvieron resultados y se trabajó en la capacitación de docentes de cuatro de esas asignaturas, cuyos sistemas de evaluación mejoraron considerablemente. Se elaboraron cinco criterios generales para el diseño de sistemas de evaluación de competencias médicas válidos y fiables. Resultados y conclusiones. a)Muchos de los instrumentos de evaluación del aprendizaje que se utilizan en la carrera no son válidos ni fiables; b) son pocas las competencias médicas definidas para la carrera que se evalúan en las rotaciones clínicas, aun cuando gran cantidad de docentes participaron de su formulación; c)capacitando al personal docente se logra que produzcan instrumentos de evaluación válidos, fiables y orientados a evaluar las competencias médicas; d) la facultad deberá esforzarse en desarrollar programas de capacitación docente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);11(4): 207-218, dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71242</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
