<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94441</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ankylosing spondylitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ankylosing spondylitis is an inflammatory disease of the spine that generally affects people between 20 and 40 years of age. It is characterized by the appearance of inflammatory lower back pain, usually during nocturnal sleep, and is associated with morning stiffness of the spine. It is sometimes accompanied by arthritis and enteritis.This disease affects approximately between 0,05 and 0,25% of the population. It affects more males than females in a 5:1 proportion.Nursing care in this pathology can be very important to facilitate self-care and the effective tackling of the disease, and should be focused on structured health education programs aimed specifically at this patient group.This article is the third of a series on rheumatology nursing care and describes ankylosing spondylitis, its main characteristics, its clinical manifestations and the management of the therapeutic regime for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Batlle Gualda, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Aboki, Jenny de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La espondilitis anquilosante es una enfermedad inflamatoria de la columna vertebral que afecta, generalmente, a personas entre la segunda y cuarta década de la vida. Se caracteriza por la aparición de dolor lumbar de características inflamatorias, que despierta durante el reposo nocturno, asociado a rigidez espinal matutina, y acompañado, en ocasiones, de artritis y entesitis. Su prevalencia se estima entre el 0,05 y el 0,25% de la población. Afecta más a varones que a mujeres en una proporción 5:1. Los cuidados enfermeros,en esta patología, pueden ser muy importantes para facilitar el autocuidado y el afrontamiento eficaz de la enfermedad y deberían estar centrados en programas estructurados de Educación para la Salud dirigidos específicamente a estos enfermos.En este artículo, tercero de una serie dirigida a los cuidados enfermeros en reumatología, se presenta la espondilitis anquilosante, recorriendo generalidades de esta patología, sus manifestaciones clínicas y el manejo del régimen terapéutico en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(8): 13-20, oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La espondilitis anquilosante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
