<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164644</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">CTNS molecular genetics profile in a Persian nephropathic cystinosis population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: In this report, we document the CTNS gene mutations of 28 Iranian patients with nephropathic cystinosis age 1-17 years. All presented initially with severe failure to thrive, polyuria, and polydipsia. Methods: Cystinosis was primarily diagnosed by a pediatric nephrologist and then referred to the Iran University of Medical Sciences genetics clinic for consultation and molecular analysis, which involved polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification to determine the presence or absence of the 57-kb founder deletion in CTNS, followed by direct sequencing of the coding exons of CTNS. Results: The common 57-kb deletion was not observed in any of the 28 Iranian patients. In 14 of 28 patients (50%), mutations were observed in exons 6 and 7. No mutation was detected in exon 5, and only one (3.6%) patient with cystinosis showed a previously reported 4-bp deletion in exon 3 of CTNS. Four patients (14.3%) had a previously reported mutation (c.969C&gt;A; p.N323K) in exon 11, and five (18%) had novel homozygous deletions in exon 6 leading to premature truncation of the protein. These deletions included c.323delA; p.Q108RfsX10 in three individuals and c.257-258delCT; p.S86FfsX37 in two cases. Other frame-shift mutations were all novel homozygous single base pair deletion/insertions including one in CTNSexon 9 (c.661insT; p.V221CfsX6), and four (14.3%) in exon 4, i.e., c.92insG; p.V31GfsX28 in two and c.120delC; p.T40TfsX10 in two. In total, we identified eight previously reported mutations and eight novel mutations in our patients. The only detected splice site mutation (IVS3-2A&gt;C) was associated with the insertion mutation in the exon 9. Conclusion: This study, the first molecular genetic analysis of non-ethnic-specific Iranian nephropathic cystinosis patients, may provide guidance for molecular diagnostics of cystinosis in Iran (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Behnam, Babak</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ghazi, Farideh</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akouchekian, Mansoureh</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teimourian, Shahram</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otukesh, Hassan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gahl, William A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hosseini, Rozita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kachoei, Zohreh Ataei</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En este informe, documentamos las mutaciones del gen CTNS de 28 pacientes iraníes con cistinosis nefropática y una edad de 1-17 años. En un principio, todos presentaron retraso del desarrollo, poliuria y polidipsia. Métodos: En primer lugar, un nefrólogo pediátrico diagnosticó la cistinosis y luego los pacientes fueron trasladados a la clínica genética de la Universidad de Ciencias Médicas de Irán para consulta y análisis molecular, que incluía la multiplicación por reacción en cadena de la polimerasa (PCR), para determinar la existencia o ausencia de la deleción del fundador del 57kb en el CTNS, seguida por la secuenciación directa de los exones de codificación del CTNS. Resultados: La deleción frecuente del 57kb no se observó en ninguno de los 28 pacientes iraníes. En 14 de los 28 pacientes (50%) se observaron mutaciones en los exones 6 y 7. No se detectó ninguna mutación en el exón 5 y solo un paciente (3,6%) con cistinosis mostró una deleción del 4pb, anteriormente comunicada, en el exón 3 del CTNS. De ellos, 4 pacientes (14,3%) tenían una mutación anteriormente comunicada (c.969C &gt; A; p.N323K) en el exón 11 y 5 (18%) tenían nuevas deleciones homocigóticas en el exón 6 que produjeron el vaciamiento prematuro de la proteína. Entre estas deleciones se puede citar c.323delA; p.Q108RfsX10 en 3 personas y c.257-258delCT; p.S86FfsX37 en 2 casos. Otras mutaciones con desplazamiento del marco de lectura fueron todas nuevas deleciones/inserciones de un par de bases únicas homocigóticas, incluyendo una en el exón 9 del CTNS(c.661insT; p.V221CfsX6) y 4 (14,3%) en el exón 4, es decir, c.92insG; p.V31GfsX28 en 2 y c.120delC; p.T40TfsX10 en 2. En total, en nuestros pacientes se identificaron 8 mutaciones anteriormente comunicadas y 8 mutaciones nuevas. La única mutación del sitio de empalme detectada (IVS3-2A&gt;C) estaba asociada con la mutación de inserción en el exón 9. Conclusión: Este estudio, el primer análisis genético molecular de pacientes iraníes con cistinosis nefropática de carácter no específicamente étnico, puede servir como guía para el diagnóstico molecular de la cistinosis en Irán (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(3): 301-310, mayo-jun. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164644</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil genético molecular del gen CTNS en una población persa con cistinosis nefropática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7659^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3572^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
