<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158899</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">End-tidal desflurane concentration for tracheal extubation in adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the end-tidal desflurane concentration required for tracheal extubation in anaesthetised adults. Material and methods. After hospital Ethics Committee approval, eighteen ASA I-II adult patients (19-65 years of age), who had been scheduled for elective ambulatory surgery were included in the study. Anaesthesia was induced with propofol 2.5mg.kg&amp;#8722;1, fentanyl 2&amp;#956;g.kg&amp;#8722;1, and rocuronium 0.6mg.kg&amp;#8722;1 for intubation. Maintenance of anaesthesia was provided by desflurane in oxygen and air (40:60), and remifentanil at 0.05-0.25&amp;#956;g.kg&amp;#8722;1.min1. Neuromuscular function was monitored with train-of-four (TOF) nerve stimulation and acceleromyography. At the end of the surgery neuromuscular blockade was reversed with sugammadex 2-4mg.kg&amp;#8722;1 in accordance with the TOF ratio. The concentration of desflurane at which extubation was attempted was determined by using Dixon's up-and-down method with 0.5% as a step size. Smooth extubation was defined as one without coughing, teeth clenching, gross purposeful movements, and no breath-holding or laryngospasm within 1min of tracheal extubation. Results. It was found that the end-tidal concentration of desflurane was 3.17±0.18% (95% CI: 3%-3.35%) for successful extubation in 50% of adults. Conclusion. Extubation in patients receiving desflurane may be feasible at 0.62 minimum alveolar concentration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaballos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canal Alonso, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gala, F de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustí, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar en el paciente adulto la concentración al final de la espiración (end-tidal) de desflurano que previene la respuesta a la extubación en el 50% de los pacientes (CAMEXT). Material y método. Tras la aprobación por el comité ético del hospital, 18 pacientes adultos ASA I y II (19-65 años) programados para cirugía ambulatoria fueron incluidos en el estudio. La inducción anestésica se realizó con propofol 2,5mg.kg&amp;#8722;1, fentanilo 2&amp;#956;g.kg&amp;#8722;1 y rocuronio en dosis de 0,6mg.kg&amp;#8722;1 para facilitar la intubación orotraqueal. El mantenimiento se llevó cabo con desflurano en oxígeno y aire (40:60) con una concentración end-tidal de 5,5 a 7,5%, acorde a la edad del paciente. Se asoció remifentanilo en perfusión continua en dosis de 0,05-0,25&amp;#956;g/kg/min. El bloqueo neuromuscular se monitorizó mediante aceleromiografía a través del «tren de cuatro» (TOF). Al finalizar la intervención se revirtió el bloqueo neuromuscular con sugammadex en dosis de 2-4mg.kg&amp;#8722;1 acorde con la relación del TOF. La concentración de desflurano en la que se realizó la extubación fue determinada con la metodología secuencial de Dixon de up-and-down con incrementos y decrementos en la concentración de desflurano del 0,5%. Se definió como respuesta la presencia de tos, movimiento, mordida del tubo endotraqueal, laringoespasmo o apnea hasta 1min tras la extubación. Resultados. La concentración end-tidal de desflurano para realizar una extubación exitosa en el 50% de los pacientes adultos fue de 3,17±0,18% (IC 95%: 3-3,35%). Un 33% de los pacientes presentó tos y un paciente presentó desaturación inferior a 90%, que se resolvió con ventilación con mascarilla facial. Conclusiones. La extubación exitosa de pacientes adultos anestesiados con desflurano puede ser realizada con una concentración alveolar mínima de desflurano de 0,62 en el 95% de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(1): 13-18, ene. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158899</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentración al final de la espiración de desflurano requerida para la extubación en el paciente adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54675^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19248^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54675^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24841^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d780^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
