<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058282</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pyroglutamic acidemia associated with acetaminophen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of pyroglutamic acidemia probably related to acetaminophen administration. A 16-month boy recovering from hemolytic uremic syndrome abruptly developed unexplained high anion gap metabolic acidosis requiring hemodialysis. Septic shock, lactic acidosis and salicylate intoxication were ruled out. Betahydroxybutyrate and acetoacetate levels were within the normal range. No osmolarity gap or high amino acid levels were found. Urine and blood pyroglutamic acid levels were 392 mmol/mol creatinine (reference range: 9-55) and 9.8 mmol/L (reference range &lt; 0.16), respectively. The patient was receiving acetaminophen. We conclude that pyroglutamic acidosis should be considered in patients receiving acetaminophen who abruptly develop high anion gap metabolic acidosis not attributable to more common causes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruza Tarrío, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Senovilla, P. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Melgar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alados Arboledas, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Muñoz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del manuscrito es comentar un caso de acidosis piroglutámica probablemente relacionada con la administración de paracetamol. Un niño de 16 meses en fase de recuperación de un síndrome hemolítico urémico desarrolló bruscamente acidosis metabólica con anión gap aumentado que precisó hemodiálisis. El paciente no presentaba signos sugerentes de sepsis y la acidosis láctica y la intoxicación por salicilatos se descartaron. Las concentraciones de betahidroxibutirato, acetoacetato, aminoácidos séricos y el osmol gap fueron normales. La determinación urinaria y sérica de ácido piroglutámico fue patológica: 392 mmol/mol creatinina (rango de referencia: 9-55) y 9,8 mmol/l (referencia &lt; 0,16), respectivamente. El paciente estaba recibiendo paracetamol. La acidosis piroglutámica se debe descartar en el paciente que esté recibiendo paracetamol y desarrolle de forma brusca acidosis metabólica con anión gap aumentado sin otra causa precipitante</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(6): 582-584, dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acidosis piroglutámica asociada a paracetamol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14910^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d143^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10171</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14910^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
