<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72430</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of haematology and biochemistry parameters to identify iron deficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There has been a continuous improvement in the methods to detect iron deficiency, a common condition in children, in the last decades or so, but it is still difficult to establish which parameters should be included in a diagnostic panel for iron deficiency and iron deficiency anaemia. The objectives of this study were to evaluate the diagnostic efficiency of commonly used haematological and biochemical markers, as well as the reticulocyte haemoglobin content (CHr) in the diagnosis of iron deficiency with or without anaemia. Study design: A descriptive cross-sectional study was carried out on an urban population of both sexes aged 6 months to 14 years. A complete blood cell count with CHr was obtained. Biochemical markers of iron metabolism, transferrin saturation, serum iron, ferritin and total iron binding capacity were also measured. Results: Samples were obtained for 237 children. A multiple stepwise logistic regression analysis identified CHr and iron serum as the only parameters independently associated to iron deficiency (P&lt;0.05). CHr was the strongest predictor of iron deficiency and iron deficiency anaemia. Conclusions: Our study indicates that the measurement of CHr may be a reliable method to assess deficiencies in tissue iron supply. CHr together with a complete blood count may provide an alternative to the traditional biochemical panel for the diagnosis of iron deficiency in children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdés Sánchez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogales Espert, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Bértolo, J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos González, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Laso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La ferropenia es una de las deficiencias nutricionales más frecuentes en la primera infancia. En las últimas décadas se han incorporado nuevas técnicas para el diagnóstico de la ferropenia a los clásicos marcadores bioquímicos; sin embargo, no se conoce bien qué parámetros deberían incluirse en un panel para identificar el déficit de hierro y la anemia ferropénica. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron los siguientes: a) determinar los valores de los parámetros hematológicos eritrocíticos y del contenido de hemoglobina eritrocitaria (CHr), así como de ferritina, de sideremia, de saturación de transferrina, de transferrina y de capacidad total de fijación de hierro, con objeto de analizar su relevancia en la identificación de la ferropenia en la muestra, y b) determinar qué parámetros hematológicos y bioquímicos son predictores independientes de ferropenia en la muestra estudiada. Pacientes y métodos: La muestra procedía de una población urbana con una edad comprendida entre los 6 meses y los 14 años, de ambos sexos. El protocolo de estudio incluía un cuestionario y la realización de una analítica que constaba de hemograma con CHr y bioquímica del metabolismo férrico. Resultados: Se incluyó a 237 niños. El análisis de regresión logística identificó al CHr y al hierro como los únicos parámetros independientemente asociados al diagnóstico de ferropenia (p&lt;0,05); la reducción relativa del riesgo fue más significativa para el parámetro CHr. Conclusiones: Este estudio apoya que un panel basado exclusivamente en parámetros hematológicos, con la inclusión del CHr, es una alternativa válida al panel conjunto hematológico y bioquímico tradicionalmente empleado para identificar el déficit de hierro y la anemia ferropénica en la infancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(2): 95-102, ago. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de los parámetros hematológicos y bioquímicos para identificar la ferropenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22302^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1800^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22198^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32967^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
