<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144041</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asthma among children in Latin America</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence of respiratory symptoms related to asthma in children from Latin America has been largely ignored. This region participated in phases I and III of the International Study of Asthma and Allergies in Childhood (ISAAC) with 17 participating centers in phase I and 78 centers in phase III. Data were obtained on asthma, rhinitis and eczema from countries and centers with markedly different climactic, cultural and environmental conditions and socioeconomic development. The results for phase I are presented herein because data from phase III are currently being revised at the ISAAC international data control center and will be officially available in the second half of 2004. Phase I provided important information on the prevalence of asthma in the participating countries and demonstrated wide variation among centers in the same country and among countries. The participating Latin American countries are all developing countries and share more or less the same problems related to low socioeconomic status. Therefore, the results and figures should be analyzed within that context. The range for accumulative and current asthma symptoms in children from the Latin American countries that participated in phase I (89,000) were as follows: the prevalence of asthma ranged from 5.5 % to 28 % in children aged 13-14 years and from 4.1 % to 26.9 % in children aged 6-7 years. The prevalence of wheezing in the previous 12 months ranged from 6.6 % to 27 % in children aged 13-14 years and from 8.6 % to 32.1 % in children aged 6-7 years. The high figures for asthma in a region with a high level of gastrointestinal parasites infestation, a high burden of acute respiratory and gastrointestinal infections occurring early in life, severe environmental and hygiene problems, suggest that these factors, considered as protective in other (developed) regions of the world, do not have the same effect in this region. Furthermore, those aggressive environmental conditions acting together from very early in life might condition different asthmatic phenotypes with more severe clinical presentation in infancy (first 2 years of life), lower atopy and enhanced airways reactivity. The present study indicates that the prevalence of asthma and related symptoms in Latin America is as high and variable as described previously for industrialized or developed regions of the world and that the environmental risk factors, mainly related with poverty, could be responsible for the different clinical and functional presentations of asthma in children from developing regions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mallol, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Apenas se ha concedido importancia a la prevalencia de síntomas respiratorios relacionados con el asma en niños de Latinoamérica. La región participó en las fases I y III del International Estudio Internacional sobre Asma y Alergias en la Infancia (Study of Asthma and Allergies in Childhood, ISAAC), con 17 centros participantes en la fase I y 78 centros en la fase III; en dicho estudio se obtuvieron datos sobre asma, rinitis y eccema de países y centros con condiciones sumamente diferentes en cuanto a clima, desarrollo socioeconómico y situación cultural y ambiental. Se exponen aquí los resultados de la fase I porque los datos de la fase III se están revisando en el Centro Internacional de Control de Datos de ISAAC y se darán a conocer oficialmente durante el segundo trimestre de 2004. La fase I proporcionó información importante acerca de la prevalencia del asma en los países participantes, información que reveló una considerable variación en las cifras entre los centros en un mismo país y entre países. Todos los países de esta región se encuentran en vías de desarrollo y comparten más o menos los mismos problemas relacionados con el bajo nivel socioeconómico. Así pues, hay que analizar los resultados y las cifras dentro de este contexto. La variedad de síntomas asmáticos acumulados y actuales en los niños de los países latinoamericanos que participaron en la fase I (89.000) fue la siguiente: en niños de 13-14 años, la prevalencia de asma en algún momento varió entre el 5,5 % y el 28 %, mientras que la prevalencia de sibilancias en los últimos 12 meses osciló entre el 6,6 % y el 27 %. En niños de 6-7 años, la prevalencia de asma en algún momento varió entre el 4,1 % y el 26,9 %, mientras que la prevalencia de sibilancias en los últimos 12 meses osciló entre el 8,6 % y el 32,1 % (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);32(3): 100-103, mayo 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144041</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El asma en niños de América Latina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3926</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
