<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60192</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implantation technique of the artificial urinary sphincter &#147;flow secure&#153;&#148; in the bulbar urethra</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Artificial urinary sphincter &#147;FlowSecureTM&#148; is a prosthesis designed for stress urinary incontinence that has achieved excellent results. Although implantation is easy, some urologist used to other prosthesis may find difficult the change to this new technique. This article shows how easily and quickly this new sphincter can be implanted and discuss the differences with the artificial sphincter AMS-800TM.METHODS: Following the case of a patient who was implanted artificial urinary sphincter &#147;FlowSecureTM&#148; in our center we describe with pictures the technique of implantation and give some advices to make this quicker and easier   RESULTS: Surgical time was 90 minutes. Patient presen-ted uneventful recovery, urethral catheter was removed 24 hours after surgery and discharge was done 72 hours after surgery. Three months after implantation patient describes complete resolution of his stress urinary incontinence.CONCLUSIONS: Artificial urinary sphincter &#147;FlowSecu-reTM&#148; is easy and quick to implant, and as its use is extended we would compare if results are better than those of the AMS-800TM model(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cecchini Rosell, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bestard Vallejo, Juan E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Montes, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mir Maresma, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morote Robles, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El esfínter urinario FlowSecureTM es una prótesis para la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo que ha proporcionado unos excelentes resultados hasta el día de hoy. Si bien su colocación es sencilla, los urólogos acostumbrados a la colocación de otros tipos de prótesis pueden encontrar inconveniente el cambio a esta nueva técnica. Este artículo pretende demostrar que este nuevo esfínter se puede colocar de forma rápida y sencilla, así como discutir las diferencias respecto del modelo AMS-800TM.MÉTODOS: A raíz de un paciente al que se colocó el esfínter urinario FlowSecureTM en nuestro centro se describe mediante dibujos la técnica de colocación y se apuntan ciertos consejos prácticos que hacen más fácil y rápida su colocación.RESULTADO: El tiempo quirúrgico fue de 90 minutos. El paciente presentó un postoperatorio correcto, retirándose la sonda vesical a las 24 horas y siendo dado de alta a las 72 horas. A los 3 meses de la intervención el paciente refiere resolución completa de su incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo.CONCLUSIONES: El esfínter urinario FlowSecureTM resulta una prótesis de colocación rápida y sencilla, y a medida que su utilización se vaya extendiendo podremos valorar si sus resultados a largo plazo son mejores que los del modelo AMS-800TM(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(3): 195-200, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60192</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnica de implantación del esfínter urinario artificial FlowsecureTM en uretra bulbar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29753^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29753^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
