<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113088</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional perception as a stable predictor of psychosocial adjustment during adolescence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Emotions are a very valuable source of information for our adjustment and well-being. Within our skills to process the emotional information, emotional perception is fundamental to begin such process successfully. Nevertheless, the majority of the studies conducted in this area have used adult or clinical samples. In this work we investigated through a prospective one-year longitudinal study the relation between emotional perception and psycho-social adjustment in a secondary student sample. The results showed emotional perception as a stable predictor of higher personal adjustment and lower emotional imbalance and clinical maladjustment. The emotional perception ability also appeared as a significant predictor of dependent variables, even when the variable criterion at time 1 was controlled. Significant variation was found depending on sex and age. Possible educational implications and future lines of research on emotional perception and emotional intelligence are discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomera, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Aranda, Desiree</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Salguero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las emociones son una fuente muy valiosa de información para nuestra adaptación y bienestar. Dentro de nuestras habilidades para procesar la información emocional, la literatura científica ha mostrado cómo la percepción emocional es fundamental para comenzar dicho proceso con éxito. Sin embargo, la mayoría de los estudios realizados en este ámbito han utilizado muestras adultas o clínicas. En este trabajo investigamos, mediante un estudio longitudinal prospectivo, la influencia de la percepción emocional sobre el ajuste psicosocial de una muestra de estudiantes de secundaria. Los resultados muestran que la habilidad para percibir emociones es un predictor estable de un menor desajuste clínico y emocional y de un mayor ajuste personal. Además, estos resultados se mantienen incluso tras controlar los niveles previos de ajuste. Igualmente, encontramos importantes diferencias de sexo y edad en la relación entre percepción emocional y el ajuste psicosocial. Se discute acerca de las posibles implicaciones educativas de los resultados y de futuras líneas de trabajo en el campo de la percepción emocional y la inteligencia emocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;20(1): 43-58, ene.-abr. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La percepción emocional como predictor estable del ajuste psicosocial en la adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
