<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100540</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Competências do gestor hospitalar: estudo em um hospital público brasileiro</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to identify know hospital manager&#146;s&#146; competencies (knowledge, skills and attitudes), so the objectives were: to identify the most important competences according to the professionals; measure what skills are most developed in these professionals, and find which competences need to be improved. A descriptive study was made, using the Lazarotto model (2001) with 24 managers of a Brazilian public hospital. The data showed that, typically, those skills identified as most important are also the most developed - IT professionals. However, there are several gaps in the skills of hospital managers, and the main skills are: public health policies, information systems, development planning, strategic management. The skills that need to be developed most are: work force management, to be an agent of innovatiion and change, troubleshooting, and management programs designed to motivate the team. Finally, the attitudes withthe biggest gaps are being a leading educator, developing initiative and autonomy of the team, encouraging the creativity of staff and community groups to be creative and encouraging teamwork. In short, the work served as an initial analysis to identify gaps in the training of professionals and pointed out that among the three types of skills, attitude of the group is considered the most important by professionals and therefore deserves the most greater attention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Battistella, LF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baratto, JS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grohmann, MZ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es conocer las competencias (conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes) del director del hospital, y sus objetivos son: identificar las competencias más importantes de acuerdo a los profesionales; medir las habilidades más desarrolladas en los profesionales encuestados, destacar las competencias con mayores carencias. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo, utilizando el modelo de Lazarotto (2001) con 24 directivos de un hospital público brasileño. Los datos mostraron que, por lo general, las habilidades identificadas como las más importantes son también las más desarrolladas por los profesionales. Sin embargo, hay varias lagunas en las competencias de los directores de hospitales, siendo las principales en: políticas de salud pública, los sistemas de información, la planificación del desarrollo, la gestión estratégica. Las habilidades que más necesitan ser desarrolladas son: dirigir el equipo de trabajo, ser agente de innovación y cambio, solucionar problemas y administrar los programas diseñados para motivar al equipo. Finalmente, las actitudes con mayores lagunas son: ser un líder educador, desarrollar la iniciativa y la autonomía del equipo y de los grupos comunitarios; ser creativo y estimular el trabajo en equipo. En resumen, el trabajo es un primer análisis para identificar las lagunas en la formación de estos profesionales señalando que entre los tres tipos de competencias, el grupo de la Actitud es considerado el más importante por los profesionales y, por lo tanto, el que merece una mayor atención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(26): 191-208, abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100540</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Competencias del gestor hospitalario: estudio en un hospital público brasileño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13034^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16616^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16616^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
