<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037468</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orthorexia nervosa. A new eating behavior disorder?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">New eating behavior disorders such as bigorexia (muscle dysmorphia) and orthorexia are appearing in developed countries. These disorders have not been officially recognized so that they are not classified as independent entities.     The term orthorexia comes from the Greek word orthos (straight, proper) and orexia (appetite). It is characterized by the pathological obsession for biologically pure food, which leads to important dietary restrictions. Orthorexic patients exclude foods from their diets that they consider to be impure because they have herbicides, pesticides or artificial substances and they worry in excess about the techniques and materials used in the food elaboration. This obsession leads to loss of social relationships and affective dissatisfactions which, in turn, favors obsessive concern about food. In orthorexia, that patient initially wants to improve his/her health, treat a disease or lose weight. Finally, the diet becomes the most important part of their lives. We present a clinical case that responds to the characteristics of orthorexia. The differential diagnosis with chronic delusional disorder, anorexia nervosa and obsessive-compulsive disorder is carried out</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bote Bonaechea, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Rial, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalina Zamora, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En las sociedades desarrolladas están apareciendo nuevos trastornos de la conducta alimentaria como la vigorexia y la ortorexia. Estos trastornos no han sido reconocidos oficialmente, por lo que no aparecen clasificados como entidades independientes.     El término ortorexia deriva del griego orthos (justo, recto) y orexia (apetito). Se caracteriza por la obsesión patológica por la comida biológicamente pura, lo que lleva a importantes restricciones alimentarias. Los ortoréxicos excluyen de la dieta alimentos que consideran impuros por llevar herbicidas, pesticidas u otras sustancias artificiales y se preocupan en exceso por las técnicas y materiales empleados en la elaboración de los alimentos. Esta obsesión conlleva a una pérdida de relaciones sociales y a una insatisfacción afectiva que a su vez favorece la preocupación obsesiva por la comida. En la ortorexia el paciente quiere inicialmente mejorar su salud, tratar una enfermedad o perder peso. Finalmente, la dieta se convierte en el centro de su vida. Presentamos un caso clínico que responde a las características de la ortorexia. Se realiza el diagnóstico diferencial con el trastorno delirante crónico, la anorexia nerviosa y el trastorno obsesivo-compulsivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(1): 66-68, ene.-feb. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ortorexia nerviosa. ¿Un nuevo trastorno de la conducta alimentaria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
