<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143055</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of secondary hyperparathyroidism in patients with stage 3 and 4 chronic kidney disease seen in internal medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Despite the high prevalence of chronic kidney disease in the elderly population, few data are available on the frequency of secondary hyperparathyroidism in the Spanish population affected by this problem. We undertook a study on this issue in patients attending the internal medicine departments in our area. Design and methods: An observational, cross-sectional survey performed at internal medicine departments on 415 patients with stage 3 and 4 chronic kidney disease. Clinical history and risk factors were collected using a standardized protocol. Serum creatinine, phosphate, calcium, intact parathormone (PTH) and 25-hydroxy-cholecalciferol (25-OH-vitD) levels were measured in all patients. Results: Among stage 3 patients, 62.9% had PTH levels &amp;#8805; 70 pg/mL and 32.7% levels &amp;#8805; 110 pg/mL. Median PTH level in stage 4 patients was 120 pg/mL (p &lt; 0.001), and 77.9% of these patients had PTH &amp;#8805; 70 pg/mL (p &lt; 0.001) and 54.1% &amp;#8805; 110 pg/mL (p = 0.015). Adequate 25-hydroxy-cholecalciferol levels were found in only 7.2% of stage 3 patients and 4.1% of stage 4 patients. Only 7.2% of stage 3 patients had hyperphosphatemia, as compared to 25.4% of stage 4 patients (p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: Hyperparathyroidism is a common complication of stage 3 and 4 chronic kidney disease which is not associated to detectable changes in serum calcium and phosphate levels. It is therefore advisable to measure PTH levels in all patients with decreased glomerular filtration rate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roberto Robles, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Morales, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bureo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adrados, Gaspar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arévalo, Jose Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: A pesar de la elevada prevalencia de insuficiencia renal en la población anciana existen escasos datos sobre frecuencia del hiperparatiroidismo secundario en la población española afecta de este trastorno. Nos propusimos estudiar este aspecto a partir de las personas atendidas por los servicios de medicina interna de nuestra área. Diseño y métodos: Estudio transversal observacional realizado en servicios de medicina interna. Se incluyeron 415 pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica estadios 3 y 4. Se recogieron antecedentes y factores de riesgo según un protocolo estandarizado. En todos los casos se determinaron niveles séricos de creatinina, fósforo, calcio, parathormona (PTH) intacta y 25-hidroxi-colecalciferol (25-OH-vitD). Resultados: De los pacientes en estadio 3 el 62,9% presentaban una PTH &amp;#8805; 70 pg/ml, y en el 32,7% los valores eran &amp;#8805; 110 pg/ml. En los enfermos en estadio 4 la mediana de la concentración de PTH era 120 pg/ml (p &lt; 0,001). De ellos, el 77,9% tenía una PTH &amp;#8805; 70 pg/ml (p &lt; 0,001) y el 54,1% una PTH &amp;#8805; 110 pg/ml (p = 0,015). Los valores de 25-OH-vitD eran adecuados en el 7,2% de los pacientes en estadio 3 y en el 4,1% de los de estadio 4. Solamente el 7,2% de los pacientes en estadio 3 tenían hiperfosfatemia, frente al 25,4% en estadio 4 (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: El hiperparatiroidismo es una complicación frecuente de la insuficiencia renal crónica en los estadios 3 y 4, sin que aparezca alteración detectable en los niveles de calcemia o fosfatemia, por lo que es aconsejable determinar PTH en todos los pacientes con filtrado glomerular disminuido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;62(7): 300-305, ago.-sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143055</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del hiperparatiroidismo secundario en pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica estadios 3 y 4 atendidos en medicina interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
