<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139808</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Deficiency, disability, neurology and television series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The portrayal of neurological disability and defi ciency on television has not always been approached in the same way, but has instead tended to refl ect the standpoint taken by society with regard to these issues and how they are dealt with according to the prevailing conceptions and values at each particular time. Aims. To address the appearance of neurological pathologies in television series and to ponder on the image they have in such contexts. Development. Defi ciency and disability of neurological origin have often been depicted on television in series, telefi lms and documentaries, and in a wide variety of ways. Here we examine diff erent television series and how they have dealt with neurological pathology, its diagnosis and its treatment, as well as the fi gure of the healthcare professional and social-familial adaptation. Examples cited include series such as House MD, Glee, American Horror Story, Homeland or Game of Thrones. Conclusions. Television series are a useful tool for making some neurological pathologies better known to the public and for dispelling the myths surrounding others, provided that the pathologies are dealt with in a realistic manner, which is not always the case. More care should be taken with regard to the way in which health professionals are portrayed in television series, as it is not always done correctly and may mislead viewers, who take what they see on the TV as being real (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano de la Cuerda, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, Ariadna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collado Vázquez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El enfoque de la deficiencia y la discapacidad neurológica en la televisión no ha sido algo unívoco, sino que ha reflejado la postura de la sociedad ante estas cuestiones y cómo se tratan éstas, desde la óptica de las concepciones y valores dominantes en cada momento. Objetivos. Abordar la aparición de la patología neurológica en las series de televisión y reflexionar sobre su imagen en dicho contexto. Desarrollo. La deficiencia y la discapacidad de origen neurológico se han reflejado ampliamente en el medio televisivo en series, telefilmes y documentales, con un tratamiento desigual. Se aborda el enfoque que ha tenido en diferentes series televisivas la patología neurológica, su diagnóstico, su tratamiento, así como la figura de los profesionales sanitarios y la adaptación socio-familiar, y se citan, a modo de ejemplo, series como House, Glee, American Horror Story, Homeland o Juego de tronos. Conclusiones. Las series de televisión son una herramienta útil para dar a conocer algunas patologías neurológicas y para desmitificar otras, siempre que dichas patologías se aborden de manera realista, hecho que no siempre ocurre. Habría que cuidar el tratamiento que reciben los profesionales de la salud en las series de televisión, pues no siempre es correcto, y eso puede llevar a errores entre los telespectadores, que aceptan lo que ven en la pequeña pantalla como real (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(11): 517-526, 1 jun., 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139808</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deficiencia, discapacidad, neurología y series de televisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14068^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14068^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
