<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149830</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Absence of cystatin C involvement in ventricular remodelling and heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystatin C (CysC) is a protease encoded by housekeeping genes. Although its prognostic value in heart failure (HF) is well known, it is debatable whether this value is due to the greater accuracy of CysC in calculating the glomerular filtration rate or to its involvement in pathological ventricular remodelling. The aim of this study was to determine whether CysC expression changes in the myocardium of foetuses of different ages and in the myocardium of adults with various cardiovascular diseases, as well as to analyse the correlation between its serum concentrations and cardiac structure and morphology in a patient group with HF. Patients and methods. We analysed the correlations (Pearson's r and Spearman's test) between the serum CysC levels and echocardiographic parameters of 351 patients with HF. We also performed immunohistochemical staining for CysC, metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9) and desmin in 9 cardiac tissue samples from autopsies of 4 foetuses of different gestational ages and 5 healthy adults or adults with cardiovascular disease. Results. For the patients with HF, there was no correlation between the CysC concentrations and the cardiac parameters measured by 2D echocardiography. The immunohistochemistry showed a weak background staining for CysC in all samples, regardless of age and the presence or absence of cardiovascular diseases. Conclusions. Our results suggest that CysC does not have a significant role in the pathological remodelling of the left ventricle in HF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Calvo, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacambra Blasco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Marteles, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Josa Laorden, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Figal, DA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio López, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castiella Muruzábal, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Búcar Barjud, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cistatina C (CisC) es una proteasa codificada por genes de mantenimiento («housekeeping genes»). Aunque su valor pronóstico en la insuficiencia cardiaca (IC) es bien conocido, se debate si es debido a su mayor precisión en la estimación del filtrado glomerular, o a su implicación en el remodelado ventricular patológico. El propósito de este estudio fue comprobar si la expresión de CisC se modificaba en el miocardio de fetos de diferentes edades y en el de adultos con diversas enfermedades cardiovasculares, así como analizar la correlación entre sus concentraciones séricas y la estructura y morfología cardiaca en un grupo de pacientes con IC. Pacientes y métodos. Se analizaron las correlaciones (test de Pearson y Spearman) entre la CisC sérica y los parámetros ecocardiográficos de 351 pacientes con IC. También se realizó una tinción inmunohistoquímica para CisC, metaloproteinasa 9 (MMP-9) y desmina en 9 muestras de tejido cardiaco procedentes de las autopsias de 4 fetos con diferente edad gestacional y 5 adultos sanos o con enfermedad cardiovascular. Resultados. En pacientes con IC no se encontró correlación entre las concentraciones de CisC y los parámetros cardiacos medidos por ecocardiografía 2D. La inmunohistoquímica mostró una débil tinción de fondo para CisC en todas las muestras, independientemente de la edad y la presencia o no de enfermedades cardiovasculares. Conclusiones. Nuestros resultados sugieren que la CisC no tiene un papel significativo en el remodelado patológico del ventrículo izquierdo en la IC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;216(2): 55-61, mar. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ausencia de implicación de la cistatina C en el remodelado ventricular y la insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13581^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33914^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33914^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13581^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5443^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53168^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5443^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53168</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
