<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91324</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carbon monoxide intoxication in the 061 Aragón out-of-hospital emergency services. Five year study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Carbon monoxide intoxication (CO) is a serious public healthproblem that results in deaths every year. The unspecificnature of its symptoms makes diagnosis difficult, often leadingto diagnosis being dependant on the expertise and knowledgeof professionals.Objective: to describe the incidence of intoxications due toCO, fumes, gases and other agents treated by the 061 Aragonout-of-hospital emergency services over five years accordingto sociodemographic variables.Material and methods: descriptive, longitudinal and retrospectivestudy performed in the 061 Aragón out-of-hospitalemergency services between june 2003 and june 2008. Afterreviewing clinical histories, information was collected on casesof intoxication due to carbon monoxide and fumes, gasesand other agents. Three working hypotheses that associate intoxicationswith the season of the year, geographic area andsex were established.Results: it was observed that over 60% of intoxications due toCO and fumes, gases and other agents took place during thecold months, the province of Teruel having the highest rate ofemergency calls, followed by Huesca and Zaragoza. Mean ratesof both types of intoxication yielded similar results for bothsexes.Conclusions: the variable nature of the presentation of theseevents throughout the year is confirmed, with no statisticallysignificant differences observed in terms of sex or province ofresidence. In accordance with other similar studies, this couldbe the starting point of future analytical studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mir Ramos, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azón López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La intoxicación por monóxido de carbono (CO) constituye ungrave problema de salud pública que anualmente se cobra víctimas.La inespecificidad de sus síntomas dificulta el diagnóstico,que en muchos casos depende de la pericia y conocimientosde los profesionales.Objetivo: describir la incidencia de intoxicaciones por CO ypor humos, gases y otros atendidas por el Servicio de EmergenciasExtrahospitalarias 061 Aragón, a lo largo de cincoaños, en función de variables sociodemográficas.Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo, longitudinal y retrospectivo,realizado en el Servicio de Emergencias Extrahospitalarias061 Aragón entre junio de 2003 y junio de 2008.Tras la revisión de historias clínicas se recogieron los casos deintoxicación por monóxido de carbono y humos, gases y otros,planteándonos tres hipótesis de trabajo que relacionan los sucesosde intoxicación con la estación del año, el área geográficay el sexo.Resultados: se observó que más del 60% de las intoxicacionespor CO y humos gases y otros ocurrieron en los meses fríos,recogiendo la mayor tasa de avisos la provincia de Teruel, seguidode Huesca y Zaragoza. Las tasas medias de ambos tiposde intoxicaciones arrojaron resultados similares para ambossexos.Conclusiones: se confirma el carácter variable de la presentaciónde estos sucesos a lo largo del año, no apreciándose diferenciasestadísticamente significativas por razón de géneroo provincia de residencia. Siguiendo la línea de otros trabajossimilares, éste podría ser el punto de partida para futurosestudios analíticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(2): 62-66, mar. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intoxicación por monóxido de carbonoen el servicio de emergencias extrahospitalarias061 Aragón. Estudio de cinco años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2288^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2288^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
