<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59565</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conjuctival tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ABSTRACTConjunctival tumors are one of the most frequent ofthe eye and adnexa. They comprise a large varietyof conditions, from benign lesions such as nevus orpapiloma, to malignant lesions such as epidermoidcarcinoma or melanoma which may threaten visualfunction and the life of the patient. They can arisefrom any cellular component, but the most frequentare of epithelial and melanocytic origin. Early diagnosisis essential for preventing ocular and systemicspread and to preserve visual function. In this paperwe review the clinical characteristics of the mostfrequent conjunctival tumors, and we discuss tumormanagement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Becerra, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saornil, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores de la conjuntiva son unos de los más frecuentes del ojo y anejos. Abarcan un amplioespectro desde lesiones benignas como el papilomaa otras malignas que pueden poner en peligro lafunción visual y la vida del paciente, como el carcinomaepidermoide y el melanoma. Pueden surgir decualquiera de las células que componen la conjuntivaaunque los más frecuentes son los de origen epitelialy melanocítico. El diagnóstico precoz es fundamentalpara prevenir la extensión ocular y sistémicay para preservar la función visual. En este artículose revisan las características clínicas de lostumores conjuntivales más frecuentes y se discutesu tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(1): 7-22, ene. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59565</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores de la conjuntiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3254^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3556^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3254^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31588^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31679^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3254^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3254^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31588^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31588^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3556^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
