<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113493</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654x</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation by SPECT-CT of an incidental finding of a thymoma and breast cancer in a myocardial perfusion SPECT with 99mTc-MIBI</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of a 78-year-old female with effort angina. A myocardial perfusion SPECT (MPS) showed increased tracer uptake in two synchronic tumor lesions, a thymoma and a breast cancer. This case highlights the contribution of SPECT-CT in the characterization of these findings and its essential role in rapid decision-making. The patient underwent surgery of both lesions that had gone undetected prior to the conduction of the MPS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olmos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamazo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz-Esteban, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Talavera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos una paciente de 78 años, derivada para estudio de angor de esfuerzo, que en el SPECT de perfusión miocárdica presentó captación aumentada del trazador en dos lesiones tumorales sincrónicas: un timoma y un cáncer de mama. Este caso clínico pone de manifiesto la aportación del SPECT-CT en la caracterización de estos hallazgos y su papel esencial para una rápida toma de decisiones. La paciente fue intervenida quirúrgicamente de las dos lesiones, insospechadas previamente a la realización del SPECT miocárdico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);32(4): 260-262, jul.-ago.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración mediante SPECT-CT de un timoma y un carcinoma de mama hallados de forma casual en un SPECT de perfusión miocardica con 99mTc-MIBI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14332^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14332^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
