<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122462</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic factors for treatment response in patients with lupus nephritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify prognostic factors associated with response to induction therapy in lupus nephritis (LN) according to the stage of treatment. Material and methods: We analyzed a retrospective cohort of patients of systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) with biopsy-proven LN from January 2001 to December 2008. LN was classified according to WHO. All patients received induction therapy and had a minimum follow-up period of two years. We analyzed 18 clinical and laboratory variables that potentially have predictive value for response to therapy. We identified predictors of therapeutic response at 6, 12 and 24 months by univariate and multivariate analysis; odds ratios (OR) with confidence intervals (CI) 95% were also calculated. Results: We reviewed the clinical records of 168 patients, 141 female (84%). The response rate was 69% at 6 months, 86.9% at 12 months and 79.7% at 24 months. Multivariate analysis found that &gt; 25 years of age at diagnosis of LN and the presence of microhematuria were factors associated with good response to induction treatment. At 12 months, baseline creatinine clearance &lt; 30 ml/min was associated with a poor response to treatment. Finally at 24 months, delay in treatment was a predictor of poor response to treatment and the presence of a histological proliferative NL and low C3 were associated with good response to treatment. Conclusions: There are treatment-modifiable factors that can alter aberrant immunologic activity of NF. Therefore, intensive early treatment of lupus nephritis is associated with favorable response to two years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saavedra, Miguel Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Reyes, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jara, Luis Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Hernández, Dafhne</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angeles, Ulises</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar los factores asociados con la respuesta al tratamiento en pacientes con nefropatía lúpica. Material y métodos: Se analizó una cohorte retrospectiva de pacientes con lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) y nefritis lúpica (NL) corroborada por biopsia, clasificada de acuerdo a la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) de junio del 2001 a diciembre del 2008. Todos los pacientes recibieron terapia de inducción a la remisión y fueron seguidos al menos 2 años. Se correlacionaron variables clínicas y de laboratorio con potencial valor predictivo de respuesta terapéutica, a los 6, 12 y 24 meses. Resultados: Se incluyó a 168 pacientes, 84% mujeres. La tasa de respuesta al tratamiento fue del 69,2% a los 6 meses, el 86,9% a los 12 meses y el 79,7% a los 2 años. En el análisis multivariado se encontró que la edad &gt; 25 a&#152;nos en el momento del diagnóstico de la NL y la presencia de microhematuria fueron variables asociadas con buena respuesta al tratamiento de inducción a la remisión. A los 12 meses, una  epuración de creatinina basal &lt; 30 ml/min se asoció a mala respuesta al tratamiento. Finalmente, a los 24 meses, el retraso en el tratamiento fue un factor predictor de mala respuesta y la presencia de una forma histológica proliferativa de NL y de C3 bajo se asociaron con buena respuesta al tratamiento. Conclusiones: Existen factores modificables con el tratamiento que pueden alterar la actividad inmunológica aberrante de la NF. Por ello, la intervención terapéutica intensa en los primeros 3 meses de inicio de la nefritis puede llevar a una respuesta favorable a los 2 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);10(3): 164-169, mayo-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predictores de respuesta al tratamiento en pacientes con nefritis lúpica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
