<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129435</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of a chronic care program in Gerona (CRONIGICAT)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the utility and viability of a chronic care program. Design: Cross-sectional descriptive study with qualitative and quantitative evaluation. Setting and participants: 26 primary care teams (PCT) from the Catalan health service of Gerona. Interventions: 20 projects within the program. Start 2011. Main outcome measures: The degree of development of the program, consensus indicators for chronic care, and the Instrument for the Assessment of Chronic Care Models (Instrumento de Evaluación de Modelos de Atención ante la Cronicidad [IEMAC]). Results: Evaluation of the degree of development: 75% of projects were partially or fully implemented, with a high degree of development in 71% of the PCT. An increasing tendency was found in the consensus indicators for process (patients contacted 48 hours after hospital discharge, population attended in chronic care programs and with the highest risk stratification).There was a slight decrease in the consensus indicators for effectiveness (readmissions, mean length of hospital stay, avoidable hospital admissions, pharmaceutical expenditure, patients attended in the emergency department, and mortality). The dimensions receiving the highest scores on the IEMAC were those evaluating information systems and clinical decision support, while those receiving the lowest scores were community health and self-care. Conclusions: When assessing the utility of CRONIGICAT, we believe that progress has been made mainly in its implantation, which has acted as a catalyst for a self-directed shift to a better chronic care model and has identified areas for improvement. We believe that the CRONIGICAT is viable and sustainable, since its actions and projects are integrated within routine clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quesada Sabaté, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>German Rebull, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balló Peña, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canet Ponsa, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avellana Revuelta, Esteve</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Requejo, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la utilidad y viabilidad del Programa CRONIGICAT. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Método de evaluación cualitativo y cuantitativo. Emplazamiento y participantes: 26 equipos de atención primaria (EAP) del Institut Català de la Salut de Girona. Intervenciones: 20 proyectos dentro del programa. Inicio 2011. Mediciones principales: Grado de desarrollo del programa, indicadores de consenso para la atención a la cronicidad y IEMAC (Instrumento de Evaluación de Modelos de Atención ante la Cronicidad). Resultados: Valoración del grado de desarrollo: 75% de proyectos implementados parcial o totalmente, con un desarrollo alto en 71% de los EAP. Tendencia a aumentar los indicadores de consenso del proceso (pacientes contactados 48 h tras el alta hospitalaria, población atendida en programas de atención a la cronicidad y con estratificación de riesgo más alto). Ligero descenso interanual de los indicadores de consenso de efectividad (reingresos, estancia media hospitalaria, hospitalizaciones evitables, gasto farmacéutico, pacientes atendidos en urgencias y mortalidad). Dimensiones mejor puntuadas del IEMAC las que evalúan los sistemas de información y el apoyo en la toma de decisiones clínicas y las peor puntuadas son la salud comunitaria y el autocuidado. Conclusiones: Respecto a la utilidad del CRONIGICAT, consideramos que existe un avance principalmente a nivel de su implantación, actuando como catalizador para el cambio autodirigido a un mejor modelo de atención a la cronicidad y identificando aspectos de mejora. Creemos que es viable y sostenible al estar sus acciones y proyectos integrados dentro de la actividad asistencial habitual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(supl.3): 24-32, jun. 2014. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129435</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa de atención a la cronicidad en Girona (CRONIGICAT)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
