<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130553</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Substance P, NK-1 receptor in the progression of pediatric cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cancer is he leading cause of death in pediatrics. Despite the great efforts made in cancer research in the past two decades the therapeutic progress has been unfortunately very limited. Thus, it is crucial to seek new avenues of scientific research to address this challenge. It is therefore necessary to recue and expand the concept of &#147;magic bullet&#148; of Paul Ehrlich for new cancer treatments. It is known that the peptide substance P (SP)  plays an important role in the progression of cancer. The SP after binding to the Neurokinin-1 (NK-1) receptor induces tumor cell proliferation, angiogenesis and migration of tumor cells for invasion and metastasis. In contrast, the NK-1 receptor antagonist after binding to NK-1 receptor blocks SP functions so inhibits tumor cell proliferations, induces tumor cell death apoptosis pathway inhibits the angiogenesis and the migration of tumor cells. These antagonists are broad-spectrum antitumor drugs. In conclusion, the NK-1 receptor and the NK-1 receptor antagonists could be considered as a new therapeutic target and a new generation of anticancer drug, respectively in cancer treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La primera causa de muerte en pediatría es el cáncer. A pesar de los grandes esfuerzos realizados en la investigación sobre el cáncer, en las últimas dos décadas el progreso terapeutico ha sido, lamentablemente muy limitado. Por ello, es crucial buscar nuevas vías de investigación capacer de dar soluciones a este reto científico. Por este motivo, es necesario rescatar y ampliar el concepto de &#147;bala mágica&#148; de Paul Ehrlich para los nuevos tratamiento del cáncer. Es conocido que el péptido sustancia (SP) desempeña un papel importante en la progresión del cáncer. La SP, al unirse al receptor neurokinina-1 (NK-1), induce proliferación de las células tumorales, angiogénesis y migración de las células tumorales para invadir y metastatizar. Al contrario, los antagonistas de los receptores NK-1 bloquean las funciones de la SP y por eso inhiben la proliferación de las células tumorales, producen muerte de las células tumorales por apoptosis, inhiben la angiogénesis e impiden la migración de las células tumorales. Estos antagonistas son antitumorales de amplio espectro. En conclusión, el receptor NK-1 y los antagonistas de los receptores NK-1 pueden ser considerados como una nueva diana terapeutica y como una nueva generación de fármacos respectivamente en el tratamiento del cáncer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;70(5): 262-266, sept.-oct. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sustancia P, el receptor NK-1 en la progresión del cáncer infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31113^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31113^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31113^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
