<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95912</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Capnography for monitoring response to care after out-of-hospital cardiac arrest</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the usefulness of capnography to monitor patients after out-of-hospital cardiorespiratory arrest, interms of the ability of capnography to confirm tracheal intubation and the ability of capnometry to promptly detect return of spontaneous circulation and predict patient recovery. Methods: Preliminary description of the first 30 cases in a prospective study of out-of-hospital cardiorespiratory arrest inelderly non-trauma patients attended by the 7 ambulance units of the SUMMA 112 emergency service in Madrid, Spain,in 2008. Clinical, evolutive and capnographic data were recorded. Results: Seventy percent of the 30 patients were men. The mean (SD) age was 64.5 (16.3) years. A capnogram was observed after the first intubation attempt in 28 cases. In the remaining 2 cases, the absence of a capnogram indicatedes ophageal intubation; correct intubation was accomplished and confirmed on the second try (positive and negativepredictive values, 100%). However, no differences were observed between end-tidal carbon dioxide partial pressure(PETCO2) in the absence or presence of a capnogram with the first and second attempts at intubation. Eight patients recovered. In 5 of them (62.5%), a significant increase in PETCO2 was observed before the change in the electrocardiographic signal and before detection of a carotid pulse (P&lt;.05). Finally, PETCO2 values after cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) were significantly higher in the patients who recovered (33.5 [12.7] mm Hg) than in those who died(15.3 [11.1] mm Hg) (P&lt;.01). After 20 minutes of CPR, PETCO2 was more than 20 mm Hg in all patients who recovered.Conclusions: Capnography monitoring in responding to out-of-hospital cardiorespiratory arrest is useful for confirming correct placement of the endotracheal tube, as indicated by the presence of a capnogram. Capnometry offers the first sign of return of spontaneous circulation in some cases and can be used to predict the success of prolonged CPR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Díez-Picazo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso Matilla, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chico Córdoba, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la eficacia de la monitorización capnográfica en la parada cardiorrespiratoria(PCR) extrahospitalaria, mediante la determinación de la capacidad de la capnografía y la capnometría para confirmar la intubación endotraqueal, la detección precoz de la recuperación de circulación espontánea mediante capnometría y el valor pronóstico de la capnometría sobre la capacidad de recuperación del paciente.Método: Estudio descriptivo preliminar del estudio prospectivo en curso realizado con los 30 primeros casos de PCR no traumática en pacientes mayores de edad atendidos por siete unidades móviles de emergencia del SUMMA 112 durante el año 2008. Se recogieron datos clínicos evolutivos y de la monitorización capnográfica. Resultados: De los 30 pacientes (70% varones, 64,5 ± 16,3 años), en 28 casos se observó capnograma tras el primer intento de intubación y en los dos restantes, la ausencia de capnograma se debió a la intubación esofágica. En ambos se obtuvo capnograma al segundo intento, y confirmó así la correcta intubación (valores predictivos positivo y negativo del100%). No se observó diferencia en los valores de end-tidal CO2 (ETCO2) obtenidos tras el primer intento de intubación en presencia o ausencia de capnograma. De los ocho pacientes recuperados, en cinco de ellos (62,5%) se observó un incremento significativo del ETCO2 anterioral cambio en la monitorización electrocardiográfica y a la detección de pulso carotídeo (p &lt; 0,05). Finalmente, se observó que los valores de ETCO2 al final de la reanimación cardiopulmonar(RCP) fueron significativamente mayores en los pacientes recuperados (33,5 ±12,7 mmHg) que en los fallecidos (15,3 ± 11,1 mmHg; p &lt; 0,01), y fueron mayores de 20 mmHg en todos los pacientes recuperados, tanto a los 20 minutos  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(5): 345-348, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La monitorización capnográfica en la parada cardiaca extrahospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33095^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
