<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159425</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Classification of idiopathic generalised epilepsies in patients over 16 years of age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Idiopathic generalised epilepsies (IGE) are a set of electroclinical syndromes with different phenotypes. Our aim is to analyse those phenotypes in patients over 16 years of age. Patients and methods. We conducted a retrospective analysis of a series of patients with IGE. They were classified as childhood absence epilepsy (CAE), juvenile absence epilepsy (JAE), juvenile myoclonic epilepsy (JME), epilepsy with tonicclonic seizures only (TCSE), epilepsy with eyelid myoclonias and absences (EMA) and pure photogenic epilepsy (PE). Results. We included 308 patients, the majority females (56.8%), in our study. JME was the most prevalent (40.9%), followed by TCSE (30%), JAE (10%), EMA (8.7%), CAE (7.7%) and PE (1.6%). The types of seizures presented by the most patients were tonic-clonic (89.6%), myoclonic (45.4%), absence (31.4%), reflex seizures (13.3%), eyelid myoclonias (12.6%), non-epileptic psychogenic seizures (3.6%) and status epilepticus (1.9%). They all had generalised spike-and-wave discharges in the electroencephalogram (EEG). 19.2% presented asymmetrical discharges and 28.2% showed a photoparoxysmal response. We observed differences between syndromes in polytherapy (p &lt; 0.0001), withdrawal of therapy (p = 0.01) and being seizure-free beyond the age of 50 (p = 0.004). Conclusions. JME was the most frequent. Generalised tonic-clonic seizures were the type of seizures presented by the most patients, followed by myoclonic, absent and reflex seizures. The EEG showed a photoparoxysmal response in over a quarter of the patients, and one in five displayed asymmetrical anomalies. Differences were observed according to the syndrome in polytherapy, persistence of seizures and withdrawal of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sueiras-Gil, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala-Padró, Jacint</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Puig, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamarina, Estevo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Cuevas, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raspall-Chaure, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las epilepsias generalizadas idiopáticas (EGI) son un conjunto de síndromes electroclínicos con distintos fenotipos. Nuestro objetivo es analizar dichos fenotipos en pacientes mayores de 16 años. Pacientes y métodos. Analizamos retrospectivamente una serie de pacientes con EGI. Los clasificamos en epilepsia de ausencias infantil (EAI), epilepsia de ausencias juvenil (EAJ), epilepsia mioclónica juvenil (EMJ), epilepsia con crisis tonicoclónicas sólo (ECTC), epilepsia con ausencias y mioclonías palpebrales (EAM) y epilepsia fotogénica pura (EF). Resultados. Incluimos 308 pacientes, mayoritariamente mujeres (56,8%). La EMJ fue más prevalente (40,9%), seguida de la ECTC (30%), la EAJ (10%), la EAM (8,7%), la EAI (7,7%) y la EF (1,6%). Los tipos de crisis que presentaron más pacientes fueron las tonicoclónicas (89,6%), las mioclónicas (45,4%), las ausencias (31,4%), las crisis reflejas (13,3%), las mioclonías palpebrales (12,6%), las crisis psicógenas no epilépticas (3,6%) y el estado epiléptico (1,9%). Todos tenían descargas punta-onda generalizada en el electroencefalograma (EEG). El 19,2% presentó descargas asimétricas y el 28,2%, respuesta fotoparoxística. Observamos diferencias entre síndromes en politerapia (p &lt; 0,0001), retirada de tratamiento (p = 0,01) y estar libres de crisis por encima de los 50 años (p = 0,004). Conclusiones. La EMJ fue la EGI más frecuente. Las crisis tonicoclónicas generalizadas fueron el tipo de crisis que presentaron más pacientes, seguidas de las mioclónicas, las ausencias y las crisis reflejas. El EEG mostró en más de una cuarta parte de los pacientes una respuesta fotoparoxística, y en uno de cada cinco, anomalías asimétricas. Se observaron diferencias según el síndrome en politerapia, persistencia de crisis y retirada de tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(2): 49-54, 16 ene., 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159425</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clasificación de las epilepsias generalizadas idiopáticas en mayores de 16 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30330^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30326^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34273^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13024^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30331^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
