<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93315</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health status and gender in Catalonia. An approach using the information sources available</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To present health status differences between men and women in Catalonia across the main available data sources. Methods: The main institutional health data sources of the Catalan population are presented. Mortality and morbidity differences by gender are studied. Results: Men die before than women and present more frequently pathologies that require hospitalary care. Unhealthy behaviours are more frequent in men than in women. Women in general, in all social classes, present more frequently chronic disorders and disabilities and declare worse perception of health status than men of the same social class. Conclusions: Institutional sources of data available in Catalonia allow the description of gender differences in health, nevertheless new variables should be included to improve gender perspective analyse  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Séculi, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fusté, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugulat, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentar las diferencias en el estado de salud de varones y mujeres en Cataluña a través de las principales fuentes de información disponibles. Métodos: Se presentan las principales fuentes de información sanitaria institucionales referidas al ámbito catalán. Se hace una aproximación a la morbimortalidad según género. Resultados: Los varones mueren antes que las mujeres y presentan con mayor frecuencia patologías que requieren ingreso hospitalario. Las conductas poco saludables son más frecuentes en los varones que en las mujeres. Éstas, en general, cualquiera que sea la clase social a la que pertenecen, presentan más enfermedades crónicas y discapacidades y declaran peor percepción del estado de salud que los varones de la misma clase social. Conclusiones: Las fuentes de información institucionales en Cataluña permiten caracterizar el estado de salud según género,si bien deberían incorporar variables que facilitaran el análisis de la información desde la perspectiva de género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;15(1): 54-60, ene. -dic. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado de salud y género en Cataluña. Una aproximacióna través de las fuentes de información disponibles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29453^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
