<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120609</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enteropathic acrodermatitis in a patient with high-out-put ileostomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Zinc deficiency is relatively common in certain pathologies, although its clinical manifestation is uncommon. We present the case of a patient who was admitted pre -senting hyponatremic dehydration and pre-renal failure secondary to high-output ileostomy and oral intolerance. Although the ileostomy output was normalized within 3days of admission and initial zinc plasma levels were normal, after being fed with TPN supplemented with 13mg/day of zinc, he suffered a severe zinc deficit with enteropathicacrodermatitis that was completely resolved after one week with 26.5 mg/day. However, plasma levels did not return to normal until one month on therapy with high doses of zinc. Zinc plasma levels are not a good indicator of zinc stores in the body and many times their changes are a late indicator of zinc deficit. There is not a correlation between the clinical improvement and normalization of zinc levels, being common the clinical resolution within few days of the supplementation without observing an increase of zinc plasma levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oria Mundín, Eugenio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella-Carretero, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Junquera Bañares, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La deficiencia de zinc es relativamente frecuente en ciertas patologías, pero su manifestación clínica es rara. Se expone el caso de un paciente que ingresó con cuadro de deshidratación hiponatrémica e insuficiencia prerrenal secundaria por ileostomía de alto débito e intolerancia oral. Aunque se normalizó el débito de la ilesotomía al tercer día del ingreso y los niveles plasmáticos de zinc iniciales fueron normales, el paciente después de estar con NPT suplementada con 13 mg/día de zinc, sufrió una deficiencia severa de zinc con acrodermatitis enteropática que se resolvió completamente después de una semana con 26,5mg/día. Sin embargo, los niveles plasmáticos no se normalizaron hasta pasado un mes de estar en tratamiento con estas macrodosis de zinc. El zinc plasmático no es un buen indicador de los depósitos de zinc en el organismo, y muchas veces, su alteración es un indicador tardío de deficiencia. Tampoco se observa una correlación entre la mejoría clínica y la normalización de sus niveles, siendo frecuente la resolución clínica a los pocos días de la suplementación sin detectarse aumento de zinc en plasma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 452-455, 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120609</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acrodermatitis enteropática en paciente con ileostomía de alto débito</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d175^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50318</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
