<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101874</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Associated To Cytomegalovirus infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We presented the case of 60 year-old male patient with the diagnosis of non-Hodgkin lymphoma associated to cytomegalovirus infection. Clinical manifestations, prognosis and the most important features in immunocompromissed patients are discussed. The diagnostic and therapeutic problems in our hospital are stood out. We concluded that a high index of suspicion is required for the timely diagnosis of cytomegalovirus infection in immunosuppressed individuals due to atypical behavior of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Benedicto, René</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pila Pérez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Holguín Prieto, Victor A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales Torres, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pila Peláez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un linfoma no &#150;Hodgkin asociado a infección por citomegalovirus en un hombre de 60 años. Se describen algunas características clínicas y pronosticas, con sus particularidades en los pacientes inmunocomprometidos. Se resaltan las dificultades diagnósticas y terapéuticas en nuestro medio., relacionadas con la no disposición de las investigaciones y los agentes farmacológicos necesarios para su manejo. Se concluye que es necesario sospechar la complicación de una infección por citomegalovirus en pacientes inmunossuprimidos que presenten cuadros de comportamiento clínico atípico para así mejorar el pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;48(2): 33-37, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma No-DHodgkin Asociado a Infección por Citomegalivrus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
