<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165938</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New sepsis criteria: do they replace or complement what is known in the approach to the infectious patient?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There have recently been profound changes in both the definitions of sepsis and septic shock and the diagnostic criteria established for daily clinical practice. In addition, a new screening tool known as qSOFA has been introduced to identify patients at risk of a poor short-term outcome. This score has been accompanied by some controversy due to presenting a lower sensitivity than the systemic inflammatory response criteria previously used to identify such patients. In this article, we shall summarise and analyse the most important recently published studies in relation to these new criteria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Candel, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González del Castillo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Sánchez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clemente, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientemente se han producido cambios profundos tanto en las definiciones de sepsis y shock séptico como en los criterios diagnósticos establecidos para la práctica clínica diaria. Además, se ha introducido una nueva herramienta de cribado para la identificación de pacientes con riesgo de malos resultados a corto plazo, el qSOFA. Esta escala se ha acompañado de cierta controversia al presentar una menor sensibilidad que los criterios de respuesta inflamatoria sistémica utilizados previamente para la identificación de estos pacientes. En el presente trabajo resumimos y analizamos los estudios más importantes recientemente publicados en relación con estos nuevos criterios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;30(supl.1): 48-51, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos criterios de sepsis: ¿sustituyen o complementan lo conocido en la aproximación al enfermo infeccioso?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7292^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32030^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
