<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81784</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute Infantile Diarrhea.  Nursing Treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute diarrhea is a common cause of sickness and hospitalization of children throughout the world. Handling children who have acute gastroenteritis includes the use of oral rehydration solutions combined with a timely reintroduction to a complete regular diet, which satisfies the energy and nutritional requirements according to the age and nutritional history of the patient under care. Children who suffer severe diarrheas might require hospitalization, but the majority of these cases can be treated in outpatient clinics or at home. For very few cases it is necessary to resort to the use of intravenous serum therapy. Parents should be aware of the risks which gastroenteritis poses for their children, and be familiar with the use of oral rehydration solutions. These solutions should be kept on hand in all homes which have children in them. Nursing personnel&#146;s role in teaching parents about how to deal with acute diarrhea or gastroenteritis van be the key to prevention and precocious, timely treatment of complications due to acute diarrhea in children(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado Dones, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diarrea aguda es causa común de enfermedad y hospitalización infantil en todo el mundo. El manejo de los niños con gastroenteritis aguda incluye el uso de soluciones de rehidratación oral, junto con la reintroducción temprana de una alimentación completa, que satisfaga los requerimientos de energía y nutrientes según la edad e historia dietética del paciente. Los niños con diarreas severas pueden precisar hospitalización, pero la mayoría de ellos pueden ser tratados ambulatoriamente o en el domicilio. En contadas ocasiones es preciso recurrir a la sueroterapia intravenosa. Los padres deberían conocer los riesgos que una gastroenteritis supone para sus hijos, y estar familiarizados con el uso de las soluciones de rehidratación oral. Éstas deberían estar presentes en cualquier hogar con niños. La educación a los padres por parte del personal de enfermería puede ser la clave para conseguir la prevención y el tratamiento precoz de las complicaciones de la diarrea aguda infantil(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(9): 610-619, sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diarrea aguda infantil. Cuidados enfermeros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24857^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52550^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52550^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
