<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057871</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Invasive pneumococcal disease in children younger than 5 years in Navarra, Spain (2000-2005). Impact of the conjugate vaccine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The 7-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV7) has been commercialized in Spain since June 2001. We aim to evaluate the impact of this vaccine in the incidence of invasive pneumococcal disease (IPD) in Navarre. Population and method: The laboratories of microbiology of Navarre declare all the isolations of Streptococcus pneumoniae in samples of normally sterile corporal fluids. We analyzed the incidence of IPD in children younger than 5 years between weeks 41 of 2000 and 40 of 2005. Results: The doses of PCV7 sold up to 2005 would provide a cover of 27% in children younger than 5 years, having assumed 4 dose schedules. In the 5 seasons, 103 cases of IPD were diagnosed. From the 2 first seasons (2000-2002) to the last one (2004-2005) a reduction of 69% in the incidence rate of IPD caused by vaccine serotypes was observed (from 33 to 10 cases by 100,000 children under 5 years; p = 0.003). Between those same periods the incidence of IPD caused by non-vaccine serotypes increased a 36% (from 42 to 57 by 100,000; p = 0.405). The global incidence of IPD diminished a 12% (from 77 to 67 by 100,000; p = 0.689). The percentage of cases that had received PCV7 increased until 45% in season 2004-2005 (p &lt; 0.001). The meningitis and bacteraemic pneumonias supposed 42% of the IPD, without significant changes during the period (p = 0.442). Conclusions: Since the PCV7 was marketed the pattern of serotypes has changed, but the expected reduction in the total IPD incidence has not been achieved</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Petit, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Setas, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torroba, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irisarri, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cenoz, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriazu, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barricarte, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Desde junio de 2001 se comercializa en España la vacuna neumocócica conjugada heptavalente (VNC7v). Nuestro objetivo ha sido evaluar su impacto en la incidencia de enfermedad neumocócica invasiva (ENI) en Navarra. Población y método: Los laboratorios de microbiología de Navarra declaran todos los aislamientos de neumococo en muestras de fluidos corporales normalmente estériles. Analizamos la incidencia de ENI en niños menores de 5 años entre las semanas 41 de 2000 y 40 de 2005. Resultados: Las dosis de VNC7v vendidas hasta 2005 permitirían alcanzar una cobertura del 27% en menores de 5 años, suponiendo 4 dosis por niño. Entre las 5 temporadas se diagnosticaron 103 casos de ENI. Comparando la incidencia de ENI en las 2 primeras temporadas (2000-2002) con la última (2004-2005), se observa un descenso del 69% en la tasa por serotipos vacunales (de 33 a 10 casos por 100.000 menores de 5 años; p = 0,003). Entre esos mismos períodos, la incidencia de ENI por serotipos no vacunales aumentó un 36% (de 42 a 57 por 100.000; p = 0,405). La incidencia global de ENI disminuyó un 12% (de 77 a 67 por 100.000; p = 0,689). El porcentaje de casos que habían recibido VNC7v aumentó hasta el 45% en la temporada 2004-2005 (p &lt; 0,001). Las meningitis y neumonías bacteriémicas supusieron el 42% de las ENI, sin cambios significativos durante el período (p = 0,442). Conclusiones: Tras la comercialización de la VNC7v ha cambiado el patrón de serotipos, pero no se ha conseguido el descenso esperado de la incidencia global de ENI</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);129(2): 41-45, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad neumocócica invasiva en la población menor de 5 años de edad de Navarra (2000-2005): impacto de la vacuna conjugada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8756^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35368^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
