<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125625</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Causes of intolerance in school sports competitions: construction of a code of conduct</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article presents a research pursuing a double objective: (a) identifying intolerant attitudes and behaviours and their causes in school sport competitions, and (b) elaborating a specific code of conduct as a framework to develop action proposals which may reduce intolerance. The identification of the intolerant attitudes and behaviours relied on the participation of students, athletes, coaches, sport experts, teachers, families, referees and institutional directors through 529 questionnaires, 44 interviews and 4 focus groups. The main results point out that the most common intolerant behaviours are related to relentless effort demands, verbal aggression and pressure to win and worry for results but not for encouraging sport&#146;s educational dimension. The study is completed with the construction of a Code of Conduct taking the Delphi method as the starting point. This contains specific indications for individuals, groups and institutions involved in school-age sports (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gairín Sallán, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Moreno, José Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Ceacero, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Vicario, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo presenta una investigación con un doble objetivo: (a) diagnosticar las manifestaciones y causas de la intolerancia en las competiciones deportivas escolares, y (b) redactar un código de conducta específico como marco para el desarrollo de propuestas de actuación ante la intolerancia. El estudio diagnóstico fue realizado con la participación de escolares, deportistas, entrenadores, técnicos deportivos, profesores, familias, árbitros y responsables institucionales a través de 529 cuestionarios, 44 entrevistas y 4 grupos de discusión. Los principales resultados destacan que los comportamientos intolerantes más frecuentes en el deporte escolar se relacionan con exigir esfuerzo sin límite, la agresión verbal, la presión por ganar y la preocupación por los resultados y no por fomentar la dimensión educativa del deporte. El estudio se completa con la elaboración de un Código de Conducta diseñado a partir del método Delphi y cuenta con indicaciones específicas para las personas, los colectivos y las instituciones implicadas en el deporte escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;23(2): 255-265, jul.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causas de la intolerancia en las competiciones deportivas escolares: Elaboración de un código de conducta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12481</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
