<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72976</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of lymphedema associated with klippel-trenaunay syndrome in a 15-month-old boy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 15-month-oldboy with lymphedema in his right lower limb associated withKlippel-Trenaunay syndrome (KTS). The importance of anearly correct diagnosis of the lymphedema based on history,physical examination and isotope lymphography is emphasized.We also emphasize the efficacy of an early treatment bymeans of decongestive physical therapy followed by long-termcontrol of lymphedema with compressive devices. The aforementionedtreatment has led to a satisfactory outcome inour patient.KTS is a rare condition characterized by vascular malformations(in veins, capillaries and lymphatic vessels) in relationshipto a mixed type of angiodysplasia. KTS has differentclinical findings and may involve multiple organs. That is why amultidisciplinary evaluation and treatment is paramount inthis syndrome.Taking into account that the result achieved with ourtreatment has been satisfactory in both adults and in thischild, we recommend it for the management of children withlymphedema associated with KTS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>VÁzquez-Ariño, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel-Alarcón, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Belmonte, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corte-Rodríguez, H, de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un niño de 15 mesesdiagnosticado de síndrome de Klippel-Trenaunay (SKT)con linfedema de miembro inferior derecho. Mostramos laimportancia de un correcto diagnóstico temprano basándoseen la anamnesis, exploración física y linfogammagrafía isotópica.Destacamos también la utilidad de un tratamiento precozmediante terapia física compleja y contención posterior dellinfedema con medidas de compresión, que en nuestro pacienteha llevado a una evolución favorable del linfedema.El SKT es una entidad poco frecuente caracterizada poruna malformación vascular (venosa, capilar y linfática) relacionadacon una angiodisplasia mixta. El SKT tiene un gran espectroclínico y múltiples órganos pueden verse afectados,por lo que su valoración y tratamiento multidisciplinar sehacen imprescindibles.Teniendo en cuenta que este tratamiento ha mostradobuenos resultados en adultos, el caso que presentamos pareceindicar que también podría ser útil en el manejo del linfedemaen niños con SKT(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(2): 81-83, mar.-abr.2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de linfedema asociado a síndrome de Klippel-Trenaunay en un niño de 15 meses</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31869^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12468^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31869^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
