<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049615</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pyruvate dehydrogenase deficit associated to the C515T mutation in exon 6 of the E1 gene</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Pyruvate dehydrogenase (PDH) deficiency constitutes the most frequent metabolic origin of congenitallactic acidosis and is also responsible for a less usual form, found exclusively in females, which leads to a dysmorphicsyndrome accompanied by severe cerebral malformations. The most common defect affects fraction E1&amp;#945; (gene Xp22.1-22.2).Aim. To report the case of a young female with PDH deficiency, dysmorphic syndrome, cerebral deformations and anunidentified mutation in the corresponding gene. Case report. An 8-month-old female with microcephaly, a narrow forehead,nasal hypoplasia, anteverted nostrils, thin lips, axial hypotonia, epileptic seizures and an umbilical hernia. Magneticresonance imaging of the brain revealed intense supra- and infratentorial cortico-subcortical atrophy, ventricular dilatationand agenesis of the corpus callosum. Lactic and pyruvic acid concentrations were high both in blood and in cerebrospinalfluid (CSF), and the level of alanine was high in CSF. Muscular histology results were normal. PDH complex activity infibroblasts and in muscle tissue, as well as that of the mitochondrial respiratory chain complexes in muscle homogenate, werefound to be normal. A molecular genetic study of the gene for PDH E1&amp;#945;, both in formed elements in the blood and infibroblasts, showed a C &gt; T change in nucleotide 515 (C515T) of exon 6, which causes a P172L change in the protein. A studyof 108 controls ruled out the possibility of a polymorphism. The parents did not have the mutation. Conclusions. The C515Tmutation of exon 6 of the gene for PDH E1&amp;#945; is described. Normal activity of the PDH complex in fibroblasts and in muscletissue does not exclude this condition</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo-Sáez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curros-Novo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Gago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eirís-Puñal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Barca, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briones-Godino, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Lado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La deficiencia de piruvato deshidrogenasa(PDH) constituye la base metabólica más frecuente de las acidosislácticas congénitas y también es responsable de una forma menoshabitual, exclusiva del sexo femenino, que cursa con un síndromedismórfico asociado a graves malformaciones cerebrales. El defectomás común afecta a la fracción E1&amp;#945; (gen Xp22.1-22.2). Objetivo.Presentar el caso de una niña con deficiencia de PDH, síndromedismórfico, malformaciones cerebrales y una mutación no descritaen el gen correspondiente. Caso clínico. Niña de 8 meses deedad con microcefalia, frente estrecha, hipoplasia nasal, narinasantevertidas, labios finos, hipotonía axial, crisis epilépticas y herniaumbilical. La resonancia magnética cerebral evidenció unaatrofia corticosubcortical intensa supra e infratentorial, dilataciónventricular y agenesia del cuerpo calloso. Las concentraciones deácido láctico y pirúvico estaban elevadas en la sangre y el líquidocefalorraquídeo (LCR), y la de alanina estaba elevada en el LCR.La histología muscular fue normal. La actividad del complejo de laPDH en los fibroblastos y en el músculo, así como la de los complejosde la cadena respiratoria mitocondrial en homogenado muscular,fueron normales. El estudio genético molecular del gen parala PDH E1&amp;#945;, tanto en elementos formes de la sangre como en fibroblastos,demostró un cambio C &gt; T en el nucleótido 515 (C515T)del exón 6, que causa un cambio P172L en la proteína. El estudio de108 controles descartó que se tratase de un polimorfismo. Los padresno presentaban la mutación. Conclusiones. Se describe la mutaciónC515T en el exón 6 del gen para la PDH E1&amp;#945;. La actividadnormal del complejo de la PDH en los fibroblastos y en el músculono excluye esta entidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(6): 341-345, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deficit de piruvato deshidrogenasa asociado a la mutación C515T en el exon 6 del gen E1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23807^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23807^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23807^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9020^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23807^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32983^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36097</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
