<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93959</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Positive occupational health psychology: an introduction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article introduces the monographic section on Positive Occupational Health Psychology (POHP), presenting eight theoretical and empirical papers about diverse topics. Traditionally, research on occupational health has mainly been focused on causes of diseases and on identifying and preventing work factors related to worker&#146;s impaired health. However, this biased view may not provide a complete understanding of the mechanisms that lead to employee well-being and performance. We discuss the differences of POHP with similar constructs, and review reasons for its importance in the development of this field. Overall, the studies included in the monographic section show the usefulness of focusing on positive constructs, and present ideas and questions that we hope may help to further our progress in the field of POHP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Muñoz, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bakker, Arnold B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo introduce la sección monográfica sobre Psicología de la Salud Ocupacional Positiva (PSOP), presentando ocho trabajos teóricos y empíricos sobre diversos temas. Tradicionalmente, la investigación en salud ocupacional ha estado centrada principalmente en las causas de las enfermedades, así como en identificar y prevenir los factores laborales relacionados con el deterioro de la salud de los trabajadores. Sin embargo, esta aproximación sesgada no puede proporcionar una comprensión completa de los mecanismos que conducen al bienestar y rendimiento óptimo de los empleados. En este trabajo se discuten las diferencias de la PSOP con constructos similares, y se repasan las razones por las que es importante desarrollar esta área. En general, los estudios incluidos en esta sección monográfica demuestran la utilidad de centrarse en constructos positivos, y plantean ideas y cuestiones que esperamos contribuyan a seguir avanzando en el ámbito de la PSOP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(1): 62-65, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93959</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Introducción a la psicología de la salud ocupacional positiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15335^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29494^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
