<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112845</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inappropriate use of health resources and the trivialisation of medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the main problems of our health care system is its excessive use. The most evident results of this misuse are the waste of resources and the iatrogenic consequences that are not justified by any expectations in health improvement. Among the possible causes of this inappropriate use, the trivialization of medical practice should be emphasized. This entails not only a loss of respect and consideration, but facilitates and even stimulates reckless use. Although patients and health care workers are both responsible for this recklessness, politicians and health care managers should be held responsible more so. Without a real emancipation allowing health care users and the population to control the factors that determine their health, it is unlikely that the inappropriate use of health resources and its associated iatrogenic consequences will be reduced (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura Benedicto, Andreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giner Ruiz, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los problemas de nuestro sistema sanitario es el consumo inapropiado cuyas consecuencias más notorias son el despilfarro de recursos y la iatrogenia que no está justificada por la expectativa de ningún beneficio en términos de salud. Entre las posibles causas del consumo inadecuado se destaca la banalización de la medicina, que conlleva la pérdida de respeto y la ausencia de miramientos y por eso facilita cuando no estimula la temeridad en el consumo. Una temeridad de la que son responsables tanto pacientes como sanitarios y seguramente todavía más gestores y políticos. Sin una efectiva emancipación que lleve a los usuarios y ciudadanos a controlar los determinantes de su salud no parece posible disminuir el consumo inapropiado ni la iatrogenia asociada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;45(5): 274-277, mayo. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consumo sanitario inapropiado y la trivialización de la medicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28841^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33125^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
