<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128698</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of Onodera&#146;s index in colorectal cancer survival</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Onodera's prognostic nutritional index (OPNI), which is calculated using total lymphocyte count and serum albumin level, has been used as a marker of nutritional status, with its potential prognostic value in colorectal cancer having recently been postulated in Japan and China. There is still no data on the predictive value of OPNI in a Western population. Patients and methods: A consecutive case series of 207 patients scheduled for colorectal cancer resection with curative intent was reviewed. Pre-treatment OPNI was calculated using the formula: [10 x serum albumin (g/dl) + 0.005 x lymphocytes/mm²]. OPNI values under 40 were considered low. Univariate and multivariate analysis were performed on survival curves, comparing cases with OPNI values less than, equal to or greater than 40 (Cox model, stepwise), in the overall series and in pTNM stage II. Results: The median for clinical follow-up was 81 months (interquartile range 60-96). Twenty-six patients (12.6%) had a low OPNI (&amp;#8804; 40). In the multivariate analysis, patients with low OPNI showed less favourable survival curves, both in the overall series: [p &lt;0.001; HR = 3.16; 95% CI = 1.67-5.94] and in the 78 cases in pTNM stage II: [p &lt;0.004; HR = 4.36; 95% CI = 1.61-11.76]. Conclusions: A low pre-treatment OPNI (&lt;40) has an independent, unfavourable predictive value on survival in European patients with resected colorectal cancer, both in the overall series and in pTNM stage II (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zozaya, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urman, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El índice de Onodera (IO) combina los valores de los linfocitos circulantes y de la albúmina sérica y se ha utilizado como marcador del estado nutricional, postulándose recientemente en Japón y China su posible valor pronóstico en el cáncer colorrectal. Todavía no disponemos de datos sobre el valor predictivo del IO en una población occidental. Pacientes y métodos: Se revisaron 207 cánceres colorrectales resecados programada y consecutivamente, con intención curativa. Se calculó el IO pre-tratamiento mediante la fórmula: [10 x albúmina sérica (g/dl) + 0,005 x cifra de linfocitos circulantes/mm²]. Consideramos bajos los valores de IO menores de 40. Se efectuó un análisis univariable y multivariable de las curvas de supervivencia entre los casos con valores de IO menores, iguales o mayores de 40 (modelo de Cox, stepwise), todo ello en la serie global y en el estadio pTNM II. Resultados: El seguimiento clínico tuvo una mediana de 81 meses (rango intercuartílico 60-96). Veintiséis pacientes (12,6%) presentaron un IO bajo (&amp;#8804; 40). En el análisis multivariable, los pacientes con IO bajo mostraron unas curvas de supervivencia más desfavorables, tanto en la serie global: [p &lt; 0,001; HR = 3,16; IC 95% = 1,67-5,94)] como en los 78 casos en estadio pTNM II: [p &lt; 0,004; HR = 4,36; IC 95% = 1,61-11,76)]. Conclusiones: También en pacientes europeos, un índice de Onodera pre-tratamiento bajo (&lt; 40) tiene un valor predictivo independiente y desfavorable sobre la supervivencia en el cáncer colorrectal resecado, tanto en la serie global como en el estadio pTNM II (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(2): 213-221, mayo-ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico del índice de Onodera en la supervivencia del cáncer colorrectal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
