<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96744</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emergency thoracotomy. Indications, surgical technique and results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Emergency thoracotomyis a surgical technique that has been extended in the last few years, and is currently included in advanced cardiopulmonary resuscitation protocols. Despite its proven use in patients with penetrating heart wounds, it is often not used due to lack of knowledge of the technique. Currently, the increase in chest wounds due to violence, traffic accidents, crashes or suicides, and advances in extra-hospital medical care systems, has currently awakened new interest in this technique. A review of emergency thoracotomy is presented in this article: indications, surgical technique, results, and its usefulness in the extra-hospital setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Estefanía, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La toracotomía de urgencia es una técnica quirúrgica que se ha extendido considerablemente en los últimos años, y que se incluye en la actualidad dentro de los protocolos de reanimación cardio-pulmonar avanzada. A pesar de su contrastada utilidad en pacientes con heridas cardiacas penetrantes, en ocasiones no se utiliza por desconocimiento de la técnica, o de sus indicaciones. En la actualidad, el aumento de las lesiones torácicas por violencia, accidentes de tráfico, atropellos, o suicidios, y los avances en los sistemas de atención extrahospitalaria, han despertado nuevamente interés sobre esta técnica.En este artículo se realiza una revisión de la toracotomía de urgencia: indicaciones, técnica quirúrgica, resultados, y su utilidad en ambiente extrahospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);89(6): 340-347, jun.-jul. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toracotomía de urgencia. Indicaciones, técnica quirúrgica y resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6488^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4692^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1025^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2349^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14285^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
