<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104050</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Positive blood cultures in a pediatric emergency department: a descriptive analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the infections and microorganisms causing bacteremia in an emergency department and to analyze the influence of a positive blood culture on subsequent management. It is a retrospective study of positive blood cultures ordered in the emergency department in 2008 and 2009. A change in therapeutic approach was defined as the initiation or modification of antibiotic therapy and/or hospital admission. A total of 7582 blood cultures were ordered. Bacteria grew in 382 (5.0%); 88 (23.0%) were true positives. Pneumonia and urinary tract infection were the main diagnoses associated with bacteremia. The pathogens implicated most often were Streptococcus pneumoniae and Escherichia coli. A positive blood culture led to a change in therapeutic approach in a third of the cases, mainly in patients with fever of unknown origin. We conclude that the management changed on the basis of blood culture findings in a significant number of cases although given the low prevalence of bacteremia, the overall impact was low (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Cabañero, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sánchez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mintegi, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azkunaga, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe las patologías y los microorganismos que causan bacteriemia y la influencia del hemocultivo (HC) positivo en urgencias en el manejo posterior. Se trata de un estudio retrospectivo de los HC positivos realizados en urgencias durante 2008 y 2009. Se consideró el cambio de la actitud terapéutica, el inicio o modificación del antibiótico y/o el ingreso hospitalario. Se realizaron 7.582 HC. En 382 (5,0%) hubo crecimiento bacteriano, 88 (23,0%) fueron verdaderos positivos. La neumonía y la infección urinaria fueron las principales patologías asociadas a bacteriemia y S. pneumoniae y E. coli los microorganismos más frecuentes. El HC positivo condicionó cambio de actitud terapéutica en un tercio de los episodios, principalmente en pacientes con fiebre sin foco. Se concluye que la positividad del HC condicionó un cambio de actitud terapéutica en un número significativo de pacientes, aunque dada la baja prevalencia de bacteriemia el impacto global fue bajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(5): 386-388, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de los hemocultivos positivos en un servicio de urgencias pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29168^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3491</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
