<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156220</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Can discuss bullying in nursing?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bullying is an unethical conduct that disrupts the balance in the workplace and appears contrary to morals and good faith that should guide social and labor relations (Alkmim, 2005). Objective: Identify and analyze the scientific literature on the phenomenon of bullying in nursing. Method: Systematic literature review with qualitative approach. Inclusion criteria: all categories of articles with full text; published in Portuguese, English or Spanish between 2005 and 2014 and articles interconnect issues about bullying, sexual harassment and nursing. Results: Among the established criteria were selected twelve articles. It was found that bullying manifests itself in different ways, in concrete situations experienced by nursing staff and grouped by similarity into categories that depict the perceptions and consequences of the phenomenon as well as the actions taken for solving them. Conclusion: We conclude that the discus-sion of the phenomenon in nursing should be expanded to better understanding and coping with bullying in this category with the expectation that the phenomenon is no longer silent, hidden and pass to be discussed openly influencing the process improvement of the nursing work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hagopian, Ellen M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, Kleber S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Genival Fernandes de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La intimidación es una conducta no ética que altera el equilibrio en el lugar de trabajo y parece contraria a la moral y la buena fe que deben guiar las relaciones sociales y laborales (Alkmim, 2005). El objetivo de este estudio consiste en identificar y analizar la literatura científica sobre el fenómeno del bullying en enfermería. Método: Revisión bibliográfica sistemática con enfoque cualitativo. Criterios de inclusión: todas las categorías de artículos con texto completo; publicado en portugués, inglés o español entre 2005 y 2014 y artículos interconexión cuestiones acerca de la intimidación, el acoso sexual y de enfermería. Resultados: Entre los criterios establecidos se seleccionaron doce artículos. Se encontró que el acoso se manifiesta de diferentes maneras, en situaciones concretas experimentadas por el personal de enfermería y agrupados por similitud en categorías que representan las percepciones y las consecuencias del fenómeno, así como las medidas adoptadas para resolverlos. Conclusión: Llegamos a la conclusión de que la discusión del fenómeno en enfermería debe ampliarse a una mejor comprensión y haciendo frente a la intimidación en esta categoría con la expectativa de que el fenómeno ya no es silenciosa, oculta y pasa a ser discutido abiertamente influir en la mejora de procesos del trabajo de enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(45): 117-125, mayo-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156220</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es posible discutir bullyin en enfermeria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55427^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9929^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
