<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106078</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autor Impact CUIDEN Citation. Relevant scientific trajectories and excellence in the Iberoamerican scientific space to Hirsch h index</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, the scientific trajectories of the most productive authors form the scientific iberoamerican space are analyzed. A relevance classification of authors after the number of citations received and after the h value of the Hirsch&#146;s index is proposed. To that end, the citations of 47 nursing journals and related areas included in the selective index CUIDEN CITACIÓN for 6 years are analyzed. The h value that defines excellence and scientific relevance of an author in the nursing field is between 6 and 9 (for a 5 year period). If a period of 10 or 30 years was analyzed, h values close to the ones found by Hirsch for the physics field would be encountered. The evaluation of researchers in our field has now the most objective assessment tool that has ever been developed and, consequently, allows to exactly and precisely discriminate between authors that are in a competitive system. This tool also evalues the impact of the authors&#146; institutions and nursing research centers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hueso Montoro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salido Moreno, M. Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Toro, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amezcua, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analizan las trayectorias científicas de los autores más productivos del espacio científico iberoamericano. Se propone una clasificación de la relevancia de los autores atendiendo al número de citas que reciben y al valor h del índice de Hirsch. Para ello se analizan las citas de 47 revistas de enfermería y áreas relacionadas incluidas en el selectivo índice CUIDEN CITACIÓN durante un periodo de 6 años. El valor h que define la excelencia y la relevancia científica de un autor del área de enfermería está comprendido entre 6 y 9 (para un periodo de 6 años). Si se analizara un periodo de 10 o 20 años se hallarían valores h cercanos a los encontrados por Hirsch para el área de la física. La evaluación de los investigadores de nuestro medio ya cuenta con el instrumento de valoración más objetivo desarrollado nunca antes y, consecuentemente, permite discriminar con exactitud y precisión entre autores que concursan en un sistema competitivo. Este instrumento también evalúa el impacto de las instituciones y centros de investigación de enfermería a los que pertenecen los autores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;15(55): 76-82, oct.-dic. 2006. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de Autor CUIDEN Citación. Trayectorias científicas relevantes y excelencia a través del Factor h (h-index) de Hirsch en el espacio científico iberoamericano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
