<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95592</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New approaches in the care of "the other"</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper aims to contribute to the debate that arise from nursing and anthropology, the increasing complexity of health care in contexts of cultural diversity and in times of glocalization. This reflection start, from the view that studies of social and cultural factors need to disassociate themselves the traditional concepts of culture and to focus their analysis in the context of the current complex society characterized by continuous mixing. Based on the experience of a fieldwork study on immigrant population it suggests a challenge to the biomedical model and a change in the professional / patient relationship (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Preciado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo pretende contribuir al debate que suscita, desde la enfermería y desde la antropología, la creciente complejidad del cuidado de la salud en contextos de diversidad cultural y en tiempos de glocalización. Esta reflexión parte de la tesis de que los estudios sobre factores sociales y culturales necesitan desmarcarse de los conceptos tradicionales de cultura e inscribir sus análisis en el contexto de la sociedad compleja actual, caracterizada por continuas mezclas y préstamos. Apoyándose en la experiencia de un trabajo de campo sobre población inmigrada, propone un cuestionamiento de la biomedicina y un cambio en la relación profesional/paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(2/3): 167-171, sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos enfoques en el cuidado del "otro"</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
