<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88714</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current Surgical Management of Severe Peyronie&#146;s Disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">RESULTS: The mean follow-up was 15 months (6-25). Mean penile length gain without prosthesis was 2.8cm (1.5-4.2) and with prosthesis 3.2cm (2-4.5cm). Insuficient straightening was in 5 patients (&gt;15 degree) where Neuro Vascular Bundle (NVB) was limiting factor. Twenty four patients reported hypoesthesia and reduced orgasmic sensitivity that recovered spontaneously after 3-6 months. De-novo ED occurred in 6 pts and progression of disease in 6 patients. Infection occurred only in one patient with penile prosthesis implantation. Overall patients&#146; satisfaction was 95%.                            CONCLUSIONS: Complete tunical reconstruction in IPP can be performed as a safe procedure by transversal, longitudinal and circular grafting with or without simultaneous penile prosthesis implantation. Maximum penile length, girth and shape restoration can be achieved using geometrical calculation, regardless of type of deformity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Djinovic, Rados P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perovic, Sava V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">RESULTADOS: El seguimiento medio fue de 15 meses (6-25). El incremento de longitud del pene fue de 2,8 cm sin prótesis (1,5-4,2 cm) y 3,2 cm (2-4,5cm) con prótesis. En 5 pacientes (&lt;15 grados), la corrección de la curvatura fue insuficiente, debido a que el haz neurovascular fue un factor limitante. Veinticuatro pacientes informaron de hipoestesia y sensibilidad orgásmica reducida que se recuperó espontáneamente al cabo de 3-6 meses. Seis pacientes presentaron una disfunción eréctil de novo y 6 pacientes progresión de la enfermedad. Sólo un paciente con implante de prótesis de pene sufrió infección. El índice de satisfacción general de los pacientes fue del 95%.CONCLUSIONES: La reconstrucción de la túnica albu-gínea completa en la enfermedad de Peyronie puede realizarse como un procedimiento seguro por medio de injertos transversales, longitudinales y circulares con o sin implante simultáneo de prótesis de pene. Se puede lograr, mediante el cálculo geométrico, la longitud máxi-ma del pene, el grosor y la recuperación de la forma, independientemente del tipo de deformidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(9): 755-770, nov. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo quirúrgico actual de la enfermedad de le Peyronie grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10604^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10604^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10604^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24829^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
