<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101043</identifier>
<setSpec>0367-2743</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An analytical descriptive study with a simple of 64 sujects treated in Fontilles was made, 30 of whom received the WHO Multidrug Therapy and the other 34 treatments in which different doses of rifampicin were used. The general objective of the study was to compare the number of Leprosy Reactions suffered by the population treated with WHO Multidrug therapy, with the Leprosy Reactions suffered by the population treated with other doses of rifampicin. In both groups the leprosy reactions were frequent, (46,7% and a 70,6% respectively). Both groups were quite similar in terms of sex (greater proportion of men than women), clinical classification (predominance of multibacilary patients with lepromatous leprosy), differed in Bacterial Index, this being higher in the second group (73,5% had a Bacterial index &gt; or = to 4 +, whereas in the group treated with WHO Multidrug Therapy the percentage was 26,7%). As for the occurrence of Leprosy Reactions and after analyzing the behavior of the different variables, a multivariant analysis was made to eliminate possible slants and an important statistical signification for an elevated Bacterial Index was obtained, a statistical signification was also observed for the sex variable, but not so for the treatment. The effect of the treatment on men and women was analyzed separately then, observing that those men who received doses of rifampicin other than those recommended by the WHO had six times more risk of undergoing Leprosy Reactions. Statistically significant differences were not observed for the women group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moll,  Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Torres, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realizó un estudio descriptivo analítico con una muestra de 64 sujetos tratados en Fontilles, 30 de los cuales recibieron multiterapia de la OMS y 34 otros tratamientos en los que se empleaban diferentes dosis de rifampicina. El objetivo general del estudio fue comparar el número de leprorreacciones sufridas por la población tratada con multiterapia de la OMS con las leprorreacciones sufridas por la población tratada con otras dosis de rifampicina. En ambos grupos las leprorreacciones fueron frecuentes, con un 46,7% y un 70,6% respectivamente. Ambos grupos eran bastante similares en cuanto a sexo (mayor proporción de hombres que de mujeres), forma clínica (predominio de enfermos multibacilares con lepra lepromatosa), diferían en cuanto a carga bacilar, siendo ésta más elevada en el segundo grupo (un 73,5% tenían un índice Bacteriológico &gt; ó = a 4 +, mientras que en el grupo tratado con multiterapia de la OMS este porcentaje era de 26,7%). Tras analizar el comportamiento de las distintas variables en cuanto a la ocurrencia de leprorreacciones, se realizó un análisis multivariante para eliminar posibles sesgos y se obtuvo una importante significación estadística para una carga bacilar elevada, también se observó significación para la variable sexo, no así para el tratamiento. Se analizó entonces el efecto del tratamiento por separado en hombres y mujeres, viéndose que los hombres que recibían otras pautas de rifampicina que las recomendadas por la OMS tenían seis veces más riesgo de sufrir leprorreacciones, no observándose diferencias estadísticamente significativas para las mujeres entre recibir uno u otro tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fontilles, Rev. leprol;26(5): 425-446, mayo-ago. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101043</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre la disminución de leprorreacciones en Fontilles desde la implantación del tratamiento con poliquimioteraia de la OMS respecto a tratamientos anteriores en los que se empleaban diferentes dosis de Rifampicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8095^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53481^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8095^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23708^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8096^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
