<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159063</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case of multifocal medulloblastoma in an adult patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Only five cases of multifocal medulloblastoma in the adult have been reported to date. We present a case in a male patient in his 50th decade of life who presented with three extra-axial lesions associated with a parenchymatous lesion of the right middle cerebellar peduncle. Sputum sample examination revealed larvae compatible with strongyloides stercoralis, which was our main differential diagnosis. Histological and immunohistochemical studies revealed the existence of a desmoplastic medulloblastoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Concha-Lopez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Cancela, Rose Marie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pombo Otero, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la literatura se han publicado únicamente cinco 5 casos de meduloblastoma multifocal en el adulto. Presentamos el caso de un paciente de sexo masculino en su quinta década de vida con un meduloblastoma multifocal. El paciente presentaba tres 3 lesiones extra-axiales y una lesión parenquimatosa del pedúnculo cerebeloso medio derecho. El estudio de esputo reveló larvas compatibles con Strongyloides stercoralis, siendo esta la primera sospecha diagnóstica. El estudio histológico e inmuhistoquímico reveló la existencia de un meduloblastoma desmoplásico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;50(1): 45-48, ene.-mar. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un caso de meduloblastoma multifocal en un paciente adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56146^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56146^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8695^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9640^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
