<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88200</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urgencies and emergencies professionals: current profile and potential development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Emergency services, both hospital based andpre-hospital, are care mechanisms that have beendeveloped above all as a result of the General HealthLaw of 1986. They are in high demand and have a careoverload, while they provide high quality care and arestrategic elements in the working of the National HealthSystem. However, their professionals, basic and substantialelements in their tasks, have been relegated instrategic planning and, above all, do not receive regulatedspecialised training in Emergency Medicine. Thiswould guarantee that from the very moment they takeup their care duties they have all of the abilities, skillsand attitudes demanded of them by the patients&#146; needs.This lack also prevents correct professional development,which is the basis of the future viability of theemergency services themselves. To resolve this dilemma,besides seeking solutions to the work and organisationalproblems of the different services, the creationof the Speciality of Accident and Emergency Medicine,in the framework of core medical studies, is an essentialrequisite. This is how it is being dealt with by ournearby countries and this need has been recognised bythe Spanish Parliament and by the majority of political,social and professional sectors(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toranzo, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aramburu, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los servicios de urgencias, tanto hospitalarioscomo extrahospitalarios, son dispositivos asistencialesque se han desarrollado, sobre todo, a raíz de la publicaciónde la Ley General de Sanidad en 1986. Tienen unaalta frecuentación y gran sobrecarga asistencial, a lavez que dispensan una elevada calidad asistencial y sonelementos estratégicos en el funcionamiento del SistemaNacional de Salud. Sin embargo, sus profesionales,elementos básicos y sustanciales en su funcionamientohan estado relegados en cuanto a la planificación estratégicay, sobre todo, sin una formación especializada regladaen Medicina de Urgencias y Emergencias que garanticeque, desde el mismo momento en que asumenresponsabilidades asistenciales, tienen todas las competencias,habilidades y actitudes que las necesidadesde los enfermos les demandan. Esta carencia tambiénimpide un correcto desarrollo profesional y es la basede la viabilidad futura de los propios servicios de urgencias.Para solventar este dilema, además de buscarsoluciones a los problemas laborales y organizativos delos distintos servicios, la creación de la Especialidad deMedicina de Urgencias y Emergencias, en el marco de latroncalidad, es un requisito imprescindible. En ese sentidolo están abordando los países de nuestro entornoy así lo han reconocido, desde el Parlamento Español,hasta la mayoría de los sectores políticos, sociales yprofesionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(supl.1): 13-18, ene.-abr. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los profesionales de urgencias y emergencias: perfil actual y posibilidades de desarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8678^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
