<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158426</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ketamine in the treatment of chronic pain as evidence-based medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ketamine is a noncompetitive NMDA receptor antagonist and has a large action&#146;s mechanism, that involves receptors: AMPA, kainate, gamma-aminobutyric acid, opioids, monoamine, muscarinic and nicotinic. It is acting on voltage-dependent calcium channels, join in the synthesis and release of nitric oxide and inhibits serotonin reuptake. The interaction with these mechanisms of action makes it an important role on mechanisms of pain, inflammation, neuroprotection and opioid tolerance. In this paper we review the different routes of administration of ketamine, dosage, modes of administration, duration of treatment, indications according to levels of evidence available and side effects to set up its efficacy in the therapy of chronic pain and promote a more specific treatment, in those pathologies where it has shown greater efficacy. We perform a search in: Trip Database Population Intervention Comparison Outcome (PICO), National Guidelines Clearinghouse, Cochrane Library, Medline, CMA infobase, Health Services/ Technology Assessment, New Zealand Guidelines Group and Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network. Ketamine is very versatile in their routes of administration: intravenous, intramuscular, subcutaneous, sublingual, oral, rectal, nasal, transdermic, epidural and subarachnoid; as well as their ways of administration (bolus, continuous infusion). However, the oral route is the most widely used and preferred for the treatment of chronic pain. However, we do not have an oral formulation marketed, making it difficult to use. Clinical use of ketamine requires careful patient&#146;s selection and assessment of the risk/benefit ratio. Ketamine has a potential risk of drug abuse; therefore, it should checked prior history of drug abuse. It is available evidence on the efficacy of ketamine in patients with refractory cancer pain and complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS). The use of low-dose intravenous ketamine has moderate evidence in CRPS, that does not justify its routine use in this syndrome. In neuropathic pain, ketamine has been particularly effective in controlling allodynia, hyperalgesia and hyperpathia, although there is controversy over its use. Oral ketamine may have a place in the treatment of chronic pain patients refractory to standard treatments. It is shown useful as an adjuvant to other analgesics, especially in patients treated with opioids, allowing reduction of doses and increasing pain relief in patients with chronic pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira Reina, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega García, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ketamina es un antagonista no competitivo de los receptores NMDA y tiene un amplio mecanismo de acción que involucra, además, a los receptores AMPA, kainato, ácido gamma-aminobutírico, opioides, monoaminérgicos, muscarínicos y nicotínicos. Actúa sobre los canales de calcio y sodio voltaje-dependientes, interviene en la síntesis y liberación del óxido nítrico e inhibe la recaptación de serotonina. La interacción con todos estos mecanismos de acción hace que tenga una importante participación sobre mecanismos del dolor, inflamación, neuroprotección y tolerancia de opioides. En este trabajo se revisan las diferentes vías de administración de la ketamina, su dosificación, las modalidades de administración, la duración del tratamiento, las indicaciones según los niveles de evidencia disponibles y los efectos secundarios; para establecer su eficacia en la terapéutica del dolor crónico y promover un tratamiento más específico, en aquellas patologías en las que se ha demostrado una mayor eficacia. Se realizó una búsqueda en Trip Database Population Intervention Comparison Outcome (PICO), National Guidelines Clearinghouse, Cochrane Library, Medline, CMA infobase, Health Services/Technology Assessment, New Zealand Guidelines Group y Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network. La ketamina tiene una gran versatilidad en cuanto a sus vías de administración (intravenosa, intramuscular, subcutánea, sublingual, oral, rectal, nasal, transdérmica, epidural y subaracnoidea), así como modalidades de administración (bolos, infusión continua). No obstante, la vía oral es la más utilizada y preferida para el tratamiento del dolor crónico. Sin embargo, no disponemos de una formulación oral comercializada, lo que dificulta su utilización. El empleo clínico de la ketamina requiere una cuidadosa selección del paciente y valoración de la relación riesgo/beneficio. Se debe tener presente los antecedentes de abuso de drogas ante el riesgo potencial de abuso del fármaco. Se dispone de evidencia sobre la eficacia de la ketamina en pacientes con dolor oncológico refractario y en el síndrome doloroso regional complejo (SDRC). Hay evidencia moderada sobre la eficacia de la ketamina intravenosa a dosis bajas, en el SDRC, que no justifica su utilización sistemática en este síndrome. En el dolor neuropático, la ketamina se ha mostrado especialmente eficaz en el control de la alodinia, hiperalgesia e hiperpatía, pero existen controversias sobre su utilización. La ketamina oral puede tener un lugar en el tratamiento del dolor crónico de los pacientes refractarios a tratamientos habituales. Se ha mostrado útil como coadyuvante de otros analgésicos, especialmente en pacientes en tratamiento con opioides, permitiendo disminuir la dosis e incrementando el control analgésico de los pacientes con dolor crónico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;23(6): 292-306, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ketamina en el tratamiento del dolor crónico según medicina basada en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d782^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55732^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
