<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134738</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-9536</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Boundaries and integrity in the 'Social Contract for Spanish Science', 1907-1939</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article analyzes the relationship between science and politics in Spain in the early 20th century from the perspective of the Social Contract for Science. The article shows that a genuine social contract for science was instituted in Spain during this period, although some boundary and integrity problems emerged. These problems are analyzed, showing that the boundary problems were a product of the conservative viewpoint on the relationship between science and politics, while the integrity problems involved the activation of networks of influence in the awarding of scholarships to study abroad. Finally, the analysis reveals that these problems did not invalidate the Spanish social contract for science (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analizan las relaciones entre ciencia y política en el primer tercio del siglo XX español desde la perspectiva del Contrato Social para la Ciencia. En él se muestra que en dicho periodo se instituyó un auténtico contrato social para la ciencia en España, aunque surgieron algunos problemas de frontera e integridad. Dichos problemas son analizados y se defiende que los problemas de frontera fueron resultado de la concepción de las relaciones entre ciencia y política de los gobiernos conservadores, mientras que los problemas de integridad tuvieron que ver con la activación de redes de influencia en la concesión de las becas para la formación en el extranjero. Finalmente, el análisis revela que estos problemas no invalidaron el contrato social para la ciencia en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dynamis (Granada);34(2): 465-487, 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frontera and integrity in the 'social contract for the Spanish science', 1907-1939</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5789^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5789^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5789^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35169^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35169^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
