<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166448</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and risk stratification in stable angina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Stable angina is a very important clinical finding because it is one of the initial presentations of ischemic heart disease. It is probably encountered most frequently in primary care and emergency departments. It has a poor prognosis. Diagnosis is based on clinical observation, on the pretest probability of coronary artery disease, and on the results of the diagnostic tests selected on the basis of that pretest probability. Attempting to diagnose chest pain without first carrying out risk stratification can result in too many inconclusive tests being performed, which can be dangerous for the patient. By using a suitable methodology, it is possible to stratify patients efficiently, thereby identifying those with significant coronary lesions who can then be offered a choice of treatment on the basis of known facts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borrás Pérez, F Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La angina estable es un cuadro clínico de gran importancia, dado que es una de las presentaciones iniciales de la cardiopatía isquémica y probablemente su frecuencia sea mayor en la atención primaria y el ámbito de urgencias. Tiene un pronóstico desfavorable y el diagnóstico se basa en los datos clínicos, la probabilidad pretest y la selección de pruebas diagnósticas acordes con esa probabilidad. Entrar en el proceso diagnóstico del dolor torácico sin una orientación previa conlleva un exceso de pruebas no concluyentes y potencialmente peligrosas para el paciente. Con una metodología adecuada, es posible estratificar eficazmente a los pacientes detectando a los que tengan lesiones coronarias significativas en los que se pueda plantear una opción terapéutica basada en los conocimientos actuales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);12(supl.D): 9d-14d, 2012. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y estratificación de la angina estable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6487^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
