<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138483</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuroscientists in the third reich</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: This article analyzes the effects that the arrival of the nazis to power as well as the participation of the neuroscientists in the programs developed by nazi medicine had on german neurology. Methods: Review of the literature related with medicine in the times of the nazis, placing special attention on the role played by the neuroscientists. Results: The physicians were the professional group that joined the nazi party the most. Many neurologists, psychiatrists and neuropathologists participated in the sterilization, euthanasia and experimenting programs in humans. Based on the experience acquired in these projects, some were chosen as personnel in charge of extermination in the concentration camps. Eminent neurologists such as Hallervorden, Spatz and Schaltenbrand took advantage of the scientific possibilities offered by the euthanasia and experimentation projects in humans with no harm being done to their careers after the war. Many Jewish neurologist or dissidents were driven out of their work, required to go into exile or, in the worst of the cases, were jailed and assassinated. Conclusions: The nazi government had two outstanding effects on german neurology. On the one hand, many neurologists were harmed due to racial or political reasons. On the other, outstanding neurologists participated in programs of nazi medicine. This reminds us of the perverse role that politics may play in medicine and that scientific knowledge should not forget ethics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarejo Galende, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el presente artículo se analizan los efectos que tuvo para la neurología alemana la llegada de los nazis al poder, así como la participación de neurocientíficos en los programas impulsados por la medicina nazi. Método. Revisión de la literatura relacionada con la medicina en tiempos de los nazis, con especial atención al papel desempeñado por los neurocientíficos. Resultados. Los médicos fueron el colectivo profesional que más se afilió al partido nazi. Numerosos neurólogos, psiquiatras y neuropatólogos participaron en los programas de esterilización, eutanasia y experimentación en humanos. Por la experiencia adquirida en estos proyectos algunos fueron elegidos como personal encargado del exterminio en los campos de concentración. Neurólogos eminentes como Hallervorden, Spatz y Schaltenbrand aprovecharon las posibilidades científicas que brindaban los proyectos de eutanasia y experimentación en humanos, sin que sus carreras tras la guerra se vieran dañadas. Un gran número de neurólogos judíos o disidentes fueron expulsados de sus trabajos, obligados a exiliarse o, en los peores casos, encarcelados y asesinados. Conclusiones. El gobierno nazi tuvo dos efectos destacados en la neurología alemana: por un lado, muchos neurólogos fueron perjudicados por motivos raciales o políticos; por otro, destacados neurólogos participaron en programas de la medicina nazi. Esto nos recuerda el perverso papel que la política puede ejercer en la medicina y que el conocimiento científico no debe olvidar la ética (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(2): 126-135, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los neurocientíficos en el Tercer Reich</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3233</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22983</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19624^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19624^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19624^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36353</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
