<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17775</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioral sequences in conflict effectiveness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze whether the use of conflict behavior over the stages of an escalated conflict episode differentiates between effective and ineffective subjects. Subjects were asked to solve -via on-line- an organizational conflict with a subordinate. The subordinate was a confederate who was instructed to escalate the conflict episode in three levels: trivialization -using avoiding behaviors-; norms attacks -using indirect fighting behaviors-, and personal attack -using direct fighting behaviors-. Conflict behavior and effectiveness were assessed through observational measures. Sequential analysis showed that it is possible to further differentiate the effective and ineffective subjects. Effective subjects reacted complementarily both to avoiding and direct fighting behavior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arévalo, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros, Inmaculada F. J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munduate, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito del presente estudio fue analizar si los negociadores efectivos e inefectivos difieren en sus respuestas al escalamiento del conflicto. Los negociadores desarrollaron un rol play, mediado por ordenador, con un oponente ficticio que escalaba el episodio de conflicto en tres niveles: trivialización utilizando conductas de evitación-; ataques a las normas de la empresa utilizando conductas de lucha indirecta- y ataques personales utilizando conductas de lucha directa-. Las conductas de gestión del conflicto utilizadas por los sujetos experimentales y la efectividad diádica se analizaron mediante la observación de las interacciones. Los resultados, derivados del análisis secuencia de la interacción, mostraron que los sujetos efectivos responden de forma complementaria tanto a las conductas de lucha directa, como a las conductas de evitación utilizadas por el oponente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(1): 12-18, feb. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Secuencias conductuales en la efectividad de la gestión del conflicto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
