<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044765</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genetic mechanisms in the hereditary predisposition to colorectal cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A proportion of colorectal cancers shows some type of genetic predisposition that can be recognised in clinical practice. From the classical dominant inheritance pattern of familial adenomatous polyposis or hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer, through the recessive transmission of the MYH associated polyposis, to the new syndromes of the &#147;serrated pathway&#148; or low-penetrance alleles, the discovery of new genes and a deeper understanding of the mechanisms of action of already-known ones are enabling us to understand new aspects of the colorectal carcinogenesis. This is throwing a new light on some of the observed familial aggregation patterns which had remained unexplained</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Arroyo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valiente, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Juana, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una proporción de los cánceres colorrectales presentan algún tipo de predisposición genética que es posible reconocer en la práctica clínica. Desde los clásicos patrones hereditarios dominantes de la poliposis adenomatosa familiar o el cáncer de colon hereditario no asociado a poliposis, pasando por la transmisión recesiva mostrada por la poliposis asociada al gen MYH, hasta llegar a los novedosos síndromes de la &#147;vía serrada&#148; o los alelos de baja penetrancia, el descubrimiento de nuevos genes y el mejor conocimiento de los mecanismos de acción de los ya conocidos, están permitiendo comprender nuevos aspectos de la carcinogénesis colorrectal que arrojan nueva luz sobre algunas de las observaciones de patrones de agregación familiar al cáncer de colon que permanecían inexplicadas</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;29(1): 59-76, ene.-abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mecanismos genéticos en la predisposición hereditaria al cáncer colorrectal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5943</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24009^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d485</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31896^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
