<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75891</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There have been great scientific and technical advances in biomedicine in the last few years, particularly after the description of the human genome. These improvements have gradually been applied in diverse fields that have gone beyond the study of the disease to enter the study of health. The latter includes research in the field of physical and sports activity. Genetics therefore provides the scientific knowledge that helps us to optimise the performance of high level sportsmen/women, to reap the benefits of carrying out physical exercise and/or to perform a safe sports practice by evaluating the risk of a hereditary disease associated to sudden death in sportsmen/women(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sànchez, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campuzano, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La biomedicina ha experimentado grandes progresos científicos y técnicos en los últimos años, especialmente tras la descripción del genoma humano. Estas mejoras se han aplicado gradualmente en diversos ámbitos, que han sobrepasado el estudio de la patología para adentrarse en el estudio de la salud. En esta última se incluyen investigaciones en el campo de la actividad física y el deporte. La genética, por tanto, aporta conocimientos científicos que pueden ayudarnos a optimizar el rendimiento de un deportista de alto nivel, rentabilizar los efectos de la práctica del ejercicio físico y/o llevar a cabo una práctica deportiva segura, evaluando el riesgo de una enfermedad hereditaria asociada a la muerte súbita en deportistas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);44(162): 86-97, abr.-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genética y deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37631</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
