<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040257</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic efficacy of fine needle aspiration biopsy in patients with thyroid nodular disease. Analysis of 510 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The prevalence of palpable thyroid nodules in the general population is 4%-7%. Although most are benign, 5% are carcinomas. This study aimed to assess the efficacy of fine needle aspiration biopsy (FNAB) of thyroid nodules to diagnose malignancy and know the benefit of repeating the FNAB in the same nodule. Patients and methods. A total of 510 patients (431 women and 79 men; mean age [standard deviation]: 47.6 [14.3] years) with surgery due to thyroid nodular condition between 1989 and 2002 and who had at least one FNAB prior to the surgery were studied. Results. The first FNAB was benign in 312 patients (61.2%), malignant in 38 (7.5%), suspicious or indeterminate in 97 (19%) and insufficient in 63 (12.4%). Sensitivity and specificity in the first FNAB for malignancy diagnosis was 76% and 84%, respectively. Successive FNABs had a moderate concordance and significance. However, repeating the puncture did not improve diagnostic performance, since sensitive increased (84%), but specificity worsened (79%) and the area under the ROC curve was similar. In the group with suspicious or indeterminate FNAB, histology was benign in 70% and malignant in 30%. Conclusions. FNAB sensitivity and specificity for diagnosis of malignancy in thyroid nodules are high. Repetition of puncture on the same nodule does not improve diagnostic performance of the cytology. Among patients with suspicious FNAB, there is a high proportion of malignancy, which makes surgery necessary in these cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saavedra Vallejo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Díaz, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Villaizán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Onsurbe, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Carrera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez Torres, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La prevalencia de nódulos tiroideos palpables en la población general es del 4%-7%. Aunque la mayoría son benignos, un 5% son carcinomas. El objetivo de este estudio fue valorar la eficacia de la punción-aspiración con aguja fina (PAAF) de los nódulos tiroideos para diagnosticar malignidad y conocer el rendimiento de repetir la PAAF en el mismo nódulo. Pacientes y métodos. Se estudiaron 510 pacientes (431 mujeres y 79 varones; edad media [desviación estándar]: 47,6 [14,3] años) intervenidos quirúrgicamente por patología nodular tiroidea entre 1989 y 2002 y que tenían, al menos, una PAAF previa a la cirugía. Resultados. La primera PAAF fue benigna en 312 pacientes (61,2%), maligna en 38 (7,5%), sospechosa o indeterminada en 97 (19%) e insuficiente en 63 (12,4%). La sensibilidad y especificidad de la primera PAAF para el diagnóstico de malignidad fue del 76% y 84%, respectivamente. Las PAAF sucesivas tuvieron una concordancia moderada y significativa; sin embargo, la repetición de la punción no mejoró el rendimiento diagnóstico, ya que aumentó la sensibilidad (84%), pero empeoró la especificidad (79%) y el área bajo la curva ROC fue similar. En el grupo con PAAF sospechosa o indeterminada la histología fue benigna en el 70% y maligna en el 30%. Conclusiones. La sensibilidad y especificidad de la PAAF para el diagnóstico de malignidad en los nódulos tiroideos son elevadas. La repetición de la punción sobre el mismo nódulo no mejora el rendimiento diagnóstico de la citología. Entre los pacientes con PAAF sospechosa existe una proporción elevada de malignidad, lo que obliga a la intervención quirúrgica en estos casos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;205(8): 374-378, ago. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia diagnóstica de la punción-aspiración con aguja fina en pacientes con patología nodular tiroidea. Análisis de 510 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29779^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
