<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62959</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Pancreatoduodenectomy (PD) with initial dissection of the superior mesenteric artery (SMA) has been described as a useful technical variant to reduce blood loss and to avoid an unnecessary intervention in those cases with arterial involvement. Objectives. To analyse the results of two recent technical modifications of PD introduced by our group: initial dissection of SMA and antecolic gastroenterostomy. Patients and method. Patients were divided into two groups: with and without initial dissection of the SMA. The results were also analysed according to the type of gastric reconstruction. Perioperative and long-term results are compared. Results. The overall mortality was 5%, with no significant differences between the initial SMA dissection and conventional PD. The transfusion rate (p &lt; 0.001), the volume of blood products transfused (p = 0.001), and the overall complication rate were lower (p = 0.01) in the initial SMA dissection group. Also the postoperative hospital stay was significantly lower (p # 0.001). Despite a higher frequency of lymph node involvement in patients treated with initial SMA dissection (p = 0.001), the recurrence rate was similar between both groups. Among patients with initial SMA dissection, those who received antecolic reconstruction had a lower rate of delayed gastric emptying (p = 0.008). Conclusions. Initial SMA dissection PD is a safe technique. The transfusion rate, morbidity and postoperative hospital stay are better when compared with conventional CPD. When an antecolic duodenal-jejunal reconstruction is associated, delayed gastric emptying cases are less frequent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardina, Berta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falgueras, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ben, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codina-Barreras, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albiol, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daniel González, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueras, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maroto, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codina-Cazador, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Bahí, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La duodenopancreatectomía cefálica (DPC) con abordaje inicial de la arteria mesentérica superior (AMS) ha sido descrita como una técnica útil para reducir las pérdidas de sangre y evitar una intervención inútil si hay afectación arterial. Objetivos. Analizar los resultados de dos modificaciones recientes en la técnica quirúrgica de la DPC introducidas en nuestro grupo: disección primaria de la AMS y la gastroenterostomía antecólica. Pacientes y método. Se dividió a los pacientes en 2 grupos, según hayan recibido o no disección inicial de la AMS. También se analizaron los resultados según el tipo de reconstrucción gástrica. Se comparan los resultados perioperatorios y a largo plazo. Resultados. La mortalidad general fue del 5% sin diferencias entre la DPC con abordaje inicial de la AMS y la técnica convencional. La tasa de transfusión (p &lt; 0,001), el volumen transfundido (p = 0,001) y la incidencia general de complicaciones fue menor (p = 0,01) en el grupo con disección de la AMS. La estancia postoperatoria también fue significativamente menor (p # 0,001). A pesar de que la afectación ganglionar fue más frecuente en los pacientes operados con abordaje inicial de la AMS (p = 0,001), la tasa de recidiva fue la misma que con la técnica convencional. Dentro del grupo con disección inicial de la AMS, aquellos con reconstrucción antecólica presentaron con menor frecuencia retraso en el vaciamiento gástrico (p = 0,008). Conclusiones. La DPC con abordaje inicial de la AMS es una técnica segura. La transfusión, las complicaciones y la estancia hospitalaria son mejores. Cuando se asocia a reconstrucción duodenoyeyunal antecólica, los retrasos de vaciamiento gástrico son menos frecuentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);83(4): 186-193, abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62959</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8236^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29913^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5887^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13866^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
