<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058075</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prospective use of an intravascular ultrasound-derived minimum lumen area cut-off value in the assessment of intermediate left main coronary artery lesions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives. Angiographic assessment of the severity of intermediate lesions in the left main coronary artery (LMCA) is subject to significant limitations. Intravascular ultrasound (IVUS) can provide accurate measurement, but there is no agreement on the minimum lumen cross-sectional area (MLA) that indicates significant disease. The aim of this study was to determine the long-term safety of applying a cut-off value of 6 mm2 for the MLA in the LMCA. Methods. The study included patients with intermediate lesions (i.e., 25­50%) in unprotected LMCAs, with no previous evidence of associated ischemia. An IVUS examination was carried out and revascularization was indicated when the MLA was &amp;#8804;6 mm2. Results. In total, 79 patients were recruited between 2000­2005. In 31 (39%), the MLA was &amp;#8804;6 mm2, and they underwent LMCA revascularization; in the remaining 48 (61%), the MLA was &gt;6 mm2, and patients either underwent angioplasty for other lesions (n=37) or continued medical treatment (n=11). In a follow-up period of 40 [17] months, four patients (8.3%) died from heart disease, all of whom had an MLA between 9­10 mm2 in the baseline study. Revascularization of the LMCA was necessary in only two patients (4.2%), both of whom had elective surgery more than 2 years after the initial study. Conclusions. Intravascular ultrasound assessment of intermediate LMCA lesions using an MLA cut-off value of 6 mm2 appears safe over the long term provided the clinical and angiographic criteria applied to patient selection are similar to those used in this study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colman, Thierry</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Lera, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz-Laso, Fermín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Friera, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueroa, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Hernández, José M de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruisanchez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zueco, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La angiografía presenta limitaciones importantes para definir la severidad de las lesiones intermedias del tronco común. La ecografía endovascular (EEV) permite realizar una evaluación precisa, pero no hay consenso respecto a los valores de área luminal mínima (ALM) que indican significación. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la seguridad a largo plazo de la aplicación de un valor de corte de 6 mm2 para el ALM en el tronco. Métodos. Se ha incluido a pacientes con lesiones intermedias (25-50%) de tronco no protegido, sin datos previos indicativos de isquemia atribuible. Se realizó estudio con EEV y se indicó revascularización en los pacientes con ALM &amp;#8804; 6 mm2. Resultados. En el período 2000-2005 se ha incluido a 79 pacientes, en 31 (39%) el ALM fue &amp;#8804; 6 mm2 y recibieron revascularización del tronco, en los restantes 48 (61%) el ALM fue &gt; 6 mm2 y sólo se actuó sobre otras lesiones (n = 37) o continuaron con tratamiento médico (n = 11). En un seguimiento de 40 ± 17 meses se han producido 4 muertes cardiacas (8,3%), que ocurrieron en casos con un ALM de 9-10 mm2 en el estudio basal. Sólo en 2 casos (4,2%) fue preciso efectuar procedimientos de revascularización del tronco que consistieron en cirugías electivas tras más de 2 años del estudio inicial. Conclusiones. La evaluación con EEV de las lesiones intermedias de tronco y la consideración de un valor de corte de 6 mm2 para el ALM resulta segura a largo plazo, siempre que se consideren unos criterios clinicoangiográficos de aplicabilidad como los considerados en este estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(8): 811-816, ago. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación prospectiva de un valor de corte de área luminal mínima por ecografía intravascular en la evaluación de lesiones intermedias del tronco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14742^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30992^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30178^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
