<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144372</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Associations of IL-2 and IL-4 Expression and Polymorphisms With the Risks of Mycoplasma pneumoniae Infection and Asthma in Children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Asthma is an inflammatory disorder of the airways and the symptoms of asthma could be exacerbated by Mycoplasma pneumoniae infection. Interleukin-2 and interleukin-4 have been implicated in immune and inflammatory reactions. We examined the associations of IL2 andIL4 polymorphisms and expression with the risks of asthma and M. pneumoniae infection in children. Methods: 392 asthmatic children and 849 controls were recruited into the study. Eight polymorphisms inIL2 and IL4 were genotyped with Sequenom MassARRAY platform. M. pneumoniae infection and copy number was determined with fluorescence PCR. IL-2 and IL-4 serum expression levels were determined by using ELISA. Results: We found a significant association of IL2 rs6534349 polymorphism with increased asthma risk (heterozygotes, P=.029; homozygous variants; P=.013) and of IL4 rs2227284 polymorphism with reduced asthma risk (heterozygotes, P=.026; homozygous variants; P=.001). Besides, the association of other polymorphisms, except rs2070874 polymorphism, became apparent when the asthmatic children were grouped according to GINA classification of asthma control and severity. In addition, IL-2 and IL-4 serum expression levels were significantly higher in M. pneumoniae negative (P=.038) and positive (P=.011) subjects respectively. This observation holds true among asthmatic patients (P=.016 for IL-2 and P=.042 for IL-4), but only the IL-4 observation remained correct among non-asthmatic controls (P=.032). We also observed that the rs6534349 GG genotype was significantly associated with increased odds of getting high load M. pneumoniae infection (P=.0376). Conclusions: IL2 and IL4 could be important biomarkers for estimating the risks of asthma and M. pneumoniae infection in children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zhi- Jin, Biao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Shang, Shi-Qiang</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jin, Hong-Xing</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liu, Xi-Yong</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wang, Rong-Shan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chen, Shu-Jun</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El asma es una afección inflamatoria de las vías respiratorias. Las infecciones porMycoplasma pneumoniae pueden exacerbar los síntomas del asma. Se ha demostrado que la interleucina2 y la interleucina4 participan en las reacciones inmunitarias e inflamatorias. Hemos estudiado la relación entre los polimorfismos de la IL2 y la IL4 y su expresión y el riesgo de padecer asma e infección por M.pneumoniae en niños. Métodos: Se reclutó a 392 niños asmáticos y 849 controles para el estudio. Se genotiparon 8 polimorfismos en IL2 e IL4 con la plataforma MassARRAY de Sequenom. La infección por M.pneumoniae y el número de copias se establecieron mediante PCR fluorescente. Los niveles séricos de expresión de IL-2 e IL-4 se midieron con ELISA. Resultados: Hallamos una relación significativa entre el polimorfismo rs6534349 de IL2 y el aumento de riesgo de sufrir asma (heterocigóticos, p=0,029; variantes homocigóticas, p=0,013), así como entre el polimorfismo rs2227284 de IL4 y una reducción del riesgo de padecer asma (heterocigóticos, p=0,026; variantes homocigóticas, p=0,001). Además, la relación con otros polimorfismos, excepto el rs2070874, se hizo evidente al agrupar a los niños asmáticos según la clasificación GINA de control y gravedad del asma. Asimismo, los niveles séricos de expresión de IL-2 e IL-4 fueron significativamente mayores en los sujetos no infectados (p=0,038) e infectados (p=0,011) por M.pneumoniae, respectivamente. Esta observación también se cumple entre los pacientes asmáticos (p=0,016 para IL-2 y p=0,042 para IL-4), pero en los controles no asmáticos solo se cumple en el caso de la IL-4 (p=0,032). Del mismo modo, observamos que el genotipo GG rs6534349 estaba claramente relacionado con un aumento de las posibilidades de tener una infección con alta carga de M.pneumoniae (p=0,0376). Conclusiones: La IL2 y la IL4 podrían ser biomarcadores importantes para calcular el riesgo de padecer asma, así como infección por M.pneumoniae, en niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(11): 571-578, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre la expresión de IL-2 e IL-4 y sus polimorfismos y los riesgos de padecer infección por Mycoplasma pneumoniae y asma en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4258^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29489^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9369^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29470^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
