<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82717</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subclinical and established kidney disease in recently diagnosed hypertensive patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective:To estimate renal disease in recently diagnosed hypertensive patients, and to identify factors related to renal disease. Patients and methods: Cross-sectional study, with 425 hypertensive patients recently diagnosed in primary health care; renal disease was estimated with serum creatinine, albumin/creatinine index and glomerular filtration rate (GFR). We analyzed cardiovascular risk factors (CRF), subclinical organ injury and cardiovascular disease following the criteria of the 2007 European Guide of Hypertension. Results: Average age: 58,96±12,73 years old, 63,3% male. We found dyslipemia in 80%, abdominal obesity in 49% and metabolic syndrome in 36% patients. These patients showed increased serum creatinine 3,3%, a reduction in GFR 9,6%, hidden renal disease 6,4%, microalbuminuria 7,5% and nephropathy 2,4%. Hypertensive patients with renal disease (17,88%) were older, with higher systolic pressure, higher incidence of metabolic syndrome, abnormal carotid intima-media thickness and ankle-arm index, and presence of cardiovascular disease. Variables associated with renal disease were metabolic syndrome (odds ratio =11,12) and ankle-arm index (odds ratio =17,55). Variables related to creatinina were sex, ankle-arm index and metabolic syndrome; variables related to GFR were sex, age, ankle-arm index, metabolic syndrome and body mass index (BMI); variables related with albumin/creatinine index included diabetes mellitus. Conclusions: Renal disease is detected in about 2 out of 10 hypertensive patients, when, besides serum creatinina, we analyze albumin/creatinine index and GFR. Metabolic syndrome and ankle-arm index are the main variables associated with renal disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Recio Rodríguez, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ortíz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Marcos, Manuel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grandes, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Sánchez, Emiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Sánchez, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Salgado, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Estimar la prevalencia de afectación renal en pacientes hipertensos de nuevo diagnóstico e identificar los factores relacionados con esta afectación renal. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio transversal de 425 hipertensos de reciente diagnóstico en atención primaria. La afectación renal se ha valorado con la creatinina, índice albumina/ creatinina y tasa de filtrado glomerular (TFG). Los factores de riesgo cardiovascular, la lesión orgánica subclínica y la enfermedad cardiovascular se analizaron según los criterios de la Guía Europea de Hipertensión de 2007. Resultados: Edad media de 58,96 (DE: 12,73) años, el 63,3% eran varones. Encontramos dislipidemia en el 80%, obesidad abdominal en el 49% y síndrome metabólico en el 36%. Presentaron creatinina elevada el 3,3%, TFG disminuida el 9,6%, afectación renal oculta el 6,4%, oligoalbuminuria el 7,5% y nefropatía el 2,4%. Los hipertensos con afectación renal (17,88%) tenían mayor edad, presión arterial sistólica más elevada, mayor porcentaje de síndrome metabólico, íntima-media de carótida e índice tobillo/brazo patológico, así como mayor proporción de enfermedad cardiovascular. Las variables asociadas a la afectación renal fueron la presencia de síndrome metabólico (OR=11,12) y el índice tobillo/brazo patológico (OR=17,55). Las variables asociadas a creatinina elevada fueron sexo, índice tobillo/brazo patológico y síndrome metabólico; las variables asociadas a TFG disminuida fueron edad, sexo, índice tobillo/brazo patológico, síndrome metabólico e índice de masa corporal, y la variable asociada al índice albumina/creatinina elevado fue la diabetes mellitus.  Conclusión: Se detecta afectación renal aproximadamente en 2 de cada 10 hipertensos cuando, además de la creatinina sérica, realizamos índice albumina/creatinina y TFG. El síndrome metabólico y el índice tobillo/brazo patológico son los principales indicadores de afectación renal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);134(6): 246-253, mar. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82717</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afección renal subclínica y establecida en pacientes hipertensos de nuevo diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
