<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77302</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Olfactory rehabilitation after total laringectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze the olfactory function in patients after total laryngectomy and evaluate the outcomes of the use of the induced nasal airflow manoeuvre. Material and methods: A prospective clinical intervention study was carried out with 41 patients who had undergone total laryngectomy, of which 39 were male and 2 female. After verifying that there were no anatomical disorders, the patients were given an olfaction test that classified them into two groups, those with olfactory perception and those without. All underwent rehabilitation using the induced nasal airflow technique and, subsequently, the olfaction test was repeated to enable a comparison with the first results obtained. A semi-structured interview was held to evaluate the senses of taste and smell of the participants, also taking into account their own opinion. Results: Out of the 41 patients included in the study, 9 had olfactory perception before rehabilitation, according to the first olfaction test. The use of the nasal airflow maneuver meant the recovery or improvement of the olfactory capacity in 90.24% of the patients. Conclusions: The induced nasal airflow technique enables an important recovery of olfaction and improvement of taste after total laryngectomy. This technique is easy to learn and to repeat. It does not require expensive materials. The recovery of olfaction and taste implies an improvement in quality of life for the patient, so this technique should be included in all protocols of comprehensive rehabilitation after total laryngectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales-Puebla, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Antolín, Jorge A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Platón, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chacón-Martínez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla-Parrado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Puebla, Ángel F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Examinar la función olfatoria en pacientes laringectomizados y evaluar los resultados de la aplicación de la maniobra de inducción de flujo aéreo nasal. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio prospectivo de intervención con 41 pacientes laringectomizados, 39 hombres y 2 mujeres. Tras la comprobación de ausencia de alteraciones anatómicas, los participantes fueron sometidos a un test olfatométrico que los dividía en pacientes con olfato y pacientes sin olfato. Todos fueron sometidos a la rehabilitación del olfato mediante la técnica de inducción de flujo aéreo nasal y, posteriormente, a un segundo test olfatométrico para comparar los resultados con el primero. La valoración del sentido del gusto y del olfato de los pacientes se realizó a través de una entrevista semiestructurada en la que se tuvo en cuenta la opinión de cada uno de ellos. Resultados: De los 41 pacientes incluidos en el estudio, 9 tenían capacidad olfativa previa a la rehabilitación según el primer test olfatométrico. La realización de la rehabilitación supuso la recuperación o mejoría de la capacidad olfativa para el 90,24% de los pacientes. Conclusiones: La inducción de flujo aéreo nasal es una técnica que permite la recuperación del olfato y mejora del gusto a personas laringectomizadas. Es de fácil aprendizaje y realización. No precisa de medios técnicos costosos. La recuperación del olfato y el gusto mejoran la calidad de vida del paciente, por lo que esta técnica debería incluirse en los protocolos de rehabilitación integral del paciente laringectomizado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;61(2): 128-134, mar.-abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77302</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación olfativa tras la laringectomía total</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
