<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131122</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">FRAX® thresholds to identify people with high or low risk of osteoporotic fracture in Spanish female population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To detect FRAX® threshold levels that identify groups of the population that are at high/low risk of osteoporotic fracture in the Spanish female population using a cost-effective assessment. Patients and methods: This is a cohort study. Eight hundred and sixteen women 40-90 years old selected from the FRIDEX cohort with densitometry and risk factors for fracture at baseline who received no treatment for osteoporosis during the 10 year follow-up period and were stratified into 3 groups/levels of fracture risk (low &lt; 10%, 10-20% intermediate and high &gt; 20%) according to the real fracture incidence. Results: The thresholds of FRAX® baseline for major osteoporotic fracture were: low risk &lt; 5; intermediate &amp;#8805; 5 to &lt; 7.5 and high &amp;#8805; 7.5. The incidence of fracture with these values was: low risk (3.6%; 95% CI 2.2-5.9), intermediate risk (13.7%; 95% CI 7.1-24.2) and high risk (21.4%; 95% CI12.9-33.2). The most cost-effective option was to refer to dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA-scan) for FRAX® &amp;#8805; 5 (Intermediate and high risk) to reclassify by FRAX® with DXA-scan at high/low risk. These thresholds select 17.5% of women for DXA-scan and 10% for treatment. With these thresholds of FRAX®, compared with the strategy of opportunistic case finding isolated risk factors, would improve the predictive parameters and reduce 82.5% the DXA-scan, 35.4% osteoporosis prescriptions and 28.7% cost to detect the same number of women who suffer fractures. Conclusions: The use of FRAX ® thresholds identified as high/low risk of osteoporotic fracture in this calibration (FRIDEX model) improve predictive parameters in Spanish women and in a more cost-effective than the traditional model based on the T-score &amp;#8804; -2.5 of DXA scan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roca, Genís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zwart, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguyé, Amada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Pérez, Adolf</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azagra, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encabo, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Sánchez, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Detectar los umbrales de la herramienta FRAX® que determinen los grupos de riesgo alto/bajo de fractura osteoporótica en la población femenina española y su valoración coste-efectiva. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio de cohortes. Ochocientas dieciséis mujeres de 40-90 años de la cohorte FRIDEX con densitometría basal, factores de riesgo de fractura y sin tratamiento para la osteoporosis en los 10 años de seguimiento. Se estratificaron en 3 grupos/niveles de riesgo de fractura principal (bajo &lt; 10%, intermedio 10-20% y alto &gt; 20%) según la incidencia real de fractura, y se buscaron los puntos de corte equivalentes de FRAX® basal. Resultados: Los umbrales de FRAX® basal para fractura principal fueron: riesgo bajo &lt; 5; intermedio &amp;#8805; 5 y &lt; 7,5 y alto &amp;#8805; 7,5. La incidencia real de fractura con estos valores fue: riesgo bajo (3,6%; IC 95% 2,2-5,9); intermedio (13,7%; IC 95%7,1-24,2), y alto (21,4%; IC 95% 12,9-33,2). La opción más coste-efectiva fue realizar una dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA, «absorciometría dual de rayos X») para FRAX® &amp;#8805; 5 (riesgo intermedio y alto) para reclasificar los casos mediante FRAX® con DXA en riesgo alto/bajo. Así se seleccionarían 17,5% de las mujeres para DXA y 10% para tratamiento. Con estos umbrales calibrados de FRAX®, comparados con la estrategia tradicional basada en la DXA, se mejoran los parámetros predictivos y se reducen las DXA (82,5%), los tratamientos (35,4%) y el coste global (28,7%) para detectar al mismo número de mujeres que tuvieron fracturas. Conclusiones: La utilización de los umbrales de FRAX® identificados como alto/bajo riesgo de fractura osteoporótica en la presente calibración (modelo FRIDEX) mejorarían los parámetros predictivos en mujeres españolas y de una forma más coste-efectiva que el modelo tradicional basado en el T-score &amp;#8804; -2,5 de la DXA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);144(1): 1-8, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Umbrales de FRAX ® para identificar personas con alto o bajo riesgo de fractura osteoporótica en población femenina española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54019^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
