<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130760</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The mediating role of empathy, prosocial and aggressive behavior in depression and anxiety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current study aims to examine the mediating role of prosocial behavior with empathy and aggressive behavior in depression and anxiety. Participants are 937 Spanish adolescents, 48% girls and 54% boys, aged between 15 and 16 years old (M = 15.32; SD = .47), with medium to medium-low income levels. The structural equation modeling shows that aggressiveness has a direct positive influence on depression. On the contrary, prosocial behavior has a direct and negative influence. That is, prosocial behavior protects adolescents from depression. Emotional instability has a direct relationship with depression and anxiety. Finally, results and their possible implications are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Samper García, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesurado, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorca Mestre, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analiza el rol mediador de la conducta prosocial junto a la empatía y la conducta agresiva en su relación con la depresión y la ansiedad. Los participantes son 937 adolescentes españoles de 15 y 16 años (M = 15.32; DT = .47), varones 54% y mujeres 48%, de nivel socioeconómico medio y medio bajo. Los modelos de ecuaciones estructurales muestran que la agresividad  tiene una influencia directa positiva sobre la depresión. En cambio, la conducta prosocial tiene una influencia directa y negativa. Es decir, la prosocialidad protege de la depresión a los adolescentes. La inestabilidad emocional mantiene una relación directa con la ansiedad y la depresión, cosa que no ocurre con las otras variables. Finalmente, se discuten los resultados y sus posibles implicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;20(2/3): 247-258, jul.-dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130760</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El rol mediador de la empatía, la conducta prosocial y la conducta agresiva en la depresión y la ansiedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
