<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141255</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aetiology, classification and pathogenesis of pulp and periapical disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present, the majority of the treatments that are performed in the clinic are due to disease entities involving the dental pulp and periapex. Dental pulp is a richly vascularized and innervated tissue, enclosed by surrounding tissues that are incapable of expanding, such as dentin. It has terminal blood flow and small-gauge circulatory access &#150; the periapex. All of these characteristics severely constrain the defensive capacity of the pulp tissue when faced with the different aggressions it may be subjected to. Pulp tissue can also be affected by a retrograde infection (1), arising from the secondary canaliculi, from the periodontal ligament or from the apex during the course of periodontitis. Due to the fact that periapical disease is almost inevitably preceded by pulp disease, we shall begin by describing the causes (2) of pulp disease and will then proceed to a discussion of the causes of periapical disease. The course of illness and classification of these pathological entities will depend on the aetiology involved. We will analyse pulp necrosis and pulp degeneration that are capable of triggering reversible apical periodontitis or irreversible apical periodontitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Marcos, Joaquín F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, gran parte de los tratamientos que se realizan en la clínica son debidos a patologías que afectan a la pulpa y al periápice. La pulpa es un tejido ricamente vascularizado e inervado, delimitado por un entorno inextensible como es la dentina, con una circulación sanguínea terminal y con una zona de acceso circulatorio &#150;periápice&#150; de pequeño calibre. Todo ello, hace que la capacidad defensiva del tejido pulpar sea muy limitada ante las diversas agresiones que pueda sufrir. El tejido pulpar también puede ser afectado por una infección retrógrada (1), a partir de los canalículos secundarios, desde el ligamento periodontal o desde el ápice durante un proceso de periodontitis. Debido a que la patología periapical va casi siempre precedida de una afectación de la pulpa, describiremos en primer lugar las causas (2) de enfermedad pulpar y a continuación las causas de la patología periapical. De dicha etiología dependerá la evolución y la clasificación de estas patologías. Analizaremos la necrosis pulpar y la degeneración pulpar que pueden desencadenar una periodontitis apical reversible o una periodontitis apical irreversible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);9(supl): 52-62, dic. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiología, clasificación y patogenia de la patología pulpar y periapical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
