<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167685</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Brief Inventory of Symptoms (BSI-18) among mexican women diagnosed with breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Distress is an unpleasant emotional experience that can affect the coping and course of an oncological disease. The Brief Inventory of Symptoms (BSI-18) is frequently used in cancer patients to measure distress. However, its factorial structure is not well established, and its metric properties have not been studied with Mexican samples. The present research aims to study the distribution, discriminability and homogeneity of BSI-18 items, estimate the internal consistency of the BSI-18, determine its factorial structure, and calculate the convergent, discriminant validity and internal consistency of its factors. An intentional sample of 203 women with breast cancer on oncological treatment was collected. All of them were adults treated in the city of Monterrey, Mexico. All BSI-18 items were discriminative and consistent. Their distributions showed higher concentration in low values. The internal consistency of the scale was high (Cronbach&#146;s &amp;#945; = .888). The model of a general distress factor with three hierarchical factors (depression, sympathetic anxiety symptoms and vasovagal anxiety symptoms) showed the best goodness-of-fit properties. Also, its factors had the best properties of convergent validity and internal consistency. In addition, this model allowed to overcome the problems of discriminant validity between the factors. We concluded that, in the studied population of women diagnosed with cancer, all items of the BSI-18 can be retained, and scale was consistent and valid from a hierarchical model of three factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miaja Ávila, Melina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral De la Rubia, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El distrés es una experiencia emocional desagradable que puede afectar al afrontamiento y curso de una enfermedad oncológica. El Inventario Breve de Síntomas (BSI-18) es usado frecuentemente en pacientes oncológicos para medir distrés. No obstante, su estructura factorial no está bien establecida, y sus propiedades métricas no han sido estudiadas con muestras mexicanas. La presente investigación tiene como objetivos estudiar la distribución, discriminabilidad y homogeneidad de los ítems del BSI-18, estimar la consistencia interna del BSI-18, determinar su estructura factorial y calcular la validez convergente, discriminante y consistencia interna de sus factores. Se recolectó una muestra intencional de 203 mujeres con cáncer de mama en tratamiento oncológico. Todas ellas eran adultas tratadas en la ciudad de Monterrey, México. Todos los ítems del BSI-18 resultaron discriminativos y consistentes. Sus distribuciones mostraron mayor concentración en valores bajos. La consistencia interna de la escala fue alta (&amp;#945; de Cronbach=0,888). El modelo de un factor general de distrés con tres factores jerarquizados (depresión, síntomas simpáticos de ansiedad y síntomas vasovagales de ansiedad) mostró las mejores propiedades de bondad de ajuste. También sus factores tuvieron las mejores propiedades de validez convergente y consistencia interna. Además, este modelo permitió superar los problemas de validez discriminante entre los factores. Se concluye que, en la población estudiada de mujeres diagnosticadas con cáncer, se pueden retener todos los ítems del BSI-18, y la escala resultó consistente y válida desde un modelo jerarquizado de tres factores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);14(2/3): 307-324, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167685</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del Inventario Breve de Síntomas (BSI-18) en mujeres mexicanas diagnosticadas con cáncer de mamaValidación del Inventario Breve de Síntomas (BSI-18) en mujeres mexicanas diagnosticadas con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
