<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057652</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elders´perspective about Aavance directives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The introduction of advance directives (AD) require to examine the perspective their potential users have about. Any public policy about the implementation of ADs adressed to elders will fall if their perspective is unknown. Objective: To examine the elders' perspective about advance directives.      Methods: Qualitative study. 40 elders, users of 3 Primary Health Care Center, and of 1 Nursing Home from Madrid. 5 focus groups were organized in 2004 April.      Participants: 14 providers recruited 2-3 participants each. Age and emplacement (home or institution) were the variables considered as the most important for the discurse differences about ADs. They were used as segmentation criteria, looking for heterogeneity between groups, and homogeneity and heterogeneity intra groups. The discussion of each group last until no new concepts arose.     Results: 4 assumptions source from groups: 1) Elder people prefer advanced care planning to only signed ADs. 2) Their opinion about ADs is linked to other events about the end of life. 3) They give a relevant role to their families. 4) They desire to control their lifes and decisions, but "without papers".     Conclusion: The implementation of ADs through educational public policies  in elder population only will sucess if elders' perspective is considered</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio Cantalejo, Inés M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón Lorda, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Bello, José M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascau González-Garzón, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Güemez Abad, M. Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La popularización del testamento vital (TV) exige conocer la perspectiva que sobre él tienen sus potenciales usuarios. Cualquier intento de generalizar el TV sin evaluar cómo será recibido por las personas mayores está condenado al fracaso.      Objetivo: Explorar la perspectiva de los mayores sobre el testamento vital.      Diseño: Estudio cualitativo. 40 personas mayores, usuarios de 3 Centros de Salud y 1 Residencia Asistida de Madrid, se reunieron en 5 grupos de discusión en abril de 2004.     Participantes: 14 mediadores captaron a 2-3 participantes cada uno. Se consideró que edad y residencia en medio familiar o institucional son las variables que más diferencian la elaboración de los discursos sobre el TV. Se utilizaron, pues, como criterios de segmentación, buscando heterogeneidad entre grupos y homogeneidad y heterogeneidad intragrupal. La saturación se consideró cuando las ideas expresadas resultaron recurrentes.     Resultados: 4 ideas se extraen de los datos: 1) los mayores prefieren la planificación anticipada de decisiones al TV. 2) Su opinión sobre el TV se asocia a la vivencia singular de otros eventos en el final de la vida. 3) Conceden un papel relevante a la familia. 4) Desean conducir su propia vida, pero &#147;sin papeles escritos&#148;. Conclusiones. La implementación del TV a través de una estrategia educativa e institucional se beneficiará si consideramos la perspectiva de la población mayor española sobre el TV</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;15(52/53): 35-39, 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La perspectiva de las personas mayores sobre el testamento vital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15318^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
