<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152429</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of olanzapine in the treatment of schizophrenia and bipolar disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Olanzapine is a derived of tienobenzodiazepina that integrate in a group of second generation of antipsychotics drugs. It was aproved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the European Medicines Agency (EMA) in the year 1996 for the treatment of schizophrenia, and in the same year the EMA authorizes their use in bipolar disorder. Sooner it was approved for the treatment of depressive Bipolar Disord episodes in combination with fluoxetine (FDA, year 2003), treatment in long term and prevention relapses of bipolar disorder I (FDA, year 2004) and resistant depression in combination with fluoxetine (FDA, year 2009). The authors carried out a critical and thorough review of existing scientific evidence about the efficacy and safety of olanzapine in schizophrenia and bipolar I disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbosa, Lucila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La olanzapina es un derivado tienobenzodiacepínico que pertenece al grupo de los fármacos antipsicóticos de segunda generación. Fue aprobada por la Food and Drug Administration (FDA) y la European Medicines Agency (EMA) en el año 1996 para el tratamiento de la esquizofrenia, y en el mismo año la EMA autorizó su utilización en el trastorno bipolar. Más tarde se aprobó para el tratamiento de episodios depresivos del trastorno bipolar en combinación con fluoxetina (FDA, año 2003), tratamiento a largo plazo y prevención de recaídas del trastorno bipolar I (FDA, año 2004) y depresión resistente en combinación con fluoxetina (FDA, año 2009). Los autores realizaron una revisión crítica y exhaustiva de la evidencia científica existente acerca de la eficacia y la seguridad de la olanzapina en la esquizofrenia y en el trastorno bipolar I (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);23(1): 4-22, ene.-abr. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de olanzapina en el tratamiento de la esquizofrenia y el trastorno bipolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28248^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12032^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
