<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048020</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Collaboration among health professionals (I). Context, dynamics and determining factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">More often at present times, services offered by health organizations are based on the collaboration amond distinct professionals. In this team work approach, nursing professionals have an important role to play. HAving as our objective providing nursing professionals with a theoretical basis which facilitates understanding collaboration, the authors publish an article having two sections. In the first section, the authors expound on the theoretical bases giving in depth analysis to the concept of inter-professional collaboration and describing those factors which, according to literature, determine the success of this collaboration in practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San Martín Rodríguez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D´Amour, Danielle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrada Videla, Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los servicios ofrecidos por las organizaciones    de salud se basan cada vez más    en la colaboración entre distintos profesionales.    En este trabajo en equipo,    los profesionales de enfermerfa tienen    un importante rol quedesempeñar. Así    pues, con el objetivo de ofrecer una    base teórica que facilite la comprensión de la colaboración, presentamos un artículo en dos partes. En el primero se exponen las bases teóricas profundizando en el concepto de colaboración interprofesional y describiendo aquellos elementos que, según la literatura determinarán el éxito en la práctica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;29(6): 425-430, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La colaboración entre los profesionales de la salud (I). Contexto, dinámica y elementos determinantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
