<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137448</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Overload, psychopathologies and relationship with the community pharmacist in informal caregivers of Alzheimer&#146;s patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Daily care for a relative who is an Alzheimer&#146;s patient (AP) entails a significant emotional and physical stress for the caregiver. This can result in an intense feeling of overload and lead to diverse psychopathologies as depression, anxiety, aggressiveness, psychophysical asthenia, etc. The increase in the rate of occurrence of the disease is causing a shortage of caregivers and a lack of social and institutional support to the families responsible for caring for an AP. Objectives: To review the characteristics of the support that the social and healthcare structures provide informal caregivers (IC) of AP, to get to know their profile, the perception they have of their situation and their state of mind, to detect psychopathologies that may affect them, to quantify their level of overload and to evaluate the social support perceived, the current degree of family satisfaction and the relationship with their regular pharmacist. Methods: Crossover descriptive study involving IC of non-institutionalized AP, recruited in associations for relatives of AP in Galicia, who are over 18 years of age and have given their informed consent. Primary variable: score on the Zarit overload scale for the caregiver. Others: socio-demographic, anxiety (STAI), depression (Beck) and the social (Duke-UNC) and family support (APGAR) perceived. Discussion: The results of the method implemented in this study be used to develop similar programs in the community pharmacy, in which the community pharmacists collaborate in the detection of possible psychopathologies, and through the provision of professionals services help to improve the quality of life and state of health of the caregiver (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vérez Cotelo, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fornos Pérez, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Rodríguez, N Floro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Iglesias, J Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mera Gallego, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Lago, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cuidado diario de un familiar enfermo de Alzheimer (EA) supondrá un estrés emocional y físico importante para el cuidador. El resultado puede desembocar en un intenso sentimiento de sobrecarga y conducir a diversas psicopatologías como depresión, ansiedad, agresividad, astenia psicofísica, etc. El aumento en la incidencia de la enfermedad está provocando escasez de cuidadores y falta de apoyo social e institucional a las familias que se encargan de cuidar a un EA. Objetivos: Revisar las características del apoyo que las estructuras sociales y sanitarias prestan a los cuidadores informales (CI) de EA, conocer su perfil, la percepción que tienen de su situación y su estado de ánimo, detectar posibles psicopatologías que les afecten, cuantificar el nivel de sobrecarga, evaluar el apoyo social percibido, el grado de satisfacción familiar y la relación con su farmacia habitual. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal en el que participan CI de EA no institucionalizados, reclutados en las asociaciones de familiares de EA de Galicia, mayores de 18 años y que den su consentimiento informado. Variable principal: puntuación del test de Zarit de sobrecarga del cuidador. Otras: socio-demográficas, ansiedad (STAI), depresión (Beck) y apoyo social (Duke-UNC) y familiar (APGAR) percibido. Discusión: Los resultados de la metodología implementada en este estudio pueden servir para desarrollar programas similares en la farmacia comunitaria, en la que los farmacéuticos comunitarios colaboren en la detección de posibles psicopatologías, y contribuir, mediante la prestación de servicios profesionales, a conseguir una mejora en la calidad de vida y estado de salud de los cuidadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);7(1): 32-37, mar. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobrecarga, psicopatologías y relación con el farmacéutico comunitario en cuidadores informales de enfermos de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
