<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84085</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spine cord descompresion and instrumentation in a case of solid aneurysmal bone cyst in the lumbar spine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a 8-year-old boy with two month historyof pain and stiffness in his left lower extremity. On xray,MRI and scintigraphy examinations a lytic lesionaffecting the body and posterior arc of his third lumbarvertebral become evident. The tumour was excisedthrough a double, anterior and posterior approach;spinal fusion with posterior transpedicular instrumentationwas also performed in the same procedure; inorder to achieve solid fusion tricortical liofilized graftwas also inserted. Histological studies evidenced findingcompatible with aneurismal bone cyst solid variant.Five years after surgery the patient is pain free and norecurrence is evident under diagnostic images tools. Forthe treatment of aneurismal bone cyst of the spine werecommend complete excision of the tumour in a combinedanterior and posterior one staged procedure, togetherwith hardware instrumentation and bone graft, norecurrence or instability is seen after five years followup (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero-Moyano, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada-Rubio, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Martín, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerado-Parra, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se discute el caso de un paciente varón de ochoaños de edad que refería dolor y limitación funcionalen extremidad inferior izquierda. Tras estudios complementariosmediante radiografías, tomografía axialcomputarizada, resonancia magnética y gammagrafíase evidenció la presencia de una lesión osteolítica encuerpo y arco posterior de la tercera vértebra lumbar.La tumoración fue resecada a través de doble abordaje(anterior retroperitoneal y posterior) e instrumentaciónpedicular posterior con aporte estructural de huesotricortical liofilizado en un solo tiempo. El diagnósticohistológico reveló la presencia de variante sólida de unquiste óseo aneurismático. Cinco años tras la cirugía elpaciente no presentó dolor lumbar ni recurrencia de laenfermedad. La resección completa del tumor junto coninstrumentación pedicular previno recidivas y desarrollode inestabilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);21(3): 240-244, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descompresión medular e instrumentación en un caso de variante sólida de quisteóseo aneurismático en raquis lumbar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33112^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13500^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28996</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33112^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13500</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13500^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13500^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
