<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154876</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization of disabled people with permanent limitations in mobility and self-care in Giron, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the characteristics of people with permanent limitations in mobility and self-care in 17 districts of the urban area of Giron, Santander 2012-2013. Materials and methods: A descriptive, observational, cross-sectional study was conducted using the tool Register for the Location and characterization of the disabled people (RLCDP), designed by the National Administrative Department of Statistics (DANE). Previously trained physiotherapy students interviewed caregivers or disabled people. Results: A total of 189 people were studied of 50.3% women, and 45.5% between 60 and 100 years old. A large majority (79.9%) had alterations in body movement, hands, arms and legs. As regards activities and participation, 91% had difficult to walk, run, jump, and 41.3% found it difficult to lead, move, and use objects with hands. Of the bodily functions, 60.3% involved mobility. General illness diseases were the main cause of disability (33.9%). Conclusions: A high percentage of persons with permanent mobility limitations and caring for themselves in the urban area of Girona are older adults from socioeconomic level 2. The predominant mobility limitations are in the hands, arms, and legs, with involvement in at least two body structures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar-Ballesta, KJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanabria-Jerez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villamizar-García, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Duarte, SA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez-Chaussinant, MX</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Miranda, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno-Balaguer, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Marín, RP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angarita-Fonseca, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila-Galván, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo-Rincón, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar las características de la población con limitaciones permanentes en movilidad y autocuidado de 17 barrios del área urbana del municipio de Girón, Santander 2012-2013. Materiales y métodos: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo, observacional y transversal, que utilizó el Registro para la localización y caracterización de las personas con discapacidad (RLCPD), diseñado por el Departamento Administrativo Nacional de Estadística (DANE). Estudiantes de fisioterapia previamente entrenados entrevistaron a cuidadores o personas con discapacidad. Resultados: Se encuestó a 189 personas, el 50,3% mujeres, el 45,5% tenía entre 60 y 100 años de edad y el 79,9% presentó alteraciones en el movimiento del cuerpo, las manos, los brazos y las piernas. En relación con las actividades y la participación, al 91% se le dificultó caminar, correr, saltar; al 41,3% llevar, mover, utilizar objetos con las manos. En las funciones corporales comprometidas, el 60,3% correspondía a movilidad. La enfermedad general fue la mayor causa de discapacidad (33,9%). Conclusiones: Las personas con limitaciones permanentes en la movilidad y el autocuidado en el área urbana de Girón en un alto porcentaje son adultas mayores pertenecientes a un estrato socioeconómico. Las limitaciones en el movimiento predominantes son las de manos, brazos y piernas, teniendo afectación en al menos dos estructuras corporales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(5): 237-245, sept.-oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de la discapacidad en población con limitaciones permanentes en movilidad o autocuidado, Girón, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28445</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
