<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125155</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pedicle flaps based on the sphenopalatine artery: Anatomical and surgical study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Local pedicle flaps based on the sphenopalatine artery make it possible to reconstruct large defects of the skull base (SB). Material and methods: From January 2008 to January 2013, 64 lesions with involvement of SB were analysed. These lesions were treated using endoscopic endonasal approach and required a pedicle flap based on the sphenopalatine artery. In addition, measurements and flexibility of the flaps were examined in 4 cadaveric nasal cavities. Results: Surgical group. Sixty-four nasoseptal flaps (NSF) were used, in 4 cases associated with a middle turbinate flap (MTF), and in 1 case supplemented with an inferior turbinate flap (ITF). Five cerebrospinal fluid fistulas (8%) were noted. Among patients with initial lesions, 7% presented an anosmia. Cadaveric group. The length of the NSF varied between 5.2 cm and 7.7 cm and the width ranged from 3 cm to 4.5 cm. The ITF provided an anterior-posterior distance between 4.2 cm and 5 cm, with a width between 1.2 cm and 2.8 cm. The mean length of MTFs varied between 3.5 cm and 4.2 cm, with a width between 1.4 cm and 1.9 cm. Conclusion: The most versatile local flap for the reconstruction of skull base defects is the NSF, and flaps pedicled to the posterolateral nasal artery offer an excellent alternative (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kolanczak, Katarzyna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monjas-Canovas, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massegur-Solench, Humbert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gras-Albert, Juan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez del Campo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gras-Cabrerizo, Juan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montserrat-Gili, Joan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Garrigós, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los colgajos locales pediculados a la arteria esfenopalatina permiten reconstruir amplios defectos de la base del cráneo (BC). Material y métodos: De enero de 2008 a enero de 2013 se analizaron 64 lesiones con afectación de la BC intervenidos con un abordaje endonasal endoscópico que requirieron una reconstrucción con colgajos locales pediculados a la arteria esfenopalatina. Adicionalmente se estudiaron cuatro fosas nasales correspondientes a dos cabezas de cadáver donde se analizaron endoscópicamente las medidas y la flexibilidad de cada uno de los colgajos. Resultados: Grupo quirúrgico. Se emplearon 64 colgajos nasoseptales (CNS), en cuatro casos asociados a un colgajo cornete medio (CCM) y en un caso complementado con un colgajo del cornete inferior (CCI). Se evidenciaron 5 fístulas postquirúrgicas (8%). Un 7% de los pacientes con lesiones iniciales presentaron una anosmia definitiva. Disección anatómica. La longitud del CNS varió entre 5,2 cm y 7,7 cm oscilando la anchura entre 3 cm y 4,5 cm. El CCI presentó una distancia anteroposterior entre 4,2 cm y 5 cm y una anchura entre 1,2 cm y 2,8 cm. La longitud media del CCM varió entre 3,5 cm y 4,2 cm con una anchura entre 1,4 cm y 1,9 cm. Conclusión: El CNS es el colgajo local que presenta una mejor versatilidad en el sellado de los defectos craneales, siendo los colgajos pediculados a la arteria nasal posterolateral una excelente alternativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;65(4): 242-248, jul.-ago. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajos pediculados procedentes de la arteria esfenopalatina: estudio anatómico y quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32869^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
