<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040959</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thinking psychiatry: the state of the matter</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Current psychiatry seems to ha ve assimilated the total hegemony of the biomedical model. Nevertheless, in Europe and America diverse attempts are being made to rejlect on the conceptual framework and the theoretical foundations of psychiatric science. The past years ha ve seen the emergence of work groups specializing in psychiatric philosophy, publishing initiatives, specijic scientijic meetings, etc. The impact of Kandel's work is a good illustration of current interests in drawing up a new theoretical foundation for psychiatry from empirical findingsCurrent psychiatry seems to ha ve assimilated the total hegemony of the biomedical model. Nevertheless, in Europe and America diverse attempts are being made to rejlect on the conceptual framework and the theoretical foundations of psychiatric science. The past years ha ve seen the emergence of work groups specializing in psychiatric philosophy, publishing initiatives, specijic scientijic meetings, etc. The impact of Kandel's work is a good illustration of current interests in drawing up a new theoretical foundation for psychiatry from empirical findings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baca Baldomero, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La psiquiatría actual parece haber asumido la hegemonía total del modelo biomédico. Sin embargo se están produciendo en Europa y América diversos intentos de rejlexionar teóricamente sobre el marco conceptual y los fundamentos teóricos de la ciencia psiquiátrica. En los últimos años han aparecido grupos de trabajo especializados en filosofía de la psiquiatría, iniciativas editoriales, reuniones científicas específicas, etc. El impacto que está teniendo la obra de Kandel es un buen ejemplo del interés actual por elaborar una nueva fundamentación teórica de la psiquiatría a partir de los hallazgos empíricos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;68(3): 171-178, jul.-sept. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040959</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pensar la psiquiatría: estado de la cuestión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10878^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
