<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153597</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of blood pressure in patients undergoing allogeneic transplant and on treatment with cyclosporine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the evolution pattern of blood pressure and the type of antihypertensive drugs required by patients undergoing allergenic transplant and on treatment with cyclosporine. Method: a descriptive study of a series of cases. A non-probability convenience sampling was conducted with a sample of 36patients. Those persons who had undergone an allogeneic transplant and required treatment with cyclosporine were selected. The variables studied were: gender, age, type of transplant, blood pressure (BP) at baseline, days and way of administration of cyclosporine, as well as pattern and evolution of blood pressure. The toxicity presented was described as associated hypertension according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE. v4).Results: the mean BP was 164.6/89.8, and a higher increase of systolic pressure vs. diastolic pressure was observed. The first hypertension peak appeared before the +13 day. A 66.7% of those patients on antihypertensive treatment required an adjustment or modification of said therapy, and 26.7% required antihypertensive drugs de novo. Conclusions: monitoring and follow-up of the patient receiving allogeneic transplant of hematopoietic stem cells and, specifically, of the potential complication of arterial hypertension secondary to the administration of cyclosporine, is the responsibility of nurses, both in the Specialized Care and in the Primary Care settings. It is pointed out that any patient, regardless of their gender or type of transplant, can present HT associated with the use of cylosporine and, therefore, nurses must conduct exhaustive monitoring and an adequate follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Gil, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Roviralta, M Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar el patrón evolutivo de la tensión arterial y el tipo de antihipertensivos que precisan los pacientes en proceso de trasplante alogénico y en tratamiento con ciclosporina. Método: estudio descriptivo de una serie de casos. Se realiza un muestreo no probabilístico de conveniencia con una muestra de36 pacientes. Se seleccionaron a aquellas personas a las que se había realizado un trasplante alogénico y precisaron de tratamiento con ciclosporina. Las variables a estudio fueron: sexo, edad, tipo de trasplante, tensión arterial (TA) de base, días y vía de administración de la ciclosporina, así como patrón y evolución de la tensión arterial. Se clasificó la toxicidad manifestada como hipertensión relacionada según la Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE. v4).Resultados: la media de TA fue de 164,6/89,8, observándose un aumento mayor de la presión sistólica que de la diastólica. El primerpico hipertensivo se dio antes del día +13. El 66,7% de los pacientes que tomaba antihipertensivo precisó de un ajuste o modificación del tratamiento y el 26,7% necesitó antihipertensivos denovo. Conclusiones: el control y seguimiento del paciente receptor de un trasplante alogénico de progenitores hematopoyéticos y, en concreto, de la complicación potencial de hipertensión arterial secundaria a la administración de ciclosporina, es una responsabilidad de la enfermera/o, tanto en el ámbito de la Atención Especializada como en el de la Atención Primaria. Se destaca que cualquier paciente, independientemente del sexo o el tipo de trasplante, puede presentar HTA relacionada con la toma de ciclosporina y, por tanto, la enfermera/o debe mantener una vigilancia exhaustiva y un correcto seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(3): 64-69, abr. 2016. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la tensión arterial en pacientes en proceso de trasplante alogénico y en tratamiento con ciclosporina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1821^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
