<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89988</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conservative management of a subcapsular liver hematoma in HELLP syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To improve morbidity and mortality in patients with subcapsular liver hematoma, clinical suspicion, a rapid diagnosis and multidisciplinary treatment are fundamental. The treatment of this complication includes expectant management with clinical and radiological observation, embolization of the hepatic arteries, and surgical treatment if there is hemodynamic instability, persistent bleeding or increasing pain. We report a case of postpartum HELLP syndrome that was complicated by a subcapsular liver hematoma, successfully treated by embolization of the right hepatic artery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cos Torrubiano, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Aguilera, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falcó Fages, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Grau, Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canet Estevez, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sospecha clínica, el diagnóstico rápido y un abordaje multidisciplinar son fundamentales para mejorar la morbimortalidad de las pacientes con hematoma subcapsular hepático. El tratamiento de esta entidad abarca desde la conducta expectante bajo vigilancia clínica y radiológica, la embolización de las arterias hepáticas o la cirugía en caso de inestabilidad hemodinámica, persistencia de sangrado o incremento del dolor. Presentamos el caso de un síndrome de HELLP posparto complicado con un hematoma subcapsular hepático y que se resolvió exitosamente con embolización de la arteria hepática derecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(9): 459-461, sept. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo conservador de un hematoma subcapsular hepático en un síndrome de HELLP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30704^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30704^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30704^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53231^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
