<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118423</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survival of cancer patients discharged to intermediate stay palliative care units according to the Palliative Performance Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The value of &#145;&#145;Palliative Performance Scale&#146;&#146; (PPS) to estimate survival of patients with terminal illness is widely recognized. This scale has also been used in care planning and resource management in palliative care. Aims: To estimate survival in the host institution for cancer patients who move to intermediatestay palliative care units (UCPME) from an acute care hospital according to the PPS value at time of transfer. To evaluate the association between this score and survival. Method: Retrospective study of cancer patients treated by a palliative care support team and transferred to an UCPME in the period 01/07/2008 to 31/12/2009. We estimated survival by Kaplan-Meier function for the group of patients with PPS score &lt;20% and PPS&gt; 20% and compared by log-rank test. A Cox model was adjusted to estimate the probability of survival at different times depending on the value of PPS at the time of discharge. Results: Seventy seven patients were included (mean age 77 (9.6) years; 42.9% women). Lung cancer was the most frequent neoplasm (14.3%). The mean PPS at the time of transfer was 40.9% (12.6). Median survival was 4 days (95% CI; 0-9) in the PPS &amp;#8804; 20% group, and 33 days (95% CI; 19-47) in the PPS&gt; 20% group (P=.006). There was a 4% increased risk of mortality per unit decrease in PPS (HR=1.04, 95% CI 1.02-1.06). Conclusions: Patients survival in the UCPME was signi&amp;#64257;cantly different depending on the PPS at the time of discharge. A death probabilities table according to the PPS at the time of transfer and the days afterwards was created from the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Roncero, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieves Plana, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Zamora, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañada Millas, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rexach Cano, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Álvaro, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La capacidad para pronosticar la supervivencia de pacientes con enfermedad terminal de la «Palliative Performance Scale» (PPS) es ampliamente reconocida. Esta escala se ha utilizado también en la planificación de cuidados y en la gestión de recursos asistenciales paliativos. Objetivo Estimar la supervivencia en el centro de destino de los pacientes oncológicos que se trasladan a unidades de cuidados paliativos de media estancia (UCPME) desde un hospital de agudos según la puntuación en la escala PPS en el momento del traslado. Evaluar la asociación entre dicha puntuación y la supervivencia. Método Estudio retrospectivo sobre pacientes oncológicos atendidos por el equipo de soporte hospitalario de cuidados paliativos del Hospital Ramón y Cajal de Madrid que fueron trasladados a una UCPME, en el período 01/07/08-31/12/09. Se estimaron las funciones de supervivencia mediante el método de Kaplan-Meier para el grupo de pacientes con puntuación en la escala PPS &amp;#8804; 20% y PPS &gt; 20% y se compararon mediante la prueba de log-rank. Para estimar las probabilidades de supervivencia a distintos tiempos en función del valor de PPS al alta se ajustó un modelo de Cox. Resultados Fueron incluidos 77 pacientes (edad media 77 [9,6] años; 42,9% mujeres). El tumor más frecuente fue el de pulmón (14,3%). Los valores medios y desviación estándar de PPS en el momento del traslado fueron 40,9 (12,6%). En el grupo PPS &amp;#8804; 20%, la mediana de supervivencia fue de 4 IC 95% (0-9) días, y en el de PPS &gt; 20% de 33 IC 95% (19-47) días (p = 0,006). Se obtuvo un 4% más de riesgo de mortalidad por unidad de descenso de PPS  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;21(1): 9-14, ene.-mar. 2014. tab, ima</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118423</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia, según la Palliative Performance Scale, de pacientes oncológicos trasladados a unidades de cuidados paliativos de media estancia por un equipo de soporte hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
