<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127203</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and epidemiology of Barrett's esophagus in the province of Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The prevalence of Barrett&#146;s esophagus (BE) varies from 0.45% to 2.2% in patients who undergo upper endoscopy and is &gt;12% when the indication is for reflux symptoms. The prevalence has progressively increased in recent years but is unknown in the population of the province of Barcelona. Objectives: To determine the prevalence of BE and its epidemiological characteristics in our population. Patients and methods: We prospectively evaluated patients referred to the Endoscopy Unit of Hospital Clinic and Hospital General de Catalunya for an upper endoscopy. We excluded patients with known BE, prior upper endoscopy, esophagogastric surgery or refusal to participate in the study. Demographic data, alcohol intake, Helicobacter pylori infection and consumption of antisecretory agents were recorded, among other information. Participants completed a standardized questionnaire to assess the presence of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) symptoms and their severity. Results: Between July 2010 and July 2012, we included 200 patients (100 in each center). The mean age was 48.9±15.6 years and the majority were women (n=120, 60%). Symptoms of GERD were present in 46 patients (23%) and some degree of esophagitis was present in 31 (15.5%). Infection by H. pylori was present in 29.7%. BE was found endoscopically in 14 (7%) patients, but was histologically confirmed in only 8 (4%). The only variable that correlated with the finding of BE was male sex. Conclusion: The prevalence of BE in our environment is similar to that reported in Western countries. The absence of reflux symptoms does not rule out the possibility of BE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saperas, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uchima, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araujo, Isis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Esparrach, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizalde, Ignasi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La prevalencia del esófago de Barrett (EB) es del 0,45-2,2% en los pacientes que se realizan una endoscopia digestiva alta y superior al 12% si la indicación es por síntomas de reflujo, habiéndose descrito un aumento progresivo en los últimos años. Sin embargo, se desconoce cuál es la prevalencia de esta entidad en la provincia de Barcelona. Objetivos Determinar la prevalencia del EB y sus características epidemiológicas en nuestro medio. Pacientes y métodos Se evaluaron de forma prospectiva pacientes que acudieron a las Unidades de Endoscopia del Hospital Clínic y Hospital General de Catalunya para la realización de una endoscopia digestiva alta. Se excluyeron pacientes con EB conocido, endoscopia digestiva alta previa, cirugía esófagogástrica o negativa de participar en el estudio. Se registraron datos demográficos, consumo de alcohol y tabaco, infección por Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori) y consumo de antisecretores, entre otros. Los participantes completaron un cuestionario estandarizado para valorar la presencia de síntomas de reflujo gastroesofágico (RGE) y su severidad. Resultados Entre julio 2010 y julio 2012 se incluyeron 200 pacientes (100 en cada centro). La media de edad fue de 48,9±15,6 y la mayoría eran mujeres (n=120, 60%). Cuarenta y seis pacientes (23%) tenían síntomas de RGE y 31 (15,5%) presentaron algún grado de esofagitis. La infección por H. Pylori estaba presente en 29,7%. En 14 (7%) pacientes hubo sospecha endoscópica de EB, con confirmación histológica en 8 (4%). La única variable que se correlacionó con el hallazgo de EB fue el género masculino. Conclusión: La prevalencia de EB en nuestro medio es similar a la descrita en los países occidentales. La ausencia de síntomas de reflujo no descarta la posibilidad de EB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;37(7): 397-401, ago.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y características epidemiológicas del esófago de Barrett en la provincia de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d877^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1493^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28919^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
