<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137248</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality in the first 4s hours of income in a general service and difestive surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. Early surgical mortality within the first 48 hours is a parameter used as &#147;sentinel" of quality in surgery, so it is important to identify its clinical and epidemiological characteristics. Materials and Methods. We performed a descriptive, retrospective, observational study including patients who died within 48 hours of admission at a plant in general and digestive surgery, during the period between January 2002 and December 2011. Demographic variables were collected, mode of admission and diagnosis, comorbidity, surgical risk and therapeutic approach. We excluded patients who died of trauma. Results. From January 2002 to December 2011 were carried out 48,716 income, of which 417 patients died (0.85%) and 28 patients died within 48 hours of admission (0.057%). The average age of these patients was 81 years (55-94), there was no predominance of sex. 96% of those died within the first 48 hours had an emergency admission. The cause of death in half of the cases was acute mesenteric ischemia. 89,% of patients had a severe comorbidity (ASA III - IV). 75% of deaths occurred in the first 5 years of the study period. Conclusion. Early surgical mortality is linked to elderly patients with poor baseline health and emergency surgery. This uniqueness of early postoperative mortality and the type of patients who present it, makes this data of little value as a criterion of quality of care. The reduced early mortality in the most recent years may have several explanations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sainz-Lete, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elorza, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enríquez-Navascués, J M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Timoteo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zeballos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goena-Iglesias, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar las características clínicas y epidemiológicas de los pacientes quirúrgicos fallecidos dentro de las primeras 48 horas, parámetro considerado como &#147;centinela&#148; de la calidad asistencial en cirugía. Materiales y Método. Estudio observacional descriptivo y retrospectivo de los pacientes fallecidos antes de las 48 horas siguientes al ingreso en una planta de cirugía general y digestiva, durante el periodo comprendido entre enero del 2002 y diciembre del 2011. Se recogen variables demográficas, forma y diagnostico de ingreso, morbilidad asociada, riesgo quirúrgico y la actitud terapéutica. Excluimos a los pacientes fallecidos por traumatismos. Resultados. Desde enero del 2002 hasta diciembre del 2011 se realizaron 48716 ingresos, de los cuales fallecieron 417 pacientes (0,85%), de éstos, 28 pacientes fallecieron en las primeras 48 horas del ingreso (0,05%). La media de edad de éstos pacientes fue de 81 años (55-94), sin predominio de sexo. El 96% de los fallecidos provenían de ingresos de urgencias. La causa principal de muerte fue isquemia mesentérica aguda. El 89% de los pacientes presentaba alguna comorbilidad severa. El 75% de los fallecimientos se produjeron en los primeros 5 años del periodo estudiado. Conclusión. La mortalidad quirúrgica temprana se encuentra ligada a pacientes de edad avanzada, frágiles y a cirugía urgente. La excepcionalidad de la mortalidad postoperatoria temprana y la tipología de pacientes que la presentan, hace que este dato tenga escaso valor como criterio de calidad asistencial. En los últimos años ha disminuido el número de estas muertes lo que puede tener varias explicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;18(1): 3-6, 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137248</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad en las primeras 48 horas del ingreso en un servicio de cirugía general y digestiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
