<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049837</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impulsiveness in cocaine addicts who give up misuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Many studies show the close relationship between impulsiveness and addictive disorders. Neuropsychology has stressed the influence the misuse of cocaine has on executive functions, and hence on the decision-taking ability. We propose to compare impulsiveness among groups of active cocaine addicts and those reacting well to the treatment in different moments of their evolution. Materials and methods. A consecutive sample of 85 subjects demanding outpatient treatment for cocaine dependence was selected. To measure impulsiveness the Barratt Impulsiveness Scale (BIS-11) was used, and the IPDE for personality diagnosis. Results. The impulsiveness previous to treatment was independt from the presence of cluster B personality disorders. After a month of evolution there appeared significant differences in nonplanning subescale among group of active cocaine addicts and those who showed some amelioration. After three months, differences were produced on global, cognitive and nonplaning scores. Discussion: The increase on impulsiveness is due, at least inpart, to the effect of a continual misuse of cocaine, and its has a certain degree of reversal, that starts to be noticeable after between 4 and 12 weeks. We propose to study in more depth the influence that the continual misuse of cocaine has in the habitual behaviour, as well as the underlying neuropsychological mechanisms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo Pavía, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bondía Soler, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forcada Chapa, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Muchos estudios relacionan la impulsividad y los trastornos adictivos. Desde la neuropsicología se ha incidido en la influencia del consumo de cocaína sobre las funciones ejecutivas y por ende sobre la capacidad de toma de decisiones valorando sus consecuencias. Se propone comparar la impulsividad entre grupos de cocainómanos en activo y aquellos con buena respuesta al tratamiento en distintos momentos de su evolución. Material y método. Se seleccionó una muestra consecutiva de 85 sujetos, que demandaron tratamiento ambulatorio por dependencia de cocaína. Para la medida de impulsividad se utilizó la Escala de Impulsividad de Barrat (BIS-11) y para el diagnóstico de personalidad el IPDE. Resultados. La impulsividad previa al tratamiento resultó independiente de la presencia de trastornos de personalidad del cluster B. Tras un mes de evolución existían diferencias significativas en la subescala de impulsividad no planificada entre quienes continuaron consumiendo y los que mostraron mejoría. A los tres meses las diferencias se produjeron en la puntuación global de la escala y en las subescalas cognitiva y no planificada. Discusión. El incremento en la impulsividad es, al menos en parte, debido al efecto del consumo continuado de cocaína y tiene un cierto grado de reversibilidad que comienza a hacerse patente entre las 4 y las 12 semanas. Se propone en el estudiar con mayor profundidad la influencia del consumo continuado de cocaína en el comportamiento habitual, así como los mecanismos neuropsicológicos subyacentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(2): 111-118, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049837</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impulsividad en dependientes de cocaína que abandonan el consumo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
