<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125604</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual theory and object in perversion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One hundred years after publication, Three essays continues to be the model of one of Freud´s fundamental discoveries: autoerotic-type infant sexuality. Sexual perversion was conceived in Three essays as an unmodified residue of infant sexuality. In this communication the evolution of the concept of perversion throughout Freud´s works is laid out, with it big advances and limitations brought about by the difficulties of the founder of psychoanalysis to understand the maternal complex and of the pre.oedipical stafes in the development of the personality. The function of the object in the development of infant and perverse sexuality is analyzed. The presentation of a clinical case is used to show the author´s ideas on perversion. This is conceived as a maniac-type alienating process, brought about by an infant psychical trauma (pathological fusion with the mother) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tabares Pujante, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A los cien años de su publicación Tres ensayos sigue siendo el exponente de un descubrimiento fundamental de Freud: la sexualidad infantil de tipo autoerótico. La perversión sexual fue concebida en Tres ensayos como un resto inmodificado de dicha sexualidad infantil. En esta ponencia, se expone la evolución del concepto de perversión a lo largo de la obra de Freud, con sus grandes avances y las limitaciones impuestas por las dificultades del fundador del psicoanálisis para la comprensión del «complejo materno» y de los estadíos preedípicos en el desarrollo de la personalidad. Se hace un análisis de la función del objeto en el desarrollo de la sexualidad infantil y perversa. La exposición de un caso clínico sirve de base para exponer las ideas del autor sobre la perversión. Ésta es concebida como un proceso alienante de tipo maníaco, provocado por un trauma psíquico infantil (fusión patológica con la madre) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(46): 101-133, sept.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125604</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Teoría sexual y objeto en la perversión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
