<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125781</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The borderline structure. A theoretical-clinical perspective from a Freudian metapsychology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper echoes the appearance of limit of borderline cases as the new clinical paradigm of contemporary psychoanalytic practice. It presents a model of borderline structure &#150; characterized by deficit and instability &#150; based on Freud´s contributions to his metapsychology, as well as that of various authors. It highlights the failures and lacks in the parental functions that are often borne by the borderline patient, which cause a series of consequences, among which stand out: the early trauma and an accumulation of helplessness and its reactivation, the compulsion to repeat, the peculiar forms of anxiety, the identification deficit and its prosthetic pseudo identifications. Denial a defense characteristic of the borderline structure, is different from that found in the perverse structure as far as its origins and finality are concerned. The corresponding splitting of the efo determines the coexistence of two contradictory nuclei in the subject: on narcissistic, precarious, in which denial prevails, and another oedipal or neurotic, equally weak , governed by repression. This structural model has as its reference important freudina works, and just as some authors propose, opens doors for the conception of a third topic. A clinical vignette is included (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Braier, Eduardo A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo se hace eco del surgimiento de los casos limítrofes o fronterizos como el nuevo paradigma clínico de la práctica psicoanalítica contemporánea. Expone un modelo de estructura limítrofe - caracterizada por ser deficitaria e inestable- basado en la metapsicología freudiana, apoyándose además en los aportes de diversos autores e incluyendo los propws. Destaca las faltas o fallas en las funciones parentales a menudo padecidas por el paciente limítrofe, las cuales provocan una serie de consecuencias, entre las que figuran: el trauma temprano y acumulativo del desvalimiento y su reactivación, la compulsión de repetición, las peculiares formas de angustia, el déficit identificatorio y las seudoidentificaciones protésicas. La desmentida, defensa característica de la estructura limítrofe, es diferenciada de la que presenta la estructura perversa en lo que respecta a sus orígenes y finalidad. La correspondiente escisión del Yo determina la coexistencia de dos núcleos contradictorios en el sujeto: uno narcisista, precario, en el que prevalece la desmentida, y otro edípico o neurótico, igualmente débil, regido por la represión. Este modelo estructural tiene como referente importantes trabajos freudianos y, tal como lo proponen algunos autores, abre puertas para la concepción de una tercera tópica. Se incluye una viñeta clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(67): 129-163, nov. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La estructura limítrofe. Una perspectiva teórico-clínica desde la metapsicología freudiana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52961</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
