<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134736</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-9536</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The reaction of Practicantes in Medicine and Surgery to the creation of a Nursing qualification in 1915</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper deals with the arguments justifying the Government's passage of the Sovereign Ordinance of 7 May 1915, which officially established a course and qualification in Nursing in Spain; and examines how and why Medical and Surgical practicantes (medical assistants) reacted to this decision. The ordinance legalized nurses' care practices, thereby providing official recognition for a healthcare profession other than that of practicante. The Government based its approval on three arguments: the physicians' recommendations; deficiencies in the basic and professional training of practicantes&#146;; and the fact that the nursing profession emerged as a new path providing Spanish women with an opportunity to acquire training and join the labour force. The new legislation was met with outrage by practicantes, who opposed it in the belief that it equated nurses' scope of practice to their own and thus jeopardized their future employment prospects. Additionally, they contended that nurses would be legally qualified to perform the same medical practices as they did, despite receiving their degrees in a shorter period of time with a less prolonged internship, at a lower economic cost and through less effort. Professional associations of practicantes immediately launched a campaign against the Sovereign Ordinance, meeting with the Minister of Public Instruction to request its repeal, organizing a massive telegram campaign directed at the minister, and requesting the nullity of the ordinance before the Supreme Court, which would reject the appeal by the practicantes two years later. Professional associations also used their press organs to publish the arguments of prominent practicantes, who vehemently voiced their opposition in extremist, uncompromising, radical, and ironic terms, arising from a strong gender ideology in tune with the patriarchal mentality of the era and the dominant position that male hegemony conferred to practicantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Calvo, Manuel-Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer los argumentos que justificaron que el Gobierno promulgase la Real Orden de 7 de mayo de 1915, que creaba oficialmente los estudios y el título de Enfermera en España, y por qué y cómo reaccionaron los practicantes en Medicina y Cirugía a esa Real Orden. Dicha norma legalizó el ejercicio asistencial de las enfermeras y se reconoció así a una profesión sanitaria alternativa a la de Practicante, lo cual fue justificado por el Gobierno con tres argumentos: que lo aconsejaron los médicos, la escasa formación básica y profesional de parte de los practicantes y que la profesión enfermera surgía como una nueva vía para que la mujer española tuviese más oportunidades de formarse e incorporarse al mercado laboral. Los practicantes acogieron dicha Real Orden con indignación y se opusieron a ella porque pensaban que atribuía a las enfermeras las mismas competencias que a ellos, y como consecuencia peligraba su futuro laboral. Además, éstos sostenían que las enfermeras para equipararse en funciones a ellos, podían formarse en un menor periodo de tiempo, con menos prácticas, inferior coste económico y menor esfuerzo que los practicantes. Los colegios profesionales de practicantes iniciaron acciones contra la Real Orden: entrevistas con el ministro de Instrucción Pública para solicitarle la derogación de la Real Orden, envío masivo de telegramas de protesta al ministro y recurso ante el Tribunal Supremo para que se declarase la nulidad de la Real Orden, el cual casi dos años después rechazó las pretensiones de los practicantes. También, desde la prensa de los colegios profesionales, significados practicantes realizaron una oposición ardorosa, extremista, intransigente, radical, irónica y guiada por una marcada ideología de género, fruto de la mentalidad patriarcal de entonces y de la superioridad que la hegemonía masculina le otorgaba al colectivo de los practicantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dynamis (Granada);34(2): 425-446, 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La reacción de los practicantes en Medicina y Cirugía frente a la creación del título de Enfermera en 1915</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54359^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54359^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54359^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55087^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55087^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13427^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55087^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13427^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54359^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13427^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13427^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
