<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91255</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Depression, anxiety and divorce in childhood. Practical aspects for the busy pediatrician</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological or psychiatric disorders are increasingly frequent in pediatric outpatient clinics of primary care. This article reviews in a practical way the depression and anxiety disorders that are commonly seen in the office. Consequences of parental divorce in children are also addressed especially when they have not been done in an intelligent and mature way. Treatment of these disorders is usually psychotherapeutic. Drugs should only be used in cases where cognitive therapy is not effective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonet de Luna, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamón Parra, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cada vez son más frecuentes los trastornos psicológicos o psiquiátricos en las consultas de Pediatría de Atención Primaria. En este artículo se revisan de forma práctica los trastornos de depresión y ansiedad que se ven habitualmente en la consulta. Además, se reflexiona sobre las consecuencias que la separación de los padres tiene en los niños, cuando no se hace de forma inteligente y madura. El tratamiento de estos trastornos es fundamentalmente psicoterapéutico, utilizándose los fármacos solo en casos en que la terapia cognitivo-conductual no haya sido eficaz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;13(51): 471-489, jul.-sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Depresión, ansiedad y separación en la infancia. Aspectos prácticos para pediatras ocupados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1015^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
