<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043426</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: hip fracture is one of the major causes ofmortality and morbility in the elderly. Together withprevention, it is unavoidably to prioritize eficiency. Weprospectively analyzed the variables influencing therehabilitation at the hospital or at home.Method: a descriptive and prospective study of patientsolder than 65-years, with surgical intervention for femurfractures in 2002 (382 patients) who were referred forrehabilitation at hospital (RH: 84 patients) or at home(RD 142 patients).Results: no significant differences were detected for age,sex, nor Barthel Index upon completion of rehabilitation.There were significant differences (p&lt;0.001) in Barthelat the commencement: UR 50.5 (SD15.9) and UD 56.41(SD 17.9). With respect to the social environment: in RH 30 (35.7%) lived alone and none in residence; but in RD12 lived alone (8.5%) and 15 in geriatric residences(17%).Conclusions: in both, the social environment and thefunctional level, the kind of rehabilitation decided uponand applied to our patients, is influential. The RH isassociated with living alone and with a worse functionalcapacity subsequent to a fracture, the RD is associatedwith previously having lived in a residence , with a betterfunctional capacity. There are no differences in thesuccessful functional improvement in the two groups</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogueras, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guirao, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilarmau, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Real, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bacos, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Díaz, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La fractura de fémur es una de las mayorescausas de morbi-mortalidad en los ancianos. Junto ala prevención, parece obligado priorizar la eficiencia enla rehabilitación. Este trabajo analiza prospectivamentelas variables ligadas a la rehabilitación hospitalaria o endomicilio.Métodos: Estudio descriptivo y prospectivo de los pacientesmayores de 65 años con tratamiento quirúrgicode fractura de fémur durante el año 2002 (382 pacientes),remitidos a rehabilitación hospitalaria (RH: 84 pacientes)o domiciliaria (RD: 142 pacientes).Resultados: No había diferencias significativas en edad,sexo ni Índice de Barthel al acabar. Si la hubo (p&lt; 0.001)en el Barthel al inicio: 50,5 (DE 15,9) frente a 56,41 (DE17,9). Así como en el entorno social: en RH 30 (35,7%)vivían solos y ninguno vivía en residencia, frente a RDdonde 12 vivían solos (8,5%) y 25 en residencias (17%).Conclusiones: Tanto el entorno social como el nivel funcionalinfluyen en la decisión del tipo de rehabilitación.La RH se asocia a vivir solo i a una peor capacidadfuncional tras la fractura, la RD se asocia a vivir previamenteen residencia i a una mejor capacidad funcional.No hay diferencias en la mejoría funcional conseguida enlos dos grupos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;15(2): 81-84, abr.-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de fémur del anciano: estudio prospectivo de las variables asociadas a la prescripción de rehabilitación hospitalaria versus domiciliaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12468^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12468^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33152^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
