<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133491</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life and its determiants in Spanish Universtiy students of health sciencies factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The quality of life of university students acquires special importance because it provides information about their life conditions and especially how they perceive it. Objetive: Evaluate the quality of life of students who are enrolled in health science studies and its relation with the following diverse factors: life and dietetic habits, anthropometric parameters and the influence of distinct variables on their perception. Methods: Transversal study of a sample of 1753 health science degree students of nine Spanish universities with a randomized design and stratified by course and faculty for which we applied an ad hoc questionnaire that considered all study variables. Results: The quality of life (QoL) perceived by the participants had a Median of 75. The factors that were explored about the quality of life correlated significantly with their global perception of it (p&lt;0.001). Three dimensions were established and the impact of each one of themon their global perception of QoL was p&lt;0.001. Men perceived better QoL then women and the students with lower Body Mass Index (BMI). Conclusions: University students are a key population for realizing health promotion and prevention activities therefore it is necessary to develop and provide better infrastructures and educative resources in order to enhance their QoL and to promote healthier habits and life styles with special attention on dietetics habits and the performance of an adequate physical activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martín, Amelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Valero, javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Luna, Pedro Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tur Marí, Josep Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novalbos Ruiz, Jose Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Maria Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irles, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wanden Berghe, Carmina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Victoria, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Rodero, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La calidad de vida en la población universitaria adquiere una especial importancia ya que permite obtener información sobre las condiciones de vida de los universitarios y, sobre todo, de cómo éstos las perciben. Objetivo: Evaluar la calidad de vida de los universitarios que cursan estudios en ciencias de la salud y su relación con diferentes factores tales como: hábitos de vida, parámetros antropométricos y la influencia de las distintas variables sobre su percepción.  Material y Método: Estudio transversal de una muestrade 1.753 estudiantes de ciencias de la salud de nueve universidades españolas con diseño muestral aleatorio y estatrificado según curso y facultad al que se le aplicóun cuestionaro ad hoc que recogía todas las variables aestudio. Resultados: La calidad de vida percibida por los participantes  fue Me = 75. Los factores explorados de la calidad de vida se co-relacionaron significativamente con la percepción global de calidad de vida de los estudiantes (p&lt;0,001). Se establecieron 3 dimensiones y el impacto de cada una de ellas sobre la percepción de calidad de vida global fue p&lt;0,001. Los varones percibieron mejor calidad de vida que las mujeres y también los estudiantes con menor Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC). Conclusión: Los universitarios son una población clave  para realizar actividades de promoción y prevención de la salud por lo que resulta necesario crear mejores infraestucturas y recursos educativos para mejorar la CV y fomentar hábitos y estilos de vida saludable con especialatención en la alimentación y la realización de una adecuada actividad física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 952-958, feb. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida y sus factores determinantes en universitarios españoles de Ciencias de la Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
