<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126546</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survival analysis in multiple cancer patients in Asturias, Spain, 1975-2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Almost one in ten survivors of cancer suffers a second primary. Some studies try to clarify the causes, but there are few that study the time variable. Our research aim was to describe this variable in multiple cancer (MC) patients and to detect others associated with time without MC and survival. Methods. We performed a descriptive study, and the Kaplan Meyer method and Cox Regression were used to study the patients with MC included in the tumour registry of the reference hospital of Asturias. Results. Time between the first symptom and diagnosis was significantly reduced in the second tumour when compared with the first one (113 to 88 days). Time between the first two tumours (median=2.93 years) and the risk of an earlier second primary was higher in older people (RR=1,03) with: primaries diagnosed in advanced stage (RR=1.55), treated with palliative surgery (RR=2.67) or chemotherapy (RR=1.51); second neoplasm located in the prostate (RR=1.67). 60.9% survived at least 5 years after the first diagnosis and 19.1% after the second. These probabilities decreased with age (RR=1.04) and advanced stages (RR=2.48). Nevertheless, locations with good prognosis (prostate, breast or skin) and almost any treatment with surgery or radiotherapy increase survival. Conclusion. Physicians should be alert to new cancer symptoms in patients with previous neoplasms during the follow-up period to improve early MC diagnosis. Survival in MC patients is acceptable, and it largely depends on the location and stage of the cancer involved, but also upon the strategy of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Rodríguez, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Folgueras Sánchez, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lana Pérez, alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueto Espinar, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Gómez, María del Olivo del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Casi uno de cada diez supervivientes de cáncer sufre un segundo primario. Algunos estudios intentan clarificar las causas pero escasean los que estudian la variable tiempo. Nuestro objetivo fue describir esta variable en pacientes con cáncer múltiple (CM) y detectar otras asociadas con el tiempo libre de CM y la supervivencia. Métodos. Se diseñó un estudio descriptivo y se utilizaron el método de Kaplan Meyer y la Regresión de Cox para estudiar los pacientes con CM incluidos en el registro de tumores del Hospital Central de Asturias. Resultados. El tiempo &#145;primer síntoma-diagnóstico&#146; se redujo significativamente del primer al segundo cáncer (de 113 a 88 días). El tiempo entre los dos primeros cánceres (mediana=2,93 años) fue menor en las personas de más edad (RR=1,03), con cánceres primarios avanzados (RR=1,55), tratados con cirugía paliativa (RR=2,67) o quimioterapia (RR=1,51) y con un segundo cáncer localizado en la próstata (RR=1,67). El 60,9% sobrevivió más de 5 años desde el primer diagnóstico y el 19,1% desde el segundo. Estas probabilidades disminuyeron con la edad (RR=1,04) y estadios avanzados (RR=2,48), sin embargo, localizaciones con buen pronóstico (próstata, mama y piel) y casi cualquier tratamiento quirúrgico o radiológico aumentan la supervivencia. Conclusión. Los médicos deben estar alerta ante nuevos síntomas de cáncer en pacientes con neoplasias previas durante su periodo de seguimiento para mejorar el diagnóstico precoz del CM. La supervivencia en estos pacientes depende en gran medida de la localización y estadio del cáncer implicado, pero también del tipo de tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;82(2): 167-177, mar.-abr. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la supervivencia en pacientes con cáncer múltiple. Asturias, 1975-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
