<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100923</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical safety plan in a university hospital complex. Initial diagnosis: Study of adverse events</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To establish the incidence of adverse events (AEs) and incidence of patients with AEs in the University Hospital Complex of Albacete (CHUA); to identify and define the AEs which are linked to health care; to analyse avoidable AE and determine their impact; to plan improvement actions. Method. Design. Retrospective cohort study. Sample. Patients registered from 5 November to 19 November, 2007. Case definition. Any accident or incident reported in the medical record which injured or may have injured the patient. Material. Adverse Events Screening Guide, adapted from the Harvard study. Spanish version of the Modular Review Form (MRF2) for retrospective case record review. Statistical Analysis. Univariate and bivariate analysis and logistic regression model. Results. The incidence of patients with AEs linked to hospital care was 6.8%. The incidence was significantly different depending on: age, presence of intrinsic or extrinsic risk factors (excluding peripheral venous catheter); 8.2% of AE was linked to care; 14.3% to medication; 26.5% to nosocomial infections; 35.7% to technical problems in procedures; 11.2% to diagnosis, and the remaining 4.1% to other types of AEs. In these incidences, 12.2% were considered mild, 78.6% moderate and 8.2% serious. Half (50%) of AEs caused an increase in hospital stay, and in 34.7% cases determined hospitalisation. A total of 63.3% of AEs were considered avoidable. Conclusions. The study of AEs in the CHUA represents an improvement within the hospital quality program. Incidences of patients with AEs and those related to health care fall within the range of those found in the studies where the objective was quality improvement(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gea-Velázquez de Castro, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranaz-Andrés, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo-Martínez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limón-Ramírez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas-Imbernón, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar la incidencia de eventos adversos (EA) y de pacientes con EA en el Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Albacete (CHUA). Identificar y definir los EA ligados a la asistencia; analizar los EA evitables y conocer su impacto; planificar las acciones de mejora. Método. Diseño. Estudio retrospectivo de cohortes. Ámbito de estudio. Pacientes dados de alta del 5 al 19 de noviembre de 2007. Definición de caso Todo accidente o incidente recogido en la historia clínica que ha causado daño al paciente o lo ha podido causar. Instrumentalización. Guía de cribado de efectos adversos, adaptada del estudio de Harvard. Versión española del formulario modular para revisión retrospectiva de casos, MRF2. Análisis estadístico. Análisis univariante, bivariante y modelo de regresión logística. Resultados. La incidencia de pacientes con EA relacionados con la asistencia hospitalaria fue de 6,8%. La incidencia fue diferente significativamente según: edad, presencia de factores de riesgo intrínseco y extrínseco (excluyendo el catéter venoso periférico). El 8,2% de los EA se relacionaron con cuidados, el 14,3% con medicación, el 26,5% con infecciones nosocomiales, el 35,7% con problemas técnicos en procedimientos, el 11,2% con diagnóstico y el 4,1% restante con otros tipos de EA. El 12,2% se consideraron leves, 78,6% moderados y 8,2% graves. El 50% de EA aumentaron la estancia, y en un 34,7% condicionó el ingreso. El 63,3% de los EA se consideraron evitables. Conclusiones. El estudio de EA en el CHUA constituye un aspecto de mejora dentro del programa de calidad del hospital. Las incidencias de pacientes con EA y con la asistencia sanitaria se encuentran entre las alcanzadas en el conjunto de estudios cuyo objetivo es la mejora de la calidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;27(4): 189-196, jul.-ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plan de seguridad clínica del Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Albacete (CHUA). Diagnóstico inicial: estudio de eventos adversos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23889^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23889^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
