<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143647</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sociodemographic and health characteristics associated with low birth weight in the Canary Islands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: since 1976, the term low birth weight (LBW) has been applied to all infants weighing less than 2  500 g and it constitutes the most important factor affecting neonatal mortality, morbidity in childhood. The aim of this study is to identify associations between biological, socioeconomic and health factors and underweight newborns in the Canary Islands. Materials and methods: a cross-sectional epidemiological study was conducted, with the files belonging to pregnant women in 2011 and 2012 (n=11.768) at the Hospital Universitario Insular Materno of Gran Canaria, which accounted for 66.3% of all births in the province for those years, excluding from the analysis the data pertaining to multiple births (393) (3.3%). The distribution and frequency of weight by sociodemographic characteristic were analyzed. Percentages were compared using the &amp;#967;2   test, means with the t-test and medians with the  Wilcoxon test for independent data. Those variables that were associated with low birth weight in the univariate analysis were entered into a logistic multidimensional analysis. Results: the distribution of birth weight revealed an of excess underweight children (9.3%), of which (62.1%) were pretermature. Mothers of children with LBW are thinner, of a smaller size and BMI (&lt;18.5 kg/m2 ), and an average age of 31.5. It was also noted that there is an increase between the age of the mothers and low weight although the effect is not linear; in fact, the increases in the risk of LBW accelerate as age increases. When maternal BMI decreases, to approximately below 25, the risk of low birth weight increases linearly. The highest OR correspond to fetal intrauterine growth retardation (CIR) (OR=6.3; 95% CI=5.3, 7.4), hypertension/eclampsia (OR=3.2; 95% CI=2.1; 5.1), in gestations of less than 37 weeks (OR=2.5; 95% CI=2.0; 3.3) and the consumption of tobacco by the mother (OR=1.9; 95% CI=1.6, 2.3). Conclusions: smoking during pregnancy appears to be the most important mediating factor in IUGR mediating factor. An overweight or obese mother did not appear to constitute a risk factor for a child&#146;s low birth weight. Intrauterine growth restriction (IGR) is the variable health that most affects low weight and high blood pressure in the mother, also associated with fetal growth retardation. While it is true that lack of antenatal care cannot be considered as a causal factor of underweight babies, 47.1% of pregnant women in the Canaries had insufficient controls (&lt;3 controls) with an increase of said controls would make it possible to reduce the frequency of the low weight in newborns (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saavedra Santana, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bello Luján, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez García, Luisa Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hernández, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: desde 1976, el término bajo peso al nacer (BPN) se aplica a todos los recién nacidos con un peso inferior a 2.500 g. y constituye el factor más importante que afecta a la mortalidad neonatal y a la morbilidad en la infancia. El objetivo de este trabajo es identificar las asociaciones entre los factores biológicos, socioeconómicos y sanitarios y el bajo peso en el recién nacido en las islas Canarias. Material y método: se realizó un estudio epidemiológico transversal, con los ficheros de las gestantes del 2011 y 2012 (n = 11,768) del Complejo Hospitalario Universitario Insular Materno de Gran Canaria, que representó el 66,3% de todos los partos de la provincia para esos años, excluyéndose del análisis los datos correspondientes a los embarazos múltiples (393) (3,3%). Se analizaron la distribución y la frecuencia del peso según características sociodemográficas; los porcentajes se compararon con el test de la &amp;#967;2 , las medias con el t-test y las medianas con el test de Wilcoxon para datos independientes. Aquellas variables que mostraron asociación con el bajo peso en el análisis univariado fueron introducidas en un análisis logístico multidimensional. Resultados: en la distribución del peso al nacer se observó un exceso de niños con bajo peso (9,3%), de los cuales el 62,1% fueron pretérmino. Las madres de estos niños son más delgadas, de menor talla y tienen un IMC promedio de &lt; 18,5 kg/m2, así como un promedio de edad de 31,5 años. Se observó igualmente que existe un incremento entre la edad de la madre y el bajo peso, aunque el efecto no es lineal; de hecho, los aumentos del riesgo de BPN se aceleran a medida que aumenta la edad. Cuando el IMC de la madre decrece, aproximadamente por debajo de 25, aumenta linealmente el riesgo de bajo peso. Las OR más elevadas corresponden al retraso fetal en el crecimiento intrauterino (CIR) (OR=6,3; IC-95%=5,3; 7,4), la hipertensión/eclampsia (OR=3,2; IC-95%=2,1; 5,1), la gestación menor de 37 semanas (OR=2.,5; IC- 95%=2,0; 3,3) y el consumo de tabaco de la madre (OR=1,9; IC-95%=1,6; 2,3). Conclusiones: el tabaquismo durante la gestación parece ser el factor mediador más importante para la restricción del crecimiento intrauterino. El sobrepeso u obesidad de la madre no parece que sean factores de riesgo para el bajo peso del niño. El crecimiento intrauterino restringido (CIR) es la variable sanitaria que más influye en el bajo peso, al igual que la hipertensión arterial de la madre, enfermedad asociada igualmente con el retraso en el crecimiento fetal. Aunque la falta de atención prenatal no puede considerarse como un factor causal del bajo peso, el 47,1% de las gestantes han tenido controles insuficientes (&lt; de tres controles); con el aumento de los mismos se lograría reducir la frecuencia del bajo peso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(4): 1541-1547, oct. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143647</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características sociodemográficas y sanitarias asociadas con bajo peso al nacer en Canarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
