<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132523</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Respiratory emergencies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Respiratory emergencies in a patient with cancer can have their origin in pathologies of the airway, of the pulmonary parenchyma or the large vessels. The cause can be the tumour itself or concomitant complications. Obstruction of the airway should be initially evaluated with endoscopic procedures. Surgery is rarely possible in serious situations. The endobronchial placement of stents or radioactive isotopes (brachytherapy), tumoural ablation by laser or photodynamic therapy can quickly alleviate the symptoms and re-establish the air flow. Treatment of haemoptysis depends on the cause that is provoking it and on its quantity. Bronchoscopy continues to be the front line procedure in the majority of cases; it provides diagnostic information and can interrupt bleeding through washes with ice-cold serum, endobronchial plugging or topical injections of adrenaline or thrombin. External radiotherapy continues to be an extraordinarily useful procedure in treating haemoptysis caused by tumours and in carefully selected situations of endobronchial therapy with laser or brachytherapy, and bronchial arterial embolisation can provide a great palliative effect. Respiratory emergencies due to pulmonary parenchyma disease in the oncology patient can have a tumoural, iatrogenic or infectious cause. Early recognition of each of these will determine the administration of a specific treatment and the possibilities of success (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boldú, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guelbenzu, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Michel, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manterola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las urgencias respiratorias en un paciente con cáncer pueden tener su origen en patologías de la vía aérea, del parénquima pulmonar o de los grandes vasos. La causa puede ser el propio tumor o complicaciones concomitantes. La obstrucción de la vía aérea debería ser inicialmente evaluada con procedimientos endoscópicos. En situaciones severas, la cirugía raramente es posible. El emplazamiento endobronquial de stents e isótopos radiactivos (braquiterapia), la ablación tumoral por láser o la terapia fotodinámica, pueden aliviar de forma rápida los síntomas y reestablecer el flujo aéreo. El manejo de la hemoptisis depende de la causa que la provoque y de la cuantía de la misma. La broncoscopia sigue siendo el procedimiento de primera línea en la mayor parte de los casos; aporta información diagnóstica y puede interrumpir el sangrado mediante lavados con suero helado, taponamiento endobronquial o inyecciones tópicas de adrenalina o trombina. La radioterapia externa sigue siendo un procedimiento extraordinariamente útil para tratar la hemoptisis de causa tumoral y en situaciones bien seleccionadas la terapia endobronquial con láser o braquiterapia y la embolización arterial bronquial pueden proporcionar un gran rendimiento paliativo. Las urgencias respiratorias por enfermedad del parénquima pulmonar en un paciente oncológico, pueden tener causa tumoral, iatrogénica o infecciosa. El reconocimiento precoz de cada una de ellas determina la administración del tratamiento específico y las posibilidades de éxito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;27(supl.3): 87-97, 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132523</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Urgencias respiratorias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
