<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77490</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception of sexuality in women with rheumatic disease: case-control pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Rheumatic diseases are characterized by chronic inflammation with systemic involvement and are often accompanied by functional limitation and depression. Their effect on sexual response has been little studied. The objective of the present study was to evaluate perception of sexuality in women with rheumatic disease. Patients and methods: We administered a questionnaire that included general data, socioeconomic aspects, disease characteristics, serum markers of inflammation and measured perception of sexuality, depression traits and self-esteem. Results: Sixteen patients were interviewed, of which nine had rheumatoid arthritis, six had systemic lupus erythematosus and one had psoriatic arthritis. Twentyfive women were selected as controls. All patients were receiving treatment and had a functional class that allowed them to be self-dependent. Patients presented a worse perception of sexuality than controls (p = 0.001) with a trend to more depressive traits and lower self-esteem. Conclusions: Patients with rheumatic disease gain benefits from treatment in terms of quality of life and functionality. Perception of sexuality is affected by chronic inflammatory disease but is independent of the patient&#146;s functional class(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flores-Flores, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gudiño-Quiroz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Fuentes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xibillé-Friedmann, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Valdez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las enfermedades reumáticas se caracterizan por ser problemas inflamatorios crónicos con afección sistémica que frecuentemente se acompañan de limitación funcional y depresión. Su repercusión sobre la respuesta sexual ha sido pobremente estudiada. El objetivo del presente estudio fue evaluar la percepción sexual en mujeres con enfermedad reumática. Pacientes y métodos: Se aplicó un cuestionario que, además de incluir datos generales, aspectos socioeconómicos, características de la enfermedad y marcadores serológicos de inflamación, midió la percepción de la sexualidad por parte de los sujetos, rasgos de depresión y el nivel de autoestima de éstos. Resultados: Se entrevistó a 16 pacientes, 9 de las cuales tenían artritis reumatoide (AR), 6 lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES), 1 artritis psoriásica. Se seleccionó a 25 mujeres sanas como grupo control. Todas las pacientes recibían tratamiento y presentaban una clase funcional que les permitía valerse por sí mismas. Las pacientes presentaron una peor percepción de la sexualidad (p = 0,001), tendiendo a presentar más rasgos de depresión y una menor autoestima que el grupo control. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con enfermedades reumáticas se benefician del tratamiento, al ser éste un adyuvante en su calidad de vida y en su funcionalidad. La percepción de la sexualidad se afecta como parte de la enfermedad inflamatoria crónica, pero es independiente de la clase funcional del paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);1(1): 20-24, mayo-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77490</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de la sexualidad en pacientes con enfermedades reumáticas: estudio piloto de casos y controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
