<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128632</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New free programs for the management of references</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Managing and classifying biomedical literature that health professionals store during healthcare, teaching, and research purposes is a huge challenge for them. Reference managers are software that helps scholars to store and organize documents and bibliographic references. They also make easier to manage bibliographic citations and creating bibliography when writing a scholarly manuscript. Reference managers evolution over the last decades, until the emergence of new software tools available free of charge either as desktop programs or as web services, is revised. Basic features of the three more complete free reference managers currently available &#150;Mendeley, Zotero, and colwiz&#150; are reviewed. As an example, use of Mendeley is described with more detail. New free reference managers are able to meet the needs of most health care professionals for comprehensive management of their documents and references collections (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Solís, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los retos a los que se enfrentan los profesionales sanitarios es la gestión y organización de la literatura científica a la que acceden en el desarrollo de sus actividades asistenciales, docentes e investigadoras. Los gestores de referencias bibliográficas son programas informáticos que ayudan al usuario a almacenar y organizar documentos y referencias bibliográficas, y que también facilitan las tareas de citación y elaboración de la bibliografía al redactar una publicación académica. Se repasa la evolución de los gestores de referencias en las últimas décadas hasta la aparición de nuevos programas disponibles de forma gratuita, ya sea en forma de programas de escritorio como de servicios web. Se revisan las características básicas de los tres gestores de referencias gratuitos más completos en el momento actual: Mendeley, Zotero y Colwiz. Como ejemplo, se describe con más detalle el funcionamiento de Mendeley. Los nuevos gestores de referencias bibliográficas gratuitos pueden cubrir las necesidades de la mayoría de profesionales sanitarios en la gestión integral de sus colecciones de documentos y referencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;54(229): 173-182, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128632</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos programas gratuitos para gestión de referencias  bibliográficas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33196</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
