<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110576</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human papillomavirus infection in men and its relation with cancer: Current status and prospectics</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Roa S., Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez G., Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brebi M., Priscilla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hartley B., Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ili, Carmen G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduction. Human papillomavirus (HPV) is one of most frequent sexually transmitted infections worldwide. It has been described as the principal agent for cervical uterine carcinoma (99.7%). There is abundant information on this infection in women, however, its characteristics in the male population still remains unclear. Materials and methods. A search of updated bibliography on HPV infection in males and its relationship with several forms of cancer was conducted. Results. HPV infection in men could be associated to skin, perianal, tonsils, oropharynx, pharynx, esophagus, prostate and urethra carcinoma. HPV infection is usually silent, so that there are no clear symptoms or clinical signs. Therefore, there are many infected people who are unaware that they have HPV infection. This is a problem for men as well as their sexual partner. Prevalence studies show that the areas having the greatest presence of the HPV virus are in the young populations of Africa and Latin America. This is where the vaccine programs against this virus are slow in materializing. Discussion. It is important to incorporate diagnosis methods in male population and to increase HPV vaccine in men. Furthermore, periodic control of the HPV-infected male population is crucial, especially in the anatomical areas associated to sexual transmission diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);11(1): 25-30, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110576</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección por el virus del papiloma humano en el hombre y su relación con el cáncer: estado actual y prospectivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14811^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14811^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
