<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140652</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family physician´s travel notebook. Iceberg</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">These stories of the FAMILY PHYSICIAN&#146;S TRAVEL NOTEBOOK, which form a library of the walking doctor or emotional traveler, are loose sheets with writings about landscapes and emotions; they are an atlas of emotional geography. The evocation of a landscape before attending a patient &#150;mountains, rivers, valleys, beaches, seas, deserts, plateaus, islands, swamps, waterfalls, dunes, forests, salt marshes, lakes, etc.-, with the sensations felt by the doctor -heat, coolness, humidity, hardship, stress, serenity, vastness, loneliness, etc. It is not a diary, only a notebook with the doctor&#146;s experiences about the patterns and processes of consultation in a clinical case, which in turn may illustrate a prototype for this type of cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Turabián Fernández, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Franco, Benjamín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estas historias de la LIBRETA DE VIAJE DEL MÉDICO DE FAMILIA, que forman una biblioteca del médico caminante o viajero emocional, son hojas sueltas en las que se escribe sobre paisajes y emociones; son un atlas de geografía emocional. La evocación de un paisaje ante la asistencia a un paciente &#150;montañas, ríos, valles, playas, mares, desiertos, mesetas, islas, pantanos, cascadas, dunas, bosques, salinas, lagos, etc.-, con las sensaciones sentidas por el médico, de calor, frescor, humedad, dificultad, agobio, serenidad, inmensidad, soledad, etc. No es un diario, solo una libreta de apuntes con las vivencias del médico sobre los patrones y procesos de la consulta en un cierto caso clínico, que a su vez, puede ilustrar un prototipo de esa clase de casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;8(2): 145-146, jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Libreta de viaje del médico de familia. Iceberg</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53786^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53786^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53786^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53786^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53786^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
