<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107542</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alzheimer&#146;s disease and fragile X syndrome: the Wnt/&amp;#946; - catenin pathway as a common biological mechanism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Various disorders affecting the canonical Wnt/&amp;#946;-catenin signalling pathway have been related to the activation or inactivation of oncogenes and tumour suppressor genes that give rise to a number of well-defined neoplasias, as well as several genes involved in a growing group of complaints, including Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD) and fragile X syndrome (FXS).Aim. To examine the Wnt/&amp;#946;-catenin signalling pathway as a possible common biological mechanism involved in the origin and development of neurodegenerative conditions and its relationship with cancer. Development. We review the most recent biomedical literature dealing with the Wnt/&amp;#946;-catenin signalling pathway and its participation in the genesis of complaints such as AD and FXS. An analysis is also conducted to determine the role that this metabolic pathway might play in explaining the lowered risk of developing cancer displayed by these patients. Conclusions. The evidence found suggests that the Wnt/&amp;#946;-catenin pathway could be regulating a set of genes linked with the control of the cell cycle and apoptosis. This would give rise to a metabolic state in which, in conditions such as AD and  FXS, the cells would be more likely to undergo apoptosis than initiate mitosis, which would in turn account for the reduced risk of developing cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juárez-Vázquez, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales-Reynoso, Mónica Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenice Ochoa-Hernández, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barros Núñez, Patricio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Diversas alteraciones en la vía de señalización canónica Wnt-&amp;#946;-catenina se han relacionado con la activación o inactivación de oncogenes y genes supresores de tumor que dan lugar a múltiples neoplasias bien caracterizadas, así como de varios genes implicados en un grupo creciente de padecimientos, entre los que se incluyen la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA) y el síndrome X frágil (SXF). Objetivo. Examinar la vía de señalización Wnt-&amp;#946;-catenina como un posible mecanismo biológico común involucrado en el origen y desarrollo de padecimientos neurodegenerativos y su relación con el cáncer. Desarrollo. Se revisa en la literatura biomédica más reciente la información relacionada con la vía de señalización Wnt-&amp;#946;- catenina y su participación en la génesis de padecimientos como la EA y el SXF. También se analiza el papel que podría desempeñar esta vía metabólica para explicar el riesgo disminuido que tienen estos pacientes de desarrollar cáncer.Conclusiones. Las múltiples evidencias encontradas sugieren que la vía Wnt-&amp;#946;-catenina podría estar regulando un conjunto  de genes relacionados con el control del ciclo celular y la apoptosis, logrando un estado metabólico en el que, en padecimientos como la EA y el SXF, las células tendrían mayor susceptibilidad a entrar en apoptosis que a entrar en mitosis, lo que explicaría una disminución en el riesgo de desarrollar cáncer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(9): 543-548, nov. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Alzheimer y síndrome X frágil: la vía Wnt-ß-catenina como mecanismo biológico común</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50821^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
