<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96169</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oncologic nanotherapies: current applications and future perspectives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The application of nanotechnology in cancer therapy has received considerable attention in recent years. This is because nanotechnology offers interesting opportunities to improve the efficacy and reduce the toxicity of cancer treatments. This review summarizes the most advanced achievements in the design and development of oncologic nanomedicines presented in a variety of nanocarriers such as liposomes, polymer micelles, nanoparticles and conjugates. Furthermore, it highlights some novel strategies for the treatment of cancer, such as gene therapy, photodynamic therapy and theranostics(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera Rodríguez, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lollo, Giovanna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplicación de la nanotecnología en la terapia del cáncer ha despertado gran interés en los últimos años. Ello se debe a que la nanotecnología aporta soluciones encaminadas en general a mejorar la eficacia y reducir la toxicidad de los tratamientos oncológicos. En este artículo, se resumen los avances más significativos en el diseño y desarrollo de nanomedicamentos oncológicos en sus diversas presentaciones, como son los liposomas, las nanopartículas, las micelas poliméricas y los conjugados. Además, se destacan algunas de las nuevas estrategias adoptadas en el tratamiento del cáncer tales como la terapia génica, la terapia fotodinámica y el llamado teranóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;77(4): 76-98, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nanoterapias oncológicas: aplicaciones actuales y perspectivas futuras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52497^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52498^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38874^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51270^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
