<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82017</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the adverse effects prevalence related to healthcare in hospitals of the Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Improvement of knowledge on patient safety by a study of the number, importance and impact of Adverse Events (AEs), analysing the patient and healthcare characteristics associated with their occurrence. Material and methods. Cross-sectional study of prevalence carried out for one week every year in the years 2005&#150;2008 in hospitals of the Comunidad Valenciana. Results. AE prevalence in participating hospitals remained constant at around 6 % during the four years of study. The mean age and sex distribution were also constant. The predominant causal factors of AEs were nosocomial infection, procedures and medicines, in that order, although we did observe an increase in AEs due to nosocomial infection during the period of study. With regard to severity, we observed a decrease in the percentage of serious AEs (31.5 % in 2005 vs.17.8 % in 2008), as well as an increase in the proportion of avoidable AEs from 50.8 % to 63.2 % in 2008. Conclusions. The results of the study demonstrate the need for a cultural change among professionals that will stimulate the promotion of a proactive culture for patient safety, and allows us to anticipate a social problem of increasing repercussions. Knowledge of EA epidemiology will help in the development of prevention strategies to avoid or to minimise them(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miralles, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gea, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranaz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitaller, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Mejorar el conocimiento en relación con la seguridad del paciente por medio de la aproximación a la magnitud, a la trascendencia y al impacto de los eventos adversos (EA) analizando las características de los pacientes y de la asistencia que se asocian a la aparición de estos. Material y método. Estudio transversal de prevalencia llevado a cabo durante una semana de mayo entre los años 2005&#150;2008 en hospitales de la Comunidad Valenciana. Resultados. La prevalencia de EA en los hospitales participantes se mantuvo constante (en torno al 6%) durante los 4 años del estudio. La edad media y la distribución por sexos también se mantuvieron constantes. Los factores causales de EA predominantes en los 4 años fueron la infección nosocomial, los procedimientos y la medicación, en ese orden, aunque apreciamos un aumento de los EA debidos a infección nosocomial en el período de estudio. Respecto a la gravedad, se observó una disminución del porcentaje de EA graves (el 31,5 en 2005 vs. el 17,8% en 2008), así como un aumento de la proporción de evitables desde un 50,8 a un 63,2% en 2008. Conclusiones. El diagnóstico de situación realizado nos acerca a la necesidad de un cambio cultural entre los profesionales, que facilite la promoción de la cultura proactiva para la seguridad del paciente, y permite anticiparse a un problema de creciente repercusión social. Conocer la epidemiología de los EA facilitará desarrollar estrategias y mecanismos de prevención para evitarlos o minimizarlos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(5): 244-249, sept.-oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la prevalencia de eventos adversos relacionados con la asistencia en hospitales de la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
