<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048410</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sources of stress met by nursing students in their clinical practice. Evolution throughout the studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the main causes of stress in clinical practice identified by nursing students, as well as their evolution during nursing studies. Method. A cohort of 86 nursing students was studied. The most important sources of stress in clinical practice were measured by means of the KEZKAK questionnaire at two different times: at the beginning and at the end of nursing studies. Results. The main causes of stress both at the beginning and at the end of the course were the following (ordered from most to least important): lack of competence, impotence and uncertainty, being harmed by the relationship with patients, emotional involvement, lack of control in the relationship with patients, contact with suffering, and relationships with work mates. During the course, there was a significant decrease in the scores for the main sources of stress except for two: the relationship with work mates and emotional involvement. Conclusions. The most important sources of stress in clinical practice according to students are the same at the beginning and at the end of nursing studies. The variation observed in the importance of stress sources is interesting and helps to identify aspects that should be reinforced in the education of future nursing professionals</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zupiria-Gorostidi, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uranga-Iturrioz, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Cascante, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberdi-Erice, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huitzi-Egileor, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barandiaran-Lasa, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer las principales fuentes de estrés de la práctica clínica desde el punto de vista de los estudiantes de enfermería, así como su evolución a lo largo de la diplomatura. Método. Se ha estudiado una cohorte de 86 estudiantes de enfermería. Se han medido las principales fuentes de estrés de la práctica clínica con el cuestionario KEZKAK en 2 momentos: al inicio y al final de la diplomatura. Resultados. Las principales fuentes de estrés, tanto al principio de la carrera como al final, son en orden de importancia: falta de competencia, impotencia e incertidumbre, dañarse en la relación con el enfermo, implicación emocional, no controlar la relación con el enfermo, contacto con el sufrimiento y relación con los compañeros. A lo largo de la diplomatura hay una disminución significativa en la puntuación de las principales fuentes de estrés, excepto en 2: la relación con los compañeros y la implicación emocional. Conclusiones. Las principales fuentes de estrés de la práctica clínica para los estudiantes de enfermería son las mismas al principio y al final de la carrera. La variación observada en la importancia de las fuentes de estrés es interesante y sugiere aspectos a potenciar en la formación de los futuros profesionales de enfermería</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(5): 231-237, sept. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fuentes de estrés en la práctica clínica de los estudiantes de enfermería. Evolución a lo largo de la diplomatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
