<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14179</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual Coercion Scale (ECS) in dating relationships: Psychometric properties in Spanish youth population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sexual violence in youths' dating relationships does not fit the explanatory models existing in adults, hence the need to have instruments to analyze this particular type of behavior. In this study the psychometric properties of the Sexual Coercion Scale (ECS) were analyzed in a sample of 3665 youngsters between 16 and 24 years old. The sample was divided into two different subsamples, with an exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis for each one. Only one factor was found. The reliability of the scale was adequate, as well as the convergent validity, with positive and significant correlations with the Modified Conflict Tactics Scale (M-CTS; Neidig, 1986) that measures physical and verbal violence. Significant differences were also found in the ECS according to age and sex, as was expected. ECS is an appropriate instrument to evaluate sexual coercion in dating relationships in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamarrón, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Rivas, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La violencia sexual en las relaciones de noviazgo en jóvenes no se ajusta a los modelos explicativos existentes en adultos, de ahí la necesidad de contar con instrumentos que permitan analizar este tipo de comportamientos en la juventud. En este estudio se analizan las propiedades psicométricas de la "Escala de coerción sexual" (ECS) con 3665 jovenes de entre 16 y 24 años. Se dividió la muestra en dos submuestras diferentes llevándose a cabo un análisis factorial exploratorio y confirmatorio con cada una de ellas. Se encontró un único factor. La fiabilidad de la escala fue adecuada, así como la validez convergente, con correlaciones positivas y significativas con la versión modificada de la "Escala de tácticas de conflicto" (M-CTS; Neidig, 1986) que mide violencia física y verbal. También se encontraron diferencias significativas, en el sentido esperado, en la ECS en función de la edad y el sexo. La ECS constituye un instrumento adecuado para evaluar coerción sexual en relaciones de noviazgo en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;25(3): 547-561, dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14179</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">"Escala de coerción sexual" (ECS) en relaciones de noviazgo: propiedades psicométricas en población juvenil española</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
