<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043945</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunohistochemical detection of the high risk Human Papillomavirus (HPV)-L1 protein in uterine cervix cytologies and biopsies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study was designed to confirm the immunohistochemicaldetection of the high risk HPV-L1 protein inabnormal epithelial cells observed in cytologies and also insquamous cells carcinomas diagnosed in biopsies. The sampleswere selected randomly: 11 cervical cytologies of theyear 2004 with a cytological interpretation of abnormalitiesin squamous cells including: atypical squamous cells and inlow and high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions; and 50cervical biopsies with squamous cells carcinomas diagnosedduring the years 1950 and 1980. All the samples, cytologicaland histological, were subjected to an immunohistochemicalprocedure in order to detect the high risk HPV-L1protein, with the antibody VAHP. 64% of the cytologicalsamples were satisfactory for evaluation, while 4/11 presentedmoderate to intense inflammation. 27% of the cervicalcytologies with a suggestive cytologic interpretation of lowgrade(67%) and high-grade intraepithelial lesion (33%),showed koilocytes with positive nuclei for the high riskHPV-L1 protein. All the cytologic samples with atipia werenegative to the immunostain, as well as the 50 cervical squamouscells carcinomas. The high risk HPV-L1 proteindetection in the studied cases was low. These results suggestthat the immunodetection of the high risk HPV-L1 protein isreduced in the severe cervical lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llombart-Bosch, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro, Morelva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para confirmar la detección inmunohistoquímica de laproteína L1 de HPV de alto riesgo, tanto en citologías conanormalidades en células epiteliales como en biopsias condiagnóstico de carcinoma epidermoide cervical, se seleccionaronaleatoriamente: 11 citologías cervicales del año2004 con interpretación citológica de anormalidades encélulas escamosas incluyendo: células escamosas atípicas ylesión intraepitelial escamosa de bajo y alto grado y 50biopsias de cérvix con carcinoma epidermoide diagnosticadosentre los años 1950 y 1980. Todas las muestras, tantocitológicas como histológicas fueron sometidas al procedimientoinmunohistoquímico para la detección de la proteínaL1 de HPV de alto riesgo, con anticuerpo de alto riesgoVAHP. El 64% de las muestras citológicas fueron satisfactoriaspara la evaluación, mientras que 4/11 presentabaninflamación moderada o intensa. El 27% citologías cervicalescon cuadro citológico sugestivo de 2 lesión de bajo grado(67%) y 1 lesión de alto grado (33%), mostraron coilocitoscon núcleos positivos para L1 de HPV de alto riesgo.Todas las muestras citológicas con atipias fueron negativaspara la inmunotinción, así como los 50 casos de carcinomaepidermoide. La detección de la proteína L1 de HPV de altoriesgo en las citologías estudiadas fue baja. Estos resultadossugieren que la inmunodetección de la proteína L1 de HPVde alto riesgo es reducida en las lesiones cervicales severas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(1): 8-13, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección inmunohistoquímica de la proteína L1 de Virus Papiloma Humano (HPV) de alto riesgo en citologías y biopsias de cuello uterino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15029^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37387^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
