<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101028</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hardy personality and sense of coherence as predictors of burnout in critical care staff</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyse the relationship between burnout syndrome and two personality variables: Hardy Personality and Sense of Coherence, in order to determine whether these variables can be considered significant predictors of burnout. A descriptive and cross-sectional study was carried out with a sample of 144 Intensive Care professionals who responded to several questionnaires: the Brief Burnout Questionnaire (CBB), Resistant Personality Questionnaire (CPR) and the Spanish version of the Orientation to Life Questionnaire (OLQ-13). A higher than average level of burnout was detected in the population. There was a negative correlation between hardiness (globally and through its components) and burnout. No correlation was found between sense of coherence (except in the comprehensibility and control dimensions). Hierarchical regression analyses showed that hardiness and comprehensibility (a sense of coherence component) modulate the effects of occupational stress (a burnout antecedent) on burnout syndrome. These results may be especially relevant when designing and implementing burnout prevention programmes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles Ortega, Humbelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Carmona, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo se ha centrado en investigar la relación del síndrome de burnout con la personalidad resistente y el sentido de coherencia, con el fin de determinar si éstas pueden ser entendidas como predictores del burnout. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo y transversal con 144 profesionales  sanitarios de Cuidados Intensivos que respondieron a varios cuestionarios: Cuestionario Breve de Burnout (CBB), Cuestionario de Personalidad Resistente (CPR), y la adaptación española del Cuestionario de Orientación a la vida (OLQ-13). Se detectó un grado medio-alto de burnout entre los participantes. Se encontró una correlación negativa entre la personalidad resistente (a nivel global y sus componentes) y burnout. Apenas se encontró correlación entre el sentido de coherencia y el burnout (únicamente la dimensión de comprensibilidad), ni entre la personalidad resistente y el sentido de coherencia (salvo la dimensión de comprensibilidad y control). Los análisis de regresión jerárquica mostraron que la personalidad resistente y la comprensibilidad, componente del sentido de coherencia, modulan los efectos de los estresores laborales (antecedentes del burnout) en el síndrome de burnout. Los resultados pueden tener especial relevancia en el diseño e implementación de programas de prevención del burnout en estos profesionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;17(2/3): 99-112, dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personalidad resistente y sentido de coherencia como predictores del burnout en personal sanitario de cuidados intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54741</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
