<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156975</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention and management of hypothermia during the perioperative period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the frequency of hypothermia during the perioperative period in patients undergoing scheduled surgery under general anaesthesia, and to understand the personal and environmental factors that have an impact on the development of hypothermia during the surgical period.  Method: a longitudinal descriptive pilot study was conducted in the Surgical Unit of the Hospital Clínico Universitario Lozano Blesa of Zaragoza, from June to October, 2015.  The study population was formed by those patients undergoing surgery who met the inclusion criteria. The study collected sociodemographical variables, environmental variables (Operating Room temperature, type of procedure and its duration, size of the surgical wound, saline therapy, anaesthetic gases, warming systems) and thermal variables (temperature at baseline, pre and post anaesthetic induction, and every 20 minutes during the perioperative period and the recovery from anesthesia, until discharge from the Post-anaesthetic Care Unit with recorded development of hypothermia. A descriptive and bivariate analysis was conducted.   Results: the total sample included 25 patients who presented a mean intraoperative reduction of 0.7 ºC from their initial temperature. Out of these patients, 40% presented mild hypothermia during the surgical procedure, which occurred during the first hour in 92% of cases. A 24% of patients suffered hypothermia during the post-operative period, and half of them had already developed it previously during the intraoperative period.  Conclusion: there is a higher frequency of intraoperative vs. postoperative hypothermia, generally recorded during the first hour of surgery and within the first 30 minutes of recovery from anaesthesia. Longer surgery duration and a larger wound size will favour the development of hypothermia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sorli Latorre, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sorli Latorre, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Lahoz, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la frecuencia de hipotermia durante el periodo perioperatorio en pacientes sometidos a cirugías programadas bajo anestesia general y conocer los factores personales y ambientales que influyen en la aparición de hipotermia durante el periodo quirúrgico. Método: se desarrolló un estudio piloto descriptivo longitudinal en el bloque quirúrgico del Hospital Clínico Universitario Lozano Blesa de Zaragoza, desde junio hasta octubre de 2015. La población del estudio fueron los pacientes intervenidos quirúrgicamente que cumpliesen con los criterios de inclusión. Se recopilaron variables sociodemográficas, variables ambientales (temperatura del quirófano, intervención y duración, tamaño de la herida quirúrgica, sueroterapia, gases anestésicos, sistemas de calentamiento) y variables térmicas (temperatura basal, pre y postinducción anestésica, y cada 20 minutos durante el periodo intraoperatorio y de recuperación anestésica hasta el alta de la Unidad de Recuperación Post Anestésica (URPA) con registro de aparición de hipotermia. Se realizó análisis descriptivo y bivariante. Resultados: la muestra total fue de 25 individuos que presentaron un descenso medio intraoperatorio de 0,7 ºC con respecto a su temperatura inicial. El 40% de los individuos presentó hipotermia leve durante la intervención quirúrgica, dando lugar durante la primera hora en el 92% de los estos. El 24% de los sujetos padecieron hipotermia durante el postoperatorio, ya habiéndola desarrollado anteriormente la mitad de estos durante el tiempo intraoperatorio.  Conclusión: hay mayor frecuencia de hipotermia intraoperatoria que postoperatoria, registrada generalmente durante la primera hora quirúrgica y en los primeros 30 minutos de recuperación anestésica. Un mayor tiempo de intervención y del tamaño de incisión facilitan la aparición de hipotermia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(7): 71-76, sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156975</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y manejo de la hipotermia en el periodo perioperatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
