<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142766</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to examine the reading comprehension problems in deaf people. Two kind of words were chosen to analyse these problems: prepositions and interrogative particles, both being very frequently found in texts and essential in the correct understanding of a sentence. Each category was evaluated with 55 items. 40 deaf people between 13 and 58 years old took part in this research. Age, moment in which hearing loss took place, degree of hearing loss and communication system were used as independent variables, and used to classify them. A group of non-deaf children aged 7 and 8 acted as control. The results show the existence of significant differences between the different subgroups indicating the difficulties that deaf people has in understanding both, prepositions and interrogative particles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuetos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monsalve, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue profundizar en los problemas de comprensión lectora que padecen los sujetos sordos. Para ello fueron elegidos dos tipos de palabras: preposiciones y partículas interrogativas, ambas muy frecuentes en los textos y decisivas para la correcta comprensión de las frases. Cada categoría fue evaluada a través de 55 items. La muestra estuvo formada por 40 personas sordas de entre 13 y 58 años, utilizándose para establecer los diferentes subgrupos los siguientes factores: edad, momento de la pérdida auditiva, grado de la misma y sistema de comunicación utilizado. Un grupo de niños oyentes de 7 y 8 años sirvió de grupo de control. Los resultados ponen de manifiesto los problemas que los sordos tienen para comprender ambos tipos de palabras, así como diferencias entre los distintos subgrupos de sordos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);22(3): 133-142, jul.-sept. 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La comprensión escrita de preposiciones y partículas interrogativas: un estudio en sujetos sordos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6462^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
