<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038513</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">On the verge of change in University Education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Changes in society as a whole oblige University education to introduce changes as well. In order to train well-equipped professionals, an open educational model is necessary, based on the ability of the student to learn, to obtain information, and to adapt to the changes inside the profession. The planning of learning programs involves new roles for the teacher and new functions for the student. It requires changes in methodology and in educational strategies. The new information and communication technologies are indispensable instruments for promoting these changes, but they are not enough in isolation. Problem based learning (PBL) is an innovative instrument in the University setting, increasing students&#146; motivation, empowering group work, stimulating the search for information and increasing the comprehension and memorizing of knowledge. PBL also emphasizes interdisciplinary work, stressing the need to cooperate and to increase students&#146; responsibility for their learning. In the field of health sciences, effective learning methods are vital for the training of competent professionals due to the close connection between the educational and work environments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escayola Maranges, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Gangolells, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cambios sociales conducen a un nuevo planteamiento en la docencia universitaria. Es necesario un modelo educativo abierto para formar nuevos profesionales competentes, basado en la capacidad de aprender del alumno, de obtener información y de adaptarse a las situaciones de cambio que presenta la profesión. La planificación de programas educativos plantea nuevos roles en la función del docente y del alumno, exige cambios metodológicos en el proceso de aprendizaje, conllevando cambios en las estrategias educativas. La nuevas tecnologías de la información y comunicación son un elemento indispensable para promover el cambio, aunque no suficientes. El aprendizaje basado en problemas (ABP) ha resultado un elemento innovador en el ámbito universitario, demostrando un aumento de la motivación para aprender, potenciando el trabajo grupal, incentivando la búsqueda de información, aumentado la comprensión y la memorización del conocimiento. A su vez, el ABP pone énfasis en la interdisciplinariedad, aumenta el espíritu de colaboración del estudiante y su nivel de responsabilidad en el aprendizaje. En el ámbito de las Ciencias de la Salud, los métodos de aprendizaje son claves en el proceso formativo de profesionales competentes, dada la estrecha vinculación entre el ámbito laboral y formativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);8(2): 69-73, jun. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038513</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">A las puertas del cambio en la Formación Universitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
