<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154465</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Critical energy deficit and mortality in critically ill patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We investigate the influence of caloric and protein deficit on mortality and length of hospital stay of critically ill patients. Methods: A cohort prospective study including 100 consecutive patients in a tertiary intensive care unit (ICU) receiving enteral or parenteral nutrition. The daily caloric and protein deficit were collected each day for a maximum of 30 days. Energy deficits were divided into critical caloric deficit (&amp;#8805; 480 kcal/day) and non-critical caloric deficit (&amp;#8804; 480 kcal/day); and in critical protein deficit (&amp;#8805; 20 g/day) and non-critical protein deficit (&amp;#8804; 20 g/day). The findings were correlated with hospital stay and mortality. Results: The mortality rate was 33%. Overall, the patients received 65.4% and 67.7% of the caloric and protein needs. Critical caloric deficit was found in 72% of cases and critical protein deficit in 70% of them. There was a significant correlation between length of stay and accumulated caloric deficit (R = 0.37; p &lt; 0.001) and protein deficit (R = 0.28; p &lt; 0.001). The survival analysis showed that mortality was greater in patients with both critical caloric (p &lt; 0.001) and critical protein deficits (p &lt; 0.01). The Cox regression analysis showed that critical protein deficit was associated with higher mortality (HR 0.25, 95% CI 0.07&#150;0.93, p = 0.03). Conclusions: The incidence of caloric and protein deficit in the ICU is high. Both caloric and protein deficits increase the length of hospital stay, and protein deficit greater than 20 g/day is an independent factor for mortality in critical care unit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dock-Nascimento, Diana Borges</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siqueira-Paese, Marcia Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Nascimento, José Eduardo de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: investigar la influencia del déficit de calorías y proteínas en la mortalidad y la duración de la estancia hospitalaria de pacientes críticos. Métodos: se realizó un estudio prospectivo de cohorte incluyendo 100 pacientes consecutivos en una unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI) terciaria que recibían nutrición enteral o parenteral. Se registraron diariamente los déficits de calorías y proteínas durante un máximo de 30 días. Los déficit de energía y proteínas fueron divididos en: déficit crítico de calorías (&amp;#8805; 480 kcal/día), déficit calórico no crítico (&amp;#8804; 480 kcal/día), déficit crítico de proteínas (&amp;#8805; 20 g/día) y déficit de proteínas no crítico (&amp;#8804; 20 g/día). Los resultados se correlacionaron con la estancia hospitalaria y la mortalidad. Resultados: la tasa de mortalidad fue de 33%. En general, los pacientes recibieron 65,4% y 67,7% de las necesidades calóricas y proteicas. El déficit calórico crítico se encontró en el 72% de los casos y el déficit proteico crítico en el 70% de ellos. Hubo una correlación significativa entre la duración de la estancia con el déficit calórico (R = 0,37; p &lt; 0,001) y el déficit de proteínas (R = 0,28; p &lt; 0,001). El análisis de sobrevida mostró que la mortalidad fue mayor en los pacientes con déficit calórico crítico (p &lt; 0,001) o con déficit proteico crítico (p &lt; 0,01). El análisis de regresión de Cox mostró que el déficit crítico de proteínas se asoció con mayor mortalidad (HR 0.25, IC 95% 0,07-0,93; p = 0,03). Conclusiones: la incidencia de déficit de calorías y de proteínas en la UCI es alta. Tanto los déficit calóricos como proteicos aumentan la duración de la estancia hospitalaria, y el déficit de proteínas superior a 20 g/día es un factor independiente de mortalidad en la ICU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 522-527, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficit crítico de energía y mortalidad en pacientes críticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
