<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122553</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Back pain, patellofemoral syndrome and &#147;growing pains&#148; are increasingly common in children and adolescents, both with incidence and precocity of appearance. In most cases their etiology is unknown. Objective: The objective of this research was to explore the possible association of these three entities with pelvic anteversion. Methods: This is a cross-sectional study with case-control analysis, comprising a group of 30 symptomatic children aged between 6 and 17 years (cases) who had consulted for low back pain, &#147;growing pains&#148; or sore knees, and a control group of 30 children with no history of pain in these areas (controls). To measure the position of the pelvis and other biomechanical variables a software programme was developed that quantifies these measurements from reflective markings located on specific anatomical landmarks of each child. Other measurements were obtained through semiological tests and interviews with children and their parents. Results: Children and adolescents with pain had more pelvic anteversion compared with controls (mean 13.3 and 5.4 degrees, p &lt; 0.001). They also had less strength in muscles: Lumbar extensor, abdominals, psoas and diaphragm. We found that psoas is the muscle most responsible for pelvis anteversion in symptomatic group. Compared with children without pain, those with back pain, patellofemoral syndrome or &#147;growing pains&#148; have 4.2 times more frequent poor or regular strength in the column extensor muscles. They also have nearly 18 times as likely to have a pelvic angle greater than 10 degrees compared with no pain children. Conclusions: Children and adolescents who suffer from back pain, patellofemoral syndrome and &#147;growing pains&#148; have increased pelvic anteversion and lower muscle strength, mainly  in the thoracolumbar spine extensors, abdominals, diaphragmand psoas. The study found that the psoas muscle is most  responsible for the development of pelvis anteversion. Pelvicanteversion is associated with low back pain, patellofemoral pain syndrome and &#147;growing pains&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz León, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez Patiño, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Jaramillo, F. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Sánchez, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el dolor lumbar, el síndrome patelofemoral y los &#147;dolores del crecimiento&#148; son cada vez más frecuentes en niños y adolescentes, tanto en incidencia como en precocidad de aparición. En la mayoría de los casos su etiología se desconoce. Objetivo: el objetivo de esta investigación fue explorar la asociación de estas tres entidades con la anteversión pélvica. Métodos: se realizó un estudio transversal, con análisis de casos y controles, en un grupo de 30 niños con edades entre 6 y 17 años que hubieran consultado por dolor lumbar, &#147;dolores de crecimiento&#148; o dolor en las rodillas (casos), y otro grupo conformado por otros 30 menores sin antecedentes de dolor en dichas regiones (controles). Para la medición de la posición de la pelvis y otras variables biomecánicas se desarrolló un software  que cuantifica estas medidas a partir de marcas reflectivas ubicadas sobre puntos anatómicos específicos en cada niño. Otrasmediciones fueron obtenidas a través de pruebas semiológicas y  entrevistas a los menores y sus padres.  Resultados: se encontró que los menores con dolor presentaronmayor anteversión de la pelvis comparados con aquellos sin dolor (medias de 13,3 y 5,4 grados, p &lt; 0,001). Igualmente, tenían menor fuerza en los músculos extensores de columna lumbar, abdominales, psoas y diafragma. Encontramos, además,  que el psoas es el músculo con mayor responsabilidad en la anteversión de la pelvis en los niños del grupo sintomático. En un menor con dolor lumbar, síndrome patelofemoral o &#147;dolores del crecimiento&#148; fue 4,2 veces más frecuente la presencia de fuerza deficiente o regular de los músculos extensores de columna que en los menores sin dolor. Igualmente, tuvieron casi 18 veces la probabilidad de tener un ángulo pélvico mayor de 10 grados comparado con aquellos menores sin dolor. Conclusión: los niños y adolescentes que sufren dolor lumbar, síndrome patelofemoral y &#147;dolores de crecimiento&#148; presentan mayor anteversión de la pelvis y menor fuerza muscular, principalmente en los extensores de columna toracolumbar, abdominales, diafragma y psoas. El estudio encontró que el músculo psoas es el que tiene mayor responsabilidad en el desarrollo de anteversión de la pelvis. La anteversión de la pelvis se asocia con dolor lumbar, síndrome patelofemoral y &#147;dolores  de crecimiento&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;21(2): 73-83, mar.-abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anteversión pélvica como causa de dolor lumbar, síndrome patelofemoral y dolores del crecimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54529^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54485^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38611^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29858^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
