<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117239</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening program for the early diagnosis of colorectal cancer in the Canary Islands: presentation of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Colorectal cancer is the second leading cause of cancer death in Spain The main objective of screening programs is the early detection, or even prevention of the development, of colon cancer, as well as the mortality that results from it. If caught early, it is easy to treat and the chances of cure are high. In 2009 only six regions in Spain, among which included the Autonomous Community of the Canary Islands, started this screening program. We report the case of a patient, who after screening for colorectal cancer, was diagnosed with adenocarcinoma of the rectosigmoid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Monje, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Cordovés, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirpuri-Mirpuri, P. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer colorrectal es la segunda causa de muerte por cáncer en España.  Los programas de cribado tienen como principal objetivo detectar precozmente o, mejor aún, prevenir la aparición de cáncer de colon y reducir la mortalidad que de él se deriva. Si se detecta a tiempo, es fácil de tratar y las posibilidades de curación son elevadas.  Solo 6 comunidades autónomas de España, entre las que se encuentra la canaria, pusieron en 2009 en marcha este programa de cribado.  Presentamos el caso de un paciente que tras el cribado de cáncer colorrectal fue diagnosticado de adenocarcinoma de unión recto-sigma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(8): e71-e74, nov.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa de diagnóstico precoz de cáncer colorrectal en Canarias. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4811^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
