<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140121</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to review the evidence about care at the end of life in patients with non-oncological disease in order to consider the key points in looking after these patients in palliative care units. Material and methods: a narrative review focusing on the current status of palliative care for non-oncological patients at the end of life, the needs of these patients, and the barriers to provide them with palliative care in specific palliative units. Results: for many years we have tended to identify patients in need of palliative care with patients with advanced oncological illness. However, the number of deaths due to non-oncological illness in patients entitled to receive palliative care, mainly organ failures and neurodegenerative illness, is higher than the number of deaths from cancer. We know that the needs of patients and their families are similar in non-oncological cases. In spite of this, many research works show that these patients receive poorer care. Thus, taking into account the principle of justice, it is an ethical obligation to promote palliative care in the setting of non oncological disease.  Conclusions: the implementation of Quality palliative care in these patients must consider the knowledge acquired in the palliative care for cancer patients. The application of screening criteria to adequately include these patients in the various programs and palliative care services available is essential to tackle care challenges in this group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rexach Cano, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert Agullar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Babarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: revisar la bibliografía existente sobre la atención de pacientes no oncológicos al final de la vida con el fin de reflexionar sobre los puntos básicos para su atención por servicios de cuidados paliativos. Material y métodos: Revisión narrativa, focalizando en la situación actual de atención a pacientes no oncológicos en la fase final de su enfermedad, las necesidades de estos enfermos y las barreras para su seguimiento en servicios específicos de cuidados paliativos. Resultados: durante muchos años hemos tendido a identificar a los enfermos susceptibles de cuidados paliativos con pacientes con enfermedad oncológica avanzada. Sin embargo, el número de fallecimientos debidos a enfermedades no oncológicas susceptibles de recibir cuidados paliativos, fundamentalmente insuficiencias orgánicas y enfermedades neurodegenerativas, es mayor Que las debidas al cáncer. Las necesidades de los pacientes y sus familias son similares en los enfermos no oncológicoso. A pesar de ello, numerosos trabajos de investigación demuestran que estos pacientes reciben peores cuidados. Por tanto, teniendo en cuenta el principio de justicia, es una obligación ética potenciar la atención paliativa de los pacientes no oncológicos. Conclusiones: la implantación de unos cuidados paliativos de calidad en estos pacientes debe tener en cuenta lo aprendido respecto al desarrollo de estos cuidados en enfermos oncológicos. La aplicación de unos criterios de selección Que nos permita la adecuada inclusión de estos pacientes en los diferentes programas y servicios de cuidados paliativos resulta esencial para enfrentarse a las dificultades de atención en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;17(3): 156-160, mayo-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140121</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados paliativos en enfermedades no oncológicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
