<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-35156</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for stroke treatment and prevention 2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. According to the World Health Organisation, cerebrovascular disease is the third most important cause of death and the leading cause of disability in the adult population in the world today. Yet, stroke patients&#146; progression improves significantly with immediate attention, hospitals that are well equipped with the necessary material and staff (expert neurologists) and the application of protocols as a programme of care, diagnostic methods and specific treatment (stroke units or teams). Development. In order to disseminate the scientific evidence available on stroke treatment and prevention, an ad hoc committee of the Latin-American Society of Cerebrovascular Diseases has drawn up this manual, which includes a summary of all the recommendations currently applicable with the levels of evidence that support them and the degree of recommendation for each case. Conclusions. This document is intended to serve as an aid and a guide to treatment and prevention in stroke patients in all Latin-American countries, and to help to attain the means needed to improve the care given to such patients in the different health care centres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Según la Organización Mundial de la Salud, la enfermedad cerebrovascular constituye la tercera causa de muerte y la primera de invalidez en la población adulta en el mundo. Sin embargo, la atención urgente del paciente con ictus, en un centro hospitalario bien dotado de medios materiales y personales (neurólogos expertos) y la aplicación de un programa protocolizado de cuidados, métodos diagnósticos y tratamiento específico (unidades o equipos de ictus) mejora significativamente la evolución de los pacientes afectados. Desarrollo. Para difundir las evidencias científicas disponibles acerca del tratamiento y la prevención del ictus, un comité ad hoc de la Sociedad Iberoamericana de Enfermedad Cerebrovascular ha redactado esta guía, que recoge de manera esquemática todas las recomendaciones vigentes, con los niveles de evidencia que las respaldan y el grado de recomendación para cada caso. Conclusiones. Este documento pretende servir de apoyo y guía para el tratamiento y la prevención en los pacientes con ictus en todos los países de Iberoamérica, y contribuir a lograr los medios necesarios para mejorar la atención al paciente con ictus en las distintas administraciones sanitarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(5): 465-486, sept. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para el tratamiento y prevención del ictus, 2004</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Díez Tejedor, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez R, GE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso de Leciñana-Cases, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-35156</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
