<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18669</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Has the time arrived for the management of waiting lists?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Individuals on the waiting list frequently suffer an additional risk caused by the mean time until they receive treatment; however, other individuals do not need the treatment for which they are waiting. Both arguments, which can be contrasted with empirical evidence, would be sufficient to affirm that waiting list management should be implemented, leaving aside policies that are more of less opportunistic. Opportunistic policies are understood as those providing misinformation on waiting lists or their "manipulation", and using programs of auto-coordination with the sole aim of reaching the end of the year without a waiting list of not more than six months, etc. The panorama is not completely bleak. Some management initiatives (and even Politics with a capital P) are opening the way forward and may enter the Agenda in the next few years. In this context, the application of guaranteed times of medical care or the prioritization of waiting lists according to explicit criteria should be highlighted. It is worth remembering that, except for the queues in the waiting rooms of health centers and emergency departments, waiting lists are mediated by the decision of the physician. Therefore, an essential strategy for managing waiting lists consists of attenuating the problems caused by uncertainty (or ignorance) of the patient's diagnosis or prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las personas que ocupan una lista de espera sufren a menudo un riesgo adicional derivado del tiempo que pasa hasta que obtienen tratamiento; sin embargo, en otras ocasiones, las personas en lista no tienen necesidad del tratamiento por el que esperan. Ambos argumentos, contrastables con evidencias empíricas, serían suficientes para afirmar que debe llegar la gestión a las listas de espera dejando a un lado políticas más o menos oportunistas. Por políticas oportunistas se entiende mantener la mala información sobre listas o su "maquillaje", utilizar programas de autoconcertación sin más horizonte que llegar a final de año sin lista de más de seis meses, etcétera. El panorama no es del todo oscuro. Algunas iniciativas de gestión (incluso de Política con mayúscula) se van abriendo paso y pueden entrar en la agenda de los próximos años. Así, cabe destacar la aplicación de tiempos de atención garantizada o la priorización de las listas en función de criterios explícitos. En todo caso, conviene recordar que, con la excepción de las colas producidas en las salas de espera de los centros de salud y aquéllas que se producen en las puertas de urgencias, el resto de colas del sistema están mediadas por la decisión de un médico. Así que una estrategia ineludible para gestionar las listas de espera consiste en atenuar los problemas derivados de la incertidumbre (o ignorancia) con respecto al diagnóstico o al pronóstico de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;16(5): 436-439, sept. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Ha llegado la hora de la gestión de las listas de espera?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Bernal, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18669</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5678</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
