<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053656</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extraintestinal infection due to Aeromonas spp: review of 38 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Aeromonas spp. typically cause gastroenteritis, but can occasionally produce extraintestinal infections. The aim of this study was to determine the clinical and microbiological characteristics of extraintestinal infections caused by Aeromonas spp. in our area. Patients and methods. The clinical histories of patients with extraintestinal infections by Aeromonas spp. diagnosed in Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara (Guadalajara, Spain) from January 1990 to December 2005 were reviewed. Identification and susceptibility testing of the strains were performed by the MicroScan WalkAway-40 automated method (DadeBerhing). Results. Thirty-eight cases of extraintestinal infections were diagnosed: 18 abdominal infections, 11 skin and soft tissue infections, 3 urinary tract infections, and 3 episodes of bacteremia with no primary focus. The species most frequently found was A. hydrophila (16 cases). Infection occurred most often in patients with underlying diseases (76,3%), including malignancy (34,2%) and diabetes mellitus (21%). Polymicrobial infections were detected in 50% and the etiology was nosocomial in 21%. The mortality rate was 16,2%. Gentamicin, amikacin, cefotaxime and ciprofloxacin had the highest activity against the Aeromonas species isolated. Conclusions. Aeromonas spp. as the causative infectious agent should be kept in mind in patients with infections of the biliary system, surgical wounds in the abdomen and posttraumatic cellulitis. Extraintestinal infection is usually polymicrobial, appears most commonly in patients with underlying diseases, and generally has a good prognosis. The most active antibiotics in vitro were gentamicin, amikacin, cefotaxime and ciprofloxacin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pomata, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tena, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bisquert, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Praetorius, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Aeromonas spp. es una causa habitual de gastroenteritis pero ocasionalmente puede producir infecciones extraintestinales. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer las características clínicas y microbiológicas de las infecciones extraintestinales producidas por este microorganismo en nuestro medio. Pacientes y métodos. Se revisaron retrospectivamente las historias clínicas de los enfermos con infecciones extraintestinales por Aeromonas spp., diagnosticadas en el Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara entre enero de 1990 y diciembre de 2005. La identificación microbiológica y la susceptibilidad antimicrobiana de las cepas aisladas se realizaron mediante el sistema automático MicroScan WalkAway-40 (DadeBerhing). Resultados. Se diagnosticaron 38 casos: 18 infecciones abdominales, 11 de piel y partes blandas, 3 del tracto urinario, 3 del aparato respiratorio y 3 bacteriemias sin foco primario. La especie más frecuente fue A. hydrophila (16 casos). El 76,3% de los enfermos presentaron patologías de base predisponentes, siendo las de naturaleza neoplásica las más frecuentes (34,2%), seguida de diabetes mellitus (21%). El 50% de las infecciones fueron polimicrobianas y el 21% de origen nosocomial. La mortalidad global fue del 16,2%. Los antibióticos con mayor porcentaje de sensibilidad fueron gentamicina, amikacina, cefotaxima y ciprofloxacino. Conclusiones. Aeromonas spp. debe ser tenida en cuenta en infecciones del sistema biliar, infecciones de heridas quirúrgicas abdominales y celulitis postraumáticas. La infección extraintestinal con frecuencia es polimicrobiana, suele aparecer en enfermos con patologías de base y en general el pronóstico es bueno. Los antibióticos más activos in vitro fueron gentamicina, amikacina, cefotaxima y ciprofloxacino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;25(4): 235-241, abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección extraintestinal por Aeromonas spp: revisión de 38 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23152^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30074^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30074^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d337^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7574^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d337^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d337^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7574^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2475^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
