<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125918</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design, Development and In vitro Characterization of Pioglitazone Loaded Mucoadhesive Buccal Devices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The mucoadhesive buccal patches were developed and evaluated for systemic administration of Pioglitazone in the oral cavity. Pioglitazone belongs to a novel class of oral antidiabetic drugs known as Thiazolidinediones. Materials and Methods: The mucoadhesive buccal patches of Pioglitazone was formulated using Eudragit RS100 and HPMC K4M (mucoadhesive polymer) and were prepared by solvent casting method. Different patch formulations were evaluated for its physical parameters like thickness uniformity, swelling index, surface pH, uniformity of weight, folding endurance, mucoadhesive strength and in vitro parameters like drug content uniformity and drug release studies, and ex vivo parameters like mucoadhesion time. Results: Data for the parameters was found to be: thickness uniformity (0.27±0.45mm); uniformity of weight (40.81±0.66 mg), surface pH (6.5), folding endurance (&gt;300), drug content uniformity (98.58±2.05%), swelling index (131±0.79%), mucoadhesive strength (38.20±1.75), in vitro drug release studies (95.18±1.98%) and ex vivo mucoadhesion, time of optimized formulation (4±1.26 h). The data was also fitted to different kinetic models to illustrate its anomalous (non-fickian) diffusion. Conclusions: The result revealed that Pioglitazone loaded buccal patches was most suitable mode of drug delivery for promising therapeutic action. Buccal patches of Pioglitazone can prove to be potential pharmaceutical dosage form for sustaining the drug release and reducing the dose frequency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Malik, Raj Kaur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gulati, Neha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nagaich, Upendra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malik, Prashant</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los parches de mucoadherente bucal fueron desarrollados y evaluados por la administración sistémica de la pioglitazona en la cavidad oral. Pioglitazona pertenece a una clase nueva de medicamentos antidiabéticos orales conocida como tiazolidindionas. Material y Método: los parches mucoadherente bucal de pioglitazona fue formulado con Eudragit RS100 y HPMC K4M (polímero mucoadherentes) y fueron elaboradas por el método de fundición solvente. Se evaluaron diferentes formulaciones de parches mediante parámetros físicos como uniformidad de espesor, índice de hinchazón, pH de la superficie, uniformidad de peso, resistencia al plegado, fuerza mucoadherentes y parámetros in vitro como uniformidad de contenido del fármaco y estudios de liberación y estudios ex vivo del tiempo de mucoadhesión del fármaco. Resultados: Los resultados obtenidos para los parámetros estudiados fueron: uniformidad de espesor, 0.27±0.45 mm; uniformidad de peso, 40.81±0.66 mg; pH superficial, 6.5; resistencia al plegado, &gt; 300. Los ensayos in vitro dieron los siguientes resultados: uniformidad de contenido del fármaco, 98.58±2.05%; índice de hinchazón, 131±0.79%; fuerza mucoadherente, 38.20±1.75; y tiempo de liberación del farmaco (95.18±1.98%) y el ensayo ex vivo del tiempo de mucoadhesión del fármaco fue de 4±1.26 h. Los datos también se ajustaron a distintos modelos cinéticos para ilustrar su difusión anómala (no Fickian). Conclusiones: El resultado reveló que los parches bucales de pioglitazona fue el modo más adecuado de fármacos de acción terapéutica prometedora. Los Parches bucales de pioglitazona pueden resultar una potencial forma de dosificación farmacéutica para sostener la liberación del fármaco y reducir la frecuencia de la dosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;55(2): 25-31[2], abr.-jun. 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125918</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño, desarrollo y caracterización in vitro de un producto mucoadherente bucal cargado de pioglitazona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54213^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
