<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74483</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attitudes, knowledge and expectations of patients with postmenopausal osteoporosis in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This study describes the profile and attitudes, knowledge and expectations of patients with postmenopausal osteoporosis. Subjects and methods: Epidemiological and cross-sectional study carried out in Spain. Participating patients were aged over 45 years and receiving treatment for postmenopausal osteoporosis. Data on personal and family medical history, diseases and concomitant medications, smoking and drinking habits, diet and physical activity, treatment and compliance were recorded. All patients completed a 17 item questionnaire on attitudes, knowledge and expectations related to their condition. Results: A total of 1179 valid patients with postmenopausal osteoporosis were included, with a mean age of 59.89 ± 7.53 years. Only 22.6% of the patients showed acceptable knowledge of osteoporosis. A large majority (74.6%) of the patients were very/quite concerned about their condition, and 53.3% described their health status as excellent/good. However, 63.6% of the patients indicated that they need more information about osteoporosis. Conclusions: The results of this study prove the need to provide accurate knowledge of their disease to patients with postmenopausal osteoporosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quereda, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Borrego, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neyro, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Este estudio describe el perfil, las actitudes, conocimiento y expectativas de las pacientes con osteoporosis posmenopáusica. Sujetos y métodos: Estudio epidemiológico, transversal, realizado en España. Participaron pacientes en tratamiento para osteoporosis posmenopáusica &gt; 45 años. Se recogieron antecedentes personales y familiares, enfermedades y fármacos concomitantes, hábitos tóxicos, dietéticos y de actividad física, tipo de diagnóstico, tratamiento y cumplimiento. Todas las pacientes cumplimentaron un cuestionario de 17 preguntas sobre las actitudes, el conocimiento y las expectativas en relación con su afección. Resultados: Se incluyó a 1.179 pacientes con osteoporosis posmenopáusica válidas, con una edad media ± desviación estándar de 59,89 ± 7,53 años. Sólo el 22,6% mostró un conocimiento aceptable sobre la osteoporosis. Al 74,6% de las pacientes les preocupaba su enfermedad mucho/ bastante. El 53,3% describió su estado de salud como excelente/bueno. No obstante, el 63,6% indicó que necesitaba más información sobre la osteoporosis. Conclusiones: Este estudio ha evidenciado la necesidad de promover el correcto conocimiento de las pacientes con osteoporosis posmenopáusica sobre su afección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(10): 562-571, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitudes, conocimiento y expectativas de las pacientes con osteoporosis posmenopáusica en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
