<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133474</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with mortality in patients with dyspahgia helpin making dietary and nutritional choices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know what factors evaluated at the moment of admission are related with mortality among in-patients with dysphagia, during their stay in a longterm care hospital and may guide the dietary and nutritional intervention. Material and methods: Retrospective, observational and descriptive cohort study over patients with dysphagia diagnosed by Volumen-Viscosity Clinical Exploration Method (VVCEM). Demographic and clinical variables were gathered, stay, mortality, when their dysphagia was re-evaluated and treatments. Results: 182 patients were included, medium age of 78 years old, 50% of them died. Following factors were  significantly associate with death by univariant analysis: aged 85 or older, previous diagnosis of dysphagia, oncological disease, high co-morbidity (Charlson between 2-5 and &gt; 5 points), low functionality before hospitalization (Barthel Index &lt; 40), MNA &lt; 17 points, albumen &lt; 3 g/ dl, high score in CONUT (5-12 points), to be on opioids, neuroleptics, antidepressants while performing VVCEM, and the assistance aim when admission. Following factors had signification for risk to die by multi-variant analysis: age, oncological disease, co-morbidity and albumen, but taking antidepressants turned out to be a protective factor. Analysis of contrast was applied by curve ROC. The area under the curve was 0.740 and the confidence interval (CI) 0.668-0.811. Conclusions: The above-mentioned information that may be evaluated in patients with dysphagia when admission, may help to define of more suitable and precocious form our welfare aims. In those cases with major risk of  dying, it should prioritize comfort and safe swallowing. In those cases with low risk, in addition, should be effective improve to the maximum their nutritional condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubia Ortí, José Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero López, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Monte, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Sanz, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano Vela, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis-Bayarri Bernal, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer en los pacientes con disfagia ingresados en un Hospital de Media y Larga Estancia, qué factores, valorados al ingreso, están relacionados con fallecer durante su hospitalización y pueden orientar la intervención dietética y nutricional. Material y método: Estudio de cohorte retrospectivo, observacional y descriptivo de pacientes diagnosticados de disfagia por el Método de Exploración Clínica Volumen- Viscosidad (MECVV). Se recogieron variables demográficas y clínicas, estancia, éxitus, revaloraciones de disfagia y tratamientos. Resultados: Se incluyeron 182 pacientes, con edad media de 78 años, fallecieron el 50%. En el análisis univariante se asociaron significativamente con el éxitus: edad &gt;= 85 años, diagnóstico previo de disfagia, padecer enfermedad  oncológica, elevada comorbilidad (Charlson entre 2-5 y &gt; 5 puntos), baja funcionalidad previa a hospitalización (Índice de Barthel &lt; 40 puntos), MNA &lt; 17 puntos, albúmina &lt; 3 g/dl, alta puntuación del CONUT (de 5-12 puntos), tratamiento con: opioide, neuroléptico o antidepresivo al realizar el MECVV, y objetivo asistencial al ingreso. En análisis multivariante obtuvieron significación: edad, enfermedad oncológica, comorbilidad, y albúmina  como factores de riesgo para fallecer, y llevar antidepresivo como factor protector. Se aplicó análisis de contraste con Curva ROC. El área bajo la curva fue 0,740 y el intervalo de confianza (IC) 0,668-0,811. Conclusiones: En pacientes con disfagia, los datos referidos valorados al ingreso, pueden ayudar a definir más adecuada y precozmente objetivos asistenciales. En los casos con mayor riesgo de fallecer se priorizará una ingesta segura y de confort, y en aquellos con bajo riesgo, además deberá ser eficaz para intentar mejorar al máximo su estado nutricional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 820-828, feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los factores relacionados con la mortalidad en pacientes con disfagia ayudan en la toma de decisiones dietéticas y nutricionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
