<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112890</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute posterior multifocal placoid pigment epitheliopathy. A rare cause of ischaemic stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Acute posterior multifocal placoid pigment epitheliopathy (APMPPE) is a rare inflammatory disease, generally of unknown aetiology, affecting the choriocapillaris, the pigment epithelium and the outer retina. It predominantly affects young patients and in some cases may involve the central nervous system in the form of strokes or meningoencephalitis. We report the clinical case of a young female with APMPPE that was complicated by stroke and intracranial hypertension. Case report. Our patient was a 16-year-old female who began with intense headaches suggesting intracranial hypertension, as well as with an acute deficit in the left hemisphere. A magnetic resonance scan of the head revealed embolic or vasculitic lesions in different territories. No evidence of meningoencephalitis was found in the cerebrospinal fluid analysis, but signs of associated intracranial hypertension were observed. The presence of very specific lesions in the posterior pole of the eye led to a diagnosis of APMPPE complicated by ischaemic stroke, probably caused by a vasculitic mechanism. An extensive aetiological study failed to identify a clear precipitating factor underlying the process. Treatment with corticoids was established, with good clinical and radiological progression. Conclusions. APMPPE is an infrequent condition that generally has a good prognosis. In some cases, however, complications may arise owing to involvement of the central nervous system, and ischaemic stroke secondary to vasculitis is the most severe complication. In young patients with stroke who present visual symptoms and chorioretinital lesions, APMPPE must be considered in the aetiological diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanca Alfaya-Muñoz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recio Bermejo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega León, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Chiclano, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Huerta, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Medina, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrid Muñíz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Medina, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saz Saucedo, Pablo del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La epiteliopatía pigmentaria placoide multifocal posterior aguda (EPPMPA) es una enfermedad inflamatoria rara, generalmente de etiología indeterminada, de la coriocapilar, el epitelio pigmentario y la retina externa. Afecta predominantemente a pacientes jóvenes y en algunos casos puede involucrar al sistema nervioso central en forma de ictus o de meningoencefalitis. Presentamos el caso clínico de una mujer joven con EPPMPA complicada con ictus e hipertensión intracraneal. Caso clínico. Mujer de 16 años que comienza con cefalea intensa sugestiva de hipertensión intracraneal, así como con un déficit agudo hemisférico izquierdo. La resonancia magnética craneal ponía de manifiesto lesiones embólicas o vasculíticas en diferentes territorios. No se evidenciaron datos de meningoencefalitis en el estudio del líquido cefalorraquídeo, pero sí de hipertensión intracraneal asociada. La presencia de lesiones muy específicas en el polo ocular posterior permitió el diagnóstico de EPPMPA complicada con ictus isquémico, probablemente por mecanismo vasculítico. Un amplio estudio etiológico fue negativo para identificar un factor desencadenante claro del proceso. Se inició tratamiento corticoideo con buena evolución clínica y radiológica. Conclusiones. La EPPMPA es una entidad rara que generalmente entraña buen pronóstico; sin embargo, en algunos casos puede complicarse con afectación del sistema nervioso central, y el ictus isquémico secundario a vasculitis es la complicación más grave. Ante un paciente joven con ictus que presente sintomatología visual y lesiones coriorretinianas, debe considerarse la EPPMPA en su diagnóstico etiológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(11): 567-572, jun. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epiteliopatía pigmentaria placoide multifocal posterior aguda. Una rara causa de ictus isquémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31421^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34213^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52978^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
