<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60283</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and safety of long-acting injectable risperidone in maintenance phase of bipolar and schizoaffective disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Our aim was to evaluate treatment safety, tolerability, efficacy and compliance of long-acting injectable risperidone (LAIR) as maintenance treatment in a bipolar and schizoaffective inpatients sample with torpid course due to poor compliance to oral therapy. Methods. 22 inpatients, 14 with a diagnosis of bipolar disorder and 8 with a diagnosis of schizoaffective disorder, were included in this study. They were treated with LAIR, 1 dose every 14 days, and were evaluated for40 weeks with the Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS), Hamilton Scale for Depression (HAM-D), UKU-Side Effect Rating Scale and Clinical Global Impression Severity of Illness scales (CGI). Results. Average YMRS scores were reduced significantly from 10.5 at baseline interview to 2.5 at week 40(p &lt; 0.001). HAM-D and UKU scales did not reach a statistically significant reduction. CGI-S scores were reduced from 3.8 at baseline to 1.5 at week 40 (p &lt; 0.001).Conclusions. LAIR could be an effective maintenance therapy for bipolar and schizoaffective patients with poor compliance to oral treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Arán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salamero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murru, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benabarre, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Moreno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Este estudio tiene como objetivo evaluar la seguridad, tolerabilidad, eficacia y cumplimiento del tratamiento utilizando una formulación de risperidona inyectable de larga duración (RILD) como terapia de mantenimiento en un grupo de pacientes bipolares y esquizoafectivos con evolución tórpida debido a una mala adherencia al tratamiento por vía oral. Metodología. Veintidós pacientes, 14 de ellos con diagnóstico de trastorno bipolar y 8 con diagnóstico de trastorno esquizoafectivo, fueron incluidos en este estudio. Recibieron una inyección de RILD cada 14 días y fueron evaluados durante 40 semanas utilizando la Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS), la Hamilton Scale for Depression (HAM-D), la Udvalg Für KliniskeUndersogesles (UKU) y las Clinical Global Impression-Scales (CGI). Resultados. Las puntuaciones de la YMRS se redujeron significativamente de 10,5 (promedio) en la entrevista basal a 2,5 (promedio) en la semana 40 (p &lt; 0,001). En las puntuaciones de la HAM-D no hubo variación estadísticamente significativa, así como tampoco en las de la escala UKU para efectos adversos. Las puntuaciones en la escala CGI-S se redujeron de3,8 (entrevista basal) a 1,5 (semana 40) (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. RILD podría ser eficaz como tratamiento de mantenimiento en pacientes bipolares y esquizoafectivos con particular dificultad para adherirse de manera adecuada al tratamiento por vía oral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(3): 143-147, mayo-jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60283</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad de risperidona inyectable de larga duración en fase de mantenimiento del trastorno bipolar y esquizoafectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32618^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32618^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7442^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
