<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156549</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Specifications from the vascular risk measuring and control service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In April 2013, the Sociedad Española de Farmacia Familiar y Comunitaria (SEFAC) [Spanish Society for Family and Community Pharmacy] submitted its proposal regarding professional pharmaceutical services (PPS), whose aim is to cover healthcare for patients who use medicines and public health. This proposal offers an approach regarding the implementation and development of PPSs to boost their provision for community pharmacies in the coming years. According to this proposal, all the PPSs included in the services catalogue will be given a specifications document. The purpose of this specifications document is to define and characterize the vascular risk prevention and control service with a double purpose: &#149; Support community pharmacies and their collaborators in the offering, providing, distributing, funding and coordinating of this service. &#149; Guide community pharmacies that want to implement this service at the pharmacy or prepare a standardized work procedure. This documented is supplemented by the Guidelines for community pharmacies for patients with high blood pressure (hypertension) and cardiovascular risk (CVR). Consensus document GIAF-UGR, SEFAC and SEH-LELHA and with the impacHta program: SEFAC and SEH-LELHA training for high blood pressure and cardiovascular risk. The use of the Framingham, SCORE (Systematic Coronary Risk Evaluation) and Regicor (Registre Gironí del Cor) tables are also recommended to calculate cardiovascular risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sociedad Española de Farmacia Familiar y Comunitaria (SEFAC). Comisión de Servicios Profesionales Farmacéuticos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En abril de 2013, la Sociedad Española de Farmacia Familiar y Comunitaria (SEFAC) presentó su propuesta sobre servicios profesionales farmacéuticos (SPF), cuyo fin es cubrir las necesidades relacionadas tanto con la atención de los pacientes que utilizan medicamentos como con la salud pública. Esta propuesta ofrece un planteamiento sobre la implantación y desarrollo de los SPF con el objetivo de impulsar su prestación por las farmacias comunitarias en los próximos años. De acuerdo con dicha propuesta, todos los SPF que constituyen el catálogo de servicios contarán con un documento de especificaciones. El objeto de este documento de especificaciones es definir y caracterizar el servicio de prevención y control del riesgo vascular con un doble objeto: &#149; Apoyar al farmacéutico comunitario y a sus colaboradores en el ofrecimiento, prestación, difusión, financiación y concertación de este servicio. &#149; Servir de guía a los farmacéuticos comunitarios que desean implantar este servicio en la farmacia o elaborar un procedimiento normalizado de trabajo para su realización. Este documento se complementa con la Guía de actuación para el farmacéutico comunitario en pacientes con hipertensión arterial (HTA) y riesgo cardiovascular (RCV). Documento de consenso GIAF-UGR, SEFAC y SEH-LELHA y con el programa impacHta: formación SEFAC y SEH-LELHA en hipertensión y riesgo vascular. Se recomienda también el uso de las tablas para el cálculo del riesgo vascular Framingham, SCORE (Systematic Coronary Risk Evaluation) y Regicor (Registre Gironí del Cor) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);8(3): 18-22, sept. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Especificaciones del servicio de medición y control del riesgo vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
