<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82856</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Driving patterns in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of the study was to describe driving patterns and traffic injuries in the elderly. To describe self-reported reasons for stopping driving and its impact in quality of life. Material and methods. Cross-sectional study in a primary health care centre. An age stratified random sample was taken of 216 males (drivers/ex-drivers) aged 65 years and older. The main measurements were obtained by clinical record audit and personal interviews, collecting medical and sociodemographic data, driving patterns, traffic injuries history, reasons for stopping driving, and psychological impact. Results. Mean age 75 (95%CI:74&#150;75.9) years. Overall, 64.8% (140) used to drive: 29.2% (41) drove daily, 70% (98) avoided night driving, and 58.6% (82) crowded roads; 97.1% (136) suffered from a chronic disease and 78.5% (110) had taken drugs that might interfere with driving abilities. Mean age for giving up driving was 73 (95%CI:71.2&#150;74.5), 34.2% (26) for medical reasons. Overall, 36.6% (79) reported a traffic accident during the previous five years and 10.1% (8) with injured persons in the last one. Of those suffering a traffic accident, 10 gave up driving definitively. Furthermore, 19.7% (15) of those giving up driving reported a decrease in quality of life and 25% (19) had a negative psychological emotional status. Conclusions. Elderly drivers suffer chronic diseases and take prescriptions that modify ability to drive safety, but they adopt driving behaviours to compensate for their deficiencies. The number of traffic accidents is also high, but without serious injuries. Giving up driving had a negative emotional impact in a sizeable number of elderly persons (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler Carrera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomàs Bertran, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centelles Mañosa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Jovani, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Busquets Poblet, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del presente estudio es describir los patrones de conducción en varones ancianos, accidentalidad vial y factores que pueden influir en la misma. En exconductores, motivos del abandono de la conducción y repercusiones en su vida. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal, en un centro de salud urbano. Muestra aleatoria, estratificada por grupos de edad, de 216 varones conductores/exconductores mayores de 64 años. Mediante revisión de historias clínicas y entrevista clínica, se recogieron variables médicas, sociodemográficas, características de conducción, accidentalidad, razones del cese de conducir y repercusión emocional. Resultados. Edad media 75 (IC95%:74&#150;75,9) años. Un 65% (140) eran conductores: el 96% (136) padecía alguna enfermedad crónica y el 78,5% (110) consumía fármacos que podían alterar la capacidad de conducción, el 29,2% (41) conducía diariamente, el 70% (98) evitaba circular de noche y el 58,6% (82) situaciones de tráfico denso. La media de edad en abandonar la conducción era de 73 (IC95%:71,2&#150;74,5) años, por razones médicas un 34,2% (26). El 36,6% (79) había sufrido algún accidente durante los 5 años previos y en el último hubieron lesionados en un 10,1% (8); un accidente influyó en dejar de conducir en 10 casos. Un 19,7% (15) de exconductores consideraba que había empeorado su calidad de vida por este hecho y un 25% (19) refería efectos negativos en su estado anímico. Conclusiones. Los conductores mayores padecen enfermedades crónicas y consumen fármacos que pueden alterar los reflejos pero modifican su patrón de conducción para compensar sus déficits. La accidentalidad es considerable, aunque de consecuencias poco graves. Renunciar a conducir genera emociones negativas en un número respetable de ancianos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(10): 566-572, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducción en la tercera edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32679^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32679^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1339^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
