<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139598</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary thromboembolism in occupational medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Occupational physicians should be familiar with the risk factors and clinical presentation of pulmonary thromboembolism (PTE). PTE belongs to the group ofis a cardiovascular diseases, which are the main cause (40%) of death in Spanish workplaces; at present, they may be considered a work-related injury because of the doctrinal evolution in the legal interpretation of the presumption of iuris tantum. We present the case of a hypertensive and obese adult male who suffered a PTE at his workplace. The availability of a portable pulse oximeter (room air SpO2, 92%) was critical in guiding the decision to refer him urgently to the hospital, where the diagnosis was confirmed. We can conclude that, independently of whether this event is later deemed to be work-related (in this case it was not), occupational physicians must know how to correctly manage and refer affected workers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Fernández, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Paredes, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado-Benedí, María-José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Garrido, Ramó</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reinoso-Barbero, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capapé-Aguilar, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El médico del trabajo debe conocer los factores de riesgo y sospechar la presencia de un tromboembolismo pulmonar (TEP) ante un cuadro clínico compatible. El TEP pertenece a las enfermedades cardiovasculares que son la primera causa (40%) de mortalidad en el lugar de trabajo en España, y actualmente pueden considerarse accidente de trabajo por la evolución doctrinal en la interpretación jurisprudencial de la presunción iuris tantum. Presentamos un varón hipertenso y obeso que tras un periodo de reposo relativo, por un esguince de tobillo, presentó un TEP en su puesto de trabajo. La información que nos facilitó un pulsioxímetro portátil (92% SpO2) nos fue de gran ayuda para derivarlo urgentemente al medio hospitalario donde se confirmó el diagnóstico de presunción. Ya sea considerado posteriormente accidente de trabajo o no (en este caso no lo fue), el médico del trabajo está obligado a atender y derivar adecuadamente al trabajador afectado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);18(3): 143-145, jul.-sept. 2015. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139598</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tromboembolismo pulmonar en Medicina del Trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
