<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117125</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the effectiveness of MTA as a barrier for bleaching of endodontically treated teeth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the sealing ability of cervical barriers used in whitening teeth treated endodonically, using materials previously studied and the MTA peroxide and sodium perborate associated with a tracer agent (methylene blue). After perfoming the cervical buffer with different materials (zinc phosphate, glass ionomer, gutta-percha associated with cement and MTA) the bleaching agent was used. Next the teeth were sectioned longitudinally to assess the infiltration linear and measure with a pachymetry. Visual inspection was performed by three previously calibrated examiners. Results. The MTA had less infiltration than other materials used as a buffer, without obtaining statistically significant difference (P=0.154). Conclusions. The MTA showed less infiltration of dye than other materials. Therefore in the marker analysis, the result was not statistically significant, and in the evaluation, which was measure by linear infiltration of the dye, we obtained a significant result of the MTA group over the control group, which was gutta- percha associated with a cement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgos Ponceiv, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aurelio Dib Marinhoii, Marco Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kenji Nishiyami, Celso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kraus Filhoii, Gilberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Fue evaluar la capacidad selladora en la infiltración de colorante en barreras cervicales, utilizadas en el blanqueamiento de dientes tratados endodónticamente, utilizando materiales anteriormente estudiados y el MTA. Material y método. Fueron utilizados 40 dientes extraídos, divididos en 4 grupos, fue realizada la técnica de walking bleach, utilizando como agente blanqueador peróxido de digrogeno asociado al perborato de sodio y un agente trazador (azul de metileno). Después de realizar el tapón cervical con los diferentes materiales manipulados (fosfato de zinc, ionómero de vidrio y la gutapercha asociada al cemento obturador y un paquímetro e inspección visual por 3 examinadores previamente calibrados. Resultados. El MTA presentó menos infiltración que el resto de los materiales utilizados como tapón sin obtener diferencia estadísticamente significante (P=0,154). Conclusiones. El MTA demostró menor infiltración del colorante sobre los demás materiales. Por lo tanto en el análisis de marcadores, el resultado estadístico no fue significante; y en la evaluación, donde fue medida la infiltración lineal de colorante, se obtuvo un resultado significativo del grupo del MTA sobre el grupo control, que fue el de gutapercha asociado al cemento obturador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);30(3): 111-116, jul.-sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la efectividad del MTA como tapón cervical en el blaqueamiento de dientes tratados endodónticamente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32944</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14464^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6322^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6039^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
