<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94072</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to effectively use methotrexate in rheumatoid arthritis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Methotrexate (MTX) is the first choice disease modifying anti-rheumatic drugs for rheumatoid arthritis. In spite of its generalized use by rheumatologists worldwide, there is a general lack of agreement regarding the route of administration, the start-up dose and the way to increase the same. In this article we propose a simplified outline for the use of the drug that should be individualized, based on it's pharmacological aspects, guidelines and recommendations published in high impact factor journals during the past few years. Adverse reactions and side effects, as well as their follow up are also reviewed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernandez-Baldizon, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El metotrexato (MTX) es el fármaco modificador de la enfermedad de primera elección en artritis reumatoide. A pesar del uso casi generalizado por reumatólogos en todo el mundo, hay mucha discordancia entre la forma de iniciar la dosis, la vía de administración y la forma de realizar el incremento de dosis. En este artículo se planteamos un esquema simplificado del uso de este fármaco a individualizar en cada caso, basado en los aspectos farmacológicos, guías y protocolos de manejo publicados en revistas de impacto de nuestra especialidad en los últimos años. Se revisa además las reacciones adversas y efectos secundarios y cómo realizar el seguimiento de éstos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);8(1): 42-45, ene.-feb.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo hacer buen uso del metotrexato en artritis reumatoide?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51811^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51811^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51811^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
