<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056071</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patterns of drug treatment for manic episode in the clinical practice. Outcomes of the Spanish sample in the EMBLEM Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Although treatment for mania has been        studied extensively in randomized clinical trials, there        are few data that address how these patients are truly        managed in clinical, functional, and economic terms in        the psychiatric practice in Spain.        Objective. To determine prescribing patterns in        Spain on the basis of the Spanish sample of bipolar patients        in manic or mixed phase included as part of the        pan-European EMBLEM Study.        Method. The EMBLEM Study recruited 3,681 patients,        312 of whom (8.47%) were included in Spain. Patients        had to be adults with a diagnosis of bipolar disorder        who were initiating treatment for a manic phase.        They underwent evaluation using the Spanish versions of        scales that measure severity of mania (the Young Mania        Rating Scale, CGI-BP and the Hamilton Scale) and functional        level (LCM, SLICE of LIFE). Information was collected        regarding drug and treatment adherence variables.        Results. Prior to being admitted into the study, 42%        of the patients were receiving polytherapy, 35% were on        monotherapy, and 23% were not taking any medication whatsoever. Forty percent of the patients presented partial        or total non-compliance with the treatment prescribed.        During the first stage of the study, in the case of        single-drug treatment, acute management for mania        consisted of mean daily doses of 25 mg of olanzapine,        6.6 mg of risperidone, 9.5 mg of haloperidol, 165 mg of        lamotrigine, 938.5 mg of valproate, and 909 mg of lithium,        whereas when combined therapy was used, the        following doses were used: olanzapine, 22.1 mg; risperidone,        7.3 mg; haloperidol, 12.3 mg; lamotrigine, 175.1 mg;        valproate, 1,038.4 mg, and lithium, 1012.6 mg. Of those        patients who were on monotherapy at the beginning of        the study 51% were treated with a single drug, whereas        48 % were receiving polytherapy. Among the participants        who were receiving combined treatment when        they began the study, almost all of them, 94 %, were        prescribed combined treatment. In the case of the hospitalized        patients who made up 88% of the sample, the        vast majority, 92%, had improved by the time the study        was completed. Mean time to release from hospital was        24 days.        Discussion. In Spain, treatment for mania is essentially        based on combined treatments, hospitalization,        and anti-mania drugs that are prescribed at somewhat        higher doses than those recommended in the corresponding        prescribing information documents, which indicates        that the clinical reality of this entity is far more complex        than clinical trials conducted in experimental conditions        suggest</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Haro, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilaberte, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tohen, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Sánchez-Toledo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pinto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Aunque el tratamiento de la manía ha sido        estudiado profusamente en ensayos clínicos aleatorizados,        existen pocos datos respecto al manejo real de estos        pacientes en términos clínicos, funcionales y económicos en        la práctica psiquiátrica en España.        Objetivo. Determinar, a través de la muestra española de        pacientes bipolares en fase maníaca o mixta del estudio paneuropeo        EMBLEM, los patrones de prescripción en España.        Método. El estudio EMBLEM reclutó a 3.681 pacientes,        312 de los cuales (8.47 %) fueron incluidos en España. Los        pacientes tenían que ser adultos con diagnóstico de trastorno        bipolar que iniciaran tratamiento para una fase maníaca.        Se les evaluó con las versiones españolas de escalas para la        gravedad (Escala de Young, CGI-BP, Escala de Hamilton) y        para la funcionalidad (LCM, SLICE of LIFE). Se recogió información        sobre variables farmacológicas y de adherencia al        tratamiento.        Resultados. Antes de entrar en el estudio el 42% de los        pacientes recibía politerapia, el 35% estaba en monoterapia        y el 23% no tomaba ninguna medicación. Un 40% de los        pacientes incumplía total o parcialmente el tratamiento        prescrito. Durante la fase inicial del estudio el manejo agudo        de la manía fue a expensas, como monoterapia, de dosis        medias diarias de: olanzapina, 25 mg; risperidona, 6,6 mg;        haloperidol, 9,5 mg; lamotrigina, 165 mg; valproato, 938,5 mg,        y litio, 909 mg, mientras que cuando fueron empleados en        combinación las dosis fueron: olanzapina, 22,1 mg; risperidona,        7,3 mg; haloperidol, 12,3 mg; lamotrigina, 175,1 mg;        valproato, 1.038,4 mg, y litio, 1.012,6 mg. De los pacientes que        al inicio del estudio estaban en monoterapia, el 51% fueron        tratados con un solo fármaco y un 48% recibió tratamiento        combinado. De entre los pacientes que iniciaron el estudio        recibiendo tratamiento combinado, el 94 % continuo recibiendo        tratamiento combinado. La gran mayoría de los pacientes        (92%) mejoraron al término del estudio. En el caso de los pacientes hospitalizados, los cuales conformaron el        88% de la muestra, el tiempo medio hasta el alta del hospital        fue de 24 días.        Conclusiones. El tratamiento de la manía en España se        sustenta fundamentalmente en tratamientos combinados,        hospitalización y dosis de fármacos antimaníacos generalmente        algo superiores a las recomendadas en las fichas técnicas,        indicando que la realidad clínica es más compleja de        lo que indican los ensayos clínicos realizados en condiciones experimentales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(5): 315-322, sept.-oct. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056071</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones de tratamiento farmacológico para el episodio maníaco en la práctica clínica. Resultados de la muestra española en el estudio EMBLEM</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32356^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
