<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72249</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7961</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmaco-Nutrients interactions in neurological pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An in-depth study is performed on the interactions between anticonvulsant drug (ACD) highlighting those ACD leading to folic acid depletion and its clinical repercussions on the different systems such as the cardiovascular system. The influence of the antioxidant components of the diet (vitaminC, vitamin E, polyphenols, flavonoids, and carotenoids) on the pathogenesis of the main neurodegenerative diseases (Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD), Parkinson &#145;s disease (PD) andamyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS)) is studied. The interactions between dietary proteins and the therapy of Parkinson&#146;s disease are discussed aiming at improving its symptoms. We incorporate an update of the recommendations of administration the most frequently prescribed medications for neurological pathologies in order to avoid possible interactions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Corrales, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realiza un estudio profundo de las interacciones delos fármacos antiepilépticos (FAE), destacando aquellosFAE que originan depleción de ácido fólico y sus repercusiones clínicas sobre diferentes sistemas, como es el caso del sistema cardiovascular. Se estudia la influencia de los componentes antioxidantes de la dieta (vitamina C, VitaminaE, polifenoles, flavonoides y carotenoides) en la patogénesis de las principales enfermedades neurodegenerativas, Enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA), Enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) y Esclerosis Lateral Amiotrófica (ELA). Se discuten las interacciones entre las proteínas de la dieta y tratamiento de la enfermedad de Parkinson con el objetivo de mejorar su sintomatología. Se incorpora una actualización de las recomendaciones de la administración de los medicamentos más utilizados en patologías neurológicas para evitar posibles interacciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;2(supl.2): 89-105, mayo 2009. graf, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones fármaco-nutrientes en patología neurológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
