<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67047</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Dependency, i.e. the need to depend on another person to perform activities of daily living, is the main concern and cause of suffering and poor quality of life in the elderly. The prevalence of dependency increases with age and is related to the presence of prior disease and fragility. Dependency is associated with increased morbidity, mortality and institutionalization, as well as with greater health and social resource utilization, all of which increases health costs. Objective. To create a consensus document on the main health recommendations for the prevention of dependency in the elderly, based on the scientific evidence available to date, with the collaboration of scientific societies and public health administrations (the Spanish Ministry of Health, Autonomous Communities and Cities). Methods. a) a preliminary consensus document was drafted by an expert group composed of representatives of various scientific societies and health administrations. This document was based on a review of the recommendations and guidelines published by the main organizations involved in health promotion and the prevention of disease, functional deterioration and dependency in the elderly; b) the consensus document was reviewed by the remaining experts assigned by the scientific societies and central and autonomous administrations; c) the final document was approved after a session in which the text was discussed and reviewed by all the experts participating in the working group (including the academic committee); d) the document was presented and discussed in the First National Conference on Prevention and Health Promotion in Clinical Practice in Spain. All participating experts signed a conflicts of interest statement. Results. The document provides recommendations, with their grades of evidence, grouped in the following three categories: a) health promotion and disease prevention, with specific preventive activities for the elderly, including prevention of geriatric syndromes; b) prevention of functional deterioration, with clinical recommendations that can be applied in primary and specialized care; c) prevention of iatrogeny (drug prescription, inappropriate use of diagnostic and therapeutic modalities and healthcare). These recommendations were tailored to the characteristics of the older person (OP), categorized in five groups: healthy OP, OP with chronic disease, fragile or at risk OP, dependent OP, and OP at the end of life. Conclusion. These recommendations should be implemented by public health administrations to improve strategies for the prevention of dependency in the elderly in the XXI century (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupos de trabajo de expertos de las sociedades científicas.</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Administraciones sanitarias</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La dependencia, depender de otra persona para realizar las actividades de la vida diaria, es la principal preocupación, causa de sufrimiento y de baja calidad de vida en las personas mayores. Su prevalencia aumenta con la edad y se relaciona con la presencia de enfermedad previa y estado de fragilidad del individuo. Se correlaciona con un aumento de morbilidad, mortalidad e institucionalización así como del consumo de recursos tanto sanitarios como sociales, todo lo cual conlleva un aumento del coste sanitario. Objetivo. Consensuar en un documento desde las sociedades científicas y las administraciones públicas sanitarias (Ministerio de Sanidad, Comunidades y Ciudades Autónomas), y basándose en la evidencia científica disponible hasta el momento, las principales recomendaciones sanitarias para prevenir la dependencia en las personas mayores. Métodos. a) elaboración de un documento preliminar consensuado por un grupo impulsor de expertos constituido por representantes de las diferentes sociedades científicas y la administración. Este documento se basó en la revisión de las recomendaciones y directrices publicadas por las principales organizaciones involucradas en la promoción de la salud y prevención de la enfermedad y del deterioro funcional y dependencia en las personas mayores; b) someter dicho documento de consenso a la revisión del resto de expertos designados por sociedades científicas y administración central y autonómica; c) determinación del documento final tras una jornada de trabajo conjunta dirigida a la discusión y revisión del texto por todos los expertos participantes en el grupo de trabajo (incluido grupo impulsor); d) presentación del documento y discusión englobado en la I Conferencia Nacional de Prevención y Promoción de la Salud en la Práctica Clínica en España. Todos los expertos han firmado una declaración de conflicto de intereses para su participación. Resultado. En el documento se especifican las recomendaciones etiquetadas con su grado de evidencia y agrupadas en 3 categorías: a) promoción de la salud y prevención de la enfermedad, con actividades preventivas específicas para personas mayores, incluida la prevención de síndromes geriátricos; b) prevención del deterioro funcional, con recomendaciones asistenciales aplicables en atención primaria y especializada; c) prevención de la iatrogenia (prescripción farmacológica, utilización inadecuada de medios diagnósticos y terapéuticos, y asistencia sanitaria). Estas recomendaciones fueron individualizadas en función de las características de la persona mayor (PM), que se categorizó en 5 grupos: PM sana; PM con enfermedad crónica; PM frágil o de riesgo; PM dependiente, y PM al final de la vida. Conclusiones. Se recomienda a las administraciones públicas sanitarias poner en marcha estas recomendaciones con el objetivo de mejorar en la estrategia de prevención de la dependencia de las personas mayores en el siglo XXI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;208(7): 361-362, jul. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67047</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
