<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054326</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-811X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meningoencefhalocele etmoidal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A case of meningoencefhalocele etmoidal is presented and the bibliography of this unusual case is checked. The incidence of oncefhaloceles is 05/10.000 (born alive), being the 80% of the occipitals and the 20% remaining are divided into frontal and parietal encefhalocele. The encefhalocele represents approximately the 10 and 15% of the neural tube's defects. This is still not clear because there are many interpretations since 1938. The treatment depends in the malformations, size, site, defect contains and the surgery correction facility. The 4D scan allows consolidating the diagnostic of fetal malformations that 2D scan describe. The 4D scan (real time) has allowed the evaluation in detail of the following pathology, aimed at the diagnostic of meningocele etmoidal. The technique provides images in deferent's rotation plans, axis and video sequences. The possibility for the parents seeing in detail the pathology of his son in the real time 4D, gave us the possibility to make a better doctor-patient relationship acceptance of the palotology and a better monitoring of the case</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canetti, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de meningoencefalocele etmoidal y se revisa la bibliografía de esta rara entidad. La incidencia de los encefaloceles es de 0,5/10.000 nacidos vivos, siendo el 80% de los mismos occipitales y el 20% restante divididos entre cefaloceles frontal y parietal. El encefalocele representa aproximadamente el 10 a 15% de los defectos del tubo neural. La patogénesis aún es poco clara, existiendo distintas interpretaciones desde 1938. El pronóstico y el tratamiento para los encefaloceles depende de las malformaciones asociadas, del tamaño, del sitio, del contenido del defecto y de la facilidad de la corrección quirúrgica. La ecografía 4D ha permitido en los últimos tiempos consolidar el diagnóstico de malformaciones fetales ya descritas en ecografía 2D. La ecografía 4D (tiempo real) nos permitió evaluar con detalle la patología descrita orientándonos al diagnóstico de meningocele etmoidal. La técnica facilita la adquisición de imágenes en distintos planos de rotación, distintos ejes y secuencias de cine. La posibilidad que los padres vean con el detalle 4D tiempo real la patología de su hijo nos dio la posibilidad de entablar una mejor relación médico-paciente, una aceptación por parte de los mismos de la patología y un seguimiento detallado del caso comunicado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. diagn. trat. prenat. (Ed. impr.);18(4): 159-162, oct.-dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningoencefalocele etmoidal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
