<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69114</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infections of the catheter wound in peritoneal dialysis are the most frequent cause of morbility in patients who undergo this technique. There are a number of procedures for the care of the wound and it is not easy to define a single method that will guarantee good condition of the wound. In order to evaluate the behaviour of the wound related to the procedure used in their care, we studied 306 patients over 24 months, compiling socio-demographic and clinical variables. We found a high incidence of infections caused by gram-positive skin and mucous germs, with a strong correlation with the fact that the patient/family carer is a nasal carer of staphylococcus aureus and that they appear more frequently in patients who do not remove the wound dressing in the shower. We also detected an increase in pseudomonas infections when the patient does not dry the wound with a hair-dryer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo Andaluz de Diálisis Peritoneal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones del orificio de salida en diálisis peritoneal son la causa de morbilidad más frecuente en los pacientes sometidos a esta técnica. Existen numerosos procedimientos para los cuidados del orificio y no resulta fácil definir un único método que garantice el buen estado del orificio. Con el fin de valorar el comportamiento del orificio relacionado con el procedimiento utilizado en sus cuidados estudiamos a 306 pacientes durante 24 meses, recogiendo variables sociodemográficas y clínicas. Hemos encontrado una alta incidencia de infecciones del orificio producidas por gérmenes gram positivos de piel y mucosas, con una correlación fuerte con el hecho de que el paciente/familiar cuidador sea portador nasal de estafilococo áureo y que aparecen con mayor frecuencia en los pacientes que no retiran el apósito para la ducha. Así mismo hemos detectado un aumento en infecciones por pseudomona cuando el paciente no procede al secado del orificio con secador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;10(4): 263-269, oct.-dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69114</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
