<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135552</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of teriparatide on quality of life in osteoporotic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Lost bone in osteoporotic patients increases the risk of fractures and back pain, and decreases quality of life. The aim of this study was to analyse the effect of teriparatide (TPTD) in osteoporotic patients with vertebral pain. Methods: A prospective observational study between April 2006 and February 2014 was done with 77 patients treated with teriparatide in the Pain Unit of Hospital Obispo Polanco of Teruel (Spain). Treatment duration was 18 or 24 months. Pain was assessed by the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). Health-related quality of life was measured using the European Quality of Life Questionnaire (EuroQol-5D) in order to obtain the social tariff (ST). Pre and post- treatment values were collected respectively. A descriptive and regression analysis was done. Results: Improvement in pain was observed (80%) and in health-related quality of life (65%). The mean VAS improved (from 5.42 to 3.47 points) and the mean health status value too (from 0.36 to 0.58 points). The regression indicated an improvement of VAS in 0.441 for each initial VAS point, and of ST in 0.0528 points for each 0.1 initial ST point. The probability of VAS reduction in 3 points (OR=2.021) was greater than in 2 points (OR=1.695). Conclusions: TPTD reduces pain and improves quality of life of osteoporotic patients. The worse the baseline situation, the more patients&#146; health improved, so it could be used as criteria for therapeutic decisions and health management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escartín Martínez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guadalajara Olmeda, Natividad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osca Guadalajara, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La pérdida ósea en pacientes osteoporóticos, conlleva riesgo de fracturas, dolor óseo vertebral y disminución de la calidad de vida. El objetivo de este trabajo fue analizar el efecto de la teriparatida (TPTD) en pacientes osteoporóticos y con dolor vertebral. Métodos: Estudio observacional longitudinal prospectivo, entre abril de 2006 y febrero de 2014, en los 77 pacientes tratados con TPTD en la Unidad del Dolor del Hospital de Teruel. La duración del tratamiento fue de 18 o 24 meses. Se utilizó la Escala Visual Analógica (EVA) para la medición del dolor y el cuestionario europeo de calidad de vida (EuroQol-5D) para obtener la tarifa social (TS), antes y después el tratamiento. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo, de regresión lineal y logística. Resultados: Se observó una mejoría del dolor (80%) y de la calidad de vida (65 %). Se mejoró la EVA media (5,42 a 3,47 puntos) y el EuroQol-5D (0,36 a 0,58 puntos). La regresión indicó una mejora de la EVA en 0,441 puntos por cada punto de EVA inicial, y de la TS en 0,0528 puntos por cada 0,1 puntos de TS inicial. La probabilidad de mejorar la EVA en 3 puntos (OR=2,021), fue mayor que de mejorar 2 puntos (OR=1,695). Conclusiones: La TPTD en pacientes osteoporóticos reduce el dolor óseo y mejora la calidad de vida. Su efecto es mayor en pacientes con peor estado de salud inicial, pudiendo ser utilizado como criterio para las decisiones terapéuticas y de gestión clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(2): 217-227, mar.-abr. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135552</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del tratamiento con teriparatida en la calidad de vida de las personas con osteoporosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33002^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55462</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
