<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055519</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of urethral stenosis: update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To compile the main methodsof surgical treatment of penile and bulbar urethral stenosis.METHODS: We review the most updated bibliography, focusing on authors with large experience in the treatmentof urethral stenosis, and we use our own experienceto contrast or reaffirm some of the techniques.RESULTS/CONCLUSIONS: The base of the treatment of urethral stenosis remains in the stenosis itself (localization,etiology and length) and also in patient&#146;s characteristics(age, past medical history). Among the techniques of urethroplasty we have techniques in one step, as the technique of excision and anastomosis, and the use of free grafts or vascularized flaps. The techniques in two steps like Johannson`s or perineostomy are very useful in certain cases of complex stenosis. We should keep an eye on the development of new techniques and the use of new materials that will help, once consolidated, to improve results</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pertusa Peña, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Ortega, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Llevar a cabo una recopilación de los principales métodos de tratamiento quirúrgico de la estenosis de uretra peneana y bulbar.MÉTODOS: Revisamos la bibliografía más actualizada,centrándonos en autores con gran experiencia en el tratamiento de la estenosis uretral, y utilizamos nuestra experiencia para contrastar o reafirmar alguna de las técnicas.RESULTADOS/CONCLUSIONES: La base del tratamientode la estenosis uretral radica en la propia estenosis,es decir, localización, etiología y longitud, así como en las características del paciente (edad, historia clínica). Entre las uretroplastias disponemos de técnicas en un tiempo, como la excisión y anastomosis, y el uso de injertos libres o colgajos pediculados. Las técnicas en dos tiempos como la de Johanson o la perineostomía son de gran utilidad en determinados casos de estenosiscomplejas. Debemos permanecer atentos al desarrollode nuevas técnicas y al empleo de nuevos materiales que ayudaran, una vez consolidados a obtener mejores resultados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(6): 633-637, jul.-ago. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía de la estenosis de uretra. Actualización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
