<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046286</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hybrid techniques in thoracic aorta pathologies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The endovascular treatment of thoracic aorta pathologies is essentially aimed at reducing therates of morbidity and mortality compared to those observed with the use of open procedures. Development. Thecomplications related to stents in the thoracic aorta are fundamentally due to the proximal or distal placement of theaorta in unsuitable regions or with very acute angles. The most frequent causes of complications were the use ofoverestimated diameters of the aorta and the fracture or emigration of the stent. These should be prevented by placementin straight, healthy areas of the thoracic aorta (proximal and distal) and by using diameters that are not above 20%.Conclusions. Hybrid techniques allow flow to be maintained in the supra-aortic trunks through supraclavicularpathways with a low morbidity rate and with techniques usually employed in endovascular surgery. Fenestrated graftsin the thoracic aorta are being designed; in the aortic arch they are capable of embolising and to date they have beendeveloped experimentally in very few centres. Both techniques pursue the same aim, that is, an adequate attachment ofthe stent and perfusion of the supra-aortic trunks</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Doblas-Domínguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orgaz Pérez-Grueso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Herrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontcuberta-García, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del tratamiento endovascular de la patología de la aorta torácica consiste en disminuirla morbilidad y la mortalidad con relación a los procedimientos abiertos. Desarrollo. Las complicaciones de lasendoprótesis en la aorta torácica se deben básicamente a la fijación proximal o distal de la aorta en zonas inadecuadaso con ángulos muy agudos. La utilización de diámetros sobreestimados de la aorta y la fractura o emigración de endoprótesishan sido las causas más frecuentes de las complicaciones. Se deben prevenir con la fijación en zonas sanas y rectasde la aorta torácica (proximal y distal) y la utilización de diámetros que no tengan un tamaño mayor al 20%. Conclusiones.Las técnicas híbridas permiten mantener el flujo en los troncos supraaórticos por vías supraclaviculares con bajamorbilidad y con técnicas habituales en cirugía vascular. Las prótesis fenestradas en la aorta torácica están en procesode diseño, en el arco aórtico tienen capacidad de embolizar y actualmente se han desarrollado de forma experimental enmuy pocos centros. Ambas técnicas tienen el mismo objetivo: el anclaje de las endoprótesis de forma adecuada y la perfusiónde los troncos supraaórticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(supl.1): S159-S164, 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnicas híbridas en aorta torácica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13736^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13736^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13736^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
