<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118843</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trans fatty acids in bakery products and snacks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bakery products and snacks have been traditionally elaborated with partially hydrogenated oils, leading to high fat content and high trans fat (TFA) content in these products. In this paper we analyzed the fat content, TFA and saturated fatty acids (SFA) of commercial products (bakery 8, and snacks 4), purchased during the last two years. The amount of fat in these products was high (20-32%). However, mean values for TFA were always lower than 0.2g/100g product. The amount of SFA was 4-18g/100g product. It can be concluded that, although the total fat and SFA remained still high in these types of products, TFA content was low, and it can not be used as a reason for not recommending their intake (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ansorena, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echarte, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astiasarán, Iciar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ollé, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los productos de bollería y los snacks han sido elaborados tradicionalmente con grasas parcialmente hidrogenadas, implicando altos porcentajes de grasa en dichos alimentos y una alta presencia de ácidos grasos trans (AGT). En este trabajo se analizó el contenido en grasa, AGT y ácidos grasos saturados (AGS) de productos comerciales correspondientes a bollería (8) y snacks (4), adquiridos en los dos últimos años. La cantidad de grasa en estos productos fue alta (20-32%). Sin embargo, la cantidad de AGT no superó la media de 0,2 g/100 g producto. La cantidad de AGS fue de 4-18 g/100 g producto. Se puede concluir que, si bien la cantidad total de grasa y de AGS sigue siendo elevada en este tipo de productos, su contenido en AGT no lo es, y por tanto, no debería emplearse la cantidad de AGT como argumento para su no recomendación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;79(4): 646-657, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presencia de ácidos grasos trans en productos de bollería y de aperitivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38235^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
