<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125950</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An evaluation of the presence and need for sanitary control of the coccidia Aggregata octopiana in the common octopus in aquaculture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coccidial infection of the intestinal tract by Aggregata octopiana is very frequent in the common octopus (Octopus vulgaris), a marine species with great potential in aquaculture. Altered host-parasite relationship under intensive rearing conditions has been described resulting in hiperinfections that compromise the health and viability of the animal and may lead to condemnation for human consumption, according to present regulations. The present study is the first to evaluate the degree of coccidial infection in octopus raised in tanks and open sea cages in southeast Spain. Results showed 100% prevalence of infection among the 49 animals analysed. However, none of the animals had coccidial nodules in muscle indicating their suitability for human consumption. Although infections by A. octopiana are not considered zoonotic, the present study indicates that health authorities should be aware that the parasite can be highly prevalent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerezo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalver, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María Dolores, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viuda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección del tracto digestivo por el coccidio Aggregata octopiana es muy frecuente en el pulpo común (Octopus vulgaris), especie que presenta una gran potencialidad en acuicultura. En condiciones de cultivo intensivo se han descrito alteraciones del equilibrio hospedador parásito, produciendo hiperinfecciones que comprometen la salud y la viabilidad del animal pudiendo conllevar que no sea apto para consumo humano en aplicación de la normativa vigente. En el presente trabajo se hace la primera valoración del grado de infección en pulpos cultivados tanto en tanques como en jaulas en mar abierto en el sureste de España, obteniéndose una prevalencia del 100% de los 49 ejemplares examinados, si bien en ningún caso se observó desarrollo de nódulos parasitarios en el tejido muscular, siendo en todos los casos aptos para su consumo. Aunque no presenta carácter de zoonosis, es importante que las autoridades sanitarias encargadas de la inspección de los productos de la pesca conozcan la existencia y prevalencia de A. octopiana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;24: 57-62, ene.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración sobre la presencia y el control sanitario del coccidio aggregata octopiana en pulpo común procedente de acuicultura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31643</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5531^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9983^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3073^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24447^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
