<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130926</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemodynamic and autonomic differences to sympathetic stimulation between power and endurance professional soccer players: A cross sectional study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Although it is recognized that there are structural and functional cardiac adaptations in power athletes and endurance athletes, it is unknown if there are cardiovascular differences among the soccer players according to their metabolic characteristics. Objective: To compare the hemodynamic and autonomic responses to sympathetic stimulation between a group of «power» professional soccer players and a group of «endurance» ones. Materials and methods: Using field tests and latent class analysis, players were classified as «power» or «endurance» players. Then, hemodynamic and autonomic responses were measured simultaneously (Task Force® Monitor, CNSystems, Austria) during supine position, 70º tilting, and sympathetic stimulation with a cold-water pressor test. Results: A total of 22 professional soccer players were included, 9 of whom were classified as «power» and the rest as «endurance» ones. In the 70º tilting test, «endurance» players showed a lower heart rate than «power» ones (68.3 vs 76.3 beats/min; difference -8.0; 95% CI, -14.5 to -1.5; P&lt; .05), diastolic blood pressure (84.9 vs 91.0 mmHg; difference -6.5; 95% CI, -12.4 to -1.5; P&lt; .05). In addition, «endurance» players showed higher stroke index (41.1 vs 34.5 mL·m2; difference 6.6; 95% CI, 2.0 to 11.2; P&lt; .05), contractility index (47.5 vs 36.8 [1000/sec]; difference 10.7; 95% CI, 2.7 to 18.7; P &lt; .05), and end-diastole volume index (73.4 vs 62.2 mL·m 2 ; difference 11.1; 95% CI, 2.4 to 19.8; P &lt; .05). Similar outcomes were found with the cold-water pressor test. Conclusions: «Endurance» professional football players have a more effective left ventricular function (systolic and diastolic) and better autonomic modulation in response to sympathetic stimulation than do «power» ones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Acevedo-Acevedo, Daniel Camilo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ospina Uribe, Carlos Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balparda Arias, Jon Kepa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aristizabal Ocampo, José Dagnovar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallo Villegas, Jaime Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Aunque se conocen las adaptaciones funcionales y estructurales cardíacas en los deportistas de potencia y resistencia aeróbica, se desconoce si existen diferencias cardiovasculares entre los futbolistas según sus características metabólicas. Objetivo Comparar la respuesta hemodinámica y autonómica a la estimulación simpática entre jugadores profesionales de fútbol «potentes» y «resistentes». Materiales y métodos Usando pruebas de campo, los jugadores fueron clasificados como «potentes» o «resistentes» mediante el análisis de clases latentes. Posteriormente, sus variables hemodinámicas y de respuesta del sistema nervioso autónomo fueron medidas simultáneamente (Task Force® Monitor, CNSystems, Austria) en un protocolo en posición decúbito, inclinación a 70º y con prueba presora de frío. Resultados Se incluyeron 22 individuos: 9 clasificados como «potentes» y los demás como «resistentes». A 70º de inclinación, los jugadores «resistentes» mostraron una menor frecuencia cardíaca (68,3 vs 76,3 latidos/min; diferencia -8,0; IC 95%, -14,5 a -1,5; p &lt; 0,05), menor presión arterial diastólica (84,9 vs 91,0 mmHg; diferencia -6,5; IC 95%, -12,4 a -1,5; p &lt; 0,05), además de un mayor índice de eyección (41,1 vs 34,5 ml·m2; diferencia 6,6; IC 95%, 2,0 a 11,2; p &lt; 0,05), un mayor índice de contractilidad (47,5 vs 36,8 [1.000/s]; diferencia 10,7; IC 95%, 2,7 a 18,7; p &lt; 0,05) y un mayor índice de volumen de final de diástole (73,4 vs 62,2 ml·m2; diferencia 11,1; IC 95%, 2,4 a 19,8; p &lt; 0,05). En la prueba presora de frío se obtuvieron resultados similares. Conclusiones Los jugadores de fútbol profesional «resistentes» tienen una función ventricular izquierda más efectiva (sistólica y diastólica) y mejor modulación autonómica que los «potentes» durante una estimulación simpática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);49(184): 113-122, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130926</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en la respuesta hemodinámica y autonómica al estrés simpático entre futbolistas profesionales potentes y resistentes: un estudio transversal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13944^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2351^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
