<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037065</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional consequences of providing care to amyotrophic lateral sclerosis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims. This study describes the emotional and personal consequences of providing care to amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) patients. Subjects and methods. Six caregivers aged from 23 to 67 years old (mean age: 38.2 ± 15.6), weight interviewed. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HAS) and the OARS Activities of Daily Living Questionnaire were applied. The subjects were interviewed with semi-structured questions about medical information, caregiver burden, coping, social support, impact on his/her health, stressor and religious resources. In order to be included in the research, the subject had to be an ALS patient caregiver. Every interview was audio recorded and transcribed, and a content analysis was realized.     Results. They show emotions caused by unfavorable life conditions and were classified into seven main categories: 1) defenselessness, 2) negative affection, 3) hope, 4) sadness, 5) depression, 6) isolation and 7) loneliness.    Conclusion. This study shows that providing care to ALS patient affects the familiar, social and emotional caregiver&#146;s system</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llanos-Del Pilar, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz-Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade-Palos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Este trabajo estudia las consecuencias que tiene el cuidado de un enfermo con esclerosis lateral amiotrófica (ELA) en la vida emocional y personal del cuidador.     Sujetos y métodos. Se entrevistó a seis cuidadores con edades entre 23 y 67 años (x = 38,2 ± 15,6), se les aplicó la escala de ansiedad y depresión hospitalaria (HAS), la escala sobre actividades de la vida diaria (OARS) y una serie de preguntas semiestructuradas sobre información médica, carga del cuidador, afrontamiento, apoyo social, impacto en la salud, agentes estresantes y recursos religiosos. Para ser incluido en la investigación, el participante debía ser el cuidador del paciente con ELA. Todas las entrevistas fueron grabadas y transcritas, y se llevó a cabo un análisis de su contenido.     Resultados. El estudio muestra la existencia de emociones provocadas por condiciones de vida desfavorable, que se han agrupado en siete categorías principales: 1) indefensión; 2) afecto negativo; 3) esperanza; 4) tristeza; 5) depresión; 6) aislamiento; y 7) soledad.     Conclusión. Se pone de manifiesto que el brindar cuidado a un enfermo con ELA afecta al sistema familiar, social y emocional del cuidador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(8): 459-464, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037065</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consecuencias emocionales del cuidado del paciente con esclerosis lateral amiotrófica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30381^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
