<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161727</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary habits of secondary school students in Andalusia during school time in relation to food stores in the environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The analysis of the environmental context is indispensable to study the eating habits in adolescents. Feeding practices during the school day the students user surrounding grocery stores of secondary schools in Andalusia and their characteristics are described. Methods: Descriptive cross-sectional study of 8068 students and 95 secondary schools. Multistage cluster sampling: Stratified random sampling by province and population size and systematic for classrooms. The analysis of the type of store, food supply, distance and visualization from the school and students´ demands was conducted by direct observation and interviews. The socio-demographic characteristics and feeding practices were got through questionnaire. Results: The schools are surrounded by shops in which the food supply is aimed at students (72, 63 %). Pubs and cafeterias (55), grocery stores and tuck shops predominate. The presence of sweets, processed baked goods and sandwiches is confirmed in all the stores. 25.73% of students buy their school meals in these shops. There are statistically significant relationships between the consumption of sweets and fried packaged packages and to go out the high school during the playground. Conclusions: The number and characteristics of the stores surrounding the schools require studying its influence over students eating habits in order to establish public health measures to control the detected unhealthy supply (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Melo Salor, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos-Cerezuela, Ildefonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liébana Fernández, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Padilla, Francisca María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, Angustias</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El análisis del contexto ambiental es imprescindible para estudiar las prácticas alimentarias en adolescentes. Se describen las prácticas alimentarias durante la jornada escolar del alumnado usuario de los comercios de alimentos circundantes a los centros de educación secundaria en Andalucía y las características de los mismos. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal, sobre una muestra de 8068 estudiantes y 95 centros de secundaria. Muestreo aleatorio polietápico por conglomerado: estratificado por provincia y tamaño de hábitat y sistemático por aulas. El tipo de establecimiento, oferta alimentaria, distancia y visualización desde el centro y demanda del alumnado se realizó mediante observación directa y entrevistas, y las características socio-demográficas y las prácticas alimentarias a través de cuestionario. Resultados: Los centros tienen establecimientos cercanos con oferta alimentaria dirigida al alumnado (72,63%). Predominan bares y cafeterías (55), tiendas de comestibles (54) y quioscos de chucherías (23). La oferta de chucherías, bollería y bocadillos se constata en todos los establecimientos. El 25,73% del alumnado compra su merienda escolar en estos comercios, encontrando relaciones significativas en el consumo de golosinas y paquetes de fritos envasados frente al alumnado que no sale del instituto durante la hora del recreo. Conclusiones: El número y las características de la oferta de los establecimientos circundantes a los centros educativos obligan a profundizar en la influencia sobre las prácticas alimentarias del alumnado para establecer medidas de salud pública que controlen la oferta insalubre detectada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(46): 94-106, abr. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas alimentarias del alumnado de secundaria durante la jornada escolar en Andalucía asociadas a la oferta del entorno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
