<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155438</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish cultural adaptation and psychometric validation of the Summary of Diabetes Self-Care Activities measure (SDSCA) among persons with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To undertake the cultural adaptation and the psychometric assessment of the Summary of Diabetes Self-Care Activities measure (SDSCA) in Spanish population with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Design: Clinimetric validation study. Setting: Primary health care centers of District Malaga and Valle del Guadalhorce. Participants: Three hundred thirty-one persons with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Main measurements: The SDSCA validated in mexican population was subjected to semantic and content equivalence using a Delphi method, its legibility was determined by INFLESZ scale. Subsequently psychometric validation was conducted through exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis (herein after EFA and CFA), internal consistency, test-retest reliability and discriminant validity. Results: Two rounds were needed to achieve the consensus in between the panel members. Then, the index provided a good readability. The EFA suggested a model with 3 factors (diet, exercise and self-analysis) with 7 items which explained 79.16% variance. The results of CFA showed a good fit of SDSCA-Sp. The Internal consistency was moderate to low (&amp;#945;-Cronbach =0.62) and test-retest reliability was evaluated in 198 patients (t=0.462-0.796, p&lt;0.001) with a total correlation of 0.764 (p&lt; 0.0001). Conclusions: The SDSCA-Sp is used, in a valid way to assess self-care in type 2 DM version in clinical practice and research with similar clinimetric properties to previous studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Fernández-Gallego, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lupiáñez Pérez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Estrada, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morilla Herrera, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro Bautista, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Asencio, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Llevar a cabo la adaptación cultural y la validación psicométrica del Summary of Diabetes Self-Care measure (SDSCA) en población española con diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Diseño: Estudio de validación clinimétrica. Emplazamiento: Centros de atención primaria del Distrito Sanitario Málaga-Valle del Guadalhorce. Participantes: 331 personas con diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Mediciones principales: La versión validada en población mexicana del SDSCA fue sometida a equivalencia semántica y de contenido mediante un Delphi de expertos, su legibilidad fue determinada mediante la escala INFLESZ. Posteriormente se llevó a cabo la validación psicométrica, evaluándose validez de constructo mediante análisis factorial exploratorio y confirmatorio (en adelante AFE y AFC), consistencia interna, fiabilidad test-retest y validez discriminante. Resultados: Dos rondas fueron necesarias para alcanzar consenso entre los miembros del panel, posteriormente INFLESZ aportó una buena legibilidad. El modelo trifactorial (dieta, ejercicio físico y autoanálisis) con 7 ítems explicaba un 79,16% de la varianza. El análisis confirmatorio mostró un buen ajuste del modelo del SDSCA-Sp. La consistencia interna fue moderada-baja (&amp;#945;-Cronbach=0,62) y la fiabilidad test-retest fue evaluada en 198 pacientes (t=0,462-0,796, p&lt;0,001) con una correlación global de 0,764 (p&lt;0,0001). Conclusiones: El SDSCA-Sp en una versión válida en la práctica clínica y en investigación para evaluar autocuidados en diabetes mellitus tipo 2 con propiedades clinimétricas similares a las obtenidas en estudios previos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(7): 458-467, ago.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación cultural al español y validación psicométrica delSummary of Diabetes Self-Care Activities measure (SDSCA) en personas con diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
