<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165628</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional experience in individual and cooperative traditional games. A gender perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study explored the effect of gender (GE) and group gender composition (GGEC) on men&#146;s and women&#146;s experiences of emotions when taking part in different games. To formulate our hypotheses we used a theoretical framework formed by the theories of Lazarus and Bisquerra on the construct of emotional competence and well-being and their relationship with gender stereotypes, Parlebas&#146;s motor action theory and previous results of empirical research related to games, emotions and gender relations. The participants (218 university students, Mage = 20.3, SD = 2.73) completed twelve sessions of individual games (IG) and cooperative games (CG). The results showed that GE and GGEC were predictors of the experience of positive emotions and that males were more likely to experience negative emotions in both games. The findings highlight gender differences and could help physical education teachers to avoid activities that reinforce the hierarchies and inequalities associated with gender and sex role stereotypes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saez de Ocáriz, Unai</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lagardera, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lavega, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio exploró el efecto del género (GE) y la composición del género del grupo (CGEC) en experiencias emocionales de hombres y mujeres cuando participaron en diferentes juegos. Para formular nuestra hipótesis se hizo uso del marco teórico elaborado a partir de las teorías de Lazarus y Bisquerra en relación al constructo de la competencia emocional y el bienestar y su relación con estereotipos de género, así como la teoría de acción motriz de Parlebas y resultados previos de la investigación empírica relativa a juegos, emociones y género. Los participantes (218 estudiantes universitarios, Medad = 20.3, DT = 2.73) realizaron doce sesiones de Juegos individuales (IG) y de Juegos cooperativos (CG). Los resultados mostraron que GE y GGEC fueron predictores de la experiencia de emociones positivas y que los hombres expresaron más emociones negativas en ambos juegos. Los hallazgos muestran diferencias de género y podrían ayudar a los profesores de educación física a evitar actividades que promuevan jerarquías y desigualdades asociadas al género y a los estereotipos de sexo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(3): 538-547, oct. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia emocional en juegos tradicionales individuales y cooperativos. Una perspectiva de género</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56170^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
