<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99530</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Solubility prediction of Allopurinol in solvent mixtures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prediction of solubility of the drugs in co-solvents systems is studied to optimize technological processes of preformulación and it is key in processes of development and research on rational pharmaceutical design of safe and effective medicines. In this work, some methods of estimation, developed in recent years, have been tested with allopurinol. Allopurinol is a drug used primarily to treat hyperuricemia and its complications, including chronic gout. We have obtained excellent correlations between the calculated and experimental solubility at 25 ºC. The results show the usefulness of these models in preformulación from medicines to reduce the number of experiments, which often consume time and resources(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escalera, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustamante, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La predicción de solubilidad de los principios activos en sistemas codisolventes se estudia para optimizar los procesos tecnológicos de preformulación y resulta clave en procesos de desarrollo e investigación en el diseño farmacéutico racional de medicamentos seguros y eficaces. En este trabajo, algunos métodos de estimación, desarrollados en los últimos años, se han probado con el alopurinol. El alopurinol es un compuesto químico empleado como medicamento frente a la hiperuricemia y sus complicaciones, como la gota. Se obtuvieron excelentes correlaciones entre las solubilidades experimentales y calculadas a 25ºC. Los resultados demuestran la utilidad de estos modelos en preformulación de medicamentos con el fin de reducir el número de experimentaciones, que a menudo consumen tiempo y recursos económicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 755-762, jul. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predicción de la solubilidad del Alopurinol en mezclas disolventes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51516</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27945^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27945^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27945^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27945^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
