<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126529</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coaching in nursing: Integrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to characterize the publications about coaching in nursing field and analyze how coaching is being used by nursing. It is an integrative literature review, qualitative and descriptive, realized in the data bases Banco de Dados de Enfermagem, Scientific Eletronic Library Online, Literatura Latino-Americana e do Caribe em Ciências da Saúde, National Library of Medicine and CUIDEN. Was used the content analysis to construct the categories: Coaching in Nursing Management, Coaching in Care and Health care Education for Pacients and Coaching in Development Staff Process. Was identify that coaching is used in nursing with international predominance, mostly in staff management, health care education and development of clinical practice. How ever is need to deepen studies about coaching in different settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soares de Lima, Suzinara Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Tonini, Tanise Finamor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nascimento Lampert, Ariele Do</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parnov Machado, Bruna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gama Paes, Lucilene</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio tuvo como objetivo caracterizar las publicaciones sobre el coaching en el ámbito de la Enfermería y analizar cómo está siendo utilizado en esta área. Se trata de una revisión integradora de literatura cualitativa y descriptiva, realizada en las bases: Banco de Datos de Enfermería, Scientific Eletronic Library Online, Literatura Latino-Americana e do Caribe em Ciências da Saúde, National Library of Medicine y CUIDEN. Fue utilizado el análisis de contenido para construir las categorías: Coaching en Gestión de Enfermería, Coaching en la atención y educación en salud para pacientes, y Coaching en el proceso de desarrollo de personas. Se identificó que el coaching es usado en la Enfermería con predominancia internacional, principalmente en la gestión de personas, educación en salud y desarrollo de la práctica clínica. Sin embargo, es necesario profundizar los estudios sobre el coaching en diferentes contextos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;23(1/2): 51-55, ene.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coaching en la enfermería. Revisión integradora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
