<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84738</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dyschromia as a cause of consultation; presentation of several case reports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pigmentation disorders are a frequent cause of consultation in primary care, especially in patients with pigmented skins. These patients have a greater predisposition to respond to the presence of dermatosis and to different injuries with alterations of the pigmentation, sometimes persistent. The case of an 18 months old boy, and a 14 years old girl with characteristic clinical findings and a 13 years old girl with acanthosis nigricans are presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agüero Orgaz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Gordo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero Sobrados, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos de pigmentación son una causa frecuente de consulta en Atención Primaria, especialmente en pacientes con pieles más pigmentadas. Estos pacientes tienen una mayor predisposición para responder a la presencia de dermatosis y frente a distintas lesiones con alteraciones de la pigmentación, en ocasiones persistentes. Se presentan los casos de un niño de 18 meses de edad y una mujer de 14 años que presentan los hallazgos clínicos característicos de una discromía postinflamatoria, y de una paciente de 13 años con acantosis nigricans (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;12(48): 639-643, oct.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discromías como motivo de consulta; presentación de varios casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30691^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11292^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30691^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11292^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
