<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59120</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The laryngeal tube</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The laryngeal tube (VBM Medizintechnic GmbH, Sulz,Germany) is a supraglottic device designed for airwaymanagement in spontaneous or positive-pressureventilation during anesthesia or in cardiopulmonaryresuscitation. Currently, the tube is available in 4versions: the standard laryngeal tube, the disposable tube(LT-D), the dual-lumen tube (with a tube for suction)(LTS II), and the disposable LTS (LTS-D). The design ofthe tube has been modified several times. It is easy toinsert and the airway seal is more effective than that ofthe laryngeal mask. The incidence of complications issimilar for both devices, though use of the laryngeal tuberequires more adjustments. The standard tube issomewhat less effective than the ProSeal laryngeal mask,though the new LTS II has been improved considerably.The laryngeal tube is effective as an aid to management ofthe difficult airway. We reviewed the literature indexed onMEDLINE through December 2006 using the searchterms laryngeal tube, anesthesia, equipment, and airway (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Madrid, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariño, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capdevila, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaitini, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tubo laríngeo (TL) (VBM Medizintechnik GMBH,Sulz, Alemania) es un dispositivo supraglótico diseñadopara el manejo de la vía aérea en ventilación espontáneao controlada durante la anestesia o en resucitación cardiopulmonar.En la actualidad existen cuatro variantesdel TL: el TL estándar, el TL de un solo uso (TL-D), eltubo laríngeo succión II (TLS II) y el TLS desechable(TLS-D). El diseño del TL ha sido revisado en diferentesocasiones. Su inserción se realiza con facilidad. El selladode la vía aérea con el TL es más eficaz que con lamascarilla laríngea (ML). La incidencia de complicacioneses similar en los dos dispositivos, aunque el TLrequiere de más reajustes para su utilización. El TLestándar es algo menos efectivo que la ML Proseal, aunqueel nuevo TLS II ha sido mejorado significativamente.Es un dispositivo eficaz como ayuda en la resolucióndel manejo de la vía aérea difícil. Hemos revisado la literaturamédica existente hasta diciembre 2006 mediantebúsqueda en MEDLINE, utilizando los términos &#147;laryngealtube&#148;, &#147;anaesthesia&#148;, &#147;equipment&#148; and &#147;airway&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;55(4): 232-241, abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59120</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El tubo laríngeo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
