<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118976</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunisation schedule of the Spanish Association of Paediatrics: 2014 recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Advisory Committee on Vaccines of the Spanish Association of Paediatrics (CAVAEP) updates the immunisation schedule every year, taking into account epidemiological data as well as evidence on safety, effectiveness and efficiency of vaccines. The present schedule includes levels of recommendation. We have graded, as routine vaccinations, those that the CAV-AEP consider all children should receive; as recommended those that fit the profile for universal childhood immunisation and would ideally be given to all children, but that can be prioritised according to the resources available for their public funding; and as risk group vaccinations those that specifically target individuals in special situations. Immunisation schedules tend to be dynamic and adaptable to ongoing epidemiological changes. Based on the latest epidemiological trends, CAV-AEP recommends the administration of the first dose of MMR and varicella vaccines at age 12 months, with the second dose at age 2-3years; the administration of DTaP or Tdap vaccine at age 4-6 years, always followed by another Tdap dose at 11-12 years; and the three meningococcal C scheme at 2 months, 12 months and 12 years of age. It reasserts its recommendation to include vaccination against pneumococcal disease in the routine immunisation schedule. The CAV-AEP believes that the coverage of vaccination against human papilloma virus in girls aged 11-12 years must be increased. Universal vaccination against varicella in the second year of life is an effective strategy, and the immediate public availability of the vaccine is requested in order to guarantee the right of healthy children to be vaccinated. Vaccination against rotavirus is recommended in all infants due to the morbidity and elevated healthcare burden of the virus. The Committee stresses the need to vaccinate population groups considered at risk against influenza and hepatitis A. The recently authorised meningococcal B vaccine has opened a chapter of hope in the prevention of this disease. In anticipation of upcoming national and international studies, the Committee recommends the vaccine for the control of disease outbreaks, and insists on the need to be available in pharmacies. Finally, it emphasises the need to bring incomplete vaccinations up to date following the catch-up immunisation schedule (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Merino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Contreras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa del Castillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arístegui Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo Ortega, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corretger Rauet, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Moína, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Sampelayo Matos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Comité Asesor de Vacunas de la Asociación Española de Pediatría (CAV-AEP) actualiza anualmente el calendario de vacunaciones teniendo en cuenta tanto aspectos epidemiológicos como de seguridad, efectividad y eficiencia de las vacunas. El presente calendario incluye grados de recomendación. Se consideran vacunas sistemáticas aquellas que el CAV-AEP estima que todos los niños deberían recibir; recomendadas, las que presentan un perfil de vacuna sistemática en la edad pediátrica y que es deseable que los niños reciban, pero que pueden ser priorizadas en función de los recursos para su financiación pública; y dirigidas a grupos de riesgo, aquellas con indicación preferente para personas en ciertas situaciones especiales. Los calendarios de vacunaciones tienen que ser dinámicos y adaptarse a los cambios epidemiológicos que vayan surgiendo. Teniendo en cuenta los últimos cambios en la epidemiología de las enfermedades, el CAV-AEP recomienda la administración de la 1.a dosis de las vacunas triple vírica y varicela a los 12 meses y la 2.a dosis a los 2-3 años; la administración de la vacuna DTPa o Tdpa a los 4-6 años, siempre acompañada de otra dosis de Tdpa a los 11-12 años; y el paso a un esquema 2 meses, 12 meses y 12 años de la vacunación frente al meningococo C. Se reafirma en la recomendación de incluir la vacunación frente al neumococo en el calendario de vacunación sistemático. El CAV-AEP estima que deben incrementarse las coberturas de vacunación frente al papiloma virus humano en las niñas a los 11-12 años. La vacunación universal frente a la varicela iniciada en el segundo año de vida es una estrategia efectiva, y se solicita la inmediata disponibilidad pública de la vacuna, reclamando el derecho a la prescripción y el derecho de los niños sanos a poder ser vacunados. La vacunación frente al rotavirus, dadas la morbilidad y la elevada carga sanitaria, es recomendable en todos los lactantes. Se insiste en la necesidad de vacunar frente a la gripe y a la hepatitis A a todos los que presenten factores de riesgo para dichas enfermedades. La vacuna frente al meningococo B, recientemente autorizada, abre un capítulo de esperanza en la prevención de esta enfermedad. En espera de próximos estudios nacionales e internacionales se recomienda, por el momento, para el control de brotes epidémicos y se insiste en el deseo de que sea comercializada libremente en las oficinas de farmacia. Por último, se insiste en la necesidad de actualizar las vacunaciones incompletas con las pautas de vacunación acelerada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);80(1): 55-55[e1-e37], ene. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calendario de vacunaciones de la Asociación Española de Pediatría: recomendaciones 2014</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29429</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23146</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8759^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35368</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
