<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69757</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Autoimmune pancreatitis is an entity that has recently been included in the differential diagnosis of chronic pancreatitis-pancreatic mass. The presence of diffuse, irregular Wirsung&#146;s duct stenosis, together with high levels of IgG4, the existence of certain autoantibodies and lymphoplasmacytic infiltration of the pancreas are key factors in the diagnosis. An early diagnostic suspicion and multidisciplinary collaboration are vital in these cases to avoid unnecessary surgery as the differential diagnosis is established with such entities as pancreas cancer, chronic pancreatitis, primary biliary cirrhosis or primary sclerosing cholangitis. Autoimmune pancreatitis has an excellent response to steroid therapy, with complete resolution of clinical, analytical and radiological parameters, as occurred in our patient. The very few cases reported sofar suggest the need for the elaboration of long-term follow-up studies to determine the prognosis and frequency of its association with other diseases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Pedro, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Morente, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Piñero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reguera Iglesias, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Huelgas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La pancreatitis autoinmune es una reciente entidad a tener en cuenta en el diagnóstico diferencial de pancreatits crónica-masa pancreática. La presencia de estenosis difusa e irregular del Wirsung, junto con niveles elevados de IgG4, presencia de determinados autoanticuerpos e infiltración linfoplasmocitaria de páncreas son la clave del diagnóstico. La sospecha diagnóstica precoz y la colaboración multidisciplinar es vital en estos casos, ya que puede evitar cirugía innecesaria, puesto que el diagnóstico diferencial se establece con entidades entre las que se encuentra cáncer de páncreas, pancreatitis crónica, cirrosis biliar primaria o colangitis esclerosante primaria. Además, la pancreatitis autoinmune tiene excelente respuesta a tratamiento esteroideo, con resolución completa de parámetros clínicos, analíticos y radiológicos, como ocurría en nuestro paciente. Debido al escaso número de casos descritos en la Literatura, sería necesario la elaboración de estudios con seguimiento largo plazo para conocer pronóstico y frecuencia de asociación a otras patologías</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(7): 359-361, jul. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69757</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23030^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8278^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8278^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23585^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23585^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10371^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
