<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054474</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurological illness in the process of canonising Saint Dominic de Gúzman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Dominic de Guzmán, the founder of the Order of Preachers (or Dominicans), was one of the most influential    and outstanding figures in medieval Hispania. His canonisation process was endorsed by a good number of miraculous    healings that took place thanks to his intervention. The descriptions of the people he cured contain several clinical pictures that    are compatible with neurological diseases. Development. We review the records of the canonisation process that have survived    in various biographies of the saint written in the Middle Ages. We also study other descriptions of pathologies that appear in the    hagiographical texts by the first Dominican monks. Six of the miracles included in the records of the canonisation process    describe clinical signs and symptoms that can be interpreted as being of a neurological nature. The most striking are those    concerning a young male with acute lumbar-radicular pain with motor involvement, a female with a clinical picture compatible    with a cervical central cord disorder and another young male probably suffering from acute myositis. The biographies of the    first preacher monks describe deficiency symptoms in the dominant hemisphere and a case of Parkinson&#146;s syndrome, among    others. Conclusions. Medieval literature, in the early hagiography of the Dominican order, provides us with exquisite, interesting    descriptions of neurological clinical cases which are outlined in this paper</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero-Peral, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Domingo de Guzmán, fundador de la Orden de Predicadores o de los dominicos, fue una de las figuras    más influyentes y destacadas de la Hispania medieval. Su proceso de canonización fue avalado por un buen número de    curaciones milagrosas llevadas a cabo gracias a su intercesión. En la descripción de los sanados se encuentran cuadros compatibles    con enfermedades neurológicas. Desarrollo. Se revisan las actas del proceso de canonización que nos han llegado a    través de varias biografías del santo escritas en época medieval. También se estudian otras descripciones patológicas que    figuran en los textos hagiográficos de los primeros frailes dominicos. En seis de los milagros recogidos en las actas del proceso    de canonización se describen cuadros clínicos que pueden interpretarse como neurológicos. Destacan los correspondientes    a un varón joven con una lumbociatalgia aguda con afectación motora, una mujer con un cuadro compatible con una    afectación centromedular cervical y otro joven con una probable miositis aguda. Las biografías de los primeros frailes predicadores    aportan, entre otros, un cuadro deficitario del hemisferio dominante, así como un síndrome parkinsoniano. Conclusión.    La literatura medieval, en la primitiva hagiografía de la orden de los dominicos, nos ofrece hermosas e interesantes descripciones    de casos clínicos neurológicos que me permito presentar en este trabajo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(3): 181-183, feb. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología neurológica en el proceso de canonización de santo Domingo de Guzmán</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8265</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
