<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143516</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary sclerosing lipogranuloma of the scrotum resembling a testicular tumour. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sclerosing lipogranuloma (SLG) of the male external genitalia is a rare benign condition which presents as subcutaneous masses. The underlying pathological process is a granulomatous reaction of fatty tissue. The cause of this disease is unclear but in many cases lipid degeneration secondary to injection of foreign bodies (secondary SLG) has been proposed. However, endogenous lipid degeneration from other causes such as infection, trauma, and allergic mechanisms has also been reported as primary SLG. Here we present a case of a 23-year-old man with apparent primary SLG of the external genitalia (scrotum). The pathological features and clinical management are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez López, Albadio Samir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Soto, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martínez, Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado, Isidro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medell Gago, Mariana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El lipogranuloma esclerosante (LGE) de los genitales externos masculinos es una enfermedad rara y benigna que se presenta habitualmente como masas subcutáneas. El proceso patológico subyacente es una reacción granulomatosa en el tejido graso. Las causas de esta enfermedad no están del todo definidas, pero en muchos casos se ha propuesto la ocurrencia de una degeneración de los lípidos como consecuencia de la inyección de cuerpos extraños (LGE secundario). Sin embargo, también se ha reportado la aparición de degeneración de lípidos endógena asociada a infecciones, trauma o alergias (LGE primario). Presentamos un caso de LGE aparentemente primario de localización escrotal en un paciente de 23 años de edad. Se realiza una revisión de los hallazgos patológicos y el manejo clínico de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;48(4): 240-244, oct.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lipogranuloma esclerosante escrotal primario simulando un tumor testicular. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53092^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6803^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
