<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85115</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peri-Operative Atelectasis and Alveolar Recruitment Manoeuvres</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Respiratory complications are a significant cause of post-operative morbidity and mortality. Peri-operative atelectasis, in particular, affects 90% of surgical patients and its effects can be prolonged, due to changes in respiratory mechanics, pulmonary circulation and hypoxaemia. Alveolar collapse is caused by certain predisposing factors, mainly by compression and absorption mechanisms. To prevent or treat these atelectasis several therapeutic strategies have been proposed, such as alveolar recruitment manoeuvres, which has become popular in the last few years. Its application in patients with alveolar collapse, but without a previous significant acute lung lesion, has some special features, therefore its use is not free of uncertainties and complications. This review describes the frequency, pathophysiology, importance and treatment of peri-operative atelectasis. Special attention is paid to treatment with recruitment manoeuvres, with the purpose of providing a basis for the their rational and appropriate use(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rama-Maceiras, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las complicaciones respiratorias postoperatorias constituyen una causa importante de morbimortalidad. Las atelectasias perioperatorias, en concreto, afectan hasta al 90% de los pacientes quirúrgicos y su repercusión puede prolongarse en el tiempo en forma de alteraciones de la mecánica respiratoria, de la circulación pulmonar y de hipoxemia. El colapso alveolar se produce en presencia de ciertos factores predisponentes, fundamentalmente por mecanismos de compresión y absorción. Para prevenir o tratar estas atelectasias, se han propuesto diversas estrategias terapéuticas, como las maniobras de reclutamiento alveolar, cuyo uso se ha popularizado en los últimos años. Su aplicación en pacientes con colapso alveolar, pero sin lesión pulmonar aguda previa relevante, presenta ciertas particularidades, por lo que su empleo no está exento de incertidumbres y complicaciones. Esta revisión describe la frecuencia, la fisiopatología, la relevancia y el tratamiento de las atelectasias perioperatorias, y hace especial incidencia en el tratamiento con maniobras de reclutamiento con el objetivo de proporcionar las bases para un empleo racional y adecuado de éstas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(6): 317-324, jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atelectasias perioperatorias y maniobras de reclutamiento alveolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
