<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136413</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Envy, soul woodworm: A psycho-literary foreshortening</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From Aristotle to Castilla del Pino, from Covarrubias to María Zambrano, from Greco-Latin classicism to modern psychology and psychoanalysis symposia, envy issues have been subject to analysis. Such subtle nuances come both from philosophy and psychology, from literature and clinical practice. Envy is kindly gazed at according to its position as universal human emotion derived from alterity, comparison and negative self-appreciation along with a defective narcissistic settlement and the craving for replacing the idealized other. Envy is the anteroom both of hatred and a parade of assorted and sibylline interpersonal and social expressions. Envy remains, even after the civilization clash that is causing the most atrocious and destructive actions committed by terrorist fanaticism hitting our world nowadays (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde Aristóteles hasta Castilla del Pino, desde Covarrubias hasta María Zambrano, desde el clasicismo grecolatino a la modernidad de los Simposiums de Psicología y Psicoanálisis, el tema de la envidia ha sido objeto de análisis. Tan sutiles matices provienen de la filosofía como de la psicología, de la literatura como de la clínica. La envidia es sometida a la mirada benevolente que exige su rango de emoción universal humana, derivada de la alteridad, la comparación y la autovaloración negativa, así como de la deficiente instalación narcisística y el anhelo de suplantación del otro idealizado. La envidia es antesala del odio y de un cortejo de expresiones interpersonales y sociales muy variadas y sibilinas. Anida, incluso, tras el choque de civilizaciones generador de los más atroces y destructivos episodios de fanatismo terrorista recientemente padecidos en nuestro mundo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;15(1): 75-95, ene.-abr. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Envidia, carcoma del alma: escorzo psico-literario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
