<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110171</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Insufficient intake of vitamin D in Spanish schoolchildren; determinants of the problem and basis for its improvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Different studies have observed deficiencies in vitamin D in a high percentage of schoolchildren, highlighting the importance of this problem in sunny populations, such as Spain, where this situation is frequently underestimated. Aim: To assess the adequacy of vitamin D intake and to find out the food sources of the vitamin in a representative sample of Spanish schoolchildren. Methods: A sample of 903 children (7 to 11 years) was studied. Ten Spanish cities were selected to be a representative sample of the Spanish schoolchildren population. Dietetic study was carried out using a three-day food record, including a Sunday. Vitamin D was compared to that recommended (RI) and energy intake was compared with energy expenditure estimated by measuring physical activity level. Weight and height were recorded and body mass index (BMI) was calculated. Results and discussion: Vitamin D intake (2.49±0.64 [ig/day) allowed cover only 49.7% of the RI of the children. It was below of 100% of RI in 99.9% of the children, and in 78.7% it was below of 67% of RI. The vitamin intake was lower in girls, those younger than 7 years and in children with obesity than in boys, those older than 7 years and in children with normal weight. The main sources of the vitamin were eggs (28.12%), cereals (24.23%), fish (20.06%) and milk (14.42%). Conclusion: Vitamin D intake is inadequate in Spanish schoolchildren between 7 and 11 years. Taking into account that the consumption of foods which are the main source of vitamin D (fish, eggs, cereals, dairy products) is often lower than the recommended, approximating the diet to the theoretical ideal could help to improve the contribution of the vitamin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Anta, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, LG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ortega, AI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estaire Gómez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Vizuete, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Sánchez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rodríguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Pese a su importancia nutricional y sanitaria, diversos estudios han señalado la existencia de deficiencias en vitamina D en un elevado porcentaje de niños y han alertado sobre una problemática que había sido olvidada en poblaciones soleadas, como España. Objetivos: Valorar la adecuación de la ingesta de vitamina D y conocer las fuentes alimentarias de la vitamina en una muestra representativa de niños españoles. Métodos: Se ha estudiado un colectivo de 903 niños de 7 a 11 años, de diez provincias españolas, seleccionados para ser una muestra representativa de la población española de dicha edad. El estudio dietético se realizó utilizando un registro del consumo de alimentos durante 3 días, incluyendo un domingo, posteriormente la ingesta de vitamina D se comparó con las Ingestas Recomendadas (IR) y la ingesta energética con el gasto estimado. Los datos antropométricos registrados fueron peso, talla, e índice de masa corporal (IMC). Resultados y discusión: La ingesta de vitamina D en los niños estudiados (2,49 ± 0,64 ug/día) supuso un 49,7% de las IR, observándose la existencia de un 99,9% de niños con ingestas menores de las recomendadas y un 78,7 con ingestas &lt; 67% de las IR. La ingesta es más baja en población femenina, niños de menor edad y en los que presentan obesidad. Al analizar la procedencia alimentaria de la vitamina D ingerida, se constata que la mayor parte procede de huevos (28,12%), cereales (24,23%), pescados (20,06%) y lácteos (14,42%). Conclusión: La ingesta de vitamina D es insuficiente en población infantil española de 7 a 11 años, teniendo en cuenta que el consumo de los alimentos, que son la principal fuente de la vitamina (pescado, huevo, cereales, lácteos) es, en muchos casos, menor del aconsejado, aproximar la alimentación al ideal teórico puede ayudar a conseguir aportes más adecuados de la vitamina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(5): 1437-1443, sept.-oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta insuficiente de vitamina D en población infantil española; condicionantes del problema y bases para su mejora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
