<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053262</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electroconvulsive therapy in the treatment of bipolar depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since its introduction, electroconvulsive therapy is a treatment used in mood disorders, especially in the depressive phases of bipolar disorder. The advance of this technique has made it a useful and current option both in the treatment of acute phases as in the prevention of recurrences. The objective of this revision is to collect available data about the use of electroconvulsive therapy in bipolar depression. Its indications, effectiveness, prediction and patterns of response are included in this work, together with its complications, adverse events and drug interactions. Differences in response between bipolar and unipolar depression are also discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vieta, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amann, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valentí, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Amador, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benabarre, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde su introducción la terapia electroconvulsiva es un tratamiento usado en los trastornos afectivos, especialmente en las fases depresivas del trastorno bipolar. El avance en su técnica lo ha convertido en una opción útil y actual tanto en el tratamiento de las fases agudas como en la prevención de las recurrencias. El objetivo de esta revisión es recoger la información disponible hasta la actualidad acerca del uso de la terapia electroconvulsiva en la depresión bipolar. Sus indicaciones, su eficacia, su predicción y su patrón de respuesta se incluyen en este trabajo, así como sus complicaciones, sus efectos adversos y sus interacciones farmacológicas. Asimismo también se recopilan las diferencias de respuesta entre la depresión bipolar y la unipolar</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(3): 199-207, mayo-jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La terapia electroconsultiva en el tratamiento de la depresión bipolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
