<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72645</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">End-stage heart disease in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This document was produced by the Spanish Society of Cardiology Section on Geriatric Cardiology &#147;Endstage heart disease in the elderly&#148; working group. Its aim was to provide an expert overview that would increase understanding of the last days of life of elderly patients with heart disease and improve treatment and clinical decision-making. As elderly heart disease patients form a heterogeneous group, thorough clinical evaluation is essential, in particular to identify factors that could influence prognosis (eg, heart disease, comorbid conditions, functional status, and frailty). The evaluation should be carried out before any clinical decisions are made, especially those that could restrict therapy, such as do-not-resuscitate orders or instructions to deactivate an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator. Elderly patients with terminal heart disease have the right to expect a certain level of care and consideration: they should not suffer unnecessarily, their freely expressed wishes should be respected, they should be fully informed about their medical condition, they should be able to express an opinion about possible interventions, and they should be entitled to receive psychospiritual care. After an incurable disease has been diagnosed, the aim of palliative care should be to control symptoms. It should not be used only when the patient is close to death. Although palliative care is relatively undeveloped in heart disease, its use must be borne in mind in elderly patients with advanced heart failure. The main aims are to make the patient as comfortable as possible in all senses and to optimize quality of life in the patient&#146;s final days, while avoiding the use of aggressive treatments that consume health-care resources without providing any benefits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidán, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rexach, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañuelos, Camino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Datino, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sellés, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Palop, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Castro, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cornide, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este documento del Grupo de Estudio «El anciano con cardiopatía terminal», de la Sección de Cardiología Geriátrica de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología, es aportar un punto de vista experto que permita un mejor conocimiento de la situación y una mejora en el manejo y la toma de decisiones en los últimos días de vida del paciente de edad avanzada que sufre una cardiopatía. Los cardiópatas ancianos constituyen un grupo heterogéneo y es necesaria una valoración exhaustiva, especialmente de los factores que condicionan el pronóstico (cardiopatía, comorbilidad, situación funcional y datos de fragilidad) antes de tomar decisiones, sobre todo aquellas que conlleven limitación del esfuerzo terapéutico como las órdenes de no reanimar o la desactivación de desfibriladores automáticos implantables. Los ancianos con cardiopatías terminales tienen derecho a disponer de una serie de cuidados y atenciones, entre ellos no sufrir inútilmente, respeto a su libertad de conciencia, conocer su situación, opinar sobre posibles intervenciones y recibir asistencia psicoespiritual. Los cuidados paliativos deben dirigirse al control de los síntomas tras el diagnóstico de la enfermedad incurable y no iniciarse únicamente en la fase de agonía. Estos cuidados están poco desarrollados en las cardiopatías y deben de tenerse presentes en los ancianos con insuficiencia cardiaca avanzada. Su objetivo es conseguir el máximo bienestar para el paciente desde un punto de vista integral, mejorar su calidad de vida antes del fallecimiento y evitar el empleo de tratamientos agresivos que consumen recursos sin resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(4): 409-421, abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72645</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El anciano con cardiopatía terminal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28615^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29108</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
