<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95638</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep disorders during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of sleep disorders during pregnancy.To identify in which moment of gestation they occur and the different factors related to their appearance. People and method: Transverse prospective observational study, performed in the Hospital Virgen de la Luz of Cuenca from December 2006 to May 2008. A specific questionnaire was designed for the data collection of the above study. All the full term expectant mothers who attended the fetal pathophysiology consultation of the hospital during the months of April to July 2007 were included. Results: A total of 290 pregnant mothers have been studied, an 86.6% of the surveyed women referred changes in their sleeping patterns since they were pregnant. The sleeping disorder that showed most prevalence was the insomnia symptomatology: sleep wakefulness, nocturnal awakening and non-refreshing sleep. The symptomatology of the restless legs syndrome was the second most frequent: affecting 67%,followed by snoring which affected 50.7%, excessive diurnal somnolence to the 39% and sleeping apnea to 5.9%. These disorders appeared throughout the whole gestation period, being the third quarter the one of most prevalence. Relation among several sleep disorders and non-modifiable variables such as age and multiparity was observed; and others modifiable like sedentary lifestyle and overweight, as well as other disorders and habits related to sleep.Conclusions: Sleep disorders are very common in mothers to be. However,either women or doctors who treat them do not consider them as actual health problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valero-Roncero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Márquez, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Aguilar, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Rodríguez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de los trastornos del sueño durante el embarazo. Identificar en qué momento de la gestación se producen,y los distintos factores relacionados con su aparición. Personas y método: Estudio observacional, transversal y prospectivo, realizado en el Hospital Virgen de la Luz de Cuenca, desde diciembre de 2006 hasta mayo de 2008. Se incluyeron todas las gestantes a término que acudieron a la consulta de fisiopatología fetal del hospital durante los meses de abril a julio de 2007. Para la recogida de datos se utilizó un cuestionario diseñado específicamente para dicho estudio. Resultados: Se ha estudiado a un total de 290 gestantes. El 86,6% de las encuestadas refirieron cambios en su patrón de sueño desde que estaban embarazadas. El trastorno del sueño que mostró una mayor prevalencia fue la sintomatología de insomnio: latencia de sueño, despertares nocturnos y sueño poco reparador. La sintomatología de síndrome de piernas inquietas fue la segunda en frecuencia, afectando al 67%, seguida del ronquido, que afectó al 50,7%, la excesiva somnolencia diurna (al 39%) y la apnea del sueño (al 5,9%). Estos trastornos aparecieron a lo largo de toda la gestación, siendo el tercer trimestre el de mayor prevalencia. Se observó una relación entre varios trastornos del sueño y variables no modificables, como la edad y la multiparidad, y con otras modificables, como el sedentarismo y el sobrepeso, así comocon otros trastornos y hábitos relacionados con el sueño.Conclusiones: Los trastornos del sueño son muy comunes en las embarazadas; a pesar de ello, no son tenidos en cuenta como verdaderos problemas de salud, ni por parte de las mujeres ni por los profesionales que las atienden (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;11(1): 11-17, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos del sueño durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13294^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
