<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74354</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-anatomical intestinal transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: intestinal transplantation is the only long-range treatment option for patients with intestinal failure. We report an exceptional case of isolated intestinal transplantation with the implant in a non-anatomical position. Clinical case: the patient was a thirty-eight-year-old man (60 kg weight, 180 cm height, 18.3 body mass index) with intestinal failure and home parenteral nutrition due to a short-bowel syndrome for which intestinal transplantation was indicated. The patient had a vascular malformation with the cava vein located left to the aorta, and the intestine was implanted with a 180º rotation around the mesenteric axis, so that the implant's superior mesenteric artery and vein matched the recipient's cava and aorta. Postoperative follow-up was excellent and the patient was discharged after six weeks with a 10-kg gain in body weight. Discussion: this non-anatomical intestinal implantation of the small bowel, previously unreported, offers technical advantages over other options. Adequate intestinal function represents a unique model to prove the viability of intestinal implants in a non-anatomical position(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Planas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Accarino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malagelada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caralt, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armengol-Miró, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Charco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilallonga, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavaldá, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dot, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azpiroz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abu-Suboh, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llopart, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el trasplante intestinal es el único tratamiento eficaz a largo plazo de los pacientes con fallo intestinal. Se presenta un caso clínico excepcional de trasplante intestinal aislado en posición no anatómica. Caso clínico: se trata de un varón de 38 años de edad con fallo intestinal y nutrición parenteral domiciliaria por un síndrome de intestino corto al que se le indicó un trasplante intestinal. Fue incluido en lista de espera con un peso de 60 kg, 180 cm de altura y 18,3 de índice de masa corporal. El receptor presentaba una trasposición de los grandes vasos con la vena cava situada a la izquierda de la arteria aorta por lo que el intestino se implantó con una rotación del injerto de 180º sobre su eje mesentérico, con el objetivo de que la vena y la arteria mesentérica superior del injerto coincidieran con la vena cava y la arteria aorta del receptor. El paciente presentó excelente postoperatorio y fue dado de alta a las 6 semanas con un aumento de peso de 10 kg. Discusión: esta implantación no anatómica del intestino, previamente no referida en la literatura, ofrece ventajas técnicas sobre otras alternativas. La adecuada función intestinal constituye un modelo único que prueba la viabilidad del intestino implantado en posición no anatómica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;101(2): 139-143, feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante intestinal en posición no anatómica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3113^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15086^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7584^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38048^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27743^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13158^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23254^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1016^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22926^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7584^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
