<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150203</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychophysiological symptoms predictive of stress in Mexican immigrants in Canada</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Emigration is a stress-related phenomenon that is manifested depending on the losses perceived when leaving one&#146;s own country of origin. This article reports the relationship between perceived stress and psychophysiological symptoms, age, gender and years of residence of Mexican immigrants living in Edmonton, Canada. Two hundred and thirty seven randomly selected immigrants were surveyed during the year 2013. A relationship was found between perceived stress and physical symptoms (cold hands and feet, neck and backaches, and fatigue), psychological symptoms (feeling depressed, anxiety and insomnia), and female gender. Assessing the symptomology of perceived stress in immigrants&#146; health, work, finance, family and social and environmental settings may offer an opportunity for efficient intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Plascencia-Campos, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Preciado-Serrano, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozos-Radillo, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La emigración es un fenómeno relacionado con el estrés, el cual se manifiesta por las pérdidas implícitas en la salida del país de origen. Este artículo reporta la relación del estrés percibido con síntomas psicofisiológicos, la edad, género y años de residencia de inmigrantes mexicanos que radican en Edmonton, Canadá. Se encuestó a 237 inmigrantes seleccionados aleatoriamente, durante el año 2013. Se utilizó el cuestionario Perfil de Estrés y el Inventario de Síntomas de Estrés. Se encontró relación entre el estrés percibido y síntomas físicos (e.g., manos o pies fríos, dolor de cuello o espalda y fatiga), síntomas psicológicos (sentirse deprimido, ansioso e insomnio), y género femenino. La identificación de la percepción de estresores de salud, trabajo, financieros, familia, entorno social y ambiental puede prevenir sintomatología psicofisiológica en inmigrantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;21(2/3): 143-156, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas psicofisiológicos predictores del estrés en inmigrantes mexicanos en Canadá</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52953</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d73</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2202^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
