<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112428</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mandalicos as a cross-cultural tool systems for organizing the international nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It starts from the assumption that the application mandalic model is a useful tool in the organization and delivery of a multicultural care nurses. Throughout history are many examples of mandalas, in psychology and anthropology have also been employed. The letter mandalic organizes cultural diversity from a circle divided into four interrelated subsystems, health is achieved by harmonizing the four subsystems. The circle is constructed from an analysis of the history of life from the expressions, values and needs of the patient /client, besides serving as an organizer of intercultural communication and cultural competence. His way of structuring the environment the person is related to the theory of complex thought of Edgar Morin, and contain many similarities and relationships with other nursing models and theories. It will be used as a tool for self-knowledge and self-transformation, seeking personal excellence, respect for ethnic and cultural variables, considering their individuality with a number of basic needs, spiritual and self-realization. It will serve as an example of creative cultural transformer provided with a value of modern civilization, with a hopeful mindset and transition to a world innovator (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salas Iglesias, Pedro Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;17(35): 115-123, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112428</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los sistemas mandálicos como herramienta intercultural para organizar la enfermería internacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
