<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72525</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Respiratory infections, Down's syndrome and congenital heart disease: The CIVIC 21 study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We compare hospitalisation rates for acute respiratory tract infection in children youngerth an 24 months with significant congenital heart disease without Down&#146;s syndrome with those with Down&#146;s syndrome with or without congenital heart disease. Material and methods: This was an epidemiological, multicentre (53 Spanish hospitals), observation al and prospective study, from October 2006 to April 2007. A total of 1085 patients were followed-up, of which 806 did not have Down&#146;s syndrome and 279 with Down&#146;s syndrome: 135 with significant, 38 with non significant and 105 without congenital heart disease. Results: A total of 147 patients (13.1%; 95% CI, 11.2&#150;15.2%) required hospitalisation due to respiratory infection. Rates in patients without and with Down&#146;s syndrome were 11% vs 19.1%. In the Down&#146;s group, 26.3%had no significant, a 23% had significant and 11.4% had no congenital heart disease. The main diagnosis was bronchiolitis (59.4%). An infectious agent was found in 36.2% cases. The specificad mission rate due to respiratory syncytial virus was 4.4%, with differences in children without vs with Down&#146;s syndrome (3.2% vs 7.8%). In the Down&#146;s patients we found rates of 15.8%, 9.3% and 3% in the non-significant, significant and no congenital heart disease. Immunoprophylaxis against respiratory syncytial virus rates were 83.4%vs 39.9%in no Down&#146;s versus Down&#146;s syndrome patients. No differences were found in hospital stay or the severity. Conclusions: Hospital admission rates due to respiratory infection, and specifically respiratory syncytial virus, were higher in the Down&#146;s patients, particularly in the group with no significant congenital heart disease and low immunoprophylaxis against respiratory syncytial virus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medrano López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lirio Casero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Guereta Silva, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se comparan las tasas de hospitalización por infección respiratoria aguda en niños con cardiopatías congénitas significativas sin síndrome de Down y en niños con síndrome de Down, con y sin cardiopatías, menores de 24 meses. Material y métodos: Estudio epidemiológico, multicéntrico (53 hospitales), observacional y prospectivo, de octubre de 2006 a abril de 2007. Se siguió a 1.085 pacientes; 806 sin síndrome de Down y con cardiopatía significativa y 279 con síndrome de Down: 135 con cardiopatía significativa, 38 con cardiopatías leves y 105 sin cardiopatía. Resultados: Ingresaron 147 (13,1%) pacientes (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 11,2 15,2%) por infecciones respiratorias. Las tasas en niños sin y con síndrome de Down fueron del 11 frente al 19,1%. Entre los últimos, el 26,3%, con cardiopatías no significativas; el 23%, con cardiopatías significativas, y el 11,4%, sin cardiopatía. El diagnóstico principal (59,4%) fue bronquiolitis. Se identificó algún germen en el 36,2%. La tasa de ingreso específica por virus respiratorio sincitial fue del 4,4%, con diferencias entre los niños sin y con síndrome de Down (el 3,2 frente al 7,8%) y entre los grupos con síndrome de Down con cardiopatías no significativas (15,8%), cardiopatías significativas (9,3%) y sin cardiopatía (3%). Había recibido profilaxis contra el virus respiratorio sincitial el 83,4 frente al 39,9% de los niños sin y con síndrome de Down. No hubo diferencias en el tiempo ni en la gravedad de las estancias. Conclusiones: Las hospitalizaciones por infecciones respiratorias y específicamente por virus respiratorio sincitial predominan en los niños con síndrome de Down, y entre ellos, en los que tienen cardiopatías leves y escasa inmunoprofilaxis frente al virus respiratorio sincitial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(1): 38-46, jul. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72525</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones respiratorias, síndrome de Down y cardiopatías congénitas: Estudio CIVIC 21</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12556</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
