<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152726</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conflicts between nursing ethics and health care legislation in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the ethical conflicts that may arise between the nursing codes of ethics and the Royal Decree-law 16/2012 modifying Spanish health regulations. Method: We conducted a review and critical analysis of the discourse of five nursing codes of ethics from Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain, Europe and International, and of the discourse of the Spanish legislation in force in 2013. Language structures referring to five different concepts of the theoretical framework of care were identified in the texts: equity, human rights, right to healthcare, access to care, and continuity of care. Results: Codes of ethics define the function of nursing according to equity, acknowledgement of human rights, right to healthcare, access to care and continuity of care, while legal discourse hinges on the concept of beneficiary or being insured. Conclusions: The divergence between the code of ethics and the legal discourse may produce ethical conflicts that negatively affect nursing practice. The application of RDL 16/2012 promotes a framework of action that prevents nursing professionals from providing care to uninsured collectives, which violates human rights and the principles of care ethics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Briones-Vozmediano, Erica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terés-Vidal, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gastaldo, Denise</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gea-Sánchez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Fidel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero-García, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evidenciar los conflictos éticos que pueden surgir entre los discursos legal y ético, a través de explorar el contenido del Real Decreto-Ley 16/2012 que modifica la ley sanitaria en España y los códigos éticos. Método: Revisión y análisis crítico del discurso de cinco códigos éticos de Enfermería de Barcelona, Cataluña, España, Europa e Internacional, y del discurso de la legislación sanitaria vigente en España en 2013, en los que se identificaron y compararon estructuras lingüísticas referentes a cinco principios y valores éticos del marco teórico de la ética de los cuidados: equidad, derechos humanos, derecho a la salud, accesibilidad y continuidad de los cuidados. Resultados: Mientras que el discurso ético define la función enfermera en función de la equidad, el reconocimiento de los derechos humanos, el derecho a la salud, la accesibilidad y la continuidad de los cuidados de la persona, el discurso legal se vertebra sobre el concepto de beneficiario o asegurado.  Conclusiones: La divergencia entre el discurso ético y legal puede producir conflictos éticos que afecten negativamente a la práctica de la profesión enfermera. La aplicación del RDL 16/2012 promueve un marco de acción que impide que los profesionales enfermeros presten sus cuidados a colectivos no asegurados, lo que atenta contra los derechos humanos y los principios de la ética de los cuidados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(3): 178-183, mayo-jun. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conflictos entre la ética enfermera y la legislación sanitaria en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37692^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36412</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
