<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147655</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion of users concerning the service of consultations of the Andalusian Drug Information Center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of the study was to assess the opinion of the users of the Andalusian Drug Information Center with respect to the quality of the service and information provided by the department of therapeutic consultations. Methods: A descriptive, cross-sectional study was carried out among health care professionals who had consulted the center during the period between June 1 2003 and May 31 2004. The information was collected by means of a telephone survey expressly designed for the study. Results: A total of 127 questionnaires were completed, for a contact rate of 94.8% and a response rate of 100%. The majority of those polled were hospital pharmacists or primary care physicians with a mean age of 43 years. Of all those who completed the questionnaire, 58.3% and 37.0%, respectively, considered the information sent to them to be of great and very great utility. With respect to the degree of satisfaction with the consultation service of the center, 56% of the users reported it to be high while, in 39.4% of cases, it was very high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Natividad Moya Garrido, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la opinión de los usuarios del Centro Andaluz de Documentación e Información de Medicamentos sobre la calidad del servicio e información aportada por el área de consultas terapéuticas. Metodología: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo transversal entre los profesionales sanitarios que realizaron consultas al centro durante el periodo comprendido entre el 1 de junio de 2003 y el 31 de mayo de 2004. La recogida de información se hizo mediante un cuestionario telefónico expresamente diseñado para el estudio Resultados: Se cumplimentaron un total de 127 cuestionarios, obteniéndose una tasa de contacto del 94,8% y una tasa de respuesta del 100%. La mayoría de los encuestados eran farmacéuticos de hospital y médicos de atención primaria con una media de edad de 43 años. Del total de encuestados, el 58,3 y el 37% consideraron que la información que se les envió era de utilidad alta y muy alta, respectivamente. En cuanto al grado de satisfacción con el servicio de consultas del centro, un 56% manifestó que era alta, mientras que en el 39,4% de los casos la satisfacción era muy alta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;9(3): 133-142, oct. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opinión de los usuarios sobre el servicio de consultas del Centro Andaluz de Documentación e Información de Medicamentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4408^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
