<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053125</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current status of islet transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to the numerous advances in islet transplantation in the last few years, clinical outcomes following this procedure are continually improving. Novel immunosuppression protocols, improved donor and recipient selection, and careful attention to the process of organ extraction, preservation and islet isolation have contributed to long-term success. The present article reviews the results of clinical islet transplantation and their relationship with the different advances introduced. The use of new islet sources such as living and non-heart-beating donors, as well as recent advances in our knowledge of the mechanisms of rejection and its prevention, are also reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Pérez, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balibrea Cantero, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vara Ameigeiras, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-Díaz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Martín, M. Cruz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balibrea del Castillo, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante de islotes pancreáticos mejora día a día sus resultados clínicos gracias a numerosas mejoras en el proceso desarrolladas en los últimos años. Tanto los nuevos protocolos de inmunosupresión como la selección de los donantes y receptores, así como un especial cuidado en la obtención, preservación y procesamiento de los páncreas, han hecho posible conseguir controles glucémicos prolongados. Uno de los objetivos principales de esta revisión es presentar la evolución de los resultados en humanos a medida que estos cambios han ido introduciéndose. Asimismo, se revisa el empleo de nuevas fuentes de islotes, como son el donante vivo y el donante a corazón parado, junto con los nuevos hallazgos en el conocimiento de los mecanismos de rechazo y las nuevas opciones terapéuticas desarrolladas para prevenirlo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);81(4): 177-191, abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual del trasplante de islotes pancreáticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24593^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24593^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29545^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29545^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37739^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29211^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28997^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
