<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81889</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Independent multiple primary tumors and second primary neoplasms. Relationship between smoking</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multiple primary tumors and second primary neoplasms have been increasing in incidence in recent decades and are reviewed in this paper. The reasons attributed to this significant increase are fundamentalment the best diagnosis of multiple concurrent cases and increased overall survival of patients diagnosed with cancer, allowing surface new primary tumors in other organs during or after standard monitoring. At the same time are invoked as possible causes of the widespread use of radio and chemotherapy for the first tumor. The genitourinary system is frequently involved in cases of multiple neoplasms; urological organs are one of the few settlement sites of primary tumors in almost a quarter of cases. This suggests a susceptibility/genitourinary system increased target for neoplastic disease. For this same reason, the urologist has a fundamental role in managing these patients and especially to follow up. We believe that the concept of clinical monitoring of this subset of patients should be revised, and should entail a screening of the most common second primary neoplasms since the risk of developing a subsequent independent cancer after presenting a urothelial tumor is considerably increased (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>las Heras Alonso, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gelabert Mas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores primarios múltiples, así como las segundas neoplasias primarias, han experimentado un aumento de la incidencia en estas últimas décadas y son objeto de revisión en este trabajo. Los motivos que se atribuyen a este aumento significativo son fundamentalmente el mejor diagnóstico de los casos múltiples concomitantes y la mayor supervivencia en general de los pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer, lo que permite que afloren nuevos tumores primarios en otros órganos durante o después del seguimiento estándar. Al mismo tiempo, se invocan como posibles causas el extenso uso de radioterapia y quimioterapia para el primer tumor. El sistema genitourinario está muy frecuentemente implicado en los casos de neoplasias múltiples; los órganos urológicos son uno de los sitios de asentamiento de algunos de los tumores primarios en casi una cuarta parte de los casos. Esto sugiere una susceptibilidad/diana incrementada del sistema genitourinario para la enfermedad neoplásica. Y, por esta misma razón, el urólogo tiene una responsabilidad esencial en el manejo de estos pacientes y de manera especial durante el seguimiento. Creemos que el concepto de seguimiento clínico de este subgrupo de pacientes debe ser revisado y debe comportar un cribaje de las más frecuentes segundas neoplasias primarias, ya que el riesgo de desarrollar un cáncer independiente subsiguiente después de presentar un tumor urotelial está considerablemente incrementado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(6): 516-521, jun. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores primarios múltiples independientes y segundas neoplasias primarias. Relación con el hábito de fumar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29936^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29575^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
