<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100574</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Purpura fulminans: functional results in two paediatric patients after suffering multiple amputations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpura fulminans (PF) is an unusual haemorrhagic process that is usually associated with meningococcal sepsis and other infectious processes. It usually affects neonates and young children, and starts with a benign infection that progresses to a high fever, purpura ecchymosis, disseminated intravascular coagulopathy, necrosis and gangrene. The treatment of these children usually requires making difficult decisions, since the surgeon and the families must come to terms with the possibility of following an aggressive line of treatment that could lead to multiple mutilating sequelae, or follow palliative treatment. In this study, we review the clinical presentation, treatment and results of two cases of PF treated in our hospital between the years 2002 and 2005. The children presented in this study had a good long-term functional result and an acceptable quality of life, despite being subjected to multiple amputations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamimi-Mariño, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendez, L. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La púrpura fulminante (PF) es un proceso hemorrágico inusual, que se asocia habitualmente a la sepsis meningocócica y a otros procesos infecciosos. Suele afectar a neonatos y a niños pequeños, y comienza como una infección benigna que progresa presentando fiebre alta, equimosis purpúrica, coagulopatía intravascular diseminada, necrosis y gangrena. El tratamiento de estos niños suele requerir la toma de decisiones difíciles, ya que el cirujano y los familiares deben plantearse la posibilidad de continuar con una línea de tratamiento agresiva que puede dejar múltiples secuelas mutilantes o seguir un tratamiento paliativo. En este estudio revisamos la presentación clínica, tratamiento y resultados funcionales de 2 casos de PF tratados en nuestro centro entre los años 2002 y 2005. Los niños presentados en este estudio tuvieron un buen resultado funcional a largo plazo y una calidad de vida aceptable a pesar de haber sido sometidos a múltiples amputaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(4): 319-322, jul.-ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100574</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Púrpura fulminante: resultado funcional en 2 pacientes pediátricos tras sufrir múltiples amputaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4502^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4272^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53099^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53099^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53099^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4502^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4272^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
