<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148624</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of HIV infected individuals traveling abroad. Results from the +REDIVI Collaborative Network</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The improvement in the prognosis of HIV infection, coupled with the increase in international travel and migration, has led to a rising number of HIV infected travelers. The objective of this study was to describe the epidemiological and clinical features of returning travelers, according to their HIV status. Methods: An observational prospective study was conducted including travelers and immigrants who traveled to visit friends and relatives (VFRs) registered in the +REDIVI collaborative network (January-2009; October-2014). +REDIVI is a national network that registers information regarding infections imported by travelers and immigrants at 21 different centers using a standardized protocol. Results: A total of 3464 travellers were identified: 72 were HIV+ (2.1%) and 3.392 HIV&amp;#8722; (98%). HIV+ vs. HIV&amp;#8722; travelers were often older (40.5y vs. 34.2y P = .001), VFRs (79.1% vs. 44.4%; P &lt; .001), and consulted less for pre-travel advice (27% vs. 37%; P = .078). The main destinations for both groups were sub-Saharan Africa and Latin America. The most frequent reasons for consultation after travel were fever, request for a health examination, gastrointestinal complaints, and abnormal laboratory tests (mainly eosinophilia and anemia), which differed between groups. The most frequent diagnoses in HIV+ travelers were malaria (38.8%), newly diagnosed HIV infection (25%), and intestinal parasites (19.4%), while for HIV&amp;#8722; travelers the main diagnoses were &#147;healthy&#148; (17.9%), malaria (14%), and intestinal parasites (17.3%). Conclusions: The typical profile of an HIV+ traveler in +REDIVI was that of a VFR traveler who did not seek pre-travel advice and made high-risk trips. This may increase the chance of acquiring travel-related infections which may pose a special risk for HIV-infected travelers. The post-travel visit was a good opportunity for HIV infection screening (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goikoetxea, Josune</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Giardín, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malmierca, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Treviño, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrús, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calabuig, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Echevarría, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Perez, Angela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Norman, Francesca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Molina, Jose A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Velez, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serre, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La mejoría en el pronóstico de la infección por el VIH, sumada al incremento de los viajes y la inmigración, han aumentado la frecuencia del binomio viajero-VIH+. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la epidemiología y hallazgos clínicos de los viajeros VIH+ en comparación con los VIH-. Métodos: Estudio observacional y prospectivo, de los viajeros e inmigrantes viajeros que se desplazan para visitar familiares y amigos (VFR) incluidos en la red +REDIVI (enero-2009; octubre-2014). +REDIVI es una red nacional que recopila información sobre infecciones importadas por viajeros e inmigrantes en 21 centros mediante un protocolo estandarizado de recogida de datos. Resultados: Se identificaron 3.464 viajeros: 72 VIH+ (2,1%) y 3.392 VIH&amp;#8722; (98%). Los VIH+ en contraste con los VIH&amp;#8722;, eran mayores (40 vs. 34 años; p = 0,001), predominantemente VFR (79,7% vs 44,4%. p &lt; 0,001), y solicitan menos consejo pre-viaje (27% vs 37%. p = 0,078). Los destinos predominantes para ambos grupos fueron África Subsahariana y Latinoamérica. Los motivos de consulta más frecuentes al retorno del viaje fueron la fiebre, solicitar un examen de salud, molestias gastrointestinales, y anomalías en los resultados de laboratorio (principalmente eosinofilia y anemia) los cuales variaron según el grupo. Los diagnósticos más frecuentes en los VIH+ fueron la malaria (38,8%), nuevo diagnóstico de VIH (25%) y parasitosis intestinales (19,4%), mientras que en los sujetos VIH&amp;#8722; los principales diagnósticos fueron &#147;sano&#148; (17,9%), parásitos intestinales (17,3%) y malaria (14%). Conclusiones: El perfil más común del viajero VIH+ atendido en +Redivi es el de un inmigrante VFR que no solicita consejo pre-viaje y hace viajes de alto riesgo. Esto puede suponer un mayor riesgo de adquisición de infecciones relacionadas con el viaje, las cuales en un viajero VIH+ pueden tener un efecto deletéreo adicional. La consulta tras el viaje es una buena oportunidad para el cribado de la infección por VIH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;34(2): 108-113, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de los individuos infectados por el VIH que viajan al extranjero. Los resultados de la red +REDIVI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29422^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
