<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146593</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of neuromuscular electrical stimulation in the functional knee rehabilitation in soldiers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The versatility of military physical therapist practice enables them not only to diagnose knee injuries but also to provide a wide range of definitive care and rehabilitation, reducing the need for costly evacuation. The aim this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of interventions by Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation (NMES) in the functional knee rehabilitation in soldiers and describe the main predictors and determinants in each intervention. Methods: A systematic search of the literature about NMES in physiotherapy was performed using the following electronic databases: Web of Science, PubMed, Cochrane, Physiotherapy Evidence Database (PEDro) and CINAHL. The search strategy was: &#145;neuromuscular electrical stimulation&#146; and &#145;physical therapy&#146; and &#145;strengthening&#146; and &#145;knee&#146;. Inclusion criteria were: original articles published and peer reviewed between 2004-2015, focusing on physiotherapy interventions by NMES on subjects older than 18 years. A total resulting from 46 studies was included in the study. Results: The results show the evidence on the effectiveness of NMES therapeutic/preventive purposes in the muscular system; and the importance of physical therapy in the army. Conclusion: As a method of functional knee rehabilitation, NMES proves effective in achieving the therapeutic/preventive objectives in soldiers. Level of Evidence: II. Systematic review of randomized clinical trials with homogeneity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Lozano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La versatilidad de la práctica de la fisioterapia militar nos permite no sólo el diagnóstico de lesiones de rodilla sino también para proporcionar una amplia gama de atención específica y rehabilitación, reduciendo la necesidad de una evacuación costosa. El objetivo de este estudio fue comparar la eficacia de las intervenciones de estimulación eléctrica neuromuscular (NMES) en la rehabilitación de rodilla funcional en soldados y describir los principales predictores y determinantes en cada intervención. Métodos: Se realizó una búsqueda sistemática de la literatura sobre la NMES en fisioterapia utilizando las siguientes bases de datos electrónicas: Web of Science, PubMed, Cochrane, Fisioterapia Evidence Database (PEDro) y CINAHL. La estrategia de búsqueda fue: &#145;neuromuscular electrical stimulation&#146; and &#145;physical therapy&#146; and &#145;strengthening&#146; and &#145;knee&#146;. Se seleccionaron artículos originales publicados y revisados por pares entre 2004-2015, centrándonos en las intervenciones de fisioterapia mediante NMES en sujetos mayores de 18 años. Un total resultante de 46 estudios se incluyeron en el estudio. Resultados: Los resultados muestran la evidencia sobre la eficacia de los propósitos terapéuticos y preventivos de la NMES en rodilla; y la importancia de la fisioterapia en el ejército. Conclusión: La fisioterapia mediante su método NMES de rehabilitación de la rodilla resulta eficaz en el logro de los objetivos terapéuticos / preventivas en los soldados. Nivel de Evidencia: II. Revisión sistemática de ensayos clínicos aleatorizados, con homogeneidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;71(4): 239-246, oct.-dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146593</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la estimulación eléctrica neuromuscular en la rehabilitación funcional de rodilla en soldados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55020^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55020^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4638^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
