<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125657</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality and resilience in a special corps of the National Police in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relationship between socio-demographic data, personality, and resilience is assessed in a sample of 348 male police intervention units (PIU) in Spain (N = 348) between 23 and 38 years (M = 26.88, SD = 3.12). The results showed that age and education, along with dominance, conscientiousness, perseverance, impulse control, and emotions were closely related to resilience. In addition, 66% of the variance in resilience would be given by four variables: age and academic level and the determination and control of emotions. The importance of some socio-demographic and individual differences as predictors of the level of resilience in specialized police professionals&#146; variables is discussed and some ways to work are open to the study of resilience in other professional groups constantly exposed to situations of extreme adversity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles Bello, Mª Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Teruel, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se valora la relación entre datos sociodemográficos, personalidad y resiliencia en una muestra de 348 policías masculinos de las unidades de intervención policial (UIP) de España (N = 348) entre los 23 y los 38 años (M = 26.88, DT = 3.12). Los resultados mostraron que la edad y el nivel educativo junto con la dominancia, la escrupulosidad, perseverancia, control de los impulsos y emociones estaban muy relacionados con la resiliencia. Además, el 66% de la varianza en resiliencia vendría dado por cuatro variables: la edad y el nivel académico y el tesón y el control de las emociones. Se discute la importancia de algunas variables socio-demográficas y diferencias individuales como predictoras del nivel de resiliencia en profesionales especializados de la policía y se abren algunas vías de trabajo para el estudio de la resiliencia en otros colectivos profesionales expuestos de forma constante a situaciones de extrema adversidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);30(2): 75-81, mayo-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125657</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personalidad y resiliencia en un cuerpo especial de la Policía Nacional de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29881^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
