<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053011</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe hydroureteronephrosis associated to asymptomatic giant anterior sacral meningocele: a case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a woman with Marfan's syndrome presenting with a clinical picture of acute gastroenteritis in whom severe bilateral hydroureteronephrosis associated to a neurogenic bladder and a giant anterior sacral meningocele was diagnosed incidentally. The importance of this case lies in the fact that the patient was asymptomatic despite the significant visceral repercussions already occurring that led to questioning of whether MRI follow-up would still be advisable even in the absence of symptoms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Travieso, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemán, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El caso que presentamos es el de una mujer con síndrome de Marfan, a la que tras acudir a su médico por un cuadro de gastroenteritis aguda se le diagnosticó casualmente una ureterohidronefrosis bilateral severa asociada a una vejiga neurógena y a un meningocele sacro anterior gigante. La importancia de este caso radica en que la paciente estaba asintomática, a pesar de las importantes repercusiones viscerales que ya se habían producido, lo que plantea si sería aconsejable el seguimiento de estos pacientes mediante resonancia magnética (RM) aun en ausencia de síntomas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);49(1): 43-46, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053011</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ureterohidronefrosis severa asociada a meningocele sacro anterior gigante asintomático: presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8554^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7022^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8335^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8758^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
