<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91358</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender issues in doctoral theses on Nursing in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to analyse scientific production of nursing in Spainaccording the gender of the individuals involved in such productionand other context variables.Methodology: quantitative study. Data were gathered in the TESEOdatabase through electronic accesses based on the search terms:nursing, female nurse, male nurse. The analysis was carried out byreading of the titles and summaries, taking into account the genderas empiric reference for identification and discussion of the gender&#146;straits.Results: 89 thesis were identified which had been produced mainlyin the last five years, female authorship was 69,3%; most of thesewere directed by men (74,2%) and only 27% of the doctoral committeeswere chaired by women. The main areas of the theses were:education, nursing, psychology and medicine. The most covered itemwas work, including occupational stress and working conditions ofnursing personnel.Conclusion: even though women account for a large amount of thesisauthorship, the proportion is lower to that of the total number ofnursing professionals in the country. On the other hand, the greaternumber of men in the doctoral committee indicated the difficultiesfound by women, and particularly by nurses, to hold posts of greatersocial prestige, which reproduces the unequal relationships of genderand power distribution in the profession as well as in the university.It is however important to highlight that there are still few researchprojects associated with doctorate courses in nursing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>do Nascimento, Enilda Rosendo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santo Tomás Pérez, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: analizar la producción científica de Enfermería en Españasegún el sexo de las personas involucradas en dicha produccióny otras variables del contexto.Metodología: estudio de naturaleza cuantitativa. Los datos fueronrecolectados en la base TESEO, a través de acceso electrónico, a partirde los términos de búsqueda: &#147;Enfermería, enfermera, enfermero&#148;.El análisis se hizo mediante la lectura de los títulos y resúmenes,teniendo en cuenta el sexo como referencia empírica para identificacióny discusión de los rasgos de género.Resultados: fueron identificadas 89 tesis, producidas mayoritariamenteen los últimos cinco años; la autoría femenina fue del 69,3%;la mayoría fueron dirigidas por hombres (74,2%) y solamente el 27%de los tribunales tenían mujeres en la presidencia. Las principalesáreas de las tesis eran: Educación, Enfermería, Psicología y Medicina.Destaca el tema trabajo, incluyendo estrés y condiciones del desarrollode las actividades del personal de Enfermería.Conclusión: aunque las mujeres estén más representadas como autorasde las tesis, la proporción es inferior a la que hay en el total deprofesionales de Enfermería del país. Por otra parte, las mayores proporcionesde hombres en los tribunales indica la dificultad de las mujeresy, en concreto, de las enfermeras, para ocupar cargos de mayorprestigio social, reproduciéndose las relaciones desiguales de géneroy distribución del poder dentro de la profesión y en la universidad,aunque es importante subrayar que el desarrollo de la investigación ligadaa cursos de doctorado propios de la Enfermería aún son pocos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(5): 72-76, jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestiones de géneroen las tesis doctorales sobreEnfermería en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4273</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
