<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75762</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequent attendance: Primary Care Professional's perceptions of definitions, motives, situations and relationships with frequent attenders patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo find out how health professionals in Primary Care (PC) perceive the definition criteria for frequent attendance, as well as their perceptions of the reasons for the visits of patients referred to as frequent attenders, their situations and their relationships with them.MethodWe performed a qualitative study using semi-structured interviews in Primary Care centers of six health areas of the Community of Madrid. Eighteen interviews were conducted, three per area (two physicians and one nurse). Structural sampling was carried out with regards to the variables that could influence the discourse: health area, occupation, sex and number of years worked. The transcriptions were analyzed by two investigators who gave a consensus interpretation.ResultsThe proportion of frequent attenders varies according to each professional and it is defined more by quality reasons than by number of visits. They make appointments associated with chronic diseases, but also for psychosocial or work problems. There are frequent attenders of all ages and both sexes, and the doctor-patient relationship depends on each individual case.ConclusionsFrequent attendance is defined by the professionals by a number of qualitative criteria in which the number of visits is of little importance. The reasons for consultation and patient characteristics are numerous, so a unique profile cannot be determined. A common factor in the discourses is that many of the frequent attenders&#146; reasons for consultation were psychosocial problems, so streamlining coordination with psychosocial resources would help to make PC consultations more efficient and effective(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conde-Espejo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandín-Vázquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoConocer la percepción de los profesionales sanitarios de atención primaria (AP) sobre los criterios para definir la hiperfrecuentación, así como sus percepciones sobre los motivos de las visitas de los pacientes denominados hiperfrecuentadores, las situaciones asociadas al fenómeno y su relación con ellos.MétodoEstudio cualitativo mediante entrevistas semiestructuradas abiertas en centros de AP de 6 áreas de salud de la Comunidad de Madrid. Se realizaron 18 entrevistas, 3 por área (2 profesionales de medicina y uno de enfermería). Se llevó a cabo un muestreo estructural en función de las variables que podían condicionar el discurso: área de salud, profesión, sexo y número de años de trabajo. Dos investigadoras realizaron el análisis y buscaron la concordancia entre ambas.ResultadosLos profesionales definen la hiperfrecuentación por una serie de criterios cualitativos en los que el número de visitas tiene poca importancia. Acuden por problemas médicos relacionados con enfermedades crónicas pero también por motivos psicosociales o laborales. Hay hiperfrecuentadores de todas las edades y de ambos sexos, y la relación médico-paciente depende de cada caso concreto.ConclusionesSegún los profesionales de AP, la definición de un paciente como hiperfrecuentador no depende del número sino de la calidad de la visita. Las razones de consulta y las características de los pacientes son múltiples, por lo que no se puede determinar un perfil único. Un factor común en los discursos es que muchos de los hiperfrecuentadores acuden a consulta por problemáticas psicosociales, por lo que sería de gran ayuda agilizar la coordinación con recursos psicosociales para conseguir consultas de AP más eficientes y efectivas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(1): 21-27, ene.-feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperfrecuentación: percepción de los profesionales de atención primaria sobre su definición, motivos, situaciones y la relación con los pacientes hiperfrecuentadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
