<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100354</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The objective structured clinical evaluation of teaching in anaesthesiology and resuscitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To find out the acquirement of professional competencies of Anaesthesiology and Resuscitation medical residents at the end of their training period using the Objective Structured Clinical Evaluation (OCSE) tool. Material and methods: Six competency components to evaluate were defined as follows: clinical interview (communication), technical ability and relationship abilities (leadership, decision making, work in a team), diagnostic assessment, therapeutic management, and medical records. Different methodologies were determined depending on the knowledge and skills to evaluate. Twelve clinical cases were developed that were performed in 12 stations. A total of 107 items, specified within the stations, evaluated the competency components. A total of 43 residents were invited to participate in the last 4 months of their training in hospitals in Andalusia and Extremadura. Results: A total of 33 residents participated. The overall mean of the classifications obtained in the 12 stations was 64.2 out of a maximum of 100. The medical residents demonstrated higher competency in obstetrics, paediatric anaesthesia, and that associated with difficult airway. The main competency gaps were detected in the area of one-day surgery, chronic pain, and literature management, in which approximately half passed the test. Conclusions: We believe that training evaluations, such as the OCSE, help in determining the skill levels of the medical resident, making it easier to continually improve the training of the future anaesthesiologist(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira Reina, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Jurado, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Cuervo Derqui, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Garcia, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Vera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luis Navarro, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Tellería, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer el nivel de adquisición de competencias de los médicos residentes de Anestesiología y Reanimación al final de su periodo formativo mediante la herramienta de Evaluación Clínica Objetiva Estructurada (ECOE). Método: Se definieron seis componentes competenciales que evaluar: la entrevista clínica (comunicación), la habilidad técnica y las habilidades relacionales (liderazgo, toma de decisiones, trabajo en equipo), la valoración diagnóstica, el manejo terapéutico y el registro clínico. Se determinaron distintas metodologías en función de los conocimientos y las habilidades en evaluación. Se desarrollaron 12 casos clínicos, que se llevaron a cabo en 12 estaciones. Dentro de las estaciones, se especificó un total de 107 ítems que evaluaban los componentes competenciales. Se invitó a participar a los 43 residentes en los últimos 4 meses de su formación en los centros hospitalarios de Andalucía y Extremadura. Resultados: Participaron 33 residentes. La media general de las calificaciones obtenidas en las 12 estaciones fue de 64,2 sobre un máximo de 100. Los MIR demostraron mayor destreza en obstetricia, anestesia pediátrica y la relacionada con la vía aérea difícil. Las principales lagunas competenciales se detectaron en el área de cirugía ambulatoria, dolor crónico y manejo bibliográfico, en las que superó la prueba aproximadamente la mitad. Conclusiones: Consideramos que evaluaciones formativas como la ECOE permiten conocer el nivel de adquisición de competencias del médico residente y facilitan la mejora continua de la formación del futuro anestesiólogo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(3): 134-141, mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación clínica objetiva estructurada en la docencia en Anestesiología y Reanimación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
