<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144043</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Introduction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Asthma is the most frequent chronic disease in childhood. Its prevalence varies (in Spain between 12 % in coastal regions and 6 % in the Castilian plateau). Asthma represents chronic inflammation of the airways associated with an increase in bronchial reactivity to various stimuli, leading to reduced air flow and subsequent remodeling of the bronchial wall. Asthma usually begins in the first few years of life and 30 % of patients will continue to be asthmatic throughout their lives. The main characteristic associated with the persistence of asthma in adulthood seems to be allergy. Another risk factor is the presence of bronchial hyperreactivity. Wheezing associated with viral infections in childhood shows a favorable outcome when not associated with atopic features. The atopic disposition is caused by the interaction between genetic and distinct environmental factors (allergens), as well as by the various clinical manifestations that favor a mainly Th2 response, with interleukins that lead to the formation of specific IgE, pro-inflammatory cytokines, bronchial hyperreactivity, etc. In most cases, asthma is mainly an allergic process, mediated by an IgE mechanism. Inhalation of allergens is considered the most important cause of the onset of asthma in predisposed children. First the presence of an allergen gives rise to sensitization, with the formation of specific IgE. In a subsequent contact, mediators are released, with inflammatory response of the airways and an increase in bronchial hyperreactivity. If the presence of the allergen is prolonged, inflammation and subsequent healing may lead to irreversible damage to the bronchial wall and permanent deterioration of respiratory function. In children with asthma, the aim is to modify the natural history of the disease and prevent its persistence in adulthood. This involves identifying the allergen or allergens causing the symptoms, confirming the role of these allergens in clinical manifestations through specific challenge tests and, lastly, indicating the treatment be followed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casas Vilá, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El asma es la enfermedad crónica mas frecuente en la infancia. La prevalencia es variable (en España, entre el 12 en zonas costeras y el 6 % en la meseta). El asma es una inflamación crónica de las vías aéreas, que se asocia a un aumento de la reactividad bronquial frente a varios estímulos, que conduce a una limitación en el flujo aéreo y a una posterior remodelación de la pared bronquial. Suele comenzar en los primeros años de vida y un 30 % de los pacientes seguirá con asma a lo largo de su vida. La alergia parece ser la característica fundamental que se asocia a la persistencia del asma en el adulto. Otro factor de riesgo es la presencia de hiperreactividad bronquial. Las sibilancias asociadas a infecciones víricas en la infancia tienen una evolución favorable, si no se acompañan de rasgos atópicos. La interacción de factores genéticos con distintos factores ambientales (alergenos) sería la responsable de la constitución atópica, así como de la distintas manifestaciones clínicas presentadas, al propiciar una respuesta predominantemente Th2, con interleucinas responsables de la formación de IgE específica, citocinas pro-inflamatorias, hiperreactividad bronquial, etc. En la mayoría de los casos el asma es fundamentalmente un proceso alérgico, a través de un mecanismo mediado por IgE. La inhalación de alergenos se considera la causa mas importante en la aparición del asma en un niño predispuesto: en un primer momento la presencia del alergeno daría lugar a la sensibilización, con formación de IgE específica. En un contacto posterior, se produce la liberación de mediadores, con la respuesta inflamatoria de las vías respiratorias y aumento de la hiperreactividad bronquial. Si la presencia del alergeno es muy prolongada, la inflamación y posterior reparación puede conducir a un daño irreversible en la pared bronquial y a un deterioro permanente de la función respiratoria. Ante un niño con asma, afán será modificar la historia natural de la enfermedad, y evitar que esta situación se prolongue hasta la edad adulta. Esto obliga a buscar el o los alergenos responsables de la clínica, comprobar el papel que estos alergenos tienen en la presentación de los síntomas, mediante las provocaciones específicas y por último, indicar el tratamiento a seguir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);32(3): 119-121, mayo 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144043</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mesa redonda: importancia de los alergenos en el asma infantil: Introducción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7147^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22205^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
