<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055239</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and safety of inhaled insulin in diabetes mellitus treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the efficacy and safety of inhaled insulin.                 Design. Systematic review.                 Data sources. Reference data bases, MEDLINE (1999 to November 2005) and EMBASE (2000 to November 2005), the CENTRAL base (Cochrane Library), the European Drug Agency, the Food and Drug Administration, the International Network of Technology Evaluation Agencies, the European Network for Early Detection (EuroScan), and various research registers.                 Studies. Eight clinical trials were recovered. Studies not comparing inhaled with subcutaneous insulin and those that did not measure metabolic control or satisfaction and quality of life were excluded.                 Data extraction. Critical reading using the methods proposed by the CASPe programme.                 Results. The difference between the 2 groups in mean values of descent of glycosylated haemoglobin was ­0.07% (95% CI, ­0.32 to 0.17) for type-2 diabetics; and between 0.16% (95% CI, ­0.01 to 0.32) and -0.16% (95% CI, ­0.34 to 0.01) in type-1 diabetics. Hypoglucaemias per subject-month were similar (between 0.83 and 1.57 in type-2 diabetics and between 8.6 and 9.9 in type-1 diabetics). Quality of life and satisfaction were favourable to the intervention group (P&lt;.05). Secondary effects were comparable except in the appearance of cough (21%-27% in inhaled and 2%-7% in subcutaneous insulin).                 Conclusions. Inhaled insulin is comparable to subcutaneous insulin in metabolic control, the number of hypoglucaemias and side-effects. However, the trials reviewed showed certain problems of internal and external validity. Studies with longer follow-up are needed, in order to evaluate possible lung disorders</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llanos Méndez, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villegas-Portero, Román</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar la eficacia y la seguridad de la insulina inhalada.                 Diseño. Revisión sistemática.                 Fuentes de datos. Bases de datos referenciales MEDLINE (1999 a noviembre 2005) y EMBASE (2000 a noviembre 2005), en la base CENTRAL (Cochrane Library), Agencia Europea del Medicamento, Food and Drug Administration, Red Internacional de Agencias de Evaluación de Tecnologías, Red Europea Detección Precoz de Tecnologías (EuroScan), y varios registros de investigación.                 Selección de los estudios. Se recuperaron 8 ensayos clínicos. Se excluyeron los estudios que no se compararon con la insulina subcutánea y los que no midieron el control metabólico o la satisfacción y la calidad de vida.                 Extracción de los datos. Lectura crítica según la metodología propuesta por el programa CASPe.                 Resultados. La diferencia de valores medios de descenso de la hemoglobina glucosilada en ambos grupos fue del ­0,07% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, ­0,32 a 0,17) para diabéticos tipo 2 y entre el 0,16% (IC del 95%, ­0,01 a 0,32) y el ­0,16% (IC del 95%, ­0,34 a 0,01) en diabéticos tipo 1. Las hipoglucemias por sujeto-mes fueron similares (entre 0,83 y 1,57 en diabéticos tipo 2 y entre 8,6 y 9,9 en diabéticos tipo 1). Los resultados de calidad de vida y satisfacción fueron favorables al grupo intervención (p &lt; 0,05). Los efectos secundarios fueron comparables, excepto en la aparición de tos (el 21-27% en la insulina inhalada y el 2-7% en la insulina subcutánea).                 Conclusiones. La insulina inhalada es equiparable a la subcutánea en el control metabólico, el número de hipoglucemias y los efectos adversos. Sin embargo, los ensayos recuperados presentaron algunos problemas de validez interna y externa. Se precisan estudios con un mayor seguimiento para evaluar las posibles alteraciones pulmonares</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;39(5): 235-239, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad de la insulina inhalada en el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19256^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
