<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103043</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe thrombocytopenia on admission to the intensive care unit in patients with multiple organ failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the frequency of severe thrombocytopenia (STCP) (&lt; 50.000/µl) in the first 24hours in patients with multiple organ dysfunction syndrome, and the factors that influence its occurrence. Design: A retrospective, observational study. Area: Medical-surgical intensive care unit (ICU). Tertiary hospital. Patients: Those with failure of at least two organs, according to SOFA criteria, with the exclusion of neurological and traumatologic critical cases. Variables: Medical history, regular medication, baseline functional status, demographic variables, severity scores in ICU, multiple-organ failure data, course in ICU and main hospital data. Results: A total of 587 patients were included; 6.3% (37 patients) presented with STCP during the first day of admission; 64.6% were men; SOFA 8 (5-10); APACHE II 18 (13-24); APACHE IV 59 (46-73); 32.5% were surgical patients. A total of 79.9% subsequently needed mechanical ventilation, and 71.4% required vasoactive drugs. Overall stay in ICU: 4 (2-10) days, main hospital stay 18 (9-35) days. A total of 29.2% died in the ICU; 11.7% developed STCP during admission to the ICU. Multivariate analysis found the main determining factors in the occurrence of thrombocytopenia on admission to be: history of hospitalization in the last year, albumin and bilirubin levels, and sepsis. Conclusion: The prevalence of STCP among critical patients was 6.3%. Its occurrence was associated with albumin and bilirubin levels, sepsis, and with patient admittance in the last year (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hortigüela-Martín, V. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco-Schulke, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Casado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Villar, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canabal-Berlanga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pedrero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco-Ramos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana-Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrese-Cosculluela, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la frecuencia de la trombocitopenia grave (TCPG) (&lt;50.000/µl) en las primeras 24 horas en pacientes con síndrome de disfunción multiorgánica (SDMO) y los factores asociados a su aparición. Diseño: Estudio retrospectivo, con diseño observacional. Ámbito: Unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI) médico-quirúrgica de un hospital de nivel III. Pacientes: Aquellos con disfunción de al menos dos órganos, según criterios SOFA; se excluyen neurocríticos y politraumatizados. Variables de interés: Antecedentes personales, medicación habitual, situación funcional basal, datos de filiación, puntuaciones de gravedad en UCI, datos de la disfunción multiorgánica, evolución UCI y datos hospitalarios. Resultados: Se incluyeron 587 pacientes. El 6,3% (37 pacientes) presentaban TCPG durante el primer día de ingreso. El 64,6% eran hombres; la mediana de edad fue 69 (56-77) años; al ingreso, SOFA 8 (5-10); APACHE II 18 (13-24); APACHE IV 59 (46-73); 32,5% son quirúrgicos. Durante su evolución 79,9% necesitaron ventilación mecánica y el 71,4% requirió fármacos vasoactivos. Estancia en UCI 4 (2-10) días; estancia hospitalaria 18 (9-35) días. El 29,2% fallecieron en UCI. El 11,7% desarrollaron durante su ingreso en UCI TCPG. En el análisis multivariable los principales determinantes de la aparición de la trombocitopenia al ingreso fueron los antecedentes de ingreso hospitalario en el último año, el peor valor de bilirrubina y albúmina sanguínea y la sepsis. Conclusión: La prevalencia de TCPG en pacientes críticos con SDMO durante el primer día de estancia en UCI es del 6,3%. Los factores asociados son: la presencia o no de ingresos hospitalarios en el último año, los niveles de albúmina y bilirrubina y la sepsis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(3): 185-192, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103043</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombocitopenia grave al ingreso en una unidad de cuidados intensivos en pacientes con disfunción multiorgánica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
