<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159130</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A study of epilepsy according to the age at onset and monitored for 3 years in a regional reference paediatric neurology unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A study of epilepsy, according to the age at onset of the crisis and its causes, monitored by a Paediatric Neurology Unit over a period of three years. Patients and methods: Historical cohorts study was conducted by reviewing the Paediatric Neurology medical records data base of epileptic children followed-up from 1 January 2008 to 31 December 2010. Results: A total of 4,595 children were attended during the study period. The diagnosis of epilepsy was established in 605 (13.17%): 277 (45.79%) symptomatic, 156 (25.79%) idiopathic, and 172 (28.43%) with cryptogenic epilepsy. Absence epilepsy and benign childhood epilepsy with centro-temporal spikes are the idiopathic epileptic syndromes most prevalent, and the most prevalent symptomatic epilepsies are prenatal encephalopathies. More than one-quarter (26.12%) of epilepsies began in the first year of life, and 67.72% were symptomatic. Refractory epilepsy was observed in 25.29%, 42.46% with cognitive impairment, 26.45% with motor involvement, and 9.92% with an autism spectrum disorder, being more frequent at an earlier age of onset. Conclusions: The absence of a universally accepted classification of epileptic syndromes makes tasks like this difficult, starting with the terminology. A useful classification would be aetiological, with two groups: a large group with established aetiology, or very likely genetic syndromes, and another with no established cause. The age of onset of epilepsy in each aetiological group helps in the prognosis, which is worsened by refractoriness and associated neurodevelopmental disorders, and are generally worse at an earlier onset and in certain aetiologies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Pisón, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuertes Rodrigo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapresta Moros,  Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Jiménez, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samper-Villagrasa, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa-Gómez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernando Martínez, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Segura, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monge-Galindo, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudio de las epilepsias según la edad de inicio de las crisis y la etiología, de los pacientes controlados en una unidad de neuropediatría durante 3 años. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio de cohortes históricas. Revisión de historias de niños con epilepsia de la base de datos de neuropediatría controlados del 1 de enero de 2008 al 31 de diciembre de 2010. Resultados: De 4.595 ni&#152;nos atendidos en el periodo, se estableció el diagnóstico de epilepsia en 605 (13,17%), siendo 277 (45,79%) epilepsias sintomáticas, 156 (25,79%) idiopáticas y 172 (28,43%) criptogénicas. La epilepsia de ausencias y la epilepsia benigna de la infancia con paroxismos centrotemporales son los síndromes epilépticos idiopáticos con mayor prevalencia, y las encefalopatías prenatales las epilepsias sintomáticas más prevalentes. El 26,12% iniciaron su epilepsia el primer a&#152;no, siendo sintomáticas el 67,72%. Se han considerado refractarias el 25,29% de las epilepsias; el 42,46% asocia déficit cognitivo, el 26,45% afectación motora y el 9,92% trastorno del espectro autista, siendo más frecuentes a menor edad de inicio. Conclusiones: La ausencia de una clasificación universalmente aceptada de los síndromes epilépticos dificulta trabajos como este, empezando por la terminología. Una clasificación útil es la etiológica, con 2 grupos: un gran grupo con las etiologías establecidas o síndromes genéticos muy probables, y otro de casos sin causa establecida. La edad de inicio de la epilepsia en cada grupo etiológico añade orientación pronóstica. El pronóstico de la epilepsia lo ensombrecen la refractariedad y las alteraciones asociadas del neurodesarrollo, siendo peor en general a más precoz inicio y en etiologías concretas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(1): 11-19, ene. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159130</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de las epilepsias según la edad de inicio, controladas durante 3 años en una unidad de neuropediatría de referencia regional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34279^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56096^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34279^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56096^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
