<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78666</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">General considerations on brain death and recommendations on the clinical decisions after its diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the Latin American Network/Council of Donation and Transplant is to develop cooperation among its member states in all aspects related to donation and transplant of organs, tissue and cells. Given that diagnosing brain death (BD) is one of the key issues for the procurement of organs for transplant, the Network/Council seeks to contribute to defining the accepted concept of BD and its diagnosis and to disseminate this information among healthcare workers.In this report, we present the general guidelines on brain death and recommendations for clinical decisions after its diagnosis established and approved by the Latin American Network/Council of Donation and Transplant at its sixth meeting held in La Havana, Cuba, in May 2008.Although there are legal differences and variations in the diagnostic criteria used to define BD among its member states, brain death is accepted as the death of an individual for all legal, ethical and scientific effects. The diagnosis of BD should be independent of the decision of whether to donor or not donate organs for transplant. Once a diagnosis of BD has been confirmed, the possibility of organ donation should always be considered and the appropriate organ maintenance measures initiated. If organ donation is contraindicated, all support measures should be withdrawn including mechanical respiration. The decision to withdraw all support measures is consistent with the clinical-legal diagnosis and supported by several scientific and bioethics societies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Matesanz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ignacio Flores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberto Soratti, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la Red/Consejo Iberoamericano de Donación y Trasplantes es desarrollar la cooperación entre los países miembros en todos los aspectos relacionados con la donación y el trasplante de órganos, tejidos y células. Considerando que el diagnóstico de muerte encefálica (ME) es una de las claves fundamentales en la obtención de órganos para trasplante, uno de los objetivos prioritarios de la Red/Consejo es contribuir a la divulgación y a la formación del concepto y el diagnóstico de ME entre los profesionales sanitarios En el presente trabajo se presentan las consideraciones generales sobre la ME y las recomendaciones sobre las decisiones clínicas tras su diagnóstico que la Red/Consejo Iberoamericano de Donación y Trasplantes elaboraron y aprobaron en su sexta reunión celebrada en mayo del año 2008 en La Habana, Cuba.Aunque existen diferencias legales y variabilidad en los criterios diagnósticos de ME en los países miembros, la ME se acepta como la muerte del individuo a efectos legales, éticos y científicos. El diagnóstico debe ser independiente de si existe o no donación de los órganos para trasplante. Una vez confirmado el diagnóstico de ME, se debe considerar siempre la posibilidad de donación de los órganos e iniciar las medidas oportunas de mantenimiento. Si la donación de órganos estuviera contraindicada, se procederá a la retirada de todas las medidas de soporte, incluida la ventilación mecánica. La decisión de retirar todas las medidas de soporte es consecuente con el diagnóstico clinicolegal y diferentes sociedades científicas y bioéticas la apoyan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(9): 450-454, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78666</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones generales sobre la muerte encefálica y recomendaciones sobre las decisiones clínicas tras su diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34530^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
