<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79045</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linoleic acid emulsion on the peri-lesion skin of venal ulcers. Action and cicatrizant effect. Corpus study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors present a clinical and documented follow up on the peri-lesion skin in 44 venal blood vessel ulcers which were treated by a hyper-oxygenized fatty acid emulsion. All the elderly in this study belonged to the Number 3 Health Department of the Valencia Sanitary Council. This study&#146;s protocol and its data collection register received a favourable report from the Committee on Research Ethics at the «La Plana» Hospital. With a total percentage of 60 in essential linoleic fatty acid, CORPITOLINOL® 60, is the emulsion which has the greatest quantity of this element so necessary for human skin. In effect, this is the essential fatty acid which has the greatest presence in human skin, besides being a vital element for skin hydration and its viability to form part of a fundamental structure: intercellular layers in the corneum layer of the epidermis. On the other hand, in the hyper-oxygenation process, this product helps the skin to obtain molecules very similar to prostaglandins 1and 2 which favour tissue perfusion. The main objective of this study has been to evaluate, after the application of this emulsion over a four week time period, the reduction of erythema and peri-lesion hyperkeratosis in venal blood vessel ulcers. But at the same time, as a secondary objective, this study evaluated peri-lesion skin based on other criteria such as pruritus, lesions due to scratching, or edema; this study verified whether treatment of peri-lesion skin influences the cicatrisation of wounds, as well as treatment acceptance by health professionals and patients. Incidences of erythemas and hyperkeratosis totally disappeared in 40% and 50% of those cases, respectively; in those lesions where these symptoms continued after four weeks of treatment, there was a significant reduction in the degree of both erythemas and hyperkeratosis, 25% in each case. These researchers consider that good treatment of peri-lesion skin combined with a standard cure protocol, using «Urgotul®» as the primary dressing, helped to achieve an overall 45% cicatrisation rate plus an 80% total cicatrized surface area. To these results, these researchers noted fine tolerance for the treatment employed and a very high acceptability level for this treatment by health professionals.To sum up, the analysis of the results of this clinical study prove the efficiency of «Corpitol Emulsion»; in addition, its fine tolerance and its high acceptability level make this product adaptable to the treatment of venal blood vessel ulcers in lower limbs when these ulcers are caused by varicose veins or a have a mixed cause with varicose veins as a predominant factor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tormo Maicas, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rochina, Iván Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se expone el seguimiento clínico y documentado de la piel perilesional de cuarenta y cuatro úlceras vasculares venosas, en las que se aplicó una emulsión de ácidos grasos hiperoxigenados. Todos los ancianos incluidos pertenecían al Departamento de Salud nº 3 de la «Consellería de Sanitat de Valencia». El protocolo del estudio y el cuaderno de recogida de datos obtuvieron el informe favorable del «Comité Ético de Investigación Clínica del Hospital de La Plana». Con un porcentaje total de ácido graso esencial linoleico del 60%, CORPITOLINOL® 60 se trata de la emulsión que mayor cantidad aporta de este elemento indispensable para la dermis. En efecto, es el ácido graso esencial de mayor presencia en la piel, además de un elemento vital para su hidratación y viabilidad por formar parte de una estructura fundamental: las laminillas intercelulares de la capa córnea de la epidermis. Por otra parte, en el proceso de hiperoxigenación se obtienen moléculas muy similares a las prostaglandinas 1 y 2 que favorecen la perfusión tisular.  El objetivo principal del estudio ha sido valorar, tras la aplicación de la emulsión durante cuatro semanas, la reducción del eritema y la hiperqueratosis perilesional en las úlceras vasculares venosas. Se han valorado también, como objetivo secundario, la evolución de la piel perilesional bajo otros criterios (prurito, lesiones por rascado, edema), el verificar si el cuidado de la piel perilesional influye en la cicatrización de las lesiones, así como la aceptación del tratamiento por parte de los profesionales sanitarios y pacientes. Los eritemas e hiperqueratosis desaparecieron totalmente en respectivamente el 40 y el 50% de los casos, produciéndose en las lesiones que persistían al cabo de las cuatro semanas de tratamiento, una disminución significativa del grado de eritema e hiperqueratosis (25% en ambos casos). Los investigadores consideraron también que el buen cuidado de la piel perilesional, acompañado de un protocolo estandarizado de curas (con Urgotul® como apósito primario), ayudó a favorecer que se alcanzara una cicatrización total del 45% de las lesiones, con una superficie total cicatrizada del 80%. Todo ello acompañado de una buena tolerancia y una muy buena aceptabilidad del tratamiento por parte de los profesionales sanitarios y pacientes.  En conclusión, el análisis de los resultados de este estudio clínico concluye en la eficacia de Corpitol Emulsión, así como en su buena tolerancia y su buena aceptabilidad que lo convierte en un producto adaptado al tratamiento de las PPL (pieles perilesionales) de las úlceras de miembros inferiores de origen venoso o mixto de predominio venoso(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(4): 266-272, abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Emulsión de ácido linoleico sobre la piel perilesional de úlceras venosas. Acción y efecto cicatricial. Estudio corpus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27774</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5331^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7809^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4732^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31040^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23298^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30505^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
