<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166387</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic evaluation of implantable cardioverter&#150;defibrillators</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of economic evaluation is to determine how available healthcare resources can be used most efficiently. Economic evaluation of implantable cardioverter-defibrillators (ICDs) can involve a prospective study carried out as part of a randomized trial, the analysis of healthcare management databases, or economic modeling. Previous studies have shown that the cost-effectiveness of ICDs depends on a number of factors, in particular on the risk of sudden cardiac death. Analysis of patient subgroups demonstrates that treatment effectiveness varies according to the presence of certain risk factors, principally impaired left ventricular function, irrespective of whether ICDs are used for primary or secondary prevention. Lower cost devices with improved longevity have more favorable costeffectiveness. The effectiveness of ICDs is influenced by the time horizon considered in the analysis. Economic studies can involve estimating how cost-effectiveness varies as the time horizon is increased under different assumptions. Although economic evaluation is a useful tool, decisions on resource allocation are complicated by societal preferences and values, such as equity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-García, F Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la evaluación económica es determinar el uso más eficiente de los recursos sanitarios disponibles. Las evaluaciones económicas de los desfibriladores automáticos implantables (DAI) comprenden estudios prospectivos como parte de un ensayo clínico, análisis de bases de datos clinicoadministrativas y modelos económicos. Los estudios demuestran que la relación coste-efectividad del DAI depende de distintos factores, especialmente el riesgo de muerte súbita cardiaca. En el análisis de subgrupos de pacientes la eficiencia varía según los factores de riesgo, sobre todo, disfunción ventricular izquierda, tanto en prevención primaria como secundaria. La utilización de dispositivos más baratos y de mayor longevidad implica una relación coste-efectividad más atractiva. La eficiencia del DAI es sensible al horizonte temporal considerado en el análisis. Los estudios económicos incluyen estimaciones de coste-efectividad conforme aumenta el horizonte temporal considerando diferentes asunciones. Aunque la evaluación económica es una herramienta útil, la decisión en la distribución de recursos es más compleja debido a las preferencias y los valores sociales, como la equidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.A): 9a-21a, 2008. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166387</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica de los desfibriladores automáticos implantables</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38829^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32142</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
