<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038530</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conjugated linoleic acid lowers hypercholesterolemia but increases the risk for biliary lithiasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The term conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) refers to a series of linoleic acid isomers present in meat and diary products from ruminants that have their double bonds in a conjugated position. The aim of the present work was to study the effects of a CLA isomer, trans-10,cis-12, on cholesterolemia and biliary lithiasis risk in an animal model of diet-induced hypercholesterolemia. For that, two groups of hamsters were fed with a hypercholesterolemic diet supplemented with 0.5% linoleic acid or with the trans-10,cis-12 CLA isomer, respectively. Daily food intake and weight were determined and, 6 weeks later, serum and bile samples were obtained, and livers and spleens were dissected and weighted. Cholesterolemia, hepatic and splenic cholesterol content, and biliary cholesterol phosnolipid and bileacid concentrations were determined; Biliary Lithogenic Index was calculated, and presence of gallstones was assessed. CLA did not modify energetic intake or final body weight, spleen size or spleen cholesterol content, but it did significantly reduce total serum cholesterol (-18%) at the expense of c-LDL (-66%), and it also significantly reduced hepatic content of free cholesterol (-26%), without changes in esterified cholesterol. Besides, CLA produced a 32% increase in biliary cholesterol concentration, a 28% increase in Lithogenic Index, and a higher incidence of biliary lithiasis. Therefore, the present study shows that the CLA trans-10,cis-12 isomer is hypercholesterolemic since it increases, at least in part, cholesterol secretion to the bile. As a consequence, this effect increases the risk for biliary lithiasis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Quintela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puy Portillo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chávarri, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, VM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macarulla, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El término ácido linoleico conjugado (ALC) designa una serie de isómeros del ácido linoleico, presentes en la carne y productos lácteos de rumiantes, que presentan sus dos dobles enlaces en posición conjugada. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue estudiar los efectos de un isómero del ALC, el trans-10, cis-12, sobre la colesterolemia y el riesgo de litiasis biliar en un modelo animal de hipercolesterolemia inducida por dieta. Para ello se utilizaron dos grupos de hámsters alimentados con una dieta hipercolesterolemiante suplementada al 0,5% con ácido linoleico o con el isómero trans-10, cis-12 del ALC, respectivamente. Se midió diariamente su ingesta de alimento y peso corporal y, tras 6 semanas, se obtuvieron muestras de suero y bilis, y se diseccionaron y pesaron sus hígados y bazos. Se determinó la colesterolemia, el contenido hepático y esplénico de colesterol, y la concentración biliar de colesterol, fosfolípidos y sales biliares; se calculó el índice litogénico biliar y se evaluó la presencia de cálculos biliares. El ALC no modificó la ingesta energética, el peso corporal final, ni el tamaño y contenido de colesterol del bazo, pero sí produjo una disminución significativa del colesterol sérico total (-18%) a expensas de la fracción c-LDL (-66%), y también redujo significativamente el contenido hepático de colesterol libre (-26%), sin cambios en el colesterol esterificado. Además, el ALC produjo un incremento del 32% de la concentración biliar de colesterol, un aumento del 28% del índice litogénico y una mayor incidencia de litiasis biliar. Por tanto, el presente estudio demuestra que el isómero trans-10, cis-12 del ALC es hipocolesterolemiante debido, al menos en parte, a que aumenta la secreción de colesterol a bilis. En contrapartida, este efecto aumenta el riesgo de litiasis biliar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(3): 223-228, mayo-jun. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El ácido linoleico conjugado disminuye la hipercolesterolemia pero aumenta el riesgo de litiasis biliar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38234^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38234^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
