<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79376</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Geoposition: a tool used to analyze and diagnose contaminated sites in the province of Jujuy, Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Georeferenced analysis has been imposed in recent years in scientific research as an essential element of the Integrated Risk evaluations,mainly due to the availability of software for data processing and Geographic Information Systems (GIS). Two works the investigations in two different locations in the province of Jujuy, Argentina were georeferenced which allowed classification as contaminated sites. The first element chemistry geoposition analysis was the arsenic. This will quantify their presence in natural waters from different watersheds in the province of Jujuy. The result of this early research was the identification of high levels of total As in surface water andground water in certain areas of the province. The second element was the geo-lead, within the framework of a comprehensive assessment in the town of Abra Pampa, Jujuy, instead of settling for a lead smelter. This study quantified the presence of Pb in blood of children inhabitants of the place. As step integral of two investigations was geoposition of the toxic in both matrices. Are georeferenced in the first investigation a total of225 sampling points for water 3 watersheds that traverse the province, and in the second investigation, 233 of lead levels among children living in the vicinity of the smelter. As end results of this processing of data yielded two thematic maps have allowed a global-spatial perception on the various situations addressed. In each was viewed, among others, the change of the content of toxic respect to the distance from the area pollutants...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubia, GF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bovi Mitre, MG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, AE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avila Carrera, NME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruggeri, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tschambler, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El análisis georreferencial se ha impuesto en los últimos años en la investigación científica como un elemento esencial de las Evaluaciones Integrales sobre el Riesgo, sobre todo debido a la disponibilidad de software de procesamiento de datos y Sistemas de Información Geográfica (GIS). Dos trabajos de investigación realizados en dos localidades distintas de la provincia de Jujuy, Argentina fueron georreferenciados lo que permitió su reconocimiento y tipificación como sitios contaminados. El primer elemento químico analizado georreferencialmente fue el arsénico (As). Para ello se cuantificó su presencia natural en aguas de distintas cuencas acuíferas de la provincia de Jujuy. El resultado de esta primera investigación fue la identificación de elevados niveles de arsénico total en aguas superficiales y subterráneas de determinadas cuencas de la provincia. El segundo elemento georreferenciado fue el plomo, en el marco de una Evaluación Integral en la localidad de Abra Pampa, Jujuy, lugar de asentamiento de una fundición de plomo. En esta investigación se cuantificó la presencia de Pb en sangre de niños pobladores del lugar. Como etapa integral de ambas investigaciones se realizó el georreferenciamiento de cada uno de los tóxicos en ambas matrices. Se georreferenció, en la primera investigación un total de 225 puntos de muestreo de agua de 3 cuencas hídricas que recorren el territorio provincial y, en la segunda investigación, 233 plumbemias de una población infantil que habita en las cercanías de la fundición. Como resultado final de este procesamiento de datos se obtuvieron dos mapas temáticos que permitieron tener una percepción global espacial sobre las distintas situaciones abordadas...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;26(2/3): 131-136, 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Georreferenciamiento: una herramienta utilizada para analizar y diagnosticar sitios contaminados en la provincia de Jujuy- Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28484^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8549</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28484^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37724^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28484^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8034^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8033^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1157^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8033^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8034^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
