<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14065</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Borderline personality disorder in the scientific literature published in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this work is to analyze the scientific literature production on borderline personality disorder in Spain over the 2010-2015 period, making a comparative study of articles collected from scientific journals in the field of psychology from several perspectives: year of publication, type of journal (indexing), type of study, clinical sample, and main topic. After the analysis of 80 articles obtained in WOS, Scopus, Psicodoc, Dialnet, and ISOC databases, it was found that most analysis units appear in type C and D publications in adult population and in theoretical studies, being the prevailing subject different psychotherapeutic strategies, especially Dialectic-Behavioral and Transference-Focused Therapy, although with increasing trends of new procedures applied to BPD population. The scarcity of publications on topics such as psychopharmacological and etiological studies, design of new measuring instruments, or differential diagnosis deserves special attention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Guerrero, María-José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios-Vicario, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar la producción científica sobre el trastorno límite de personalidad (TLP) presente en revistas editadas en España en el lustro 2010-2015, haciendo un estudio comparativo de artículos recogidos de revistas científicas del ámbito de la psicología desde varias perspectivas: año de publicación, tipo de revista (indexación), tipo de estudio, muestra clínica y temática central. Tras analizar los 80 artículos obtenidos mediante el rastreo de las bases de datos WOS, Scopus, Psicodoc, Dialnet e ISOC se ha obtenido que la mayoría de las unidades de análisis utiliza población adulta y la temática predominante aborda distintas estrategias psicoterapéuticas, sobre todo la terapia dialéctico-conductual y la terapia focalizada en la transferencia, aunque con tendencia al alza de nuevos procedimientos aplicados a la población con TLP. En nuestro país destaca la escasez de publicaciones sobre aspectos psicofarmacológicos y etiológicos, diseño de nuevos instrumentos de medida o diagnóstico diferencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;28(3): 147-153, nov. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14065</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El trastorno límite de personalidad en la producción científica publicada en revistas editadas en España</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
