<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134049</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psoriasis and Ischemic Coronary Artery Disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Psoriasis is a chronic inflammatory disease associated with an increased risk of ischemic coronary artery disease (CAD) in some populations. We aimed to determine the association between these 2 diseases in our geographic area. Material and method: We performed a cross-sectional study of patient records between 2005 and 2012 in the database (Abucacis, Datamart) that contains all medical case histories in the province of Castellón, Spain. Patients diagnosed with psoriasis were compared with a control group of patients diagnosed with melanocytic nevus. The prevalence of CAD and the presence or absence of the main cardiovascular risk factors were analyzed in each group. Results: A total of 9181 patients with psoriasis and 21925 with melanocytic nevus were studied. Univariate logistic regression analysis showed that CAD was significantly associated with psoriasis, age (in years), sex, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, and obesity (P &lt; .05). On adjustment for age, sex, and the other cardiovascular risk factors, multivariate regression analysis established that psoriasis was independently associated with CAD (P &lt; .029). Conclusion: Our findings in a large sample of patients in a Mediterranean area support the hypothesis that patients in this population have an increased risk of ischemic CAD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pitarch-Bort, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez-Pastor, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valcuende-Cavero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano-Navarro, C. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomas-Cabedo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mahiques-Santos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La psoriasis es una enfermedad inflamatoria crónica que se ha asociado a un aumento de riesgo de enfermedad arterial coronaria isquémica (EACI) en algunas poblaciones. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue determinar la asociación entre psoriasis y EACI en nuestro medio. Material y método: Se realizó un estudio transversal en la provincia de Castellón con datos procedentes del sistema de información asistencial Abucasis (Datamart) desde el ano&#152; 2005 hasta el 2012. Se seleccionó a los pacientes con psoriasis y como grupo control a los pacientes con nevus melanocítico. Se estudió la prevalencia de EACI en ambos grupos estratificando por los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Resultados: Se estudiaron 9.181 pacientes con psoriasis y 21.925 con nevus melanocítico. En el análisis de regresión logística univariante la EACI se asoció significativamente a las variables psoriasis, edad (en anos), &#152; sexo, hipertensión, diabetes mellitus, dislipidemia y obesidad (p &lt; 0,05). En el análisis de regresión logística multivariante, tras ajustar por edad, sexo y el resto de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular, se establece una relación independiente entre la presencia de EACI y psoriasis (p &lt; 0,029). Conclusión: Nuestros resultados apoyan la existencia de mayor riesgo de EACI en pacientes con psoriasis en una población amplia del área mediterránea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;106(2): 112-116, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psoriasis y enfermedad arterial coronaria isquémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9695^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9695^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
