<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87336</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on the treatment of Fabry&#146;s disease: pathophysiological concepts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Fabry&#146;s disease is a consequence of the deficiency of lysosomal alpha-galactosidase A, which gives rise to excessive depositing of glycosphingolipids in endothelial cells, smooth muscle cells in vessels, podocytes, neurons, etc. The symptoms begin in childhood, with neuropathic pain, and progress towards kidney and heart failure, as well as cerebrovascular  accidents from the third decade of life onwards. Development. This review presents the changes in the pathophysiological concepts that have been acquired in the nine years since enzyme replacement therapy started to be employed. The earlier enzyme replacement is started, the more effective it is, which thereby calls for a review of the criteria for its use in patients. Furthermore, the need for concomitant treatments is also evaluated based on the pathophysiology of the disease.  Conclusions. The joint use of enzyme replacement therapy, antiproteinuric drugs, statins and acetylsalicylic acid must be evaluated as initial treatment in all patients with Fabry&#146;s disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Politei, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Fabry es la resultante de la deficiencia de alfa-galactosidasa A lisosomal, lo que genera un depósito excesivo de glucoesfingolípidos en células endoteliales, musculares lisas de los vasos, podocitos, neuronas, etc. Los síntomas se inician en la niñez, con dolor neuropático, para progresar a la insuficiencia renal, cardíaca y accidentes cerebrovasculares desde la tercera década de vida. Desarrollo. Esta revisión presenta los cambios en los conceptos fisiopatológicos que se han adquirido después de nueve  años de inicio de la terapia de reemplazo enzimático. La sustitución enzimática muestra utilidad cuanto más temprano se inicie, lo que lleva a revisar los criterios para su uso en los pacientes. Por otro lado, se evalúa la necesidad de tratamientos  concomitantes basándose en la fisiopatología de la enfermedad. Conclusión. Se debe evaluar el uso conjunto de terapia de reemplazo enzimático, antiproteinúricos, estatinas y ácido acetilsalicílico como tratamiento inicial en todos los pacientes con enfermedad de Fabry (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;51(9): 561-570, nov. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Fabry: conceptos fisiopatológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30299^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31710^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30299^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23273^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
