<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137648</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-5887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The beginning of life: bioethical and legal discourse in Mexican Legislation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In accordance with Article 124 of the Mexican Constitution, all powers not reserved to the federation are understood to be granted to the states of the Republic, and in accordance with the federal pact, civil matters are reserved to the states while in issues health coexists concurrence competence. As we know, most of bioethical issues have civil or family implications as well as other implications related to health issues. Therefore, depending on the approach that is given to bioethical issues, we will find different results. In Mexico, the civil perspective has been privileged, resulting in the appearance of different legal expressions that end up being dissimilar and sometimes even contradictory. In our opinion, the legal implications of biotechnology should be addressed from a national perspective by a specific legislation, in order exactly to avoid what is now occurring, that is to avoid the contradictions and/or legal absurdities among the different local legislations. This paper analyzes the inconsistencies and absurdities that have been generated under this civil perspective in different local legislations regarding bioethical issues (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza C, Héctor A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De acuerdo con el artículo 124 de la Constitución mexicana, todas aquellas facultades no reservadas a la federación se entienden concedidas a los estados de la república así, la materia civil está reservada a los estados mientras que en temas de salud coexiste una concurrencia competencial. Como sabemos, la mayoría de los temas bioéticos tienen por un lado implicaciones civiles o familiares y por el otro implicaciones relacionadas con temas de salud. En consecuencia, dependiendo del enfoque que se le dé a los temas bioéticos encontraremos resultados diferentes. En México, se ha privilegiado la perspectiva civil, lo que ha ocasionado que surjan diversas expresiones jurídicas que terminan siendo dispares y en algunos casos contradictorias. En nuestra opinión, las implicaciones jurídicas de la biotecnología deberían ser abordadas desde una perspectiva nacional, mediante una legislación especializada, a fin de evitar, lo que ahora ocurre, es decir las contradicciones y/o absurdos jurídicos entre las diferentes legislaciones locales. En este trabajo se analizan, precisamente, las inconsistencias y absurdos que se han generado en diversas legislaciones locales, en virtud de esta visión civilista de los temas bioéticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. bioét. derecho;(33): 28-43, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El inicio de la vida: discurso bioético-jurídico en la Legislación Mexicana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38821^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2986</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37709^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36295^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
