<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140282</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The use of ultrasound in regional anesthesia requires the acquisition of new knowledge and skills not only by anesthesiologists in training but also by anesthesiologists experienced in neurostimulation-guided peripheral nerve blocks. We studied the effect of training on 2 anesthesiologists who were skilled in neurostimulation-guided regional anesthesia. Patients and methods: Observational, controlled study of the first 45 ultrasound-guided axillary blocks of the brachial plexus performed by two anesthesiologists with expertise in the neurostimulation-guided axillary procedure. For analysis of results, groups of 15 patients from each anesthesiologist were assigned consecutively (G15, G30 and G45). We assessed the duration of the block procedure, the incidence of vascular puncture and effectiveness of the block. Results: The mean (SD) duration of the procedure was 547 (16) seconds in G15. It was significantly lower in G30 and G45 (393 [104] seconds and 397 [111] seconds). The incidence of vascular puncture dropped significantly after completion of the first 15 blocks, from 20% in G15 to 3% in G30 and 0% in G45. The results of the block procedure also significantly improved after the first 15 blocks: 89% effectiveness in G15, 93% in G30, and 100% in G45. The variables assessed were similar for the 2 anesthesiologists. Conclusions: For an anesthesiologist with experience establishing a conventional axillary brachial plexus block using a nerve stimulator, 15 ultrasound-guided axillary blocks are required before good results can be expected with the new procedure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sala-Blanch, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Cuenca, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cedó, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morros, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El empleo de la ecografía en anestesia regional requiere de nuevos conocimientos y habilidades. Este aprendizaje es aplicable, no sólo a los anestesiólogos en formación, sino también a los anestesiólogos experimentados en técnicas de bloqueo periférico con neuroestimulación. Estudiamos el efecto de esta formación en dos profesionales expertos en anestesia regional guiada por neuroestimulación. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional controlado de los primeros 45 bloqueos ecoguiados del plexo braquial por abordaje axilar realizados por dos anestesiólogos expertos en técnica axilar guiada por neuroestomulación. Para analizar los resultados los pacientes fueron divididos en tres grupos de 30 tomados de forma correlativa (15 de cada anestesiólogo) y comparándolos entre si (G15, G30 y G45). Se valoró el tiempo de realización del bloqueo, la incidencia de punciones vasculares y la eficacia del bloqueo. Resultados: El tiempo de realización del bloqueo fue de 547 ± 16 segundos para G15 reduciéndose significativamente en G30 y G45 (393 ± 104 seg y 397 ± 111 seg). La incidencia de punción vascular se redujo significativamente tras la realización de los 15 primeros bloqueos, pasando del 20% en G15, al 3% en G30 y finalmente al 0% en G45. El resultado del bloqueo también mejoró significativamente tras los primeros 15 bloqueos, pasando del 89% de eficacia al 93% y al 100% para G15, G30 y G45 respectivamente. No hubo diferencias entre los anestesiólogos en los distintos parámetros estudiados. Conclusiones: Un anestesiólogo experto en el bloqueo axilar del plexo braquial clásico mediante neuroestimulación precisa de 15 bloqueos axilares ecoguiados para obtener unos buenos resultados con dicha técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(2): 74-79, feb. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo axilar del plexo braquial guiado por ecografía. Curva de aprendizaje y resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55680^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
