<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87096</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Optimization of proteomic techniques for the study of the common bean Phaseolus vulgaris L</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study is the optimization of two-dimensional electrophoresis (2-DE) technique and the evaluation of different protein extraction methods to obtain and study the proteome of the common bean Phaseolus vulgaris. As biological material, seed and leaf tissues have been used. These tissues belong to the Calima line of the Andean gene pool and to the Ica-Pijao line of the Mesoamerican pool of this species, respectively. Three protein extraction methods have been evaluated: TCA-acetone, phenol and the commercial kit «clean up».  Two-dimensional electrophoresis gels have been optimized for a gradient of pH 4-7 in the first dimension. The results show that phenol is the optimal method of seed protein extraction while the optimal method of leaf protein extraction is based on the precipitation kit. This study determines the most appropriate protocol of precipitation for each tissue of Phaseolus, and settles one of the most controversial topics of the technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borajo López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La finalidad del presente trabajo es la optimización de la técnica de electroforesis bidimensional (2-DE) y la evaluación de los diferentes métodos de extracción de proteínas para la obtención y estudio del proteoma de la judía común Phaseolus vulgaris. Como material biológico se han usado tejidos de semilla y hoja de la línea Calima perteneciente al acervo genético andino y de la línea ICA-Pijao perteneciente al acervo mesoamericano de esta especie, respectivamente. Se han evaluado tres métodos de extracción de proteínas: TCA-acetona, fenol y el  kit comercial clean up. La electroforesis bidimensional se ha optimizado para geles con un gradiente de pH 4-7 en la primera dimensión. Los resultados obtenidos ponen de manifiesto que el método óptimo de extracción de semilla es el fenol y para la hoja, el idóneo es el basado en el kit de precipitación. Con este estudio se puede ver cuál es el protocolo de precipitación más adecuado para cada tejido de Phaseolus por lo que con estos resultados se intenta dar solución a uno de los temas más controvertidos de la técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;66(4): 217-222, oct.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Optimización de técnicas proteómicas para el estudio de la judía común Phaseolus vulgaris L</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23625^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15075^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11267^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35830^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
