<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74029</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Participatory ergonomics: a model for the prevention of occupational musculoskeletal disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Participatory ergonomics is an intervention strategy actingon physical load exposures occurring in occupational settings,scarcely known in Spain but with a number of experiences andevidences coming from other countries. There are severalreasons justifying the interest of this approach. First,participatory ergonomics focuses on one of the categories ofoccupational exposures with the largest impact on workers&#146;health in a majority of countries all over the world, in terms ofincidence, prevalence and disability. Secondly, basic principlein participatory ergonomics is empowerment of workers forthem to participate identifying risks and injuries caused byphysical exposures at work as well as proposing andevaluating proper control measures for each situation. Thirdly,it allows dealing and solving a number of problems withoutthe use of complex technical protocols. From a public healthperspective, participatory ergonomics is a largely tried modelof community empowerment for the control of (occupational)factors affecting health and wellbeing. In this paper we revisesome basic principles of participatory ergonomics, wecomment on the keys leading to success or failing of theinterventions and we present some main results coming fromparticipatory ergonomics experiences developed for a longtime in countries such as Canada, United Kingdom,Netherlands or Finland(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sevilla, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ronda, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gadea, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Genís, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ergonomía participativa es una estrategia de intervenciónsobre los riesgos por carga física en los lugares de trabajoescasamente conocida en España, aunque en otros países secuenta con numerosas experiencias y evidencias en estecampo. Son varias las razones que justifican su interés. En primerlugar, aborda una de las categorías de riesgos laboralesque mayor impacto tiene sobre la salud de los trabajadores enla mayoría de países, tanto en términos de incidencia, como deprevalencia o incapacidad. En segundo lugar, el principio básicode la ergonomía participativa es la capacitación de los trabajadorespara que participen tanto en la identificación de losriesgos y daños a la salud derivados de las exposiciones acarga física en el trabajo como en la propuesta y evaluación delas medidas de corrección adecuadas a cada situación. En tercerlugar, permite el tratamiento y la solución de muchos problemassin necesidad de complicados protocolos técnicos.Desde el punto de vista de la salud pública, la ergonomía participativaes un modelo muy ensayado de empoderamiento(empowerment) de la población para controlar los determinantesdel entorno (laboral) que afectan a su salud y bienestar. Eneste trabajo se revisan algunos de los principios básicos de losprogramas de ergonomía participativa, se comentan las clavesrelacionadas con el éxito o fracaso de los programas y se presentanalgunos resultados principales de las experiencias deergonomía participativa que se vienen desarrollando desdehace años en países como Canadá, Reino Unido, Holanda oFinlandia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(4): 509-518, jul.-ago.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74029</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ergonomía participativa: empoderamiento de los trabajadores para la prevención de trastornos musculoesqueléticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6956^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6956^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3722</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
