<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117897</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the prevalence of anemia in patients admitted for COPD exacerbations, the characteristics of these patients, the associated factors with the presence of anemia, and the influence of anemia on survival. Patients and methods: A cohort prospective observational study of patients admitted for COPD exacerbation. Demographic data, clinical characteristics, lung function tests, blood tests and bioelectrical impedance were analyzed. After discharge, monitoring was performed to estimate survival and determinants of mortality. Results: We evaluated 106 patients (93 males), mean age 71 ± 9 years, mean BMI 25.7 ± 5.6 kg/m2 and mean FEV1 39 ± 13%. 88.9% were smokers or former smokers. The prevalence of anemia was 37.7%. The most frequent comorbidities were dyslipidemia (73.6%), hypertension (59.4%) and heart disease (59.4%). The mean Charlson index was 5.9 ± 1.4 and the average META index, measured by bioimpedance, 22.3 ± 7.8. The logistic regression analysis showed that associated factors with anemia were age, creatinine levels, iron and META index. The median survival of patients with anemia was 31 ± 4.4  months versus 48.1 ± 2.9 in those without anemia (p &lt;0.001). The determinants of mortality were BMI and creatinine levels.  onclusions: A high percentage of COPD patients admitted with an exacerbation have anemia. Factors associated with the presence of anemia in these patients are age, iron and creatinine levels and META index. The presence of anemia has a significant impact on survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juárez Morales, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castuera Gil, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Oteyza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Díez, J de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la prevalencia de anemia en pacientes con EPOC ingresados por exacerbación de su enfermedad, características de estos enfermos, factores asociados a la existencia de anemia e influencia de ésta en la supervivencia. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio de cohortes observacional, prospectivo, realizado en pacientes con EPOC ingresados por exacerbación. Se analizaron datos demográficos, características clínicas, estudio funcional respiratorio, impedanciometría bioeléctrica y analítica sanguínea. Tras el alta se realizó seguimiento para calcular supervivencia y factores determinantes de mortalidad. Resultados: Se evaluaron 106 pacientes (93 varones), con edad media 71 ± 9 años, IMC medio 25,7 ± 5,6 kg/m2 y FEV1 medio 39 ± 13%. El 88,9% eran fumadores o exfumadores. La prevalencia de anemia fue 37,7%. Las comorbilidades más frecuentes fueron: dislipemia (73,6%), hipertensión arterial (59,4%) y cardiopatía (59,4%). El índice de Charlson medio fue  de 5,9 ± 1,4 y el índice META medio, medido por bioimpedancia, de 22,3 ± 7,8. El análisis de regresión logística mostró quelos factores determinantes de anemia fueron: edad, niveles de hierro y creatinina e índice META. La supervivencia media de los pacientes que tenían anemia fue 31 ± 4,4 meses frente a 48,1 ± 2,9 en los que no tenían anemia (p &lt; 0,001). Los factores determinantes de mortalidad fueron IMC y niveles de creatinina. Conclusiones: Un elevado porcentaje de pacientes con EPOC ingresados por una exacerbación tienen anemia. Los factores asociados a la existencia de anemia en estos pacientes son edad, niveles de hierro y creatinina e índice META. La presencia de anemia tiene un impacto significativo en la supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;16(2): 37-41, abr.-jun. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anemia en pacientes ingresados por una exacerbación de EPOC. Influencia sobre el pronóstico de la enfermedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11520^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
