<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053323</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Narrow band UVB therapy in early stage mycosis fungoides. A study of 23 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Phototherapy is effective for mycosis fungoides. Narrow band UVB (UVB1) therapy is being used as an alternative to PUVA therapy for its efficacy and less adverse events. The objective of the study was to determine the efficacy of narrow band UVB therapy in early stage mycosis fungoides.                 Methods. It is a retrospective study of 23 patients with stage IB mycosis fungoides that have received UVB1 therapy following the phototherapy protocol of the Spanish Photobiology Group.                 Results. Thirteen patients (57 %) had a complete response, eight patients (35 %) had a partial response and two patients (8 %) did not respond. Half of the patients with complete response (n = 6) relapsed after one year of follow-up.                 Conclusions. We consider that UVB1 therapy is a good alternative for treatment of early stage mycosis fungoides, although the disease-free period is short</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrizosa-Esquivel, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coronel-Pérez, I. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho-Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La fototerapia ha demostrado ser de utilidad en la micosis fungoide. La radiación UVB de banda estrecha (UVB1) está siendo utilizada como alternativa a la radiación UVA por su eficacia y menores efectos secundarios. El objetivo del estudio fue determinar la eficacia del tratamiento de la fototerapia con UVB1 en los estadios iniciales de la micosis fungoide.                 Métodos. Estudio retrospectivo sobre 23 pacientes con micosis fungoide en estadio IB que habían recibido fototerapia con UVB, según el protocolo de fototerapia del Grupo Español de Fotobiología.                 Resultados. Se obtuvo respuesta completa en 13 pacientes (57 %), respuesta parcial en 8 (35 %) y no respondieron 2 (8 %). La mitad de los pacientes con respuesta completa que finalizaron el año de seguimiento (n = 6) presentaron recidivas.                 Conclusiones. Consideramos que la fototerapia con UVB1 es una buena opción en el tratamiento de las fases iniciales de la micosis fungoide, aunque el intervalo libre de enfermedad no es prolongado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;98(4): 259-264, mayo 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con UVB de banda estrecha de los estadios iniciales de la micosis fungoide. Estudio de 23 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29031^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14866^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
