<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91621</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Training of interdisciplinary teams in obstetric emergencies through clinical simulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe the healthcare team training in obstetric emergencies using clinical simulation with an interdisciplinary approach, developed at the Hospital virtual Valdecilla. Material and methods. The program was aimed at health professionals involved in emergency obstetric care (obstetricians and gynecologists, anesthesiologists, intensivists and midwives). A working team was established to define the objectives, design the scenarios, and coordinate the completion of each course. Two simulation rooms were available with patient simulators, control rooms and audiovisual recording systems, an analysis room, a multipurpose classroom, and diverse medical and surgical equipment. To analyze the results of the program, the participants completed an evaluation survey. Results. A total of 30 members of clinical teams underwent training in the clinical entities most frequently involved in cases of maternal mortality (postpartum hemorrhage, amniotic fluid embolism and eclampsia), selected from the results of a survey of maternal death mailed to 69 Spanish hospitals. Each course consisted of three clinical cases performed in the operating room, postpartum and birthing room, followed by a debriefing session. Participants rated the courses as highly useful, highlighted the opportunity provided by clinical simulation to practice without risk and to train teamwork skills, and would recommend their peers to undergo the same training. Conclusions. Training of healthcare teams in obstetric emergencies using simulation with an interdisciplinary approach provides safe and effective practice of diagnostic and treatment algorithms, as well as of communication and teamwork skills, before these situations are met in daily practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Odriozola Feu, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestre Alonso, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Pinto, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral Vicente Mazariegos, Ignacio del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Sesmero, José Ramón de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir el programa de entrenamiento de equipos sanitarios en urgencias obstétricas graves mediante simulación clínica con un abordaje interdisciplinar, desarrollado en el Hospital virtual Valdecilla. Material y métodos. El programa fue dirigido a los profesionales implicados en la atención de la urgencia obstétrica (obstetras y ginecólogos, anestesiólogos, intensivistas y matronas). Se constituyó un equipo de trabajo para definir los objetivos, diseñar los escenarios y coordinar la realización de cada curso. Se dispuso dos salas de simulación con simuladores de pacientes, salas de control y sistemas de grabación audiovisual, un aula de análisis, un aula polivalente, y diverso material médico-quirúrgico. Para analizar los resultados de la actividad los participantes completaron una encuesta de evaluación. Resultados. Un total de 30 miembros de los equipos clínicos realizaron el entrenamiento en las entidades clínicas más frecuentemente implicadas en los casos de mortalidad materna (hemorragia postparto, embolismo de líquido amniótico y eclampsia), seleccionadas de los resultados de una encuesta de muerte materna enviada por correo a 69 hospitales españoles. Cada curso consistió en 3 casos clínicos realizados en quirófano, sala de puerperio y paritorio, seguidos de una sesión de análisis de la experiencia vivida. Los resultados valoraron como muy útil la experiencia vivida, destacaron la oportunidad que la simulación clínica brinda para practicar sin riesgo y entrenar el trabajo en equipo, y recomendarían su realización a otros compañeros. Conclusiones. El entrenamiento de profesionales sanitarios en urgencias obstétricas mediante simulación clínica con un abordaje interdisciplinar permite una práctica segura y efectiva de los algoritmos de diagnóstico y tratamiento, y de las habilidades de comunicación y trabajo en equipo, antes de enfrentarse a estas situaciones en la práctica diaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(12): 618-524, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrenamiento de equipos interdisciplinares en urgencias obstétricas mediante simulación clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54365^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28136^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
