<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84426</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and classification on intellectual disability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnosis of intellectual disability and classification systems have been a maintopic of interest to all those who try to understand this phenomenon and get a little closerto the complex intervention in this field. The aim of this article is to undertake a short historical tour on the implications, dangers and benefits of classification systems in the fieldof intellectual disability to finally address the multidimensional approach with whichhealth and services professionals are approaching now to that disability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, L. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdugo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico de la discapacidad intelectual así como los sistemas de clasificación dela misma han constituido un tema de interés principal para todos aquellos que intentancomprender este fenómeno y acercarse un poco más al complejo entramado de intervenciónen este campo. El objetivo de este artículo consiste en realizar un pequeño recorridosobre las implicaciones, peligros y beneficios de los sistemas de clasificación en el campode la discapacidad intelectual para finalmente abordar el enfoque multidimensional con elque los profesionales de la salud y los servicios se acercan actualmente a la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;17(2): 143-152, ene.  2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y clasificación en discapacidadintelectual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33554^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28445</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
