<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98175</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vocal cord dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract. Vocal cord dysfunction (VCD) is a well-defined clinical condition, which often goes unnoticed. The patients generally have a previous diagnosis of asthma, with a history of multiple visits to the emergency services and anti-asthmatic treatments without clinical results. We present the case of a 45-year old woman, nurse assistant, previously diagnosed of  bronchial asthma, who consulted several times in the emergency service, and was treated with bronchodilators and corticosteroids with scarce clinical response. She was sent to Pneumology for study and diagnosed of VCD, with subsequent clinical improvement when initiating an adequate medical treatment. A review of the literature published up to date has been made (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Culebras Amigo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Lessmann, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. La disfunción de cuerdas vocales (DCV) es una entidad clínica bien definida, que a menudo suele pasar desapercibida. Los pacientes generalmente tienen un diagnóstico previo de asma, con historia de múltiples visitas a urgencias y tratamientos antiasmáticos sin resultados clínicos. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 45 años, auxiliar de enfermería, diagnosticada previamente de asma bronquial, que consultó en varias oportunidades a urgencias, siendo tratada  con broncodilatadores y corticoides con escasa respuesta clínica. Fue remitida a Neumología para estudio y se diagnosticó de DCV, con posterior mejoría clínica al iniciar un tratamiento médico adecuado. Se realiza una revisión de la literatura publicada hasta la fecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;13(2): 85-87, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfunción de cuerdas vocales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15228^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28119^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
