<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111250</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of the psychometric properties of the Detection of Emotional Distress Scale in cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate and alleviate the emotional distress suffered by advanced cancer patients, simple screening methods that can be easily used by health staff and easily understood by patients are required. The objective of this multicenter study was to analyze the psychometric properties and clinical utility of the Detection of Emotional Distress (DED) scale in advanced cancer patients attending a palliative care unit. Methods The DED scale was administered to 105 advanced cancer patients attended in five palliative care units in Catalonia (Spain).Results A total of 58.3% of the patients had moderate to severe emotional distress, a result similar to those of other scales such as the emotional thermometer. Statistical analysis of ROC curves suggested that the cutoff for the detection of emotional distress by the DED scale was equivalent to a score of &amp;#8805; 9 points, with a sensitivity and specificity above 75%.ConclusionsThe DED scale is useful and easy to use in the identification of emotional distress in advanced cancer patients attended in palliative care units. This scale could also be applied in other patients and health care fields, such as patients with chronic diseases, home care, and primary care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sirgo, Agustina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Barboteo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaus, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limonero, Joaquín T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayés, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maté-Méndez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viel, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Con el fin de valorar y aliviar el malestar emocional al final de la vida, se necesitan instrumentos de cribado sencillos, de fácil uso por los sanitarios y comprensibles por los enfermos. En el presente estudio multicéntrico se analiza la utilidad clínica del cuestionario de Detección del Malestar Emocional (DME) en enfermos hospitalizados con cáncer avanzado. Métodos Para determinar las propiedades psicométricas de la escala se administró, a la vez que otros instrumentos y procedimientos, a 105 pacientes con enfermedad oncológica avanzada ingresados en unidades de cuidados paliativos de cinco hospitales de Cataluña. Resultados Se observó que el 58,3% presentaba malestar emocional moderado o muy intenso, similar al objetivado con otras escalas, como el termómetro emocional. El análisis estadístico de las curvas ROC sugiere que el punto de corte para la detección de malestar emocional que muestra el DME equivale a una puntuación &amp;#8805; 9 puntos, con una sensibilidad y una especificidad superiores al 75%.ConclusionesEl DME es útil y de fácil manejo para la identificación del malestar emocional en los enfermos oncológicos avanzados ingresados en unidades de cuidados paliativos. Se sugiere que esta escala también se podría aplicar a otros enfermos y ámbitos de la atención sanitaria, por ejemplo la atención domiciliaria o la atención primaria en enfermos crónicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(2): 145-152, mar.-abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111250</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las propiedades psicométricas del cuestionario de Detección de Malestar Emocional (DME) en pacientes oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
