<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157291</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interventions directed at eating habits and physical activity using the Transtheoretical Model: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The multi-behavioral Transtheoretical Model (TTM) addresses multiple behaviors and it is a promising strategy to control multifactorial morbidities, such as chronic diseases. The results obtained using the TTM are positive, but are not consistently methodical. Objectives: The aim of this study was to systematically review the effectiveness of the Transtheoretical Model in multi-behavioral interventions for changing eating habits and levels of physical activity. Methods: A search on PubMed and SciELO databases was performed with inclusion criteria set for intervention studies before 2016 using the Transtheoretical Model for more than one behavior, including eating habits and/or engaging in physical activity. Results and conclusion: Eighteen studies were identified; there was a predominance of randomized clinical trials, studies conducted in the United States, and the use of the Internet and/or telephone. The selected studies were aimed at changing eating behaviors; five of the studies did not address physical activity. The main results were reduction of fat consumption, an increase in the consumption of fruit and vegetables, and increases in physical activity, which are progressions in the stages of change and weight loss identified by the Transtheoretical Model. However, the studies showed methodological weaknesses, including high participant loss and the omission of information about randomization and blinding (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bedeschi, Lydiane Bragunci</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menezes, Mariana Carvalho de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes, Aline Cristine Souza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Luana Caroline dos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el Modelo Tranteórico multiconductual aborda distintas conductas y es una estrategia prometedora para el abordaje de patologías multifactoriales, sobre todo en las enfermedades crónicas. Los resultados iniciales de su empleo han sido favorables, pero no han sido probados con rigor. Objetivos: el objetivo de este estudio fue realizar una revisión sistemática de la eficacia del Modelo Transteórico en el cambio de hábitos dietéticos y en el grado de actividad física con intervenciones en varias áreas de la conducta. Métodos: se realizó una búsqueda en PubMed y SCieLO utilizando como criterios de búsqueda estudios de intervención realizados antes de 2016 y que incluyeran más de un hábito, incluyendo hábitos alimentarios y/o actividad física. Resultados y conclusión: se identificaron 18 estudios, con un predominio de ensayos clínicos aleatorizados, estudios realizaos en Estados Unidos de Norteamérica, y uso de Internet y/o teléfono. Los estudios seleccionados tenían como meta el cambio en los hábitos dietéticos. En 5 de los estudios no se incluía la actividad física. El principal resultado de la intervención fue la disminución en el consumo de grasa y el aumento en la ingestión de frutas y verduras, así como un aumento en la actividad física. Estos cambios supusieron progresos en la pérdida de peso. Sin embargo, los trabajos eran metodológicamente débiles, incluyendo una alta tasa de abandonos, y falta de información sobre la aleatorización y cómo se realizó el estudio ciego (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(5): 1194-1204, sept.-oct. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157291</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervenciones dirigidas a los hábitos alimenticios y la actividad física mediante el Modelo Transteórico: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
