<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62809</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Waldenström macroglobulinemia associated with cutaneous lesions and type I cryoglobulinemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Waldenström macroglobulinemia is a blood dyscrasia characterized by monoclonal proliferation of Bcells in the bone marrow, lymph nodes, and spleen. Patients with this disease show elevated serum levels and tissue deposition of monoclonal immunoglobulin (Ig) M produced by these aberrant cells. We present the case of a patient with Waldenström macroglobulinemia who suffered cutaneous lesions resulting from deposition of k light chains of IgM and clinical manifestations secondary to associated type I cryoglobulinemia. We discuss the different pathological cutaneous processes caused by IgM in Waldenström macroglobulinemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>España, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Idoate, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Panizo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmo, J. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La macroglobulinemia de Waldenström (MW) es una discrasia sanguínea caracterizada por la proliferación monoclonal de células linfoplasmocitarias en la médula ósea, ganglios linfáticos y bazo. Estos pacientes tienen niveles elevados en suero y depósito en tejidos de la inmunoglobulina (Ig) M, de tipo monoclonal, producida por estas células aberrantes. Presentamos el caso de un paciente afecto de MW, con lesiones cutáneas debidas al depósito de cadenas ligeras Kappa de IgM y con manifestaciones clínicas secundarias a la crioglobulinemia tipo I que el paciente tenía asociada. Discutimos los distintos proceso patológicos cutáneos provocados por la IgM en la MW (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(2): 138-144, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Macroglobulinemia de Waldenström asociada a lesiones cutáneas y crioglobulinemia tipo I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22207^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30383^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30383^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30383^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3466^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29203^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24758^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29510^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30383^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24758^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3466^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10454^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
