<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121701</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determination of the bone age by the oss ification centers of the first and third fingers &#150; A comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to compare the epiphyseal events of the proximal phalanx of the thumb with the medial and distal phalanxes of the third finger in the determination of the bone age. The sample comprised 131 hand-wrist radiographs of males and females selected from the archive of the Orthodontics Clinic of the School of Dentistry of Araçatuba &#150; UNESP and from PROFIS/Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial Anomalies-USP. The ossification centers were analyzed by only one examiner. The comparison between the osseous events of the proximal phalanx of the thumb and the medial and distal phalanxes of the third finger has shown a 91.6% agreement. Evaluation of the radiographs that did not show any agreement revealed that 1.5%presented the thumb in a more advanced maturational stage when compared to the third finger, while 6.8% showed a more advanced level of bone development when the third finger was analyzed. Comparison using the McNemar test (p = 0.07) revealed no statistically significant difference in the determination of bone age when either the first or third fingers were used. The findings show that the epiphyseal stages are coincident and, therefore, can be used independently in the evaluation of maturational stage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tulio Silva, Lara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sánches, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertoz, Francisco Antônio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Lauris, José Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira de Moraes, Bruna Condi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo consistió en la comparación de las modificaciones epifisarias ocurridas en la falange proximal del 1º dedo y falanges media y distal del 3º dedo para la determinación de la edad ósea. La muestra se basó en 131 radiografías cárpales de pacientes de ambos sexos seleccionados de la clínica de ortodoncia de FOA-UNESP y HRAC-USP, Brasil. Los centros de osificación fueron analizados individualmente por un único examinador. La comparación entre los cambios óseos ocurridos en la falange proximal del 1º dedo y falanges media y distal del 3º dedo mostro una similitud del 91,6%. La evaluación de las radiografías que no presentaron similitud revelo que 1,5%presentaban el 1º dedo en una fase de maduración más avanzada al ser comparado son el 3º dedo. Ya el 6,8% exhibió un nivel más maduro del desarrollo óseo cuando el 3º dedo fue analizado. La comparación por el test de McNemar reveló un valor de p=0,07, reflejando que no hay diferencia estadísticamente significativa entre las diferencias presentadas en la determinación de la edad ósea por el 1º o 3º dedos. Los resultados mostraron que los estadios epifisarios en estos dos centros de referencia fueron coincidentes, y por tanto pueden ser utilizados de manera independiente en la evaluación de la fase de maduración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);50(1): 352-358, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación de la edad ósea mediante los centros de osificación presentes en el 1º y 3º dedos &#150; Estudio Comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23231^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23151^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10148^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5521^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
