<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106386</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The pathophysiological changes that determine the severity of dengue are still not wellknown, therefore it is important to study the probable relationship with the host genetic. Methods: We analyzed the possible association between the Fc RIIa polymorphism and clinical signs in individuals who suffered dengue infection in 2006, using contingency tables. Results: We found that bleeding was signi&amp;#64257;cantly associated to Fc RIIa H/H131 genotype (80%).Conclusion: Our results suggest that in clinical dengue infection the bleeding could be associated toFc RIIa H/H131 genotype (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Lizet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Ana B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán, María G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Gissel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Los cambios fisiopatológicos que determinan la severidad del dengue son aún poco conocidos, de ahí la importancia de aclarar su posible relación con la genética del huésped.  Métodos Se determinó la posible asociación entre las variantes genéticas del receptor Fc&amp;#947;RIIa y signos clínicos en individuos que sufrieron la infección por dengue en 2006 empleando tablas de contingencia.  Resultados Solo el sangrado mostró asociación significativa para el genotipo HH (80%).  Conclusiones En la infección clínica por dengue el sangrado podría estar relacionado al receptor Fc&amp;#947;RIIa-HH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;30(10): 621-623, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismo del receptor FcgammaRIIa y su posible relación con las manifestaciones clínicas del dengue</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33342^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3727^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3728^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
