<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136508</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Latest advances in pancreatic tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pancreatic cancer (PC) continues to have a very poor prognosis. New epidemiological trials suggest that statins could play a protective role in smokers, while HbsAg-positive hepatitis B virus could be a risk factor. Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) is the main diagnostic tool for PC, and new technologies associated with this technique have emerged, such as quantitative elastography, intravenous contrasts or, more recently, LASER confocal endomicroscopy. New markers in urine or pancreatic juice have appeared to distinguish between PC and chronic pancreatitis. The role of the &#147;on site&#148; cytopathologist to increase the diagnostic yield of EUS-guided pancreatic sampling is completely supported by new prospective trials and some multicenter studies have been reported that compare the standard cytologic needles with the new procore-histology needles. Regarding cystic pancreatic tumors, most studies have aimed to validate the 2012 Sendai international guidelines and to ascertain predictive factors of malignancy in cystic lesions, mainly intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm (IPMN). The role of intracystic CEA levels in determining malignancy is challenged. From a therapeutic point of view, EUS-guided radiofrequency ablation of cystic and solid lesions has emerged as a feasible and safe procedure in specific circumstances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lariño Noia, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de páncreas (CP) continúa siendo una entidad de pésimo pronóstico. Estudios epidemiológicos sugieren que las estatinas en los fumadores podrían constituir un factor protector mientras que la positividad del HbsAg del virus de la hepatitis B podría ser un factor de riesgo. La ultrasonografía endoscópica (USE) continúa siendo el pilar fundamental diagnóstico y surgen avances asociados a ella, como el empleo de la elastografía cuantitativa, los contrastes intravenosos y, más recientemente, la endomicroscopia láser confocal. Surgen nuevos marcadores en orina y en jugo pancreático para la diferenciación del CP con la pancreatitis crónica. Se refuerza claramente el papel del patólogo &#147;en la sala&#148; para aumentar el rendimiento diagnóstico de las punciones guiadas por ecoendoscopia y aparecen estudios multicéntricos comparativos entre agujas de citología y de histología o procore. En relación con los tumores quísticos, los trabajos se centran en validar las nuevas guías de 2012 y en determinar los factores predictivos de malignidad de las lesiones quísticas, fundamentalmente del tumor mucinoso papilar intraductal. Desde el punto de vista terapéutico, la ablación con radiofrecuencia guiada por ecoendoscopia emerge como una técnica factible y segura en tumores solidos y quísticos en determinadas circunstancias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;36(supl.2): 90-97, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Últimos avances sobre los tumores pancreáticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
