<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-21217</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of medical advice for reducing excessive alcohol conssumption. Meta-analysis of Spanish studies in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Former systematic reviews have backed the efficacy of medical counselling, a form of brief intervention, on the treatment of excessive drinkers detected in primary care settings. Nevertheless, these results cannot be applied without criticism to Mediterranean populations which, so far, have not been represented in the aforementioned studies. The aim of the present study was to update the results on the efficacy of brief interventions in primary care by pooling Spanish studies. Methods: Studies were searched for by using appropriate databases and also by consulting to experts in the field to retrieve grey literature. Pooled estimations of effect sizes were calculated for two outcomes, the reduction in the amount of alcohol consumption and the decrease in the number of excessive drinkers. Results: Two over the 5 retrieved studies were not included in a former review. The effect size regarding the decrease of alcohol consumption was medium (d = - 0.46; 95% CI, - 0.29 to - 0.63; p &lt; 0.0005; the intervention group outperformed the control by a 22%) and small for the decrease in the frequency of excessive drinkers (OR = 1.55; 95% CI, 1.06 to 2.26; p = 0.02; the intervention group outperformed the control by a 11%). The analysis by complimented protocols at the end of the study showed an effect size 1.5 times larger than the analysis performed on intention-to-treat basis. Conclusions: The results of this meta-analysis support the efficacy of brief intervention for excessive drinkers in primary care settings in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Revisiones sistemáticas previas han apoyado la eficacia del consejo médico, como intervención breve, en el abordaje de bebedores excesivos detectados en la asistencia primaria. Sin embargo, estos resultados no pueden extrapolarse directamente a poblaciones que, como las mediterráneas, no están representadas en dichas revisiones. El objetivo de este estudio fue actualizar la evidencia sobre la eficacia de la intervención breve en consumidores excesivos de alcohol según estudios españoles. Métodos: Búsqueda de estudios en bases bibliográficas y consultas a expertos para localizar estudios no publicados. Se calcularon las estimaciones combinadas para dos variables de resultado, la reducción del consumo de alcohol y la disminución de la frecuencia de bebedores excesivos. Resultados: Dos de los 5 estudios localizados no estaban incluidos en una revisión previa. La eficacia de la intervención breve fue moderada para la disminución del consumo de alcohol (d = -0,46; intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95 por ciento, -0,29 a -0,63; p &lt; 0,0005; el grupo tratado mejoró un 22 por ciento más que el control) y pequeña para la disminución de la frecuencia de bebedores excesivos (OR = 1,55; IC del 95 por ciento, 1,06 a 2,26; p = 0,02; el grupo tratado mejoró un 11 por ciento más que el control).El análisis basado en el cumplimiento del protocolo sobrestimó 1,5 veces el tamaño del efecto respecto del análisis basado en la intención de tratamiento. Conclusiones: Los resultados del estudio señalan que, en nuestro país, la intervención breve en atención primaria sobre bebedores a riesgo es eficaz, aunque su efecto sea sólo moderado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;17(2): 116-122, mar.  -abr.  2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del consejo médico para la reducción del consumoexcesivo de alcohol. Metaanálisis de estudios españolesen atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Querejeta, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pinto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-21217</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3391</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
