<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166092</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current status of congenital myasthenic syndromes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since Engel reported the first case of congenital myasthenia in 1977 and the first pathogenic gene was found in 1995, knowledge about congenital myasthenic syndromes has continued to grow. Over the years, the pathogenic basis, its clinical features, the phenotype-genotype correlations that have been established and its therapeutic management have all been described. In this group of diseases the safety margin of neuromuscular transmission is altered by different mechanisms: in the synthesis or storage of acetylcholine quanta in the synaptic vesicles, in the calcium-mediated release of acetylcholine in the nerve terminal or in the efficiency of the quantum released to generate a post-synaptic depolarisation. Increased knowledge about them has enabled a number of different therapeutic strategies to be established. In this review the main updates on these syndromes are reported, including: the genes described as classifying 50% of cases, their current classification based on the localisation of the proteins that alter neuromuscular transmission, including a new group of congenital myasthenias, glycosylation disorders, the main key diagnoses and the therapeutic management of this group of under-diagnosed patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Natera-de Benito, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bestué-Cardiel, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde la descripción de Engel del primer caso de miastenia congénita en 1977 y el hallazgo en 1995 del primer gen patógeno, el conocimiento de los síndromes miasténicos congénitos se ha ido desarrollando, y se han descrito la base patógena, sus características clínicas, las correlaciones fenotipo-genotipo establecidas y su abordaje terapéutico. En este grupo de enfermedades se altera el margen de seguridad de la transmisión neuromuscular por distintos mecanismos: en la síntesis o almacenamiento de los quantum de acetilcolina en las vesículas sinápticas, en la liberación de acetilcolina en el nervio terminal mediada por calcio o en la eficiencia de la cuanta liberada para generar una despolarización postsináptica. Su conocimiento ha permitido establecer distintas estrategias terapéuticas. En esta revisión se describen las principales actualizaciones de estos síndromes: los genes descritos que clasifican un 50% de los casos, su clasificación actual basándose en la localización de las proteínas que alteran la transmisión neuromuscular, incluyendo un nuevo grupo de miastenias congénitas, los trastornos de la glicosilación, las principales claves diagnósticas y el abordaje terapéutico de este grupo de pacientes infradiagnosticados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(4): 161-176, 16 ago., 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166092</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual de los síndromes miasténicos congénitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34336^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32819^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34210^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9661^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
