<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036387</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8241</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity as cardiovascular risk factor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is a chronic metabolic disease associated with cardiovascular risk and increased morbidity and mortality. Being overweighted and obese are now considered to be as important as other classic risk factors related to heart disease. Fatty tissue not only acts as stores of fat molecules but synthesizes and releases hormones to the blood which are related to the metabolism of basic food molecules and regulation of food intake. Likewise, obesity is associated with numerous cardiovascular risk factors such as dyslipidemia, hypertension, diabetes, inflammatory markers and prothrombotic state. Weight loss can prevent acute progression of atherosclerotic plaque and coronary events in obese subjects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Esteban, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zugasti Murillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad es una enfermedad metabólica crónica con riesgo cardiovascular asociado y una morbimortalidad aumentada. Actualmente el sobrepeso y la obesidad se consideran tan importantes como otros factores de riesgo clásico relacionados con la enfermedad coronaria. El tejido adiposo no sólo actúa como almacén de moléculas grasas, sino que sintetiza y libera a la sangre numerosas hormonas relacionadas con el metabolismo de principios inmediatos y la regulación de la ingesta. Asimismo, la obesidad se asocia a numerosos factores de riesgo cardiovasculares como dislipidemia, hipertensión, diabetes, marcadores inflamatorios y estado protrombótico. La pérdida de peso puede evitar la progresión de la placa de aterosclerosis y los eventos coronarios agudos en los sujetos obesos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertensión (Madr., Ed. impr.);22(1): 32-36, ene. 2005. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036387</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad como factor de riesgo cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37291^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
