<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131710</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The building of Urology as a specialty in Mallorca</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The research of the origin and development of the Medical-surgical specialties in our environment has been, to my knowledge, limited. The aim of this work is to review it in reference to Urology, one of the first specialties developed in Mallorca during the second half of the XIX Century and the beginning of the XX century. Evidence acquisition has been performed through research of the archives of the Royal Academy of Medicine of the Balearic Islands (RAMIB) and the Medical College and the study of the Balearic Journal of Medical sciences. Furthermore, the biographies of the main precursors and pioneers of Urology in Mallorca have been reconstructed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mercant Ramírez, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación del origen y desarrollo de las especialidades médico-quirúrgicas en nuestro medio ha sido hasta donde llega mi conocimiento, escasa. La finalidad de este trabajo es dar cuenta de ello en lo que se refiere a la Urología, especialidad que fue una de las primeras en construirse en Mallorca en la segunda mitad del siglo XIX y principios del XX. La adquisición de la evidencia ha sido realizada fundamentalmente a través de la investigación de los archivos de la RAMIB (Real Academia de Medicina de les Illes Balears) y del Colegio de Médicos y del estudio de la RBCM (Revista Balear de Ciencias Médicas). Por otro lado se han reconstruído las biografías de los principales presursores y pioneros de la Urología mallorquina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(10): 803-822, dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131710</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La construcción de la especialidad urológica en Mallorca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50131</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
