<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84399</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transdifferentation of mesenchymal stem cells from adipose tissue: Through a cellular therapy for degenerative retinal diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To obtain adult mesenchymal stem cells from adipose tissue to be used in cellular therapies aimed to retinal regeneration. Material and Methods: isolation of adult mesenchymal stem cells from adipose tissue of green fluorescent protein transgenic mice. Recipient mouse eyes were transplanted with these cells by using intravitreal and subretinal procedures. We have used a mice model of human autosomal recessive retinitis pigmentosa (rd10). Gene expression by means of RT-PCR of mRNA isolated from embryo eyes (E9,5 to E18,5); post-natal eyes (P1 to P10) and adults eyes .That technique was also used in mouse embryoid bodies spontaneously differentiated from embryonic stem cells ES-D3. Results: In both surgical procedures we observed survival, migration and integration of mesenchymal stem cells into several retinal layers. We have also identified the expression of some retinal genes (Otx2, NF200,Pax6, peripherin,IRBP) wich may help to drive the mesenchymal stem cells transdifferentiation. Conclusions: Mesenchimal cells are very promising to be used in degenerative retinal diseases. We emphasize the usefulness of mouse embryoid bodies as a model to study the regulatory mechanisms of retinal neurons differentiation and its potential for obtaining retinal progenitors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaén, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avilés, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Obtención de células troncales mesenquimales de tejido adiposo para trasplante y recuperación funcional de retinas degeneradas. Material y metodología: Extracción de la grasa inguinal de ratones transgénicos para proteína verde fluorescente y aislamiento de las células troncales mesenquimales. Estas células fueron implantadas utilizando inoculaciones intravítreas y subretinianas en un modelo murino (rd10) que asemeja la retinosis pigmentaria autosomal recesiva humana. Expresión de genes involucrados en el desarrollo de la retina mediante RT-PCR. Resultados: Nuestros resultados demuestran que en ambos abordajes quirúrgicos las células trasplantadas sobreviven, migran y se integran en diferentes capas de la retina de los ratones rd10. Además hemos identificado la expresión de genes en embriones y cuerpos embrionarios (Otx2, NF200,Pax6 periferina, IRBP) que pueden ser utilizados como activadores o potenciadores de la transdiferenciación. Conclusiones: las células mesenquimales del tejido adiposo reúnen las condiciones necesarias para su potencial uso en la terapia de enfermedades degenerativas de la retina. Los cuerpos embrionarios representan un modelo útil para estudiar los mecanismos reguladores de la diferenciación de las células retinianas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(3): 183-190, jul.-sept. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84399</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transdiferenciación de células mesenquimales del tejido adiposo: hacia una terapia celular para enfermedades degenerativas de la retina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12578^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10984^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10984^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54432^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52893^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52893^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23492^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12581^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12581^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
