<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60234</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurodevelopmental outcome of very low Barth weight infants alter discharge from the intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To evaluate the relationship between risk perinatal factors included intraventricular hemorrhage and neurodevelopment outcome after three years of very low birth weight after discharge form the intensive care unit. Material and methods. A retrospective study was undertaken of 70 preterm babies discharge form the intensive care unit between 2002-05 weighting less than 1.500 g. They were followed-up with a neurological evaluation for three years. The presence of neurological sequelae and risk perinatal factors were compared. Results: Seventy patient followed-up during three years (mean weight 1.191 g), 46,6% (21) of these presented intraventricular haemorrhage. A significant association between neurological sequelae and maternal chorioamnionitis (p&lt;0,01) a low Apgar score (p&lt;0,05) was found, but not in relation to other risk factors. Conclusions. The results suggest that preterm infants exposed to maternal chorioamnionitis or low Apgar score are at a higher risk of poor neurological outcome at the age of three years. Other pathology or aggressive treatments associate a transitory delay that does not relate to alteration in the psychomotor long-term development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayerza Casas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ventura Faci, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samper Villagras, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariño Galve, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la relación entre factores de riesgo perinatal, incluyendo la hemorragia intraventricular (HIV), y el desarrollo neurológico tras tres años de seguimiento en los niños con muy bajo peso al nacer dados de alta en nuestra Unidad Neonatal. Material y método. Estudio retrospectivo de 70 recién nacidos con un peso&amp;#8804; 1,500 g dados de alta entre los años 2002 y 2005. Se realizó seguimiento del desarrollo psicomotor hasta los tres años y se comparó la presencia o no de secuelas con los distintos factores de riesgo perinatales. Resultados. De los 70 niños, 45 fueron seguidos hasta los tres años (peso medio 1.191 g) y el 46,4% (21) tenían antecedente  de HIV. La presencia de secuelas (26,6%) se relacionó con el antecedente de corioamnionitis materna (p&lt;0,01) y con una puntuación baja en el test de Apgar (p&lt;0,05), pero no con otros factores de riesgo. Comentarios. Nuestros resultados sugieren que la corioamnionitis y una puntuación baja en el test de Apgar asocian significativamente alteraciones en el desarrollo psicomotor a los tres años de edad. La existencia de otras patologías o tratamientos más agresivos asocian un retraso transitorio que no se relaciona con alteración en el desarrollo psicomotor a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;64(6): 426-431, nov.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo neurológico en prematuros de muy bajo peso tras ser dados de alta en la Unidad Neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2871^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32719</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
