<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72481</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the care of the healthy normal newborn at delivery and during the first postnatal hours</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Standardised normal newborn care at delivery and during the first hours of life is one of the objectives of the Spanish National Society of Neonatology. The object of this review is to apply the best evidence possible to the procedures of the care of the newborn from delivery and during the first moments after delivery; as well as standards and routines in care to improve quality and the safety of the newborn. A PubMed (MeSH) review using the key words: term newborn; prophylaxis of ophthalmia neonatorum; haemorrhagic disease of the newborn; neonatal jaundice; neonatal screening and hospital discharge. Concepts of regular care of the healthy newborn at delivery; normal practices in the delivery room; prophylaxis of ophthalmia neonatorum; prevention of vitamin K deficiency bleeding; care of the umbilical cord; newborn screening and hospital discharge are reviewed. The standard of care of the newborn at delivery and during the first hours of life have been updated; recommendations based on evidence and on experts of the standard committee of the spanish society of neonatology are done (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Botet Mussons, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Luna, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narbona, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echániz Urcelay, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallás Alonso, C. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Conde, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estandarización de los cuidados del recién nacido (RN) desde el nacimiento y en las primeras horas de la vida posnatal son parte de los objetivos de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología. El objetivo de estas recomendaciones es aplicar la mejor evidencia científica a los procedimientos en el cuidado del RN desde el nacimiento y en los primeros momentos de la vida posnatal. Se quieren contrastar ciertas prácticas y rutinas para ajustarlas al conocimiento y la evidencia médica actuales y así mejorar la calidad asistencial y la seguridad del RN. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica en PubMed (MeSH) de las palabras clave: Recién nacido a término; Recién nacido; Oftalmia neonatal; Enfermedad hemorrágica del recién nacido; Ictericia neonatal; Cribado neonatal; Diagnóstico precoz. Se han revisado los conceptos de RN sano, cuidados en el momento inmediato al nacimiento, prácticas en el paritorio, profilaxis de la oftalmia neonatal y de la enfermedad hemorrágica por defecto de la vitamina K, cuidados del cordón umbilical, cribado neonatal y alta hospitalaria. Se han actualizado los estándares en el cuidado y en la atención del RN en el parto y las primeras horas de vida, se han hecho recomendaciones basadas en la evidencia médica y en la opinión del Comité de Estándares de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(4): 349-361, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72481</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para el cuidado y atención del recién nacido sano en el parto y en las primeras horas después del nacimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
