<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80540</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of family satisfaction of pediatrics emergency services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the level of satisfaction of families of the pediatric department hospital emergency services; to identify the key service performance factors that could influence their final satisfaction and to find best practices from a review of experiences evaluated.MethodologyA descriptive retrospective study was carried out. Family members who accompanied a child during his stay in the hospital emergency service were included in the study. The sample was defined using a random systematic methodology with telephone surveys as the main tool. The statistical methods used were standard deviation for categorical variables and the analysis of the variance for the continuous variables. The SPSS 16.0 programme was used as the main tool for evaluating the results.ResultsA total of 120 surveys were made with 96 responses obtained. The demographic profile of the main companion of the child was a woman, married, active worker with medium/university education. In 100% of the cases the main companion was a direct member of the family, and 85% of cases it was the child's mother. The pathology was considered mild in 65% of cases, with 86% of them being being resolved. There was very little difference between the actual time and the perceived time. From the information obtained, a high level of general satisfaction was perceived, with a positive assessment (in 76% of the cases), on the way the were treated by hospital staff. The areas for improvement were those associated with the identification of the health staff and facilities.ConclusionAs a general assessment of the study it was shown that the main factors of satisfaction for the family members were those related to being able to accompany the child, and the kindness and the respect(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogales-Cortés, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sánchez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Tirado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Blanco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosDeterminar el grado de satisfacción de los familiares usuarios del servicio de urgencias pediátricas, identificar factores que puedan influir en la satisfacción y establecer las áreas de mejora.Material y métodosEstudio retrospectivo y descriptivo. Se incluyó en el estudio a los familiares que acompañaron al niño durante su estancia en urgencias. El muestreo fue aleatorizado, sistemático y se utilizó como instrumento una encuesta telefónica. En el estudio divariado se utilizó el estadístico chi-cuadrado para variables categóricas y análisis de variancia para aquellos que presentaban una distribución continua. El análisis se realizó con el programa SPSS 16.0.ResultadosSe realizaron 120 encuestas, de las cuales se obtuvieron 96 respuestas. El perfil demográfico de los acompañantes fue mujer, casada, en situación laboral activa y estudios medios/universitarios. En el 100% de los casos el acompañante era un familiar, en un 85% era la madre. En un 65% se consideró la enfermedad del niño leve, y se resolvió en el 86% de los casos. Se constató poca discrepancia entre el tiempo objetivo y la percepción subjetiva. Los encuestados manifestaron un alto grado de satisfacción con la información recibida. Se observó una valoración muy positiva (76%) ante el trato humano recibido. Las áreas susceptibles de mejora fueron las relacionadas con la identificación del personal sanitario y las instalaciones.ConclusiónEn las condiciones del estudio se detectó que los factores más determinantes en la satisfacción del familiar son aquéllos relacionados con el acompañamiento, la amabilidad y el respeto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(2): 58-63, mar.-abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80540</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la satisfacción de los familiares en las urgencias pediátricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
