<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057023</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment related complications in distal radius fractures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fractures of distal radius, and, overall, high energy fractures,    have been related to many complications. Although    many of these are directly related to the fracture itself, the    use of internal or external fixation, even a plaster of paris,    adds an increased risk of complications. Closed reduction    and casting increase malunion, arthritis and late carpal    tunnel syndrome, but decrease the risk of surgical complications.    Internal or external fixation may increase risk of    deep infection, tendon irritation and nerve injuries.    Specific treatment related complications have been reported.    Knowledge of these may help surgeons in avoidance    and prevention of them, and, consequently, improve fracture    outcome.    When selecting the best treatment, the surgeon must not    forget that a functional outcome depends not only on the    fracture pattern but on the treatment itself and its correct    perform. Moreover, a close follow-up in order to avoid and    prevent complications is also advised</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graupera, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruzafa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza-Vera, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fracturas de radio distal y, en concreto, las de alta    energía, se han asociado a múltiples complicaciones. A    pesar de que muchas son inherentes a la fractura, el uso    de fijación interna o externa, o incluso el yeso de parís, incrementa    el riesgo de complicaciones. La reducción cerrada    y el vendaje enyesado aumenta la incidencia de consolidación    viciosa, artritis y síndrome del tunel carpiano    tardío, pero disminuye el riesgo de todas las complicaciones    relacionadas con la cirugía. La fijación interna o externa    aumenta el riesgo de infección profunda, irritación tendinosa    y lesiones nerviosas.    Se han descrito complicaciones específicas a cada tipo de    tratamiento. El conocimiento de estas puede ayudar al cirujano    a evitarlas y prevenirlas, y, consecuentemente, mejorar    el resultado de la fractura.    En la elección del tratamiento a aplicar, el cirujano no debe    olvidar que el resultado funcional no depende sólo del tipo    de fractura sino también del tratamiento y de la correcta    ejecución del mismo. Para evitar y prevenir complicaciones    se aconseja un estrecho seguimiento del paciente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(supl.2): 91-96, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057023</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones del tratamiento de las fracturas de radio distal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10161^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5734^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
