<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038939</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of optical coherence tomography to study variations of normal parameters with age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine by Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) the variation of a variety of measurable parameters (macular thickness, retinal parapapillary fiber layer thickness and optic disc morphology) with age.Method: We carried out OCT in 40 normal subjects (80 eyes) aged between 20 and 60 years, divided into 4 groups according to the age decades.Results: Statistically significant differences were found in the macular thickness in the comparative study groups but the differences varied according to the sector assessed; the superior outer sector (p=0.00), temporal outer sector (p=0.01), temporal inner sector (p=0.04), nasal inner sector (p=0.03) and inferior inner sector (p=0.00).In the study of retinal parapapillary fiber layer thickness, statistically significant differences were found between groups in the inferior sector only (p=0.04).No statistically significant differences were found between groups in the study of optic disc morphology.Conclusions: Both the macular thickness and the nerve fiber layer in the inferior sector decrease with age. These differences in thickness are statistically significant between the extremes of age decades</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baquero Aranda, I. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo Sánchez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Campos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito: El propósito de este trabajo es determinar, con el Tomógrafo Óptico de Coherencia (OCT), los siguientes parámetros (grosor macular, grosor de capas de fibras nerviosas peripapilar y morfología de la cabeza del nervio óptico) en relación a la edad.Métodos: Par ello se ha realizado una Tomografía Óptica de Coherencia a 40 sujetos emétropes (80 ojos), con edades comprendidas entre los 20 y los 60 años. Los 80 ojos se dividieron en cuatro grupos (1-4) por décadas de edad.Resultados: Se ha encontrado diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre grupos en el estudio del grosor macular: en el cuadrante superior externo (p=0,00), cuadrante temporal externo (p=0,01), cuadrante temporal interno (p=0,04), cuadrante nasal interno (p=0,03), cuadrante inferior interno (p=0,00).En el estudio del grosor de capas de fibras nerviosas peripapilar se obtuvo diferencia estadísticamente significativa entre los grupos en el cuadrante inferior (p=0,04). No se encontraron diferencias entre los grupos en el estudio morfológico de la cabeza del nervio óptico.Conclusiones: Se destaca la disminución del grosor retiniano en el área macular, así como de la capa de fibras nerviosas en la región inferior peripapilar a medida que aumenta la edad. Estas diferencias de grosor son estadísticamente significativas entre edades extremas de la vida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;80(4): 225-232, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038939</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de parámetros de normalidad en relación a la edad con el tomógrafo óptico de coherencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12578^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10078^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9605</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
