<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121752</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and management of sinusitis: attitudes of the pediatricians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: sinusitis is a common condition whose approach in daily pediatric practice is not well known. Methods: performing a national level cross-sectional study through a survey distributed "on line" to members of 2 pediatric societies, in March 2013. Results: 994 responses were obtained (78% of Primary Care). Most professionals estimated the frequency of sinusitis being about 1% of the visits. 76.6% reported exclusively diagnosis with clinical criteria, considering (92%) an association of symptoms including persistent / purulent rhinorrhea (89%), facial pain / headache (84%), prolonged or nocturnal cough and fever in the context of upper respiratory infection (URI) (54%). Between 19.7 and 33.4% of professionals (primary / specialist) would request radiographs. 90% reported using antibiotics with or without other adjunctive treatments, being amoxicillin-clavulanate (52%) the chosen antibiotic, followed by amoxicillin 46%. 81% of pediatricians diagnose URI in more than 30% of visits and in 85% of cases do not prescribe drug treatment. When the URI lasts more than 14 days, 70% of them decide to treat. The most widely used treatments are anti-inflammatory / analgesics (54.5%) and antibiotics (51.4%). Conclusions: pediatricians' knowledge and clinical practice in URI and sinusitis indicate a high level of compliance with the most recent clinical practice guidelines, highlighting the limited use of antibiotics in the URI, the clinical diagnosis of sinusitis and the empirical choice of antibiotic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Aurrecoechea, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albañil Ballesteros, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Helguero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Campos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la sinusitis es una patología frecuente de la que desconocemos su abordaje en la práctica pediátrica diaria. Material y métodos: se realiza un estudio trasversal, de ámbito nacional mediante una encuesta distribuida on-line a los socios de dos sociedades pediátricas en marzo de 2013. Resultados: se obtuvieron 994 respuestas (78% de Atención Primaria). La mayoría de profesionales estima una frecuencia de sinusitis de alrededor del 1% de las visitas, el 76,6% refiere diagnosticarla exclusivamente con criterios clínicos, y el 92% considera una asociación de síntomas que incluyen rinorrea persistente/purulenta (89%), dolor facial/cefalea (84%), tos prolongada o nocturna y fiebre en el contexto de infección respiratoria de vías altas (IRA) 54%. El 19,7% de los profesionales de primaria y el 33,4% de los de especializada solicitarían un estudio radiológico. Un 90% refiere utilizar antibióticos con o sin otros tratamientos: amoxicilina-clavulánico (52%), seguido de amoxicilina 46% (relación que se invierte en especializada). Un 81% de los pediatras refiere diagnosticar IRA en más del 30% de las visitas, y en el 85% de los casos no prescriben tratamiento farmacológico. Ante una sintomatología catarral prolongada más de 14 días, un 70% decidiría tratar. Los tratamientos más utilizados serían antiinflamatorios/analgésicos en el 54,5% de los casos, y antibióticos en el 51,4%. Conclusiones: las respuestas de los pediatras sobre conocimientos y práctica clínica en IRA y sinusitis indican un alto nivel de adecuación a las Guías más recientes, destacando la escasa utilización de antibióticos en las IRA, el diagnóstico eminentemente clínico de la sinusitis y la elección empírica de antibióticos en la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;16(61): 23-33, ene.-mar. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y manejo de la sinusitis: actitudes de los pediatras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
