<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116824</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictors of poor Self-Rated Health in an ederly population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Self-Rated Health is part of the comprehensive concept of Quality of Life and is a valid measurement of health status. The main objective of this study was to test the predictive value of some different variables on the poor Self-Rated Health among elders. Material and methods. We performed a cross-sectional study on a sample consisting of 140 participants. Measurements: age, gender, level of education, environment, cognitive status, physical impairment, diseases, health perception and social support. The influence of the studied variables on the poor Self-Rated Health was performed with a logistic regression analysis and a ROC curve to establish the cut-off values for these variables with the best sensitivity and specificity to predict the poor Self-Rated Health. Results. A poor Self-Rated Health was significantly associated with age, comorbidity, and the perception of poor functional social support, whereas no association was found with gender, environment and educational level. Conclusions. Old age, the number of diagnosed diseases, and functional social support are Self-Rated Health risk factors, while the characteristics and repercussions of the diseases should not be considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, Trinidad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo-López, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán-Calenti, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maseda, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La salud autopercibida forma parte del concepto global de «calidad de vida», además de ser una medida válida para conocer el estado de salud. El objetivo principal de este trabajo es evaluar el efecto predictor de ciertas variables sobre la mala salud autopercibida en una población de personas mayores. Material y métodos. Se lleva a cabo un estudio transversal con una muestra de 140 personas mayores. Mediciones: edad, género, estudios, hábitat, estado cognitivo, discapacidad física, enfermedades, percepción de la salud y apoyo social. Para analizar el efecto de las diferentes variables sobre la mala salud autopercibida se aplicó un modelo de regresión logística y una curva ROC para establecer los valores de corte de dichas variables, con la mejor sensibilidad y especificidad para la predicción de mala salud autopercibida. Resultados. Se observa una asociación significativa entre una mala salud autopercibida con la edad, la comorbilidad, y con la percepción de apoyo social funcional débil, mientras que no existía asociación con el género, el hábitat o el nivel educativo. Conclusiones. La edad elevada, el número de enfermedades diagnosticadas, y el apoyo social funcional son los factores de riesgo de la salud autopercibida, mientras que las características y repercusiones de las enfermedades no deben ser consideradas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);48(6): 272-275, nov.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116824</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predictores de mala salud autopercibida en una población de personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
