<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131944</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Description of dysphonia cases evaluated in a mutua in 2013</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe a case series of patients with dysphonia evaluated in a national Spanish mutua. Methods: Computerized medical records of 2013 were reviewed and 129 patients with diagnoses compatible with dysphonia were identified. Results: Eighty-six (67%) of the 129 cases were recognized as occupational diseases, three cases were considered as occupational injuries (two with a diagnosis of Reinke's edema) and the remaining 40 cases were considered to not be work-related. Most of the cases (90%) occurred in women between the ages of 30 and 49 years. Ninety-three percent of the cases diagnosed as occupational diseases underwent speech therapy and, of these, 72% were cured. The majority of the cases(61%) occurred in teachers. Average duration of sickness absence, among those patients who took it, was 113.5 days. Conclusions: All cases reported as occupational disease met the criteria set by the Spanish legislation (RD 1299/2006).Non-occupational diseases were referred to the national health service. Customized speech therapy was effective for most of the patients. The average duration of sick leave in our series was high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Linares Salas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Llorente, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveres Verges, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puget Bosch, Dulce</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Bayarri, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los casos de disfonía atendidos en una Mutua española de ámbito nacional. Métodos: Se revisan las historias clínicas informatizadas durante 2013, identificándose 129 pacientes con diagnósticos compatibles con disfonías. Resultados: De los casos analizados 86 han sido declarados enfermedad profesional (67%), tres casos accidente de trabajo(dos de ellos diagnosticados con edema de Reinke) y 40 contingencia común. La mayoría de casos son mujeres (90%)entre 30 y 49 años. Han seguido tratamiento logopédico el 93% de las Enfermedades Profesionales, siendo las altas por curación en este grupo del 72%. La mayoría de los casos (61%) son profesionales de la enseñanza. En los casos que cursaron con baja laboral (n=36), la duración media de la baja fue de 113,5 días. Conclusiones: Todos los casos declarados como enfermedad profesional cumplen los requisitos marcados por la normativa(RD 1299/2006). Los casos considerados contingencia común se derivaron al Sistema Público de Salud. El tratamiento logopédico personalizado ha permitido la mayoría de las altas por curación. En nuestra serie, la media de días de baja por esta patología resulta elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);18(1): 12-16, ene.-mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de los casos de disfonías atendidos en una mutua durante el año 2013</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53079^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55210^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
