<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92829</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of the body mass index and postural balance in young healthy university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective The purpose of this study was to analyze the influence of the Body Mass Index (BMI) on the anterior-posterior and middle-lateral postural balance in young and healthy university students.Material and methodsThe study included a sample of 68 healthy university students (50 female and 18 male) aged 18-35 years old. BMI and postural balance control with both open and closed eyes were studied in each of the subjects.ResultsAll the stabilometric parameters showed strong evidence against normality. Therefore, the Spearman's rank correlation coefficient was used. Statistically significant results were found between Body Mass index (BMI) and anterior-posterior postural balance control with closed eyes (APPBCOE) (P=0.042). The R2=0.037 Coefficient of Determination showed that the influence of BMI on APPBCOE was 3.7%. No statistically significant results were obtained for the other related variables studied.ConclusionsWe can establish that, in absence of an important condition, a high BMI is related to worse postural balance control with closed eyes in the sagittal plane (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Amat, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lomas-Vega, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hita Contreras, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Gómez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos El propósito de este estudio ha sido analizar en una población de jóvenes universitarios la influencia del índice de masa corporal (IMC) en el equilibrio general, antero-posterior y medio-lateral.Material y métodoSe ha trabajado con una muestra de 68 jóvenes (edad=20,82±3,46), 18 hombres y 50 mujeres, universitarios. Se analizó el IMC y el equilibrio con ojos abiertos y con ojos cerrados de cada uno de los sujetos.ResultadosTodas las variables estabilométricas presentan fuerte evidencia contra la normalidad. Por ello se utilizó el coeficiente de correlación Rho de Spearman. En la relación del índice de masa corporal (IMC) con el índice de estabilidad antero-posterior ojos cerrados (IAPOCX) se observan resultados estadísticamente significativos (p=0,042). El coeficiente de determinación R2=0,037 indica que la influencia del IMC sobre el IAPOCX es del 3,7%. En el resto de variables relacionadas y llevadas a estudio no se obtuvieron resultados estadísticamente significativos.ConclusionesPodemos afirmar que en ausencia de patología relevante, cuando el sujeto se encuentra con los ojos cerrados cuanto mayor es el IMC, peor es la estabilidad en el plano sagital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(3): 93-97, may. -jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo del índice de masa corporal y el equilibrio postural en estudiantes universitarios sanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
