<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145744</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unexpected reaction to intravenous methylprednisolone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite the widespread use of corticosteroids in children, hypersensitivity reactions to corticosteroids are rarely. However, life-threatening reactions have been described, and clinicians should be aware of the risk posted by potential allergy to corticosteroid. Parenteral administration of such corticosteroids as methylprednisolone and hydrocortisone is more commonly associated with severe hypersensitivity reactions than other routes. A close and detailed evaluation is required to confirm the presence of a true hypersensitivity reaction to the suspected drug, and a challenge test with a different steroid must be performed in order to offer a safe alternative for further treatments. We report the case of a 14-year-old boy with an adverse reaction caused by methylprednisolone (AU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mastro Martínez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Camacho, G del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Catalán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incidencia de reacciones alérgicas a los corticoides en los niños es baja, especialmente si tenemos en cuenta su amplia utilización en pediatría. Se han descrito reacciones graves tras la administración de corticoides, por lo que la alergia a éstos debe tenerse presente cuando se utilicen. La vía de administración que más frecuentemente induce reacciones adversas graves es la sistémica, y los fármacos más frecuentemente implicados son la metilprednisolona y la hidrocortisona. Se debe realizar un diagnóstico adecuado que confirme la hipersensibilidad al corticoide sospechoso, así como pruebas de tolerancia a otros corticoides con el objetivo de ofrecer al paciente un tratamiento alternativo. Presentamos el caso de un adolescente de 14 años de edad con una reacción alérgica grave tras la administración de metilprednisolona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(9): e247-e251, oct. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacción inesperada tras la administración de metilprednisolona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
