<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141236</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Accreditation model for acute hospital care in Catalonia, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The implementation of an accreditation model for healthcare centres in Catalonia which was launched for acute care hospitals, leaving open the possibility of implementing it in the rest of lines of service (mental health and addiction, social health, and primary healthcare centres) is described. The model is based on the experience acquired over more tan 31 years of hospital accreditation and quality assessment linked to management. In January 2006 a model with accreditation methodology adapted to the European Foundation for Quality Management (EFQM) model was launched.  83 hospitals are accredited, with an average of 82.6% compliance with the standards required for accreditation. The number of active assessment bodies is 5, and the accreditation period is 3 years. A higher degree of compliance of the so-called "agent" criteria with respect to "outcome" criteria is obtained. Qualitative aspects for implementation to be stressed are: a strong commitment both from managers and staff in the centres, as well as a direct and fluent communication between the accreditation body (Ministry of Health of the Government of Catalonia) and accredited centres. Professionalism of audit bodies and an optimal communication between audit bodies and accredited centres is also added  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manzanera, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallès, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tirvió, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Viñas, Maria Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Davins, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Constante, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe la implantación de un modelo de acreditación para centros sanitarios de Catalunya que se inicia para hospitales de agudos y deja abierta la posibilidad de aplicación al resto de líneas de servicios: centros de salud mental y adicciones, sociosanitarios y atención primaria. El modelo se basa en la experiencia adquirida a lo largo de más de 31 años de acreditación de hospitales y de la evaluación de la calidad ligada a la gestión. En enero de 2006 se pone en marcha un modelo con metodología de acreditación, adaptado al modelo de la European Foundation for Quality Management (EFQM). Se acreditan 83 hospitales, con una media del 82,6% de cumplimiento de los estándares necesarios para acreditarse. El número de entidades evaluadoras en activo es de 5 y el período de acreditación es de 3 años. Se obtiene un mayor grado de cumplimiento de los denominados criterios "de agentes" respecto a los "de resultados". Como aspectos cualitativos, destacar en la implantación una gran implicación, tanto a nivel directivo como del personal de los centros, así como una comunicación directa y fluida entre órgano acreditador (Departament de Salut) y centros acreditados. Se añade también la profesionalidad de las entidades auditoras y una óptima comunicación entre entidades auditoras y centros acreditados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(supl.1): 68-73, jul. 2014. ^f68^l73</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141236</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo de acreditación de centros de atención hospitalaria aguda de Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6227</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
