<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117403</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Positive Psychology is being called into question. It has received substantial criticism, to which its advocates, naturally, have reacted. The present article sets out, above all, to establish the reasoning behind the criticisms of Positive Psychology&#146;s very foundations: positivity and scientificity. In contrast to the marked emphasis on the benefits of positive affect, research has shown that negative affect can be positive, just as positive affect can be negative. Positivity is not on the positive side (since no such side actually exists). Regarding what Positive Psychology purports to know scientifically about happiness, such knowledge does not appear to add anything to what we already knew. Even the best theories, such as the positive-activity model and the broaden-and-build theory, seem strikingly trivial, replete with tautology. Also noteworthy is the clear fallacy of the positivity ratio. Finally, it is asserted here that happiness cannot be sustained as either a life-guiding principle (its pursuit is neither universal nor the best thing to do in life) or a scientific objective, unless it be at the cost of reifying subjective experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Álvarez, Marino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Psicología Positiva está en debate. Ha recibido importantes críticas, a las que reaccionan sus defensores, como es natural. El presente artículo trata, más que nada, de establecer las razones de una crítica dirigida a los fundamentos mismos de la Psicología Positiva: la positividad y la cientificidad. Frente al marcado énfasis en los beneficios de los afectos positivos, los estudios muestran que los afectos negativos pueden ser tan positivos, como negativos pueden ser los afectos positivos. La positividad no está del lado positivo (porque no hay tal lado). Tocante a lo que la Psicología Positiva dice saber científicamente de la felicidad, no parece ser nada que no se supiera. Incluso las mejores teorías, como el modelo de actividad positiva y la teoría de la extensión-y-construcción impresionan por sus trivialidades según están plagadas de tautologías. Notable es también la falacia demostrada de la ratio de positividad. Finalmente, se plantea que la felicidad no es sostenible como principio de vida (su búsqueda no es universal ni lo mejor que hacer en la vida), ni como objeto científico, como no sea acosta de hipostasiar la experiencia subjetiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;34(3): 208-226, sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La psicología positiva y sus amigos: En evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31198</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
