<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76782</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant luteinised follicular cyst during the puerperium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non neoplasic masses that appear during pregnancy or postpartum together with obstetric complications are extremely rare, most times because of the size they can reach.The finding of an adnexal mass is usually casual as not-complicated ones provoque very few symptoms. The extended use of the ecography during pregnancy and postpartum will bring out a casual finding of this pathology.The management of adnexal masses during pregnancy or postpartum must be individualiced and depends on the symptoms, gestacional age, size and features of the mass.Massive luteinized follicular cyst in postpartum is an infrequent lesion in ovary that may appear during pregnancy and increases its size during postpartum untill it is detected. depenWepresent a case of a massive luteinized follicular cyst in a patient in her 6th week alter a vaginal delivery. We also perform an overview of the literature about most frequent non-oncologic ovarian masses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blasco Alonso, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Gor, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Damas López, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Gor Crooke, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Mesa, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Son extremadamente infrecuentes los tumores no neoplásicos que aparece durante el embarazo o el puerperio y originan complicaciones obstétricas, la mayor parte de las veces debido al tamaño que pueden llegar a alcanzar.El hallazgo de una masa anexial es, en general, casual ya que las no complicadas producen escasa sintomatología. El uso generalizado de la ecografía durante el embarazo y el puerperio permite su diagnóstico.El manejo de un tumor anexial durante la gestación o el puerperio debe ser individualizado, dependiendo de los síntomas de la paciente, la edad gestacional y el tamaño y las características de la tumoración.El quiste folicular gigante solitario luteinizado del puerperio es una lesión poco frecuente del ovario que puede surgir en el embarazo y aumentar de tamaño durante el puerperio hasta que es detectado.Presentamos el caso de un quiste folicular gigante luteinizado del puerperio diagnosticado en una paciente en la 6.ª semana del puerperio. Realizamos asimismo una revisión de las masas ováricas no neoplásicas más frecuentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(7): 422-426, jul. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste folicular gigante luteinizado del puerperio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31332^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19174^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
