<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051294</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of splenic function by dynamic gammagraphy, study of pitted erythrocytes and submembranous vacuoles in patients with slight and severe splenic trauma receiving conservative treatment or splenectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The splenic function of patients followed by the Department of General and Digestive Surgery in the Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol (HUGTiP) from 1985 to 2003 for different degrees of splenic trauma according to the classification of the American Association for the Surgery of Trauma (AAST) 1994 was quantified and related to the treatment received (non surgical, total splenectomy with or without splenosis and splenectomy plus autotransplantation) to detect splenic dysfunction predisposing the development of postsplenectomy sepsis (PSS). Patients and method: 43 patients underwent an isotopic study with dynamic splenic gammagraphy and pitted erythrocytes (Normarsky optics) and submembranous vacuoles (transmission electron microscopy) were evaluated. Results: The non surgical group presented normal phagocytic and filtration function with the median speed of splenic enhancement being 3.46 Kcts/s2 (interval: 0.8-6.98). The percentage of pitted erythrocytes was 2% (0-8.8), the number of pits per erythrocyte was 0.03 (0-0.12) and the percentage of erythrocytes with 1,2,3 and 4 pits was 1.6%, 0.4%, 0% and 0%, respectively. The percentage of red cells with submembranous vacuoles was 2.55% (0-5.6), the number of vacuoles per red cell was 0.03 (0-0.06) and the percentage of red cells with 1,2,3 and 4 vacuoles was 2%, 0.2%, 0% and 0%, respectively. In the operated group, the splenic enhancement speed was 0.08 Kcts/s2 (0-1.75) (p &lt; 0.0001). The percentage of pitted erythrocytes was 38% (0.2-64) (p &lt; 0.0001), the number of pits per erythrocyte was 0.86 (0-1.8) (p &lt; 0.0001) and the percentage of erythrocytes with 1,2,3 and 4 pits was 16.39%, 7.2%, 3.59% and 2.52%, respectively (p &lt; 0.0001). The percentage of red cells with submembranous vacuoles was 11.2% (1.8-31.9) (p = 0.0006); the number of vacuoles per cell was 0.16 (p = 0.0022) and the percentage of red cells with 1,2,3 and 4 vacuoles was 6.51%, 1.73%, 0.4% and 0.2%, respectively (p = 0.0246, 0.0010, &lt; 0.0001 and 0.0002, respectively). Conclusions: Splenic function of patients with a history of splenic trauma receiving conservative treatment is normal, independently of the degree of the lesion, thereby reinforcing the use of this therapeutic approach to avoid the development of postsplenectomy sepsis. In the patients treated with splenectomy, with or without splenosis, splenic function was absent or very altered being partially conserved in cases treated with splenectomy plus autotransplantation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pacha-González, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraile, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oller-Sales, Benjamí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Nivardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troya, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riba, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millá, Fuensanta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol-Borrell, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feliu, Evarist</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cáceres, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xandri, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Llamazares, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Cuantificar la función esplénica de los pacientes controlados en el Servicio de Cirugía General y Digestiva del Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol (HUGTiP) desde 1985 hasta 2003 tras haber sufrido diferentes grados de lesión traumática del bazo según la clasificación de la American Association for the Surgery of Trauma (AAST) del año 1994 y relacionarla con el tratamiento recibido (no operatorio, esplenectomía total con o sin esplenosis y esplenectomía más autotrasplante), con la finalidad de detectar disfunciones esplénicas que predispongan al desarrollo de la sepsis tras la esplenectomía. Pacientes y método: Se ha realizado a 43 pacientes un estudio isotópico con gammagrafía esplénica «dinámica», estudio de «pits» de la membrana eritrocitaria (óptica de Nomarsky) y de vacuolas submembranarias (microscopia electrónica de transmisión). Resultados: El grupo de no operados presenta una función normal de fagocitosis y filtración, con una mediana de velocidad de captación esplénica de 3,46 Kcts/s2 (intervalo, 0,8-6,98). El porcentaje mediano de «pits» de membrana fue del 2% (intervalo, 0-8,8%); el número de «pits» por hematíes, de 0,03 (intervalo, 0-0,12), y el porcentaje de hematíes con 1, 2, 3 y 4 «pits», del 1,6, el 0,4, el 0 y el 0%, respectivamente. El porcentaje mediano de hematíes con vacuolas submembranarias fue el 2,55% (intervalo, 0-5,6%); el número de vacuolas por hematíe, de 0,03 (intervalo, 0-0,06), y el porcentaje de hematíes con 1, 2, 3 y 4 vacuolas, del 2, el 0,2, el 0 y el 0%, respectivamente. En el grupo operado, la velocidad mediana de captación esplénica fue de 0,08 Kcts/s2 (intervalo, 0-1,75; p &lt; 0,0001); el porcentaje mediano de «pits» de membrana, del 38% (intervalo, 0,2-64; p &lt; 0,0001); el número mediano de «pits» por hematíe, de 0,86 (intervalo, 0-1,8; p &lt; 0,0001), y el porcentaje de hematíes con 1, 2, 3 y 4 «pits», del 16,39, el 7,2, el 3,59 y el 2,52%, respectivamente (p &lt; 0,0001). La mediana del porcentaje de hematíes con vacuolas submembranarias fue del 11,2% (intervalo, 1,8-31,9; p = 0,0006); el número mediano de vacuolas por hematíe, de 0,16 (p = 0,0022), y el porcentaje de hematíes con 1, 2, 3 y 4 vacuolas, del 6,51, el 1,73, el 0,4 y el 0,2%, respectivamente (p = 0,0246; p = 0,0010; p &lt; 0,0001, y p = 0,0002, respectivamente). Conclusiones: La función esplénica de los pacientes con antecedentes de traumatismo esplénico tratados de forma conservadora es normal, independientemente del grado de la lesión. Ello refuerza la conveniencia de aplicar de entrada esta actitud a todos los protocolos para intentar evitar la sepsis tras la esplenectomía. En los casos tratados con esplenectomía, con o sin esplenosis, la función esplénica está ausente o muy alterada, mientras que en los casos tratados con esplenectomía y autotrasplante está parcialmente conservada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(5): 161-167, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051294</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la función esplénica mediante gammagrafía dinámica y estudio de «pits» de la membrana eritrocitaria y de vacuolas submembranarias en los pacientes con traumatismo leve y grave de bazo tratados de forma conservadora o mediante esplenectomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13538^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13539^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13434^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13544^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13544^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4997^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10777^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
