<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127754</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teamwork: vision of nurses in a hospital of Murcia / Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the vision of nurses who work in a Hospital of Murcia in Spain, a bout teamwork. Method: This was a qualitative, descriptive and exploratory study, conducted from November 2011 to January 2012, with 14 nurses who worked at the University Hospital Reina Sofía. The data collection occurred through two focus group meetings. Data were analyzed by the proposed operative of Minayo. Results: The nurses recognize that all team members are important and that each one contributes with its specificities. However, many difficulties are faced in carrying out the daily work, such as individualism, high staff turnover, lack of autonomy, vertical power relations, lack of time for meetings and of leaders to build and to encourage the teamwork. Conclusion: It is emphasized that effective communication in the workplace may be able to reduce conflicts and promote the formation of healthy professional links. Thus, dialogical attitudes are fundamental to promote collective work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Mondejar, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amestoy, Simone Coelho</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mikla, Marzena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Montesinos, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porto, Adrize Rutz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bettin, Andréia Coelho</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes, Helen Nicoletti</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thofehrn, Maira Buss</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la visión de las enfermeras, que trabajan en un hospital de Murcia, en España, sobre el trabajo en equipo. Método: Un estudio cualitativo, descriptivo y exploratorio, fue realizado desde noviembre de 2011 a enero de 2012, con 14 enfermeras en el Hospital General Universitario Reina Sofía. La recolección de datos ocurrió a través de dos reuniones de grupos focales. Los datos se analizaron por la propuesta operativa de Minayo. Resultados: Los enfermeros reconocen que todos los miembros del equipo son importantes y que cada uno aporta sus especificidades. Sin embargo, hay muchas dificultades en el trabajo diario: individualismo, alta rotación de personal, falta de autonomía, relaciones verticales de poder, falta de tiempo para las reuniones y de líderes para construir y fomentar el trabajo en equipo. Conclusión: Se destaca que la comunicación efectiva en el lugar de trabajo puede ser capaz de reducir conflictos y promover la formación de vínculos profesionales saludables. Por lo tanto, las actitudes dialógicas son fundamentales para promover el trabajo colectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;13(36): 223-237, oct. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127754</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trabajo en equipo: visión de los enfermeros de un hospital de Murcia/España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
