<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148704</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emergency unit of pediatrics of the Hospital Infantil Universitario Miguel Servet</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Children&#146;s Emergency Department at the Miguel Servet University Hospital in Zaragoza, as a reference centre in Aragon, has a commitment to the hospital strategies emphasising health care, teaching and research activities, in which all professionals Working in the department are involved. Its purpose is, focused on the patient and their family, the urgent solution to all clinical situations requiring immediate attention due to medical, surgical or trauma problems with the greatest effectiveness and optimum scienti&amp;#64257;c and technical quality 24 hours a day, every day of the year (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Barrena, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Calleja, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Unidad de Urgencias de Pediatría del Hospital Universitario Miguel Servet de Zaragoza, centro de referencia de la Comunidad Autónoma de Aragón, tiene un compromiso con las líneas estratégicas del centro, destacando la actividad asistencial, docencia e investigacion clínica en las que están involucrados todos los profesionales de la Unidad. Su &amp;#64257;nalidad está centrada en el paciente y sus familias, en la resolución urgente de todas las situaciones clínicas que requieran atención inmediata por problemas médicos, quirúrgicos o traumatológicos, en el menor tiempo posible, con la mayor efectividad y con una óptima calidad cientí&amp;#64257;co- técnica, durante las 24 horas del día, todos los días del año.  Exponemos los principales datos asistenciales, docentes y de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;71(6): 374-379, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148704</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Unidad de Urgencias de Pediatría del Hospital Infantil Universitario Miguel Servet</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
