<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111806</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atypical lumbar Schuermann's disease: a presentation of 6 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scheuermann's disease is the most common cause of kyphosis in adolescence, and one of the most common causes of back pain in this age group. It is most commonly located in thoracic spine and is generally painless. Scheuermann's disease in the lumbar spine is less known and may go undetected in daily clinical practice. Blumenthal described this entity as atypical lumbar Scheuermann's disease. This form presents with Schmorl's hernias in one or two vertebral bodies, with narrowing of disc space and changes in the vertebral plates. It is more often painful and it can be confused with traumatic, infectious or tumor diseases. In most patients, a radiographic study is enough to establish the diagnosis and to differentiate both forms. Our series consists of six patients affected with the atypical form of lumbar Scheuermann's disease and diagnosed by us. All patients had a repeated history of back pain with associated Schmorl's hernias, and a very high increase in lateral diameter in radiographic views of the lumbar spine. Involvement of a single vertebral body was the most prevalent (50% of cases), and the 4th lumbar vertebra was the most commonly affected. All patients returned to normal activities after conservative treatment with temporary immobilization and NSAIDs during pain episodes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicent-Carsí, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas-García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Scheuermann es el origen más común de cifosis de la columna dorsal en el adolescente. Es uno de los orígenes más comunes de la dorsalgia en este grupo de edad. Se trata de una enfermedad cuya localización más frecuente es la torácica, siendo generalmente indolora. La forma de enfermedad de Scheuermann en el raquis lumbar es menos conocida, pudiendo pasar desapercibida en la práctica clínica habitual. Esta entidad fue descrita por Blumenthal como enfermedad de Scheuermann lumbar atípica. La forma lumbar atípica consiste en la aparición de hernias de Schmorl en uno o 2 cuerpos vertebrales con estrechamiento del espacio interdiscal y cambios en los platillos vertebrales. Con mayor frecuencia es dolorosa, lo que puede ser confundida con afecciones traumáticas, infecciosas o tumorales. En la mayoría de los pacientes el estudio radiográfico es suficiente para establecer el diagnóstico y diferenciar ambas formas. Nuestra serie de 6 enfermos afectados de la forma atípica lumbar de la enfermedad de Scheuermann y diagnosticados por nosotros, presentaron una historia clínica de lumbalgias de repetición. Asociaban hernias de Schmorl y un aumento muy evidente del diámetro lateral en las proyecciones radiográficas de la columna lumbar. La afectación de un solo cuerpo vertebral fue la más predominante (50% de los casos) y la vértebra más comúnmente afectada fue la L4. Todos los pacientes se reincorporaron a sus actividades habituales tras ser tratados con medidas conservadoras de inmovilización temporal y antiinflamatorios durante los periodos de dolor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);57(2): 135-139, mar.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111806</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Scheuermann lumbar atípica: a propósito de 6 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7915^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12980^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12980^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7915^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
