<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79372</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of clinical toxicology to total toxicological research in Spain (1991-2005)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective measurement of scientific production by individuals, research groups or scientific areas using bibliometric parameters is increasingly important. The aims of this study were to analyze the research made by spanish toxicologists during a 15-year period, to compare it with that of other scientific areas and toxicologists from other countries and to determine the contribution of clinical toxicology to total spanish toxicological lresearch. The Web of Knowledge programme of the Institute for Science Information (ISI) and the Science Citation Index (SCI) database were used to carry out a bibliometric search for scientific documents published by spanish toxicologists from 1991 to 2005.The data tabulated were: year of publication, names of the journal and its impact factor, nationality of the journal's editor, type and language of the document, centre, province and community of the first toxicologist author, collaboration with other toxicology services and number of citations of each article. The statistical analysis was made using the SPSS version 12.0 statistical programme. During the study period, 1904 works authored by spanish toxicologists appearing in523 different journals were identified. There was a significant, progressive increase in the number of works authored by toxicologists and the number of works in the area of toxicology during the study period. However, as global scientific production in Spain increased markedly during this period, the percentage of toxicological works as a percentage of total spanish scientific production fell significantly. There was international collaboration in16% of the toxicological studies included. A total of 79 spanish toxicological centres authored scientific works, with the greatest number being produced by the autonomic communities of Catalonia, Andalusia and Madrid...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogué, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montori, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cada vez resulta más importante medir de forma objetiva la producción científica individual, de los grupos de investigación o de un área científica, para lo que se utilizan parámetros bibliométricos. En el presente estudio se analiza la actividad investigadora llevada a cabo por los toxicólogos españoles durante 15años, se compara con la de otras áreas científicas y con la de los toxicólogos de otros países y, finalmente, se investiga la aportación de la toxicología clínica al conjunto de la investigación toxicológica española. Se empleó como herramienta de búsqueda bibliométrica de documentos científicos publicados por toxicólogos españoles el programa Web of Knowledge del Institute for Science Information(ISI) y como base de datos el Science Citation Index (SCI). El periodo de tiempo analizado fue de 1991 a 2005. Los datos tabulados fueron: año de publicación, nombre de la revista y su factor de impacto, país del editor de la revista, tipo e idioma del documento, centro, provincia y comunidad del primer toxicólogo firmante, colaboración con otros servicios de toxicología y número de citas que recibió el artículo. Para el análisis estadístico, los datos se introdujeron en el programa informático SPSS versión 12.0. Durante los 15 años estudiados se han identificado 1904 documentos firmados por toxicólogos españoles y publicados en 523 revistas diferentes. Durante este periodo de tiempo, se ha observado un incremento progresivo y significativo del número de documentos firmados por toxicólogos, así como de los documentos encuadrados en el área de toxicología. Sin embargo, como la producción científica global en España ha mostrado un marcado aumento, el porcentaje que supone la toxicología respecto a la producción total española, ha experimentado un significativo descenso. En un 16% de los trabajos se estableció una colaboración internacional...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;26(2/3): 104-116, 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones de la Toxicología Clínica al conjunto de la investigación toxicológica en España durante 15 años (1991-2005)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
