<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107391</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: a study on chronic pain has been performed in a sample of people in Andalusia, in order to assess its prevalence, features, diagnosis, treatment, and impact. Material and methods: a cross-sectional survey with stratified randomised sampling, including 1,200 phone interviews on pain was performed in people aged &gt; 18 years in Andalusia, by means of the CATI system (Computer Assisted Telephone Interviewing) designed by IMC (Instituto de Investigación, Marketing y Comunicación, Sevilla). Results: from 1,200 interviewees, a sample of 405 patients with recent pain was obtained (30% of participants with current pain; 3.8% with pain in previous month but not currently). 15.5% of participants have chronic pain. Mean intensity is 5.4 (on a 1-10 scale). Most common sites are back, legs and knees; and rheumatologic pain is the most common type. Impact on quality of life is high. 77.5% of people with pain use prescribed oral drugs. About half of participants have heard about pain units, and have a positive opinion on them. Conclusions: current data provide information on the presence of pain in Andalusian population, and will be useful to build up strategies to deal with it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira Reina, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras de la Fuente, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Moraleda, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Ortiz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de la Torre, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Silva, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares del Río, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Liébanas, R. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Armenta, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Andrada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Matallana, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: se ha realizado un estudio sobre el dolor crónico en una muestra de población de Andalucía para explorar su prevalencia, características, forma de diagnóstico, tratamiento e impacto. Material y métodos: se llevó a cabo un estudio transversal con muestreo aleatorio estratificado, con 1.200 entrevistas telefónicas mediante el sistema CATI (Computer Assisted Telephone Interviewing), diseñado por el IMC (Instituto de Investigación, Marketing y Comunicación, Sevilla), a sujetos residentes en Andalucía, mayores de 18 años a los que se les realizaron diferentes preguntas sobre el dolor. Resultados: de los 1.200 entrevistados se obtuvo una muestra de 405 pacientes con dolor reciente (30% del total de entrevistados con dolor actual y 3,8% con dolor en el último mes, pero no en este momento). El 15,5% de la población sufre un dolor de tipo crónico. La puntuación media de la intensidad del dolor es de 5,4 (escala 1-10). El dolor afecta sobre todo a espalda, piernas y rodillas; y domina el de tipo reumatológico. El impacto sobre la calidad de vida es notable. El 77,5% de la población con dolor toma medicación oral de prescripción. Casi la mitad de la población ha oído hablar de las unidades del dolor, y la opinión al respecto es favorable. Conclusiones: los datos del estudio aportan información sobre la presencia del dolor en la población andaluza y servirán de base para diseñar estrategias para hacerle frente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;19(5): 239-251, sept.-oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio epidemiológico del dolor en la comunidad autónoma de Andalucía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
