<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046474</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of FDG-PET in the diagnosis of patients with chronic severe brain injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. To describe the changes in cerebral glucose metabolism after a severe traumatic brain injury (TBI), at the beginning of the rehabilitation, to analyze its diagnostic agreement with morphologic neuroimaging technologies (MR/CT) and to correlate the neuroimaging findings with the intensity of the TBI and the functional ability for daily activities. Material and methods. Prospective study of 55 patients who had sustained a severe TBI (GCS &lt;= 8) by means of 18F-FDG PET and MR/CT. The agreement between anatomical and functional neuroimagen studies was measured. Correlation between cerebral injury severity in neuroimaging, clinical functional evaluation assessed with Barthel-M Index and GCS were tested. Results. 100 % of patients showed changes in cerebral metabolism, being the thalamus the area more frequently affected. 60 % of patients showed injuries in MR/CT, more frequently in frontal areas. The agreement for the diagnosis of pathology between morphologic and functional neuroimagen was very low. The TBI severity showed significant statistical correlation with the degree of cerebral metabolism and the level of disability. Conclusions. 18F-FDG PET allows to know the cerebral glucose metabolism at the beginning of the rehabilitation, being correlated with the TBI severity and the level of patient's disability for daily activities. 18F-FDG PET diagnoses major number of injuries that traditional neuroimaging and demonstrates a high thalamic vulnerability, with injuries in up to 76 % of patients with severe TBI</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uruburu, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sopena, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirivella, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueva, L. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Aznar, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir los cambios del metabolismo glucolítico cerebral tras un traumatismo craneoencefálico (TCE) severo en el momento de iniciar la rehabilitación, medir su nivel de acuerdo diagnóstico con las técnicas de neuroimagen morfológica (RM/TC) y correlacionar los hallazgos en neuroimagen con la intensidad del TCE sufrido y con la discapacidad funcional para las actividades de la vida diaria. Material y métodos. Estudio prospectivo de 55 pacientes con antecedente de TCE severo (GCS &lt;= 8) mediante 18F-FDG PET y RM/TC. Medida del acuerdo entre los estudios de neuroimagen anatómica y funcional. Valoración funcional mediante el test de Barthel-M y cálculo de correlación entre la afectación cerebral en neuroimagen y el test de Barthel y la GCS. Resultados. El 100 % de los pacientes presentó alteración en el metabolismo cerebral, siendo los tálamos las áreas más frecuentemente afectadas. El 60 % de los pacientes mostró lesiones en RM/TC, más frecuentemente frontales. El grado de acuerdo para el diagnóstico de patología entre la neuroimagen morfológica y funcional fue muy bajo. La intensidad del traumatismo sufrido y el nivel de discapacidad se correlacionaron de forma estadísticamente significativa con el grado de afectación del metabolismo cerebral. Conclusiones. La PET con 18F-FDG permite conocer el estado del metabolismo glucolítico cerebral en el momento de iniciar la rehabilitación, correlacionándose con la severidad del traumatismo sufrido y con la discapacidad para las actividades de la vida diaria. La PET diagnostica mayor número de lesiones que la neuroimagen anatómica y demuestra una elevada vulnerabilidad talámica, con lesiones hasta en el 76 % de pacientes con antecedente de TCE severo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;25(2): 89-97, mar. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la PET con FDG en la valoración del paciente con traumatismo craneoencefálico severo crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2568^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14167^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2568^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14167^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1501^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1501^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
