<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104192</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish version of the short forms of the Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6) and the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire (IIQ-7) in pregnant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To validate two measurement instruments, the UDI-6 and the IIQ-7, for the study of urinary incontinence and its impact on the quality of life of pregnant women. Methods We carried out a validation study of a diagnostic tool. A total of 181 pregnant women completed the UDI-6 and IIQ-7 questionnaires. Feasibility, internal consistency, reliability, and construct and criteria validity were analyzed. Results Self-administration of the short forms of the UDI-6 and IIQ-7 questionnaires took less than 5minutes and the maximum rate of no answer per item was 3.3%. Cronbach's  alpha was 0.667 for the UDI-6 and was 0.910 for the IIQ-7. The reliability of the UDI-6 in the diagnosis of urinary incontinence showed Kappa statistic values of between 0.856 and 0.966, and the intra-class correlation coefficients of the UDI-6 and IIQ-7 were 0.902 and 0.954, respectively. Average values of the UDI-6 and IIQ-7 were higher in women with mixed incontinence, were lower in women with stress incontinence and increased with daily losses (p&lt;0.01). The correlation between the UDI-6 and the International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire &#150; Short Form (ICIQ-SF) (CCI=0.497; 95% CI: 0.326-0.625) and between the IIQ-7 and ICIQ-SF (CCI=0.472; 95% CI: 0.268-0.619) was moderate. The sensitivity and specificity of the UDI-6 for the diagnosis of urinary incontinence was 98.9% and 86.5%, respectively. Conclusions The Spanish versions of the IIQ-7 and UDI-6 are feasible, reliable, consistent and valid in the measurement of symptoms and quality of life in pregnant Spanish women with urinary incontinence(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Viñaspre Hernández, Regina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Aznar, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Aranda, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Validar dos instrumentos de medida, el UDI-6 y el IIQ-7, para el estudio de la incontinencia urinaria y de su repercusión en la calidad de vida de las mujeres gestantes. Métodos Estudio de validación de un instrumento diagnóstico. Autocumplimentaron los cuestionarios UDI-6 e IIQ-7 181 mujeres embarazadas. Se analizaron la factibilidad, la consistencia interna, la fiabilidad y la validez de constructo y de criterio. Resultados La autocumplimentación del UDI-6 y del IIQ-7 llevo menos de 5 minutos y la tasa máxima de no respuesta por ítem fue del 3,3%. El coeficiente alfa de Cronbach del UDI-6 fue 0,667 y el del IIQ-7 de 0,910. La fiabilidad del UDI-6 para el diagnóstico de incontinencia urinaria presentó valores en el índice Kappa entre 0,856 y 0,966, y la fiabilidad de las puntuaciones del UDI-6 e IIQ-7 mostró valores en el de correlación intraclase de 0,902 y 0,954, respectivamente. Los valores medios del UDI-6 y el IIQ-7 fueron más altos en las mujeres con incontinencia mixta, más bajos en la incontinencia de esfuerzo y aumentaron con las pérdidas diarias (p&lt;0,01). La correlación entre los cuestionarios UDI-6 e ICIQ-SF (coeficiente de correlación intraclase [CCI]=0,497; intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%]: 0,326-0,625) y entre los cuestionarios IIQ-7 e ICIQ-SF (CCI=0,472; IC95%: 0,268- 0,619) resultó mediocre. La sensibilidad y la especificidad del UDI-6 para el diagnóstico de incontinencia urinaria fueron del 98,9% y el 86,7%, respectivamente. Conclusiones Las versiones españolas del IIQ-7 y del UDI-6 son instrumentos factibles, fiables, consistentes y válidos para medir los síntomas y la calidad de vida en las mujeres gestantes españolas con incontinencia urinaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(5): 379-384, sep. - oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104192</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión española de las formas cortas del Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6) y del Incontinence Impact Questionnaire (IIQ-7) en mujeres embarazadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37736^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
