<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96540</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conservative femoral implants. Short stems</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Uncemented hip replacement matches the best results of classic cemented replacements. With the aim of preserving bone and soft tissue, implants with shorter stems and proximal metaphyseal support have been developed. Likewise, the lack of distal load should avoid cortical diaphyseal remodelling phenomena and the thigh pain of some cylindrical and wedge implants. The resurfacing implant, very popular as a conservative hip replacement in the young adult, has disadvantages associated with the fragility of the neck and with large head metal friction torque. Short stem hip replacement may be a reasonable alternative to classic implants and surface hip replacements. The different designs of conservative short stem implants are analysed, and are classified according to their morphology and biomechanical characteristics. Some medium term series show promising results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Belda, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Mordt, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artroplastia de cadera no cementada iguala los mejores resultados de las artroplastias cementadas clásicas. Con el fin de preservar el tejido óseo y las partes blandas, se han desarrollado implantes con vástagos más cortos y con apoyo proximal en la metáfisis. Además, la ausencia de carga distal evitaría los fenómenos de remodelación cortical diafisaria y el dolor de muslo de algunas prótesis de geometría cilíndrica o en cuña. Las prótesis de superficie, muy populares como artroplastia conservadora en el adulto joven, han generado inconvenientes relacionados con la fragilidad del cuello y con el par de fricción metálico de cabeza grande. Las prótesis femorales de vástago corto pueden ser una alternativa ventajosa a las prótesis clásicas y a las artroplastias de superficie. Se analizan los diferentes diseños de prótesis conservadora de vástago corto y se clasifican según su morfología y características biomecánicas. Algunas series, a medio plazo presentan resultados prometedores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(1): 72-79, ene.-feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96540</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prótesis femorales conservadoras. Vástagos cortos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5377^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3993^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3993^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5377^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5369^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5369^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
