<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90893</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic factors of functional impairment in hip fracture patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine the factors that affect functional recovery after a hip fracture. Methods. A study was conducted on a cohort of 333 patients aged 65 years or over with hip fractures who were admitted to Carlos Haya hospital between February 2004 and February 2005. Epidemiological, clinical and functional activity data were recorded by applying generally used scales to determine the patients&#146; functionality before and after the fracture, by means of telephone interviews 6 months after the fracture. Results. Prognostic factors of functional incapacity 6 months after the fracture were age, being institutionalised, having poor functionality before the fracture, being dependent for basic activities of daily living and having had an extracapsular fracture or undergoing osteosynthesis. Conclusions. It is possible to determine the prognosis of a hip fracture patient on admission. The use of extramedullary fixation systems failed to show good results compared with arthroplasty. Intramedullary osteosynthesis (used only in 5 patients), and an early start of rehabilitation could improve the functional results of these patients. In fact, intramedullary nailing has demonstrated better outcomes in unstable trochanteric and subtrochanteric femoral fractures vs Dynamic Screw and Plate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Collado-Torres, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jódar, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez-Pérez, L. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo-Bardají, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuellar-Obispo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva-Pareja, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer los factores que determinan la recuperación funcional tras haber sufrido una fractura de cadera. Método. Se ha realizado un estudio de cohortes sobre 333 fracturas de cadera en pacientes mayores de 65 años, que ingresaron en el Hospital Regional Universitario Carlos Haya entre febrero de 2004 y febrero de 2005. Hemos recogido datos epidemiológicos, clínicos y de actividad funcional de dichos pacientes mediante la aplicación de escalas de uso generalizado, para conocer la funcionalidad que presentan antes de la fractura y en el seguimiento posterior, mediante entrevistas telefónicas a los 6 meses tras la misma. Resultados. A los 6 meses de la fractura los factores pronósticos de incapacidad funcional son la edad, el hecho de estar institucionalizado, presentar una mala funcionalidad previa a la fractura, ser dependiente para las actividades básicas de la vida diaria y la circunstancia de haber presentado una fractura extracapsular o que haya sido sometida a osteosíntesis. Conclusiones. Podemos conocer el pronóstico del paciente con fractura de cadera al ingreso, el uso de sistemas de fijación extramedular no ha mostrado buenos resultados en nuestro trabajo frente a la artroplastia. La osteosíntesis intramedular (usada únicamente en 5 casos) junto a un inicio precoz de la rehabilitación podrían mejorar los resultados funcionales de estos pacientes, ya que ha demostrado ser superior en las fracturas pertrocantéreas inestables y en las subtrocantéreas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(5): 334-339, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores pronósticos de incapacidad funcional en pacientes con fractura de cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
