<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143735</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linear shock wave therapy in the treatment of erectile dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Linear Shock Wave Therapy (LSWT) is a new noninvasive therapy that uses low-intensity shock waves to induce local angiogenesis promising modality in the treatment of erectile dysfunction (ED). Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness of LSWT in men with vasculogenic erectile dysfunction (ED), in a Tertiary Care Center. Material and methods: Included 15 men aged 45-70 years, sexually active with mild and moderate vascular ED evaluated with the International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF). The study was conducted in three stage: screening, treatment and results. Treatment stage: 4 weekly sessions LSWT (RENOVA ®) 5000 waves (.09 mJ/mm2). Erectile function was assessed with IIEFF-EF, SEP (Sexual Encounter Profile) and GAQ (Global Assessment Questions) at one and six months after treatment. Results: The rate of success was 80% (12/15). Patients with mild ED (6/15) 40% and moderate ED (9/15) 60%. We found a positive association between IIEF-Basal (average 14.23 pts) and IIEF at one month and six months after therapy (19.69 pts) a difference of 5.46 pts. (P &lt; .013). Conclusions: The feasibility and tolerability of this treatment, and rehabilitation potential features, make it this an attractive new treatment option for patients with ED (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bertrand-Noriega, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelayo-Nieto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño-de la Rosa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alias-Melgar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa-Pérez Grovas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linden-Castro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortez-Betancourt, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La terapia de ondas de choque lineales (LSWT) es una nueva terapia no invasiva que utiliza ondas de choque de baja intensidad para inducir la angiogénesis local controlada y mejorar significativamente la función eréctil. Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia de la LSWT en hombres con disfunción eréctil vasculogénica (DE) en un centro de atención de tercer nivel. Material y métodos: Se incluyeron 15 hombres de edades comprendidas entre 45 y 70 años, sexualmente activos con DE vascular leve y moderada, evaluados con el índice internacional de función eréctil (IIEF). El estudio se realizó en 3 etapas: detección, tratamiento y seguimiento. Recibieron 4 sesiones de LSWT semanales (RENOVA®) 5.000 ondas (0,09 mJ/mm2). La función eréctil se evaluó con IIEFF-EF, Perfil del encuentro sexual (SEP) y Cuestionario de evaluación global (GAQ) al mes y a los 6 meses después del tratamiento. Resultados: La tasa de éxito fue del 80% (12/15). Pacientes con DE leve 40% y DE moderada 60%. Se encontró una asociación positiva entre el IIEF-basal (promedio 14,23 pts) y IIEF un mes y 6 meses después del tratamiento (19,69 pts) una diferencia de 5,46 puntos (p &lt; 0,013). Conclusiones: La factibilidad y tolerabilidad de este tratamiento, y sus características potenciales de rehabilitación, hacen que pueda ser una nueva opción terapéutica atractiva para pacientes con DE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;39(7): 456-459, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de ondas de choque lineales en el tratamiento de la disfunción eréctil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32177^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38327^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32177^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
