<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61159</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on infections in ICU patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Studies carried out in 2006 on severe community-acquiredpneumonia or nosocomial pneumonia requiring admissionto the ICU are numerous and of a high quality. Amongstudies of community-acquired pneumonia, the mostrelevant are those focused on the development andevaluation of systems for the identification of patientswith severe pneumonia, analysis of the impact of theinitial inflammatory response on the course of the disease,and level of adherence to therapeutic guidelines proposedby different scientific societies. Among studiesof nosocomial pneumonia, those involving ventilatorassociatedpneumonia and health care-associatedpneumonia should be emphasized. The reliabilityof different respiratory sampling methods for theetiological diagnosis of pneumonia, the impact of differentetiological agents, and the efficacy of prophylacticmeasures have been the object of different investigations.Important aspects of these studies include the assessmentof different strategies in the use of antimicrobial agentsto decrease the selection of multiresistant pathogens.Moreover, early identification of patients at risk of invasivefungal infections, as well as preemptive treatmentof these infections in selected patients have beentopics of increasing interest(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solé-Violán, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Baño, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garnacho-Montero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olaechea, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borges, Marcio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Cristóbal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Lerma, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, Leonardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Rocha, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaragoza, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios realizados en 2006 sobre la neumoníaextrahospitalaria grave o la neumonía nosocomialque requieren el ingreso en la UCI son numerosos y degran calidad. Entre los trabajos sobre la neumoníaextrahospitalaria, los más relevantes son los que se basanen el desarrollo y la valoración de los sistemas paraidentificar a los pacientes con neumonía grave, en elanálisis del impacto de la respuesta inflamatoria inicialsobre el curso de la enfermedad, y en el nivel deseguimiento de las normas terapéuticas propuestas pordiferentes sociedades científicas. Entre los estudios sobrela neumonía nosocomial, cabe destacar los relacionadoscon la neumonía asociada al respirador o a la asistenciasanitaria. La fiabilidad de los distintos métodos paraobtener muestras respiratorias con el fin de establecerel diagnóstico etiológico, el impacto de los diferentesagentes etiológicos, y la eficacia de las medidasprofilácticas, han sido objeto de diversas investigaciones.Entre los aspectos importantes de estos estudios se hallala valoración de las diferentes estrategias para el usode los agentes antimicrobianos con el fin de reducir laselección de los gérmenes plurirresistentes. Además,la identificación precoz de los pacientes con riesgo deinfecciones micóticas invasivas, así como el tratamientoprecoz de estas infecciones en determinados pacientes,han sido otros tantos temas de interés general(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.3): 39-48, abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización sobre infecciones en pacientes de la UCI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
