<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049991</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Skin lesions and muscle weakness in an 11-year-old girl</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dermatomyositis is an idiopathic inflammatory myopathy associated with characteristic cutaneous findings. In 1975, Bohan and Peter first suggested a set of criteria to aid in the diagnosis and classification of dermatomyositis and polymyositis. Four of the five criteria are related to the muscle disease, as follows: progressive proximal symmetrical weakness, elevated muscle enzymes, an abnormal finding on electromyogram, and an abnormal finding on the muscle biopsy sample. The fifth criterion was compatibles kin disease. The pathogenesis of the cutaneous disease is poorly understood. Dermatomyositis is a systemic disorder that frequently affects the esophagus and lungs and, less commonly, may affect the heart. Calcinosisis a complication that is observed most often in children or adolescents. Therapy for the muscle component involves the use of corticosteroids with or without an immunosuppressive agent. The skin disease is treated with sun avoidance, sun screens, topical corticosteroids, antimalarial agents, methotrexate, mycophenolate mofetil and/or intravenous immuneglobulin. The prognosis depends on the severity of the myopathy, the presence of a malignancy, and/or the presence of  cardiopulmonary involvement</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernanz Hermosa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabeza Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leis Dosil, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barchino, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dermatomiositis es una miopatia inflamatoria idiopática con unos hallazgos cutáneos característicos. En 1975, Bohan y Peter establecen por primera vez una serie de criterios clínicos para ayudar al diagnóstico y clasificación de la dermatomiositis y la polimiositis. Cuatro de los 5 criterios guardan relación con la afección muscular: la debilidad muscular proximal y simétrica de cintura escapular y pelviana, la elevación de enzimas musculares séricas, los cambios electromiográficos y la biopsia muscular compatible. El quinto criterio es compatible con lesiones cutáneas características. La patogenia de esta enfermedad está poco clara. La dermatomiositis es una enfermedad sistémica que frecuentemente afecta al esófago y los pulmones, siendo menos común la afectación cardiaca. La calcinosis es una complicación que se observa especialmente en niños y adolescentes. La terapia dirigida a la inflamación muscular incluye el uso de corticoterapia sistémica, acompañada o no por otros agentes inmunosupresores. La clínica cutánea se puede tratar con la prohibición de exposición solar, corticoides tópicos, antipalúdicos, metrotexato, micofenolato de mofetil y/o inmunoglobulinas intravenosas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;64(8): 386-390, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049991</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones cutáneas y deilidad muscular en una niña de 11 años de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1329^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30612^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14062^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
