<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80865</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional outcome total elbow arthroplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Total elbow arthroplasty (ATC) is indicated in patients with disabling pain and severe functional limitation, which is not possible another surgical technique that preserves the mobility. The objetive of our work is to evaluate the clinical and functional results of the ATC at the Hospital Clinic of Barcelona in the last 10 years (January 1999&#150;January 2009). Patients and methods. Cross-sectional study including 25 patients. We analyzed demographic variables (age and sex), clinical (etiology, pain, joint of motion and muscular streng) and functional outcome measured with the MEPI scale (Mayo Elbow Performance Index) and the DASH questionnaire (Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand). Results. Mean age 63,7 (11,9) years, 68,42% women. As main etiologies found rheumatoid arthritis (35%), primary osteoarthritis (20%), postraumatic osteoarthritis (35%) and other causes (10%). The mean pain score was 2,78 (SD 2,01) in the visual analogue scale. The average joint stock was found: &amp;#8722;33,42° (SD 23,86) in length, 125,26° (SD 24,76) of flexion, 86,3° (DE11,65) of pronation, 72,36° (SD 26,47) of supination. The muscular strengt in Newtons was 27,98 (of 19,06) for extension, 78,72 (OF 49,62) for flexion and a force of Paw Pounds 33,82 (SD 21,01). We obtained a mean score of 76,7 (SD 16,3) in the MEPI scale and 78,5 (SD 28,9) in the DASH questionnaire. Conclusions. Total elbow arthroplasty provides over other surgical techniques, a good range of motion and functionality to the basic activities of daily living, like this as it improves the pain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cáneva, F. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Mariscal, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarrasa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arandes Renu, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López O&#146;Rourke, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Corretger, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orient López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sañudo Martín, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La artroplastia total de codo (ATC) está indicada en pacientes que presentan dolor incapacitante y limitación funcional severa, en los que no es posible realizar otra técnica quirúrgica que conserve la movilidad. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo es valorar los resultados clínicos y funcionales de las ATC realizadas en el Hospital Clínic de Barcelona en los últimos 10 años (enero de 1999&#150;enero de 2009). Pacientes y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal que incluye a 25 pacientes. Se analizan variables demográficas (edad y sexo), clínicas (etiología, dolor, balance articular y balance muscular) y resultados funcionales medidos con la escala de Mayo Elbow Performance Index y el cuestionario Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand. Resultados. Edad media de 63,7 años (DE 11,9); el 68,42% eran mujeres. Como principales etiologías encontramos artritis reumatoide (35%), artrosis primarias (20%) artrosis postraumática (35%) y otras causas (10%). La puntuación media de dolor fue de 2,78 (DE: 2,01) en la escala visual analógica. El balance articular medio encontrado fue de &amp;#8722;33,42° de extensión (DE: 23,86), 125,26° de flexión (DE: 24,76), 86,3° de pronación (DE: 11,65) y 72,36° de supinación (DE: 26,47). El balance muscular medio en newtons fue de 27,98 para la extensión (DE: 19,06), de 78,72 para la flexión (DE: 49,62) y una fuerza de garra de 33,82 pounds (DE: 21,01). Se obtuvo una puntuación media de 76,7 (DE: 16,3) en la escala de Mayo Elbow Performance Index y una puntuación media de 78,5 (DE: 28,9) en el cuestionario Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand. Conclusiones. La ATC proporciona, respecto a otras técnicas quirúrgicas, un buen rango de movilidad y funcionalidad para las actividades básicas de la vida diaria, así como mejoría de la sintomatología dolorosa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);44(3): 216-222, jul.-sep.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados funcionales en artroplastia total de codo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4624^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4624^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
