<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045968</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteochondroma of the coronoid process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteochondroma is the most common benign neoplasia of the skeleton. In the head it was been described in cranial base, posterior maxillary surface, maxillary sinus, and different mandibular areas like condyle, ramus, body and symphysis. Osteochondroma of the coronoid process are rare.    We present a review of the literature and the report of the cas of a 44 years old female patient presenting limited mouth opening and swelling of the left cheek, with diffuse limits, bony consistency, painless, and covered of normal skin. No temporomandibular joint disease was present.    In panoramic radiographs was evident a coronoid tumor localized in the union of zigomatic arch and bone.    Under general anaesthesia coronoidectomy was made, recovering mouth opening until 43 mm. The post-operative period was performed without complications.    Histopatological examinations revealed normal trabecular bone covered with hyaline cartilage. The histopatological diagnosis was osteochondroma.    Clinical and pathological aspects, treatment and differential diagnosis with other lesions are discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Cristián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cornejo, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encina, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El osteocondroma es la neoplasia benigna más común del esqueleto. En la cabeza se ha descrito su localización en base de cráneo, cara posterior del maxilar, senos maxilares, y en diferentes áreas de la mandíbula, como cóndilo, rama, cuerpo y región sinfisiaria, siendo los osteocondromas coronoídeos de baja frecuencia.    Presentamos una revisión de la literatura y el informe de un nuevo caso. Una mujer de 44 años que consulta por limitación    de la apertura bucal y deformidad en la mejilla izquierda, de límites difusos, consistencia ósea, indolora y cubierta por piel de aspecto normal. No presentaba patología en la articulación témporomandibular.    En la radiografía panorámica se evidencia un tumor coronoídeo localizado en la zona de unión del arco cigomático y el hueso malar.    Se realizó la coronoidectomía bajo anestesia general, recuperándose inmediatamente la apertura bucal hasta 43 mm. El postoperatorio se desarrolló sin complicaciones.    El estudio histopatológico reveló hueso esponjoso normal sobre el cual se encontró cartílago hialino. El diagnóstico fue osteocondroma.    Los aspectos clínicos y patológicos, su tratamiento y diagnóstico diferencial son discutidos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(3): E289-E291, mayo 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteocondroma de apófisis coronoides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
