<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68052</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To investigate the colon&#146;s development in rats subjected to protein energy malnutrition followed by supplementation with rice bran. Materials and methods: Weaned Wistar male rats (21days old), weight (40-50 g) were divided into two groups: diet with 17% protein (C; control group) or an aproteic diet (A; aproteic group), for 12 days. After this, 50% of the rats from each group were sacrificed. The remaining rats were further distributed in the three groups for are covery (21 days): control (C) continued to receive the control diet whereas the aproteic group (A) received either a control diet (AC) or a control diet supplemented with 5% of rice bran (ARB).Results: The A group showed alterations in the colon and cecum, excreted dry feces mass and fecal nitrogen, compared with C rats. In the proximal colon of A rats, the external muscularis and the width of the colon wall were higher whereas in the distal colon they were lower than C. After the recovery period, the relative cecum mass, colon mass and colon length of the recovered groups (AC and ARB) were higher than in the C group. Dry feces and fecal nitrogen excreted of the rats from recovered groups were lower than C group. Colon length of the AC group was lower than in the C group. Only the crypt&#146;s depth from ARB group was higher than in the C group. Conclusion: Control diet supplemented with 5% rice bran, reestablished the large intestine of aproteic rats. The recovery in the ARB group was even better than in the AC rats</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latorraca, MQ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nascimento, CM Oller do</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martins, M. Salete F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dores, EFGC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Nascimento, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Missae Oyama, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomes-da-Silva, MHG</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: investigar el desarrollo del colon en ratas sometidas a malnutrición proteico-calórica seguida de complementación con salvado de arroz. Material y métodos: se emplearon ratas Wistar macho destetadas (de 21 días de edad), peso (40-50 g) que se dividieron en dos grupos: dieta con 17% de proteínas (C, grupo control) y dieta a proteica (A, grupo a proteico),durante 12 días. Tras ello, se sacrificó al 50% de las ratas de cada grupo. A las ratas restantes se las dividió en tres grupos de recuperación (21 días): grupo control (C) que continuó recibiendo la dieta control mientras que el grupo a proteico (A) recibía o bien una dieta control (AC) o una dieta complementada con salvado de arroz al 5% (ARB).Resultados: El grupo A mostró alteraciones en el colon y el ciego, excretaba heces secas y nitrógeno fecal, en comparación con las ratas C. En el colon proximal de las ratas A, la capa muscular externa y el grosor de la pared del colon estaba aumentados mientras que en el colon distal estaban disminuidos con respecto a C. Tras el periodo de recuperación, la masa relativa del ciego, la masa del colon y la longitud del colon de los grupos recuperados (AC y ARB) eran mayores que en el grupo C. Las heces secas y el nitrógeno fecal excretados por las ratas de los grupos con recuperación eran menores que los del grupo C. La longitud del colon del grupo AC era menor que la del grupo C. Tan sólo la profundidad de las criptas en el grupo ARB era mayor que la del grupo C. Conclusión: Una dieta control complementada con salvado de arroz al 5% restableció el intestino grueso de las ratas a proteicas. La recuperación en el grupo ABR fue incluso mejor que en las ratas AC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(6): 648-653, nov.-dic. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68052</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12685^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3138^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30578^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
