<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131152</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pre-analgesic consultation for labour: a project comes true</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of this study is to report the strategy followed in the Hospital Universitario Puerto Real (Cádiz, Spain) to create a pre-analgesic consultation for labor in order to provide an appropriate analgesia during delivery, complying with Law 41/2002 which regulates the autonomy rights and obligations of patients regarding information and clinical documentation. We evaluate the approach taken in the rest of the hospitals in Andalusia. Material and method: We analyzed the challenges and difficulties that arose at the time and the strategy for the creation of this consultation. The questions which were raised were: At what stage of pregnancy pregnant women should attend the consultation? What staffing and training would be required to create this consultation? Where would it be located? What materials would be needed to properly inform our pregnant women? We conducted a phone survey in order to determine how our response was given to labor analgesia and how Law 41/2002 was being applying in the rest of hospitals in Andalusia. Results: The pre-analgesic labor consultation of the Hospital Universitario Puerto Real was created in February 2007. Training courses were developed for delivery room staffing. Consultations are currently carried out during the 20th week of gestation, coincident with the echography done by the Gynecology Service of the Hospital. The staffs assigned are a nurse assistant and the anesthesiologist on duty in the delivery room. The consultation room is located in the in the outpatient department of the hospital and has a capacity for 12 people. Pregnant women receive a lecture and an informative video. After this, we complete the individualized pre-analgesic assessment of each patient and the informed consent process. Since its creation, they have been cited 12,990 pregnant women. The annual average of pregnant women informed and preoperatively evaluated is of 1,384; which represents the 63.93 % of all pregnant women. Twenty-seven of the 33 hospitals of the Andalusia Health System in which deliveries are practiced, telephone survey respondents. The results of this survey show that the pre-anesthetic assessment for pregnant women is only performed in 8 centers (29.63 %), in 5 of them routinely (8.52 %) and only to high-risk pregnant women in 3 (11.1 %). The informed consents are obtained before the delivery only in 9 of the 27 hospitals surveyed (33 %). In the 18 centers remaining they were obtained at delivery (66.67 %). Conclusions: Since the foundation of the pre-analgesic consultation for delivery in our hospital, we have improved the pre-analgesic assessment of pregnant women and we have achieved complying with Law 41/2012 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira Reina, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega García, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aceña Fabian, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vasquez Lobo, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el objetivo del presente estudio es dar a conocer la estrategia seguida en el Hospital Universitario Puerto Real para crear una consulta preanalgésica del parto con el fin de dar respuesta a los derechos de la embarazada a recibir una adecuada analgesia durante el trabajo del parto, cumpliendo la Ley 41/2002 Reguladora de la autonomía del paciente y de derechos y obligaciones en materia de información y documentación clínica. Valorar la situación en el resto de los hospitales andaluces. Material y método: analizamos los retos y dificultades que se plantearon en su momento y la estrategia para la creación de esta consulta. Las cuestiones que se plantearon fueron: ¿en qué momento de la gestación deberían acudir las gestantes? ¿Qué necesidades de personal y formación de personal supondría la creación de esta consulta? ¿Dónde se ubicaría la consulta? ¿Qué material didáctico sería necesario para informar adecuadamente a nuestras gestantes? Para determinar cómo se había dado respuesta a la analgesia del parto y la aplicación de la Ley 41/2002 en el resto de los hospitales andaluces realizamos una encuesta telefónica. Resultados: la consulta de preanalgesia para el parto comenzó en nuestro hospital en febrero del año 2007. Se desarrollaron cursos de formación para el personal de paritorio. La consulta se realiza en la semana 20 de gestación haciéndola coincidir con la ecografía que realiza el Servicio de Ginecología en la semana 20. El personal asignado es una auxiliar de enfermería y el anestesiólogo de guardia asignado a paritorio. La consulta se ubica en una sala en el Hospital de Día con capacidad suficiente para 12 personas, donde se imparte una charla y se proyecta un vídeo informativo. Posteriormente se hace una valoración individualizada, se cumplimenta y firma el consentimiento informado. Desde la creación de la consulta de preanalgesia del parto han sido citadas en la consulta 12.990 gestantes. La media anual de gestantes informadas y valoradas preoperatoriamente es de 1.384, lo que supone un 63,93 % del total de las gestantes. Los datos obtenidos de las encuestas telefónicas realizadas en los Centros Hospitalarios del Sistema Andaluz de Salud, corresponden a 27 de los 33 centros hospitalarios en los que se atienden partos. La valoración preanestésica a las gestantes sólo se realiza en 8 centros (29,63 %), en 5 de ellos de forma rutinaria (18,52 %) y en 3 (11,1 %) sólo a las gestantes de alto riesgo. El consentimiento informado se obtiene previamente al momento del parto tan sólo en 9 de los 27 hospitales encuestados (33,33 %), en los 18 centros restantes se obtiene en el momento del parto (66,67 %). Conclusiones: desde que se instauró la consulta de preanalgesia del parto en nuestro hospital se ha mejorado la valoración preanalgésica de la gestante y hemos conseguido dar cumplimiento a la Ley 41/2012 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;21(6): 315-322, nov.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consulta preanalgésica del parto. Un proyecto hecho realidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38636^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38636^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
