<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121145</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Involvement of HLA Class I Molecules in the Immune Escape of Urologic Tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Context and objective: To analyze the influence of different alterations in human leukocyte antigen class I molecules (HLA I) in renal cell carcinoma, as well as in bladder and prostate cancer. We also study the correlation between HLA I expression and the progression of the disease and the response after immunotherapy protocols. Evidences acquisition: It has been shown, experimentally, that the immune system can recognize and kill neoplastic cells. By analyzing the expression of HLA I molecules on the surface of cancer cells, we were able to study the tumor escape mechanisms against the immune system. Evidences synthesis: Alteration or irreversible damage in HLA I molecules is used by the neoplastic cells to escape the immune system. The function of these molecules is to recognize endogenous peptides and present them to T cells of the immune system. There is a clear relationship between HLA I reversible alterations and success of therapy. Irreversible lesions also imply a lack of response to treatment. The immune system activation can reverse HLA I molecules expression in tumors with reversible lesions, whereas tumors with irreversible ones do not respond to such activation. Determine the type of altered HLA I molecules in tumors is of paramount importance when choosing the type of treatment to keep looking for therapeutic success. Those tumors with reversible lesions can be treated with traditional immunotherapy; however, tumour with irreversible alterations should follow alternative protocols, such as the use of viral vectors carrying the HLA genes to achieve damaged re-expression of the protein. Conclusion: From studies in urologic tumors, we can conclude that the HLA I molecules play a key role in these tumors escape to the immune system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cózar, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castiñeiras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Julio, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Alonso, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Contexto y objetivo: Analizar la influencia de las distintas alteraciones de las moléculas del antígeno leucocitario humano de clase i (HLA I ) en la promoción del cáncer renal, vesical y prostático. También estudiaremos la correlación entre la expresión de estas moléculas y la progresión de la enfermedad neoplásica, además de la respuesta al tratamiento. Adquisición de evidencias: Se ha podido constatar, experimentalmente, que el sistema inmunitario puede reconocer y destruir células tumorales. Mediante el análisis de la expresión de las moléculas HLA I, en la superficie de células tumorales, hemos podido estudiar este mecanismo de escape tumoral frente al sistema inmunitario. Síntesis de evidencias: Una alteración o daño irreversible en las moléculas HLA de clase i es utilizado por las células cancerígenas como mecanismo de escape frente al sistema inmunitario. La función de estas moléculas es reconocer péptidos endógenos y presentarlos a los linfocitos T del sistema inmunitario. Existe una clara relación entre alteraciones reversibles de HLA I y el éxito de la terapia, mientras que las lesiones irreversibles implican una falta de respuesta al tratamiento. La activación del sistema inmunitario puede revertir la expresión de moléculas HLA I en aquellos tumores con lesiones reversibles, mientras que los tumores con lesiones irreversibles no responden a dicha activación. Determinar el tipo de alteración HLA I en los tumores es de vital importancia a la hora de elegir el tipo de tratamiento a seguir buscando el éxito terapéutico. Aquellos tumores con lesiones reversibles pueden ser tratados con inmunoterapias clásicas, sin embargo, los tumores con alteraciones irreversibles deberían seguir protocolos alternativos, como el uso de vectores virales que trasporten los genes HLA dañados para conseguir la reexpresión de la proteína. Conclusión: A partir de los estudios realizados, en tumores urológicos, podemos concluir que las moléculas HLA de clase i tienen un papel fundamental en el escape de estos tumores frente al sistema inmunitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;38(3): 192-199, abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicación de las moléculas HLA de clase I en el escape inmunitario de tumores urológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6837^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29575^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
