<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046001</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of metabolic syndrome in the adult population of Yecla (Murcia). Degree of agreement between three definitions of it</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the prevalence of metabolic syndrome (MS), its components and insulin resistance (IR) in the adult population of Yecla. To study the variability between 3 definitions of the syndrome and IR. To identify the variables that predict the presence of IR and to verify the diagnostic validity of several strategies for predicting it.                 Design. Descriptive, cross-sectional study.                 Setting. Primary care, Yecla (Murcia), Spain.                 Participants. We studied 317 persons (292 with analysis) out of 424 selected by stratified (age and sex) random sampling from 18 059 people &gt;=30 years old and possessing a health card.                 Main measurements. We used WHO-98, NCEP III, and EGIR criteria for diagnosing MS, and WHO-99 for defining DM2, impaired basal glucose and impaired glucose tolerance. The following variables were collected: social, demographic and personal details, plasma lipid, glycosylated haemoglobin, microalbuminuria, and insulin levels. IR was defined by the HOMA method at &gt;=3.8 or as the highest quartile of basal insulinemia in normoglycaemic persons.                 Results. MS prevalence was NCEP 20.2% (95% CI, 15.6-24.8), WHO 35.3% (95% CI, 29.8-40.8), EGIR 24% (95% CI, 19.1-28.9), and IR was 27.7% (95% CI, 22.6-32.8). The sensitivity and specificity of NCEP, WHO, and EGIR criteria for detecting IR were (46% and 90%), (78% and 81%), and (73% and 95%), respectively. Insulin resistance was associated significantly with age, basal glycaemia, triglycerides, and waist circumference.                 Conclusions. Metabolic syndrome is common in Yecla (more so in men). There is disagreement between several diagnostic criteria for the syndrome, with NCEP criteria less sensitive in determining IR. A generally accepted definition is needed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cánovas Domínguez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Candela, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Martín, Arístides</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páez Pérez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franch Nadal, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Ortiz, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Detectar la prevalencia del síndrome metabólico (SM), sus componentes y la resistencia a la insulina (RI) en la población adulta de Yecla. Estudiar la concordancia de         3 definiciones del SM entre sí y con la RI. Identificar variables que puedan predecir la presencia de RI y comprobar la validez diagnóstica de varias estrategias para predecirla.                 Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, transversal.                 Emplazamiento. Población de Yecla (Murcia). Ámbito de atención primaria.                 Participantes. Estudiamos a 317 personas         (292 aportaron analítica) de 424 seleccionadas mediante muestreo aleatorio estratificado (edad y sexo) de 18.059 con tarjeta sanitaria y edad é 30 años.                 Mediciones principales. Utilizamos los criterios NCEP III, OMS-98 y EGIR (Grupo Europeo de Estudio de la Resistencia a la Insulina) para diagnosticar el SM y OMS-99 para definir la diabetes mellitus no insulinodependiente, la glucemia basal alterada y la tolerancia alterada a la glucosa.                 Recogimos variables sociodemográficas y antropométricas, y determinamos la presencia de lípidos, microalbuminuria, HbA1c e insulinemia; definimos RI si el índice HOMA é 3,8 o como cuartil más alto de insulinemia basal en normoglucémicos.                 Resultados. La prevalencia del SM fue, según los criterios NCEP, del 20,2% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 15,6-24,8), OMS del 35,3% (IC del 95%, 29,8-40,8), EGIR del 24% (IC del 95%, 19,1-28,9) y RI del 27,7% (IC del 95%, 22,6-32,8).                 La sensibilidad y la especificidad de NCEP, OMS y EGIR para detectar RI fueron del 46 y el 90%, del 78 y el 81% y del 73 y el 95%, respectivamente. La edad, la glucemia basal, los triglicéridos y el perímetro de la cintura se asocian significativamente con RI.                 Conclusiones. Hay una alta prevalencia de SM en el área (mayor en los varones). Hay diferencias entre los diferentes criterios diagnósticos del síndrome, y los de NCEP son menos sensible para determinar la RI. Es necesario establecer una definición universalmente aceptada del SM</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;38(2): 72-79, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del síndrome metabólico en la población adulta de Yecla (Murcia). Grado de acuerdo entre tres definiciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
