<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79618</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in delivery in Spain. Analysis of the minimum data set for hospital discharges</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To describe variations in the utilization rates of distinct delivery-related procedures in the various autonomous regions, provinces and types of hospital in Spain. Subjects and methods A cross-sectional study was conducted, using the number of deliveries performed in Spain (2001-2006) as the unit of analysis, together with data drawn from the Minimum Data Set (MDS) for hospitable discharges. Data were pooled and a descriptive analysis was performed according to the study variables.ResultsThe number of childbirths in Spain increased at a rate of 10,000 to 15,000 per annum. The percentage breakdown of deliveries was as follows: non-instrumental 62.7%; instrumental, 15.1%; and cesarean section, 22.2%. There was wide variability in all the procedures studied among provinces, autonomous regions and types of hospital. Conclusions The results obtained highlight the wide variability in delivery in Spain in terms of time and geography, as well as of clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Ratón, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maceira Rozas, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado Barreira, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atienza Merino, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Describir las variaciones existentes en las tasas de utilización de los diversos procedimientos relacionados con el parto, en las diferentes comunidades autónomas españolas, provincias y tipos de hospital. Sujetos y métodos Estudio transversal; la unidad de análisis fueron los partos realizados en España (2001-2006) y la fuente de información, el CMBD al alta hospitalaria. Se realizó una agregación de los datos y un análisis descriptivo en función de las variables de estudio. ResultadosEl número de partos se incrementó en España a un ritmo de 10.000-15.000 partos al año. El porcentaje de partos no instrumentados fue del 62,7%, el de partos instrumentados del 15,1% y el de cesáreas del 22,2%. Se observó una gran variabilidad en todos los procedimientos estudiados, tanto entre provincias, como CCAA o tipos de hospitales. Conclusiones Los resultados obtenidos muestran la gran variabilidad existente en la asistencia al parto, tanto desde el punto de vista temporal, geográfico, y de la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(6): 215-222, jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79618</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad del parto en España. Análisis del conjunto mínimo básico de datos al alta hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4920^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
