<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121183</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasonography managed by internists: the stethoscope of 21th Century?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ultrasonography in the hands of the internist can answer important clinical questions quickly at the point of patient care. This technique &#147;enhance&#148; the senses of the physicians and improves their ability to solve the problems of the patient. Point of care ultrasonography performed by clinicians has shown good accuracy in the diagnosis of diverse cardiac, abdominal and vascular pathologic conditions. It may also be useful for evaluation of thyroid, osteoarticular and soft tissue diseases. Furthermore, the use of ultrasound to guide invasive procedures (placement of venous catheters, thoracentesis, paracentesis) reduces the risk of complications. We present 5cases to illustrate the usefulness of this technique in clinical practice: (i)peripartum cardiomyopathy; (ii)subclinical carotid artery atherosclerosis; (iii)asymptomatic abdominal aortic aneurysm; (iv)tendinitis of long head of biceps brachii and supraspinatus, and (v)spontaneous soleus muscle haematoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Casasola, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ecografía en manos del internista permite responder preguntas clínicas concretas de forma rápida en el lugar de atención al paciente. Esta técnica «potencia» los sentidos del clínico y mejora su capacidad para resolver los problemas del enfermo. La ecografía clínica ha mostrado una buena precisión en el diagnóstico de diversas patologías cardíacas, abdominales y vasculares. También es útil para la evaluación de la patología tiroidea, osteoarticular y de partes blandas. Además, el uso de la ecografía para guiar procedimientos invasivos (accesos venosos, toracocentesis, paracentesis) reduce el riesgo de complicaciones. Presentamos 5casos para ilustrar la utilidad de esta técnica en la práctica clínica habitual del médico internista: a)miocardiopatía periparto; b)ateromatosis carotídea subclínica; c)aneurisma de aorta abdominal asintomático; d)tendinitis de los tendones largo del bíceps braquial y supraespinoso, y e)hematoma espontáneo en sóleo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(3): 155-160, abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ecografía en manos del internista: ¿el estetoscopio del sigloxxi?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30992^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30992^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
