<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85168</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of flow cytometry in assessing the effect of atorvastatin on platelet function and Ca2+ in hyperlipemic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Thrombotic events are common in hyperlipemic patients in which platelet activation play a decisive role. The presence of activated platelets, as described in a previous paper, is a major risk factor for thrombosis in patients with a high plasma cholesterol and it is therefore of great interest to have a lipid lowering drug that, in addition to normalising plasma lipids, also decreases this activation of circulating platelets. The main aims of this study are to assess whether the increased platelet activation in hypercholesterolemic patients is accompanied by changes in cytoplasmic free calcium mobilisation in platelets and the formation of platelet microaggregates, and whether these changes are normalised by treatment with atorvastatin. Material and methods. To achieve these aims 30 hypercholesterolemia patients and 40 normolipemic controls were recruited. The percentage of CD62 positive platelets, the number of spontaneously formed platelet microaggregates (MAP/5000 platelets) and the free calcium mobilization in platelets were evaluated in citrated blood . An EPICS-XL flow cytometer and the antibodies and fluorochromes CD61.PE, CD62.FITC and FLUO3-AM were used for this study. The patients were evaluated before and after two months of atorvastatin (20mg/day) treatment. Results. The results show that atorvastatin treatment significantly decreases the plasma concentration of total and LDL-Cholesterol and triglycerides. In parallel a decrease was noted in the percentage of activated circulating CD62 positive platelets (2.41±1.55% to 1.45±1.06%, P&lt;0.05) and also in the number of spontaneously formed MAP (390±43 to 322±48, P&lt;0.05). These changes were accompanied by the normalization in the free calcium mobilization in platelets. Conclusions. As a conclusion it is noted that the flow cytometry of whole blood is a useful technique for evaluating aspects such as those raised in this study. Hypercholesterolemia patients showed more spontaneous platelet activation, which was accompanied by the formation of platelet microaggregates and changes in the cytoplasmic free calcium mobilization, which were normalised by treatment with atorvastatin, which has not been previously reported in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gabriel Botella, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muresan, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guiral Olivan, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Silvestre, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñarrocha García, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labiós Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En pacientes hiperlipémicos resultan frecuentes los procesos trombóticos, en los que las plaquetas desempeñan un papel decisivo. La presencia de plaquetas activadas circulantes, descrito en un trabajo anterior, constituye un importante factor de riesgo trombótico, por lo que resulta de gran interés disponer de un fármaco hipolipemiante que, además de normalizar los lípidos plasmáticos, también disminuya la activación de las plaquetas circulantes.Los principales objetivos del presente estudio son valorar si la mayor activación plaquetaria de los pacientes hipercolesterolémicos se acompaña de cambios en la movilización del calcio libre citoplasmático plaquetario y si dichas alteraciones se normalizan mediante la medicación con atorvastatina. Material y métodos. Para alcanzar éstos objetivos se estudian 30 pacientes hipercolesterolémicos y 40 controles normolipémicos. En sangre anticoagulada con citrato, se determina el porcentaje plaquetas CD62+, el número de microagregados plaquetarios formados espontáneamente (MAP/5.000 plaquetas) y la movilización del calcio libre citoplasmático. Para ello, se utiliza un citómetro EPICS-XL, y los anticuerpos y fluorocromos CD61.PE, CD62.FITC y FURA3-AM. Los pacientes se estudian antes y después de 2 meses de tratamiento con atorvastatina (20mg/día). Resultados. Los resultados obtenidos indican que el tratamiento con atorvastatina disminuye significativamente la concentración de colesterol total, colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) y triglicéridos. En paralelo se observa una disminución del % plaquetas circulantes CD62+ (2,41±1,55% a 1,45±1,06%; p&lt;0,05) y del número de MAP (390±43 a 322±48; p&lt;0,05). Estos cambios se acompañan de la normalización de la movilización del Ca2+ libre citoplasmático plaquetario. Conclusiones. Como conclusión, se observa que la citometría de flujo de sangre entera constituye una técnica útil para abordar temas tales como los planteados en el presente trabajo. Los pacientes hipercolesterolémicos presentan mayor activación plaquetaria, que se acompaña de la formación de microagregados plaquetarios y de cambios en la movilización del Ca2+, que se normalizan mediante el tratamiento con atorvastatina, hecho que no se ha comunicado previamente en la bibliografía revisada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;2(2): 73-79, abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la citometría de flujo para valorar el efecto de la atorvastatina sobre la función plaquetaria y la movilización del Ca2+ en pacientes hiperlipémicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
