<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112584</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subcutaneous phaeohyphomycosis due to Curvularia lunata in a renal transplant patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Phaeohyphomycosis is defined as an infection caused by melanized fungi. It predominates in tropical climate and is currently classified as superficial, allergic, central nervous system or lung infections, and disseminated. Curvularia is one of the many genres which can cause this disease. Phialophora, Alternaria and Exophiala are more commonly isolated from subcutaneous lesions. Case report. A 25-year-old male, renal transplant recipient presents with an ulcer on his left leg. Subcutaneous phaeohyphomycosis due to Curvularia lunata was diagnosed based on mycological examination and histopathological findings. He was successfully treated with systemic itraconazole and surgical resection. Conclusion. The incidence of phaeohyphomycosis has increased in the last decades, especially in immunosuppressed individuals; nevertheless the number of cases does not allow for therapeutic controlled trials to be performed. Hence, we consider that it is important to communicate individual cases and reviews of the literature, to increase awareness of the disease, its clinical presentation and response to treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arenas, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lammoglia, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez-del-Mercado, Elsa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La feohifomicosis se define como una infección causada por hongos dematiáceos (melanizados). Predomina en climas tropicales y en la actualidad es bien conocido que se manifiesta en forma superficial, cutánea, subcutánea y sistémica del sistema nervioso central o pulmonar diseminada. Curvularia es uno de los numerosos géneros que pueden causar esta infección. En las formas subcutáneas es más frecuente aislar Phialophora, Alternaria o Exophiala. Caso clínico. Un hombre de 25 años de edad, receptor de un trasplante renal, se presentó con una úlcera en la pierna izquierda. Mediante examen micológico y los hallazgos histopatológicos se estableció el diagnóstico de feohifomicosis subcutánea producida por Curvularia lunata. Se trató satisfactoriamente con itraconazol sistémico y la resección quirúrgica de la úlcera. Conclusión. A pesar de que, en las últimas décadas, se ha incrementado la incidencia de feohifomicosis, en particular en pacientes inmunosuprimidos, el número de casos no permite que se emprendan ensayos controlados terapéuticos. Por esta razón, consideramos que es importante comunicar los casos clínicos individuales y revisar los estudios publicados para aumentar los conocimientos sobre esta enfermedad, su presentación clínica y la respuesta al tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;30(2): 116-118, abr.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Feohifomicosis subcutánea producida por Curvularia lunata en un paciente receptor de un trasplante renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d529^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54474^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19530^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d529^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9364^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54474^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54474^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54474^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54474^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9364^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19530^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31378^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
