<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88795</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Psychology of the Sport and the Psychology of the Health: two professional fields and a common aim</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The expansion of the psychology of the sport like discipline cient'fica and applied in the last years it takes as a consequence the opening of new fields of intervention, but also the interrelationship with already existing some. The aim of this work is define which are the areas of work that the psychology of the sport shares with the psychology of the health and which are those in which though they share the aim, the means are different (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Checa Esquiva, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantón Chirivella, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La expansión de la psicología del deporte como disciplina cient´fica y aplicada en los últimos años tiene como consecuencia la apertura de nuevos campos de intervención, pero también la interrelación con algunos ya existentes. El objetivo de este trabajo es definir cuáles son los ámbitos de trabajo que la psicología del deporte comparte con la psicología de la salud y cuáles son aquellos en los que aunque compartan el objetivo, los medios son diferentes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;28(2): 307-314, mayo-ago. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Psicología del Deporte y la Psicología de la Salud: dos campos profesionales y un objetivo común</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
