<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150491</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Randomised clinical trial to compare two tracheotomy care methods in an Intensive Care Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Tracheotomy is a common technique in Intensive Care Units (ICU). It is known that nursing care during and after that procedure is directly related to its success, by reducing the possible complications to a minimum, such as the stoma infection, and contributing to a favourable outcome in critical patients. Objectives: To compare the use of polyhexanide (PLX) versus saline + povidone iodine (PY) as antiseptics and infection incidence in tracheostomies performed in Intensive Care Units. Material and method: A 2-year, experimental, randomised, open-label trial carried out in a multidiscipline ICU with 32 beds. The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Principality of Asturias. Results: The overall infection rate observed for every hundred patients was 1.34 (95% CI; 0.81-2.01), with 1.46 when using PLX and 1.21 for PY (P=.685). Conclusions: In spite of the experimental treatment (PLX) was shown to be effective in other types of wounds in our study. No significant differences were found between this technique and the standard one. Since there is no national registry of tracheotomy- associated infections, it is not possible to know whether the rate observed is within the usual parameters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Mier, MB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Camblor, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavero Ballester, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Gutiérrez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wensell-Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La traqueotomía es una técnica habitual en las Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI). Es sabido que los cuidados enfermeros durante y posteriores al procedimiento están directamente relacionados con el éxito del mismo, minimizando el riesgo de aparición de complicaciones como la infección del estoma y favoreciendo la adecuada evolución del paciente crítico. Objetivos: Comparar la incidencia de infección en las traqueotomías realizadas en UCI según el antiséptico empleado: cura con polihexanida (PLX) y cura con suero fisiológico + povidona yodada (PY). Material y método: Ensayo experimental, aleatorizado y abierto, realizado en una UCI polivalente de 32 camas durante 2 años. El estudio fue aprobado por el Comité Ético de Investigación del Principado de Asturias. Resultados: La tasa observada de infecciones por 100 pacientes-día de traqueotomía fue de 1,34 (IC del 95%, 0,81-2,01): 1,46 en PLX y 1,21 PY (p valor 0,685). Conclusiones: A pesar de que el tratamiento experimental (PLX) ha mostrado su eficacia en otro tipo de heridas, en nuestro estudio no se encontraron diferencias significativas entre esta técnica y la estándar. Dado que no existe un registro nacional de incidencia de infección asociada a traqueotomías, no se puede saber si la observada está dentro de los parámetros habituales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;27(1): 4-12, ene.-mar. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo clínico aleatorizado para la comparación de dos métodos de cura de traqueotomía en una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11644^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14530^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
