<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038288</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A comparison of ready-to-use systems for evaluating the microbiological quality of acidic fruit juices using non-pasteurized orange juice as an experimental model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several alternative analytical methods are currently available for the rapid microbiological testing of food. Due to their many advantages, particularly their convenience of use, the popularity of ready-to-use systems for the enumeration of hygiene indicator microorganisms is increasing. However, the ability of these systems to enumerate stressed microorganisms, such as those that may be found growing in acidic foods, is unknown. Therefore, the aim of this study was to evaluate the performance of Petrifilm (TM) and SimPlate (TM) plates for the enumeration of total aerobes and fungi (yeasts and molds) in acidic fruit juices, using non-pasteurized orange juice as an experimental model. The samples were analyzed before and after neutralization of pH, and the results were compared with those obtained using conventional procedures, i.e. pour-plates containing Standard Methods Agar, acidified potato dextrose agar, or dichloran-glycerol agar. The results obtained with Petrifilm and SimPlate for counts of mesophilic aerobes as well as for yeast and mold correlated well with those obtained using conventional procedures. Although no statistically significant differences were observed between counts of non-neutralized and neutralized samples (&amp;#945; &amp;#8804; 0.05), better correlation indexes were observed in the neutralized samples. Both Petrifilm and SimPlate proved to be good alternative methods for testing the microbiological quality of acidic fruit juices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramazotti Ferrati, Anali</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Destro, Maria Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landgraf, Mariza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, Bernadette DGM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tavolaro, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente se dispone de varios métodos analíticos alternativos para el análisis microbiológico rápido de alimentos. Debido a sus muchas ventajas, especialmente su facilidad de uso, cada vez es mayor la popularidad de los sistemas listos para usar en la enumeración de los microorganismos indicadores de las condiciones higiénicas. Sin embargo, no se sabe cómo actúan estos sistemas en la enumeración de microorganismos sometidos a situaciones de estrés. El objetivo de este estudio era evaluar el funcionamiento de las placas Petrifilm (TM) and SimPlate (TM) en la enumeración total de aerobios y hongos (levaduras y mohos) en zumos de frutas ácidas, usando zumo de naranja no pasteurizado como modelo experimental. Las muestras se analizaron antes y después de la neutralización del pH y los resultados se compararon con los obtenidos usando métodos convencionales, como el de vertido en placa agar nutritivo estándar, y el cultivo en placas con agar glucosado de patata acidificado y con agar diclorán-glicerol. Los resultados obtenidos con Petrifilm y con SimPlate en el recuento de aerobios mesófilos y en el de levaduras y mohos se correlacionaban bien con los resultados obtenidos usando métodos convencionales. Aunque no se apreciaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los recuentos de las muestras neutralizadas y las que no lo estaban (&amp;#945; &amp;#8804; 0.05), en las muestras neutralizadas se observaron mejores índices de correlación. Ambos sistemas (Petrifilm and SimPlate) demuestran ser buenos métodos alternativos para analizar la calidad microbiológica de los zumos de frutas ácidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(1): 49-53, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de algunos sistemas listos para usar en la evaluación de la calidad microbiológica de zumos de frutas ácidas, usando zumo de naranja no pasteurizado como modelo experimental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24959</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30077^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1652^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
