<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046035</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bronchial and appendiceal carcinoid tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Carcinoid tumor (CT) is an unusual neoplasm observed in several locations and associated with the production of vasoactive substances and occasionally with carcinoid syndrome (flushing, diarrhea, wheezing).         Patients and methods: A retrospective review of the medial records of all children with a diagnosis of CT treated in our service between 1966 and 2003 was performed.         Results: Ten patients (5 boys and 5 girls with a mean age of 8 years) were diagnosed with CT. Eight had CT of the appendix, of which 4 showed the typical clinical presentation of acute appendicitis. Seven of these tumors were localized at the tip of the appendix and measured 2 cm or less. In one patient, the tumor was located at the cecum and measured 3.5 cm. In this patient, reoperation with ileocecal resection was performed. Two patients (4 and 6 years old) had bronchial CT associated with chronic respiratory manifestations. An accurate diagnosis was made after a 1-year follow-up. Pneumonectomy and tracheobronchial sleeve resection were carried out. None of the patients showed symptoms of carcinoid syndrome. All the patients underwent biochemical and radiological studies and fiberoptic bronchoscopy during follow-up. All the patients are currently disease-free.         Conclusions         Typical symptoms of acute appendicitis were not observed in half of patients with CT of the appendix. CT associated with carcinoid syndrome is exceptional in pediatric patients. In most CT of the appendix, simple appendicectomy was associated with an excellent prognosis. Diagnosis of bronchial TC tends to be delayed and consequently CT should be considered in the differential diagnosis of children with respiratory symptoms unresponsive to standard medical treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encinas, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tovar, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luis, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cabeza, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El tumor carcinoide es una rara neoplasia neuroendocrina con localizaciones diversas, capaz de producir sustancias vasoactivas y asociada ocasionalmente al síndrome carcinoide (enrojecimiento, diarrea y sibilancias).         Pacientes y métodos: Revisamos las historias de los pacientes con diagnóstico de tumor carcinoide en nuestro servicio entre 1966 y 2003.         Resultados: Diez pacientes (5 niños y 5 niñas con una edad media de 8 años) fueron diagnosticados de tumor carcinoide. Ocho tenían carcinoides apendiculares de los que cuatro presentaron síntomas de apendicitis aguda. De estos ocho, siete eran menores de 2 cm y estaban localizados en la punta del apéndice. El paciente restante presentaba un tumor carcinoide de 3,5 cm en la base apendicular por lo que fue reintervenido para realizar una resección ileocecal. Dos pacientes de 4 y 6 años presentaron un tumor carcinoide bronquial asociado a sintomatología respiratoria crónica y se llegó en ambos al diagnóstico acertado tras un año de seguimiento. Se realizó neumonectomía en un caso y resección bronquial con anastomosis traqueobronquial en el otro. Ningún paciente de la serie presentó sintomatología carcinoide. Se realizaron controles bioquímicos, radiológicos y fibrobroncoscópicos en los bronquiales. Todos se encuentran actualmente libres de enfermedad.         Conclusiones: El tumor carcinoide apendicular no se asocia a sintomatología característica de apendicitis aguda en la mitad de los pacientes. Encontramos que el síndrome carcinoide asociado al tumor carcinoide es excepcional en la edad pediátrica. En la mayor parte de los tumores carcinoides apendiculares la apendicectomía simple es suficiente con un pronóstico excelente. El tumor carcinoide bronquial es diagnosticado generalmente de manera tardía por lo que debemos considerar este diagnóstico en pacientes con sintomatología respiratoria crónica</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(5): 474-477, mayo 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor carcinoide bronquial y apendicular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2319^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1069^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2014^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8476^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
