<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155027</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Level of control and treatment adherence of anticoagulation with acenocoumarol in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the level of control in treatment compliance in a sample of patients who were treated with acenocoumarol attended in Primary Care settings. Material and methods. Cross-sectional study. Patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation treated with acenocoumarol were included. The sample size was calculated based on previous studies. Data of patients who possessed International Normalized Ratio (INR) values in last 6 months in medical consult were collected. It was considered that the INR control was inadequate when the percentage of INR values within the therapeutic range was less than 60% in the last 6 months. Assessment of compliance by telephone interview was conducted by the Morisky-Green Test. Results. One hundred and ninety-one patients, 110 women (57.6%) with an average age of 76.5±9.4 years were included. Seventy-six patients (39.8%) were in therapeutic range (INR: 2-3) and 115 patients (60.2%) were out of range (below 2 the 20.9% and above 3 the 39.3%). Poor control of INR increased to the age of 85 years (&lt;75 years: 57.8%; 75-85 years: 67.6%;&gt;85 years: 61.5%). Ninety patients responded to the compliance questionnaire (78.3%), being compliant 74 (82.2%) and non-compliant 16 (17.8%). Conclusions. Six of 10 patients undergoing treatment with acenocoumarol are out of range and nearly 2 of each 10 patients out of range does not accomplish the treatment. We call attention to the need to make a systematically review of adherence in anticoagulated patients attended in Primary Care settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llisterri Caro, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larré Muñoz, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silvero, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Sepúlveda, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Precioso Costa, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Ros, FM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar el grado de control y cumplimiento terapéutico en una muestra de pacientes tratados con acenocumarol asistidos en Atención Primaria. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en pacientes diagnosticados de fibrilación auricular no valvular tratados con acenocumarol en Atención Primaria. Se recogieron los datos de los pacientes que disponían de los valores de la International Normalized Ratio (INR, «razón normalizada internacional») de los últimos 6 meses en la consulta del centro de salud. Se consideró control de INR inadecuado cuando el porcentaje de valores de INR dentro del rango terapéutico fue inferior al 60% en los últimos 6 meses. Se realizó valoración de cumplimiento por entrevista telefónica mediante el Test de Morisky-Green. Resultados. Se incluyeron 191 pacientes, 110 mujeres (57,6%), con una edad media de 76,5±9,4 años. Setenta y seis pacientes (39,8%) estaban en rango terapéutico (INR: 2-3) y 115 pacientes (60,2%) fuera de rango (por debajo de 2 el 20,9% y por encima de 3 el 39,3%). El 62,9% de los varones y el 58,2% delas mujeres estaban mal controlados (p&lt;0,05). El mal control de INR aumentó hasta la edad de 85 años (&lt;75 años: 57,8%; 75-85 años: 67,6%;&gt;85 años: 61,5%). Respondieron al cuestionario de cumplimiento 90 pacientes (78,3%), siendo cumplidores 74 (82,2%) y no cumplidores 16 (17,8%). Conclusiones. Seis de cada 10 pacientes que están en tratamiento con acenocumarol están fuera de rango y casi 2 de cada 10 pacientes fuera de rango no cumple el tratamiento con acenocumarol. Llamamos la atención sobre la necesidad de evaluar sistemáticamente el cumplimiento terapéutico en los pacientes anticoagulados en Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(6): 367-369, sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155027</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grado de control y cumplimiento terapéutico de la anticoagulación con acenocumarol en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
