<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99381</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testicular cancer: our experience after 10 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Testicular cancer represents about 1% of malignant tumors in men. Of these tumors 95% are germ cell tumors (GCTs), which have a maximum incidence between the second and third decades of life. Our objective was to carry out a retrospective analysis of testicular tumor cases that had been diagnosed in our Health Area between the years 2000 and 2010. METHODS: We performed a retrospective descriptive study between the years 2000 and 2010 analyzing 43 patients treated for testicular cancer, including in the analysis tumor incidence, the patient&#146;s age, clinic attended, patient&#146;s time until appointment, presence of tumor markers, patient&#146;s time before treatment, use of testicular prostheses, histological type and their typical characteristics, oncological treatment, tumor progression and mortality rate. RESULTS: We found an incidence of 4-5 cases/100,000 population/year in our Health Area. Two-thirds of the cases were detected in Stage I, and 100% of these cases showed complete remission. Among those with higher stage tumors, two out of three patients were cured after chemotherapy. For the remaining one-third, rescue treatments managed to achieve a remission rate of 66%. Mortality was low and was linked to lymphoma or metastatic dissemination. CONCLUSION: The trend towards early diagnosis with detection during the initial cancer stages, together with current chemotherapy protocols, enables a high cure rate for testicular cancer. Mortality in our series was associated with primary or secondary lymphomas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Lagarto, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valsero Herguedas, María Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortiñas González, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Moreno, María Fe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martín, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Samaniego, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El cáncer de testículo representa alrededor del 1% de los tumores malignos en el varón. El 95% corresponde a tumores germinales (TTG) cuya máxima incidencia tiene lugar entre la 2ª y 3ª década de la vida. Nuestro objetivo es realizar un análisis retrospectivo de los tumores testiculares diagnosticados en nuestra Área de Salud entre los años 2000 y 2010. MÉTODOS: Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de los pacientes con cáncer testicular entre los años 2000 y 2010, analizándose un total de 43 pacientes, con evaluación de la incidencia, edad, presentación clínica, tiempo hasta la consulta, marcadores tumorales, tiempo hasta el tratamiento, solicitud de prótesis testicular, tipo histológico y características anatomopatológicas propias, tratamiento oncológico, progresión tumoral y mortalidad. RESULTADOS: En nuestro área de salud encontramos una incidencia de 4-5 casos-/100000habitantes/año. Las dos terceras partes de los casos se detectaron en Estadio I, consiguiendo remisión completa en el 100%. En Estadios superiores hay curación en 2 de cada 3 pacientes tras la quimioterapia y en el tercio restante, los tratamientos de rescate consiguen la remisión en el 66%. La mortalidad es baja y asociada a afectación por Linfoma o a diseminación metastásica. CONCLUSIÓN: La tendencia al diagnóstico precoz con detección en estadios iniciales, asociado a los actuales protocolos de quimioterapia, permiten altos índices de curación en el cáncer testicular. La mortalidad en nuestra serie se asocia mayoritariamente a afectación por Linfoma primario o secundario(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(4): 467-475, mayo 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99381</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer testicular: Nuestra experiencia en 10 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31880^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
