<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053015</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnetic resonance imaging of glenohumeral instability: new concepts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The shoulder is the most unstable joint in the human body and is therefore susceptible not only to acute dislocations but also to minimal states of subluxation related to overuse. The latter condition is known as microinstability and is translated clinically into internal impingement syndromes. Both in dislocations due to acute traumatism and in microinstability, a series of injuries to the glenoid lip, glenohumeral capsule, the articular cartilage, the head of the humerus, the tendons of the rotator cuff, the long tendon of the biceps, the glenohumeral ligaments, and coracohumeral ligament can occur. Glenoid lip lesions are the most common and may present as isolated lesions or in combination with lesions of any of the other structures. These lesions most often affect the anteroinferior margin of the glenoids (the classic Bankard lesion), with different characteristics and variations on its location, (Bankard variants). Another predominant location of glenoid lip lesions is the superior margin (SLAP lesions). Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), especially after intra-articular injection of contrast material, has shown great diagnostic accuracy in this type of lesions, although the interpretation of these images requires knowledge not only of the different lesions and combinations of lesions, but also of the normal variants that can easily be confused with these lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hombro es la articulación más inestable del cuerpo humano y, por tanto, es susceptible no solo a dislocaciones agudas sino también a mínimos estados de subluxación en relación con el sobreuso. A esta última situación se la llama microinestabilidad y se traduce clínicamente como síndromes de pinzamiento interno. Tanto en las dislocaciones por traumatismo agudo como en la microinestabilidad pueden tener lugar una serie de lesiones del labio glenoideo, la cápsula glenohumeral, el cartílago articular, la cabeza del húmero, los tendones del manguito rotador, el tendón largo del bíceps, los ligamentos glenohumerales y el ligamento coracohumeral. Las lesiones del labio glenoideo son las más frecuentes y pueden presentarse como lesiones aisladas o en combinación con cualquiera de las otras estructuras. Dichas lesiones se localizan más frecuentemente en el borde anteroinferior de la glenoides (la lesión de Bankard clásica), con diferentes características y variaciones de localización (las variantes de Bankard). Otro lugar preferente de localización de las lesiones del labio glenoideo es en su borde superior (lesiones de SLAP). La resonancia magnética, especialmente tras la inyección intraarticular de contraste, ha demostrado una gran precisión diagnóstica en este tipo de lesiones, aunque para su interpretación adecuada es necesario conocer no solamente las diferentes lesiones y la combinación de las mismas, sino también las variantes de la normalidad que pueden confundirse fácilmente con dichas lesiones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);49(2): 63-81, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia magnética de la inestabilidad glenohumeral: nuevos conceptos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6963^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7761^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
