<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145556</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutoff point of the phase angle in pre-radiotherapy cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: malnutrition is a common complication for cancer patients. The phase angle (PA), direct measurement of bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA), has been considered a predictor of body cell mass and prognostic indicator. Cutoff points for phase angle (PA) associated with nutritional risk in cancer patients have not been determined yet. Objectives: assess the possibility of determining the cutoff point for PA to identify nutritional risk in pre-radiotherapy cancer patients. Methods: sample group: Patients from both genders diagnosed with cancer and sent for ambulatory radiotherapy. Variables studied: body mass index (BMI), percentage of weight loss (% WL), mid-arm circumference (MAC), triceps skinfold thickness (TST), mid-arm muscle circumference (MAMC), mid-arm muscle area (MAMA), score and categorical assessment obtained using the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment (PG-SGA) form, PA and standardized phase angle (SPA). Kappa coefficient was used to test the degree of agreement between the diagnoses of nutritional risk obtained from several different methods of nutritional assessment. Cutoff points for the PA through anthropometric indicators and PG-SGA were determined by using Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curves, and patient survival was analyzed with the Cox regression method. Results: the cutoff points with the greatest discriminatory power were those obtained from BMI (5.2) and the categorical assessment of PG-SGA (5.4). The diagnosis obtained using these cutoff points showed a significant association with risk of death for the patients in the sample group. Conclusion: we recommend using the cutoff point 5.2 for the PA as a criterion for identifying nutritional risk in pre-radiotherapy cancer patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castanho, Ivany Alves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velarde, Luis Guillermo Coca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Motta, Rachel Souza Thompson</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la desnutrición es una complicación frecuente en los pacientes con cáncer. El ángulo de fase (AF), medición directa del análisis de impedancia bioeléctrica (AIB), puede ser considerado un factor de predicción de la masa celular corporal e indicador de pronóstico. Los puntos de corte para el ángulo de fase (PA) que se asocian con el riesgo nutricional en pacientes con cáncer aún no han sido determinados. Objetivos: evaluar la posibilidad de determinar el punto de corte para el AF para identificar riesgo nutricional en pacientes con cáncer antes de la radioterapia. Métodos: grupo muestreado: pacientes de ambos sexos con diagnóstico de cáncer y enviados para radioterapia ambulatoria. Variables estudiadas: índice de masa corpórea (IMC), porcentaje de pérdida de peso (% PP), circunferencia del brazo (CB), pliegue cutáneo del tríceps (PCT), circunferencia muscular del brazo (CMB), área muscular del brazo (AMB), puntuación y evaluación categóricas obtenidas utilizando la Valoración Global Subjetiva Generada por el Paciente (VGS-GP), AF y ángulo de fase estandarizado (AFS). El coeficiente Kappa se utilizó para probar el grado de concordancia entre los diagnósticos de riesgo nutricional obtenidos de diferentes métodos de evaluación nutricional. Los puntos de corte del AF a través de indicadores antropométricos y VGS-GP se determinaron utilizando la curva ROC (Receiver Operating Characteristic), y la sobrevivencia de los pacientes se analizó con el método de regresión de Cox. Resultados: los puntos de corte con mayor poder discriminatorio fueron los obtenidos de IMC (5,2) y la evaluación categórica del VGS-GP (5,4). El diagnóstico obtenido mediante estos puntos de corte mostró una asociación significativa con el riesgo de muerte de los pacientes incluidos en este trabajo. Conclusión: se recomienda utilizar el punto de corte 5.2 para el AF como criterio para la identificación de riesgo nutricional en pacientes con cáncer antes de la radioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 2253-2260, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145556</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El punto de corte de ángulo de fase en pacientes con cáncer en la pre-radioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
