<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86542</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of inorganic element exposure (Cr, Mn, Ni, Cu, Zn, As, Se, Cd and Pb) in great cormorants (Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis) from the Mar Menor coastal lagoon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For this study, the levels of nine inorganic elements such as chromium, manganese, nickel, copper, zinc, arsenic, selenium, cadmium and lead, have been measured in different tissues coming from liver, kidney, muscle, bone and feather in great cormorant (Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis), which are installed in the Mar Menor coastal lagoon during the winter. We have had juvenile birds found dead on La Manga del Mar Menor coast. The analyses were made by inductive coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS). Waterbirds are useful for biomonitoring contaminant exposure in aquatic ecosystems as they are on the top of food webs. The Mar Menor coastal lagoon (Murcia, Spain) has high ecological value which integrity is threatened due to impacts of mining and agricultural activities, and urban growing and touristic development that contributes with considerable quantities of contaminants, which can get into the food web joining different strata leading to biomagnification, endangering not only wildlife but also humans. Feathers are presented as an excellent sample for monitoring lead and chromium pollution. Kidney and liver are presented as the most appropriate sample for monitoring cadmium and selenium pollution. Lead and chromium levels are higher than those obtained by other authors from other geographic locations, while other element levels are lower. We have confirmed the utility in the biomonitoring of inorganic elements in great cormorant (Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis) from the Mar Menor coastal lagoon(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farinós, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Motas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robledano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio, se han analizado las concentraciones de nueve elementos inorgánicos (cromo, manganeso, níquel, cobre, zinc, arsénico, selenio, cadmio y plomo) en distintos tejidos (hígado, riñón, músculo, hueso y pluma) de individuos jóvenes de cormorán grande (Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis), hallados en estado cadáver en los alrededores de la laguna costera del Mar Menor durante su invernada. Los análisis se realizaron mediante espectrometría de masas con fuente de plasma acoplado inductivamente (ICP-MS). El Mar Menor posee un elevado valor ecológico cuya integridad puede verse amenazada por la presión urbanística, los efluentes de la agricultura intensiva y los residuos de la actividad minera que aportan cantidades considerables de elementos contaminantes. Estos pueden incorporarse a la cadena trófica y ocasionar una biomagnificación, que puede poner en peligro tanto a la fauna como a los seres humanos. Las aves marinas son de gran utilidad en la biomonitorización de contaminantes presentes en el entorno y permiten la evaluación de su exposición y mostrar el estado ecotoxicológico de la zona estudiada. La pluma se presenta como una muestra excelente para la monitorización de la contaminación por plomo y cromo, mientras que el riñón y el hígado son las muestras más adecuadas para la monitorización de la contaminación por cadmio y el estudio de los niveles de selenio. Los niveles de plomo y cromo hallados en los principales órganos de acumulación son elevados, mientras que los niveles del resto de elementos estudiados son reducidos en comparación con la bibliografía consultada.                             Los resultados obtenidos permiten confirmar la utilidad en la biomonitorización de elementos inorgánicos del cormorán grande (Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis) en la laguna costera del Mar Menor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;26: 97-110, ene.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la exposición a elementos inorgánicos (Cr, Mn, Ni, Cu, Zn, As, Se, Cd and Pb) en cormoranes grandes (Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis) de la laguna costera del Mar Menor de Murcia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8517^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2138</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15427^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3321^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32965^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2906^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1157^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32965^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9717^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2906^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
