<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119504</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adipose tissue: Cell heterogeneity and functional diversity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are two types of adipose tissue in the body whose function appears to be clearly differentiated. White adipose tissue stores energy reserves as fat, whereas the metabolic function of brown adipose tissue is lipid oxidation to produce heat. A good balance between them is important to maintain energy homeostasis. The concept of white adipose tissue has radically changed in the past decades, and is now considered as an endocrine organ that secretes many factors with autocrine, paracrine, and endocrine functions. In addition, we can no longer consider white adipose tissue as a single tissue, because it shows different metabolic profiles in its different locations, with also different implications. Although the characteristic cell of adipose tissue is the adipocyte, this is not the only cell type present in adipose tissue, neither the most abundant. Other cell types in adipose tissue described include stem cells, preadipocytes, macrophages, neutrophils, lymphocytes, and endothelial cells. The balance between these different cell types and their expression profile is closely related to maintenance of energy homeostasis. Increases in adipocyte size, number and type of lymphocytes, and infiltrated macrophages are closely related to the metabolic syndrome diseases. The study of regulation of proliferation and differentiation of preadipocytes and stem cells, and understanding of the interrelationship between the different cell types will provide new targets for action against these diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteve Ràfols, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el organismo existen 2 tipos de tejido adiposo cuya función parece estar bien diferenciada. El tejido adiposo blanco almacena reservas energéticas en forma de lípidos, mientras que la función metabólica del tejido adiposo marrón es la oxidación de lípidos para producir calor. Un buen equilibrio entre ambos va a ser importante para mantener la homeostasis energética. En las últimas décadas ha cambiado radicalmente el concepto de tejido adiposo blanco, considerándose hoy en día un órgano endocrino que secreta numerosos factores con funciones autocrinas, paracrinas y endocrinas. Además, ya no podemos hablar del tejido adiposo blanco como un solo tejido, ya que las diferentes localizaciones muestran un perfil metabólico diferente con consecuencias también diferentes. Si bien la célula que caracteriza el tejido adiposo es el adipocito, este no es el único tipo celular presente en el tejido adiposo, ni siquiera el más abundante. Entre los otros tipos celulares del tejido adiposo se han descrito células madre, preadipocitos, macrófagos, neutrófilos, linfocitos y células endoteliales. El equilibrio entre estos diferentes tipos celulares, así como su perfil de expresión, están estrechamente relacionados con el mantenimiento de la homeostasis energética. El incremento del tamaño de los adipocitos, del número y del tipo de linfocitos y macrófagos infiltrados está estrechamente relacionado con las enfermedades del síndrome metabólico. El estudio de la regulación de la proliferación y diferenciación de preadipocitos, células madre, así como la comprensión de la interrelación entre los diferentes tipos celulares, nos van a aportar nuevas dianas para actuar frente a estas patologías (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(2): 100-112, feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tejido adiposo: heterogeneidad celular y diversidad funcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52013^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8436^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52012^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31672^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52657^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52011^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9692^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
