<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88171</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">P4 Medicine: the Future Around the Corner</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traditional medical practice has been &#147;reactive&#148; (doctor takes part when disease appears). The theoretical (scale free networks and complex systems), technological (high efficiency &#147;omic&#148; technologies) and conceptual (biology systems) advances throughout the last decade, allow us to anticipate the transition to an &#147;anticipatory&#148; medicine, based on health (not on disease). This review establishes the conceptual bases and discusses the principal aspects of this new medicine, known as &#147;P4 Medicine&#148; standing for personalized, predictive, preventive and participatory(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agustí, Álvar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobradillo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La práctica médica tradicional ha sido &#147;reactiva&#148; (el médico interviene cuando hay enfermedad). Los avances teóricos (redes libres de escala y sistemas complejos), tecnológicos (tecnologías &#147;ómicas&#148; de alta eficiencia) y conceptuales (biología de sistemas) habidos en la última década, permiten anticipar la transición hacia una medicina &#147;anticipatoria&#148;, centrada en la salud (no en la enfermedad). Esta revisión establece las bases conceptuales fundamentales y discute los principales aspectos de esta nueva medicina, denominada &#147;Medicina P4&#148; por ser personalizada, predictiva, preventiva y participatoria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(1): 35-40, ene. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicina P4: el futuro a la vuelta de la esquina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38835^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
