<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94637</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Markers of alcohol consumption in hair samples</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">lcohol is perhaps the most widely consumed licit drug in the world. Despite the wide range of health implications associated with alcohol use, its consumption continues to be socially accepted in most countries. This situation leads to a considerable demand for reliable alcohol markers to discriminate between social drinking and alcohol abuse or to verify claims of abstinence after previous harmful drinking. Despite the considerable progress, the situation is still not satisfactory, since the indirect blood or serum markers can be altered with other pathogenic situations, and the direct markers have too short a detection window in blood or urine. Using hair, the last drawback could be avoided due to the unique ability of this matrix to serve as a long-term storage of foreign substances. The objective of the present review is to demonstrate the capacity of hair to establish chronic excessive alcohol consumption. Up to now, only two ethanol metabolites, ethyl-glucuronide (EtG) and fatty acid ethyl esters (FAEE) have been analyzed in hair, both of which will be here studied at length.  After this review, it is possible to conclude that both markers, EtG and FAEE, allow us to discriminate between excessive drinkers, on the one hand, and social drinkers or teetotallers, on the other. Nevertheless, they never allow us to diagnose alcoholism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jurado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de alcohol está aceptado socialmente en la mayoría de los países, sobretodo en los que es una droga lícita, a pesar de las implicaciones que conlleva sobre la salud. Esta situación hace necesarios unos marcadores adecuados que permitan discriminar entre consumo social y excesivo de alcohol, así como también, en algunos casos, verificar la abstinencia después de un periodo de consumo abusivo de alcohol.Existe una gran variedad de marcadores que se pueden analizar en fluidos biológicos, pero ninguno de ellos es definitivo. Los marcadores indirectos en sangre o suero pueden verse alterados por otras causas patógenas; mientras que los marcadores directos tienen un tiempo de detección muy corto en sangre u orina. Este último problema se resolvería usando el pelo debido a la característica única de esta matriz biológica de permitir la acumulación indefinida de los compuestos absorbidos. El objetivo de la presente revisión es demostrar la utilidad del pelo para establecer el consumo excesivo de alcohol durante periodos prolongados de tiempo. Se estudiarán los dos marcadores del consumo de alcohol analizados, hasta el momento, en el pelo, el etil-glucurónido (EtG) y los ésteres etílicos de los ácidos grados (FAEE). Después de toda la revisión podemos concluir que ambos marcadores, EtG y FAEE, permiten discriminar entre consumo excesivo, por un lado, y consumo social o abstinencia, por otro, pero en ningún caso permiten diagnosticar el alcoholismo en una persona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;15(58): 265-278, oct. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94637</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores del consumo de alcohol en muestras de pelo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5111^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6350^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34391^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
