<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88358</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-monitoring of blood glucose and therapeutic education in diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are currently two methods for the health care professional and the patientto evaluate glycaemic control and determine the efficacy of the treatmentplan in diabetes: 1) self-monitoring of blood glucose and/or continuous glucosemonitoring of interstitial tissular glucose by the patient, and 2) measurementof glycosylated haemoglobin. The possibility of obtaining information relatedto glycaemic control by self-monitoring of capillary glycaemia allows thepatient himself to make real-time therapeutic decisions and/or for planningdaily activities, making a structured educational process adapted to the patient&#146;sneeds increasingly more necessary. This article is focused on self-monitoringof blood glucose and therapeutic education, analysing, on the one hand,their utility according to the type of diabetes and treatment following the recommendationsof the different scientific societies and, on the other hand, describingthe characteristics of the different glucose meters and the digitalpuncture devices currently available in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jansà, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad existen dos métodos para que el profesional de la salud y elpaciente puedan evaluar el control glucémico y conocer la efi cacia del plan detratamiento en la diabetes: 1) la automonitorización de la glucemia capilar y/ola monitorización continua de la glucosa tisular intersticial realizadas por el propiopaciente, y 2) la medición de la hemoglobina glicosilada. La posibilidad detener información del control glucémico mediante la automonitorización de laglucemia capilar permite al propio paciente tomar decisiones en tiempo realsobre la pauta de tratamiento y/o en la planifi cación de sus actividades, lo quehace necesario un proceso educativo estructurado y adaptado a sus necesidades.Este artículo se centrará en la automonitorización de la glucemia capilar yla educación terapéutica, analizando por un lado la utilidad de la automonitorizaciónglucémica según el tipo de diabetes y el tipo de tratamiento, y según lasevidencias actuales y las recomendaciones de diferentes sociedades científi cas,y por otro lado describiendo las características de los diferentes glucómetros ydispositivos de punción de glucemia capilar disponibles actualmente en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(supl.1): s15-s28, abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización glucémica y educación terapéutica en la diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
