<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051372</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a hitoric over view of plague, a disease that devastated, with its high rate of mortality, several countries for centuries. Known since ancient times, it was only in the XIV century that the worst epidemic took place taking the life of over 25 million people in Europe. Its decline took place ar the begining of the XVIII century, after the epidemic of Marseille. Neverthless, the plague has kept its morbid activity up to the XX century, although limited to some areas and with much less intensity. We study it socio-economic effects due to the demographic imbalance secondary to the epidemics, which were worsened by the effects of wars and famine. At the end, we make reference to the prophylactic measures that were taken then of which two deserve to be mentioned specially: isolation and quarantine. We include a revision of treatments. These included all kinds of remedies until the discovery of sulfamides in the XX century. These offered some positive results. Streptomycin is the prevaling treatment since 1948</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Realizamos una revisión histórica de la peste, enfermedad que durante siglos cursó en numerosos países, con una extraordinaria mortalidad. Conocida desde la antigüedad, es en el siglo XIV cuando tuvo lugar la epidemia más grave que acabó con más de 25 millones de personas en Europa. A comienzos del siglo XVIII, tras la epidemia de Marsella, comenzó su declive, si bien se ha mantenido activa hasta el siglo XX, aunque en áreas limitadas y con menor intensidad. Se estudia la repercusión socio-económica derivada de las epidemias que supusieron un desequilibrio demográfico, agravado por las guerras y el hambre. Finalmente hacemos referencia a las medidas profilácticas adoptadas, destacando dos fundamentales, el aislamiento y la cuarentena; se revisa también el tratamiento, que incluyó prácticamente todos los remedios existentes, hasta llegar el siglo XX en que las sulfamidas ofrecieron algún resultados positivo, siendo desde 1948 la estreptomicina el tratamiento de elección</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;12(3): 36-46, jul.-sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución al estudio histórico e iconográfico de la peste</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11362^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23466^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
