<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81499</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric performance of the 6th version of the Addiction Severity Index in Spanish (ASI-6)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work analysed the psychometric properties of the 6th version of the Addiction Severity Index (ASI-6) translated and adapted to the Spanish language. A multicentre, observational and prospective design was used. A total of 258 participants were included, 217 were patients (35 stable patients and 182 unstable patients), and 41 were controls. The results show satisfactory psychometric performance of the ASI-6. The degree of the internal consistency of the standardized objective scores ranged between .47 and .95. As for test-retest reliability, the values were acceptable, varying from .36 to 1. The study of the internal structure revealed a good fit to a unidimensional solution for all scales taken independently. Regarding convergent-discriminant validity, the correlations between the primary and secondary scales of the ASI-6 and the Clinic Global Impression score were low, with values from .01 to .26. Likewise, 8 of the 15 scales differentiated between controls and unstable patients. The psychometric properties of the ASI-6 Spanish version seem to be acceptable, though it is necessary to carry out new studies to test metric quality with independent samples of patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Portilla, PAz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáiz, Pilar A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terán, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bobes Bascarán, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flórez, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Mesa, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereiro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardia, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio examinó las propiedades psicométricas del Addiction Severity Index-6 (ASI-6) en su versión traducida y adaptada al español. Se realizó un estudio multicéntrico, observacional y prospectivo donde participaron un total de 258 sujetos, siendo 217 pacientes (35 estables y 182 inestables) y 41 controles. Los resultados muestran que el ASI-6 presentó un buen comportamiento psicométrico. Los niveles de consistencia interna de las puntuaciones objetivas estandarizadas de las escalas del ASI-6 oscilaron entre 0,47 y 0,95. Por su parte, los valores de fiabilidad test-retest fueron aceptables, oscilando entre 0,36 y 1. El estudio de la estructura interna del ASI-6 informó que todas las escalas, considerándolas de forma independiente, se ajustaron a una solución esencialmente unidimensional. En cuanto a la obtención de evidencias de validez convergente-discriminante, las correlaciones entre las escalas primarias y secundarias del ASI-6 y las puntuaciones en la Impresión Clínica Global de Gravedad fueron bajas, oscilando entre 0,01 y 0,26. Asimismo, ocho de las quince escalas del ASI-6 lograron diferenciar entre controles y pacientes inestables. La versión española del ASI-6 presenta propiedades psicométricas que pueden ser consideradas aceptables, aunque sería necesario llevar a cabo nuevos estudios que continúen examinando su calidad métrica en muestras independientes de pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(3): 513-519, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81499</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rendimiento psicométrico de la sexta versión del Addiction Severity Indez en español (ASI-6)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
