<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33114</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dementia and cognitive impairment pattern: its association with e4 allele of apolipoprotein E gene</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The APOE e4 allele is a well-established risk factor for Alzheimer&#146;s disease. This disease is characterized by a typical progressive cognitive impairment pattern, different from that of other primary dementias such as dementia with Lewy bodies or frontotemporal and vascular dementias, for which there are no conclusive results on the influence of the APOE genotype. Objective. Our aim is to study how the APOE genotype associates with different dementia types, and the asso ciation of this genotype with mild cognitive impairment and age-related cognitive decline, which might be stages in a continuum between normality and dementia. Patients and methods. From a group of 1.022 people we selected 733 patients with different dementia diagnosys and 205 controls. APOE genotype for each participant in the study was determined. Results. As it was already known, the e4 allele is associated to senile Alzheimer&#146;s disease (OR = 5,6; 95% CI = 3,6-8,9; p &lt; 0,001) and presenile Alzheimer&#146;s disease (OR = 5,4; 95% CI = 2,1-13,8; p &lt; 0,001). It is also associated to mild cognitive impairment (OR = 3,7; 95% CI = 2,3-6,0; p &lt; 0,001) and to age-related cognitive decline (OR = 3,0; 95% CI = 1,2-7,3; p &lt; 0,01). Female Alzheimer patients with at least one e4 allele present significantly an earlier age at onset (e4 + = 73,4 ± 5,4; e4 - = 76,9 ± 5,5; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusion. The APOE genotype is associated to Alzheimer&#146;s disease and to its cognitive impairment pattern. This association has a growing value according to the degree of clinical impairment. The APOE genotype could be used in differential diagnostic of cognitive impairment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El alelo e4 de la APOE es un factor de riesgo bien establecido para la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA). Esta enfermedad se caracteriza por un patrón de deterioro cognitivo (DC)progresivo bastante típico, diferente del de otras demencias, como la demencia con cuerpos de Lewy, la demencia frontotemporal o la demencia vascular, en las que no se han obtenido resultados concluyentes sobre la influencia de este gen. Objetivo. Estudiar la asociación del genotipo APOE con diferentes tipos de demencia, y la asociación de este genotipo con el deterioro cognitivo ligero (DCL) y eldeterioro cognitivo asociado a la edad (DECAE), posibles estadios de un continuo entre la normalidad y la demencia. Pacientes y métodos. Se reclutaron 1.022 personas, de las que se seleccionaron 733 pacientes con distintos subtipos de demencia y 205 controles, a los que se determinó el genotipo del APOE. Resultados. Como ya se conocía, el alelo e4 se asocia a la EA de edad de inicio senil (OR = 5,6; IC 95 por ciento = 3,6-8,9; p &lt; 0,001) y presenil (OR = 5,4; IC 95 por ciento = 2,1-13,8; p &lt; 0,001). También se asocia al DCL (OR = 3,7; IC 95 por ciento = 2,3-6,0; p &lt; 0,001) y al DECAE (OR = 3,0; IC 95 por ciento = 1,2-7,3; p &lt; 0,01). La edadde inicio de la EA es significativamente inferior en las pacientes que poseen al menos un alelo e4 (e4+ = 73,4 ñ 5,4; e4- = 76,9 ñ 5,5; p &lt;0,001). Conclusiones. El genotipo APOE se asocia a la EA y alpatrón de deterioro que la caracteriza. Esta asociación tiene un valor creciente según el grado de deterioro objetivable. El genotipo APOE podría servir en el diagnóstico diferencial del DC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(9): 801-807, mayo 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demencia y patrón de deterioro cognitivo: asociación con el alelo e4 del gen de la apolipoproteína E</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Arbeloa Rigau, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosich Estragó, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual San Emeteio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrufat Cardús, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labad alquézar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilella Cuadrada, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulet Pérez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33114</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1063</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
