<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161911</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fractional carbon dioxide laser associated with topic corticosteroid for the treatment of scar pruritus in burn patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Itch is a frequent sequelae in burns that might be disabling and hardly managed with medical treatment. We present a case of a burn patient with medical refractory pruritus and the result after treatment, consisting of laser assisted corticosteroid delivery. He was a severe burn patient with 70% total body surface area burned, with medical refractory pruritus and secondary skin lesions resulting from scratching, needing of sedation and intubation to control. One session of fractional carbon dioxide laser was performed, covering the treated area with an occlusive dressing soaked in triamcinolone acetonide dissolved with saline (20 mg/ml). Results were evaluated by using Burn Itch Questionnaire to assess the pruritus, and both Vancouver Scar Scale and Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale to assess the scar aesthetic result. We were able to control itch and stop scratching skin lesions, without any complication associated to the procedure. Laser assisted drug delivery was the mainstay concept of our patient treatment, where the ablative laser creates transepidermal channels that allow the corticosteroid to reach the dermis, and therefore the immediate effect of the drug. Both, this modality of treatment and new clinical concept are becoming an increasingly important tool for refractory pruritus management in burns (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villamarín Bello, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo Losada, Jesús del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez Rodríguez, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Porto, Sara A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El prurito en los pacientes quemados supone una secuela frecuente que puede ser incapacitante y difícilmente controlable mediante tratamiento médico. Presentamos el caso de un paciente con prurito grave resistente a tratamiento médico y los resultados tras el tratamiento con láser ablativo y liberación de corticoide local asistida por láser. Se trata de un paciente con quemaduras graves en el 70% de superficie corporal, con prurito refractario a tratamiento médico y lesiones por rascado que precisaron de sedorrelajacion e intubación orotraqueal, y en el que realizamos una sola sesión de tratamiento con láser CO2 fraccionado tras la que se aplicó cura oclusiva con triamcinolona acetonido disuelta en suero (20 mg/ml). La evaluación del resultado se realizó mediante valoración del prurito (escala Burn Itch Questionnaire) y del resultado clínico y estético de la cicatriz (escalas Vancouver Scar Scale y Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale). Logramos un buen control del prurito y de las lesiones por rascado sin complicaciones asociadas. La liberación de fármacos asistida por láser fue la base del nuestro tratamiento, en el que el láser ablativo crea canales de comunicación transepidermicos que favorecen la entrada del corticoide a la dermis y el efecto inmediato del mismo. Esta modalidad de tratamiento y este nuevo concepto clínico se presentan como una alternativa terapéutica importante en el tratamiento del prurito refractario en el paciente quemado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;43(1): 69-75, ene.-mar. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161911</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Láser de dióxido de carbono fraccionado asociado a corticoide tópico para el tratamiento del prurito en las secuelas cicatriciales del paciente quemado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52876^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11976^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6248^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
