<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92395</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mismatch Negativity (MMN) and schizophrenia: A revision</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Mismatch Negativity (MMN) is an auditory Event-Related Potential which is generated as an automatic cerebral response to any change in the auditory stimulation that exceeds a limit corresponding to the discrimination threshold. It has been widely and consistently reported that patients with recent and chronic schizophrenia display smaller MMN amplitudes, suggesting that this component may be related with alteration in sensory memory and stimuli integration capacities, which seem to increase with the disease progression. Recently, new research areas have emerged, and studies of MMN of relatives of patients with schizophrenia have been conducted in order to assess the MMN efficacy as an endophenotype. Likewise, there have been MMN studies in schizophrenia prodromes or clinical high risk subjects, aiming to know if there are cerebral processing disturbances prior to the onset of the disease. The results of these studies have been promising, suggesting the presence of auditory stimuli processing disturbances in this population. These disturbances are subtle and seem to increase as the disease appears. The MMN component maybe a very effective electrophysiological tool that provides information about the automatic auditory processing in schizophrenia related to its chronicity. It may also be a relative reliable index of genetic vulnerability and clinical risk for developing schizophrenia. Nevertheless, it is necessary to continue performing studies to get comparable and replicable studies in the future that could confirm the information about MMN utility (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mondragón-Maya, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Hernández, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yáñez-Téllez, Guillermina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Agudelo, Yaneth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El componente Mismatch Negativity (MMN) es un Potencial Relacionado con Eventos (PRE) de tipo auditivo, que es generado por la respuesta cerebral automática a cualquier cambio en la estimulación auditiva que excede un límite correspondiente al umbral de discriminación. Se ha reportado amplia y consistentemente menor amplitud de MMN en pacientes con esquizofrenia reciente y crónica, por lo que se ha propuesto que este componente se relaciona con alteraciones en la memoria sensorial y en las capacidades de integración del estímulo, las cuales parecen progresara lo largo de la enfermedad. Recientemente se han abierto nuevas líneas de investigación al respecto, y se han realizado estudios con familiares de pacientes con esquizofrenia para evaluar la eficacia de la MMN como endofenotipo. Asimismo, se han llevado a cabo estudios de MMN en pródromos o sujetos en riesgo clínico de desarrollar esquizofrenia, con la finalidad de conocer si existen alteraciones en el procesamiento cerebral previas al inicio de la enfermedad. Los resultados de estos trabajos han arrojado resultados prometedores, que sugieren la presencia de alteraciones sutiles en el procesamiento de estímulos auditivos en esta población, las cuales parecen aumentar con la aparición de la enfermedad. Es así como el componente MMN puede ser una herramienta electrofisiológica eficaz para proporcionar información sobre el procesamiento automático auditivo relacionado con la esquizofrenia y su cronicidad, así como para indicar la vulnerabilidad genética y riesgo clínico para desarrollarla. Sin embargo, es necesario realizar estudios futuros comparables y replicables que permitan confirmar tales hallazgos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(6): 363-373, nov.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mismatch Negativity (MMN) y esquizofrenia: Una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54335^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30524^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
