<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038195</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital admission due to varicella: a retrospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To describe the features of the patients admitted to our hospital with varicella and analyze the complications that lead to hospital admission. Material and methods: We carried out a retrospective study of the children admitted with varicella between January 1996 and December 2002. Results: We identified 61 children who had been hospitalized for varicella during the study period. They represented 7.65% of the patients that were brought to the emergency room. The mean age was 3.1 ± 3.37 years. The children were admitted mainly for treatment of complications, for antiviral therapy or for observation. The mean length of the hospital stay was 5.32 days. The most prevalent reasons for admission were neurological and cutaneous complications (21.3%), followed by respiratory complications. Other complications were scarlet fever (8.2%), hematological disorders, vomiting, neonatal patient, tonsillitis and hemorrhagic varicella. Group A streptococcus was the cause in 11.4% of the cases (5 cases of scarlet fever, one case of skin infection with positive blood culture and another case in which beta hemolytic streptococcus was isolated from varicella skin lesions). Conclusion: Complications of varicella were the cause of 0.5% of emergency room visits; 7.65% of the patients with complications were admitted to the hospital. The introduction of a varicella vaccination program could decrease the number of hospital admissions produced by complications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lassaletta Atienza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Santiago, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Frías, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martino Alba, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevilla Ramos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manglano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características de los pacientes ingresados por varicela en el Hospital «Príncipe de Asturias» y analizar las complicaciones que motivan su ingreso. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes ingresados por varicela entre enero de 1996 y diciembre de 2002. Resultados: Se encontraron 61 pacientes ingresados por varicela. El 7,6% de los casos que consultaron en el Servicio de Urgencias fueron ingresados. La media de edad de estos pacientes fue de 3,1 ± 3,37 años. Fueron hospitalizados, fundamentalmente, para el tratamiento de complicaciones, terapia antiviral u observación. El tiempo medio de estancia fue de 5,32 días. Las complicaciones neurológicas y cutáneas fueron las más frecuentes (21,3%), seguidas de las respiratorias (16,9%). Otras complicaciones fueron: la escarlatina (8,2%), complicaciones hematológicas, vómitos, casos neonatales, amigdalitis y varicela hemorrágica. El 11,4% de los casos se produjeron por estreptococo betahemolítico del grupo A (5 pacientes con escarlatina, un caso de infección cutánea con hemocultivo positivo y otro caso en el que se aisló Streptococcus pyogenes de las lesiones cutáneas). Las complicaciones por varicela supusieron el 0,5% de los motivos de consulta en el Servicio de Urgencias, y un 7,6% de éstas precisó ingreso hospitalario. Conclusión: La introducción de la vacuna de la varicela en el calendario vacunal podría disminuir el número de ingresos debidos a complicaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(3): 101-104, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingresos por varicela: estudio retrospectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33082^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33082^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
