<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153761</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phenomenology: a vision for nursing research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The discipline of nursing needs to identify with a philosophy that allows give an interpretive sense of social or individual phenomena; and qualitative research provides the necessary methodology to perform the interpretation of the meanings under a critical and reflective analysis. The aim of this study was to reflect on different philosophical traditions around phenomenology, exploring the thoughts of Edmund Husserl, Martin Heidegger and Alfred Schütz. A theoretical essay whose literary input was obtained from repositories and electronic data sources was conducted, published in the years 2010 to 2014 were included combinations of eight key words were used and those items not mentioned the theoretical approach of philosophers were excluded Of interest. It is concluded that the three philosophical perspectives pose a feasible methodological strategy to be used in qualitative research in nursing, either under the descriptive school of Husserl, Heidegger interpretive stance or the social vision of Schütz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Arcos, Lubia-del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras-de-la-Fuente, H-Saray</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disciplina de enfermería necesita identificarse con una filosofía que le permita otorgar un sentido interpretativo a los fenómenos sociales o individuales; y la investigación cualitativa ofrece la metodología necesaria para llevar a cabo la interpretación de los significados bajo un análisis crítico y reflexivo. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue reflexionar sobre diferentes tradiciones filosóficas en torno a la fenomenología, al explorar los pensamientos de Edmund Husserl, Martin Heidegger y Alfred Schütz. Se realizó un ensayo teórico cuyo insumo literario se obtuvo de repositorios y fuentes de datos electrónicas, se incluyeron artículos publicados de los años 2010 al 2014, se utilizaron combinaciones de ocho palabras clave y se excluyeron aquellos artículos que no mencionaron el enfoque teórico de los filósofos de interés. Se concluye que las tres perspectivas filosóficas plantean una estrategia metodológica factible de ser utilizada dentro de la investigación cualitativa en enfermería, ya sea bajo la escuela descriptiva de Husserl, la postura interpretativa de Heidegger o la visión social de Schütz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(44): 15-24, ene.-abr. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153761</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fenomenología: una visión investigativa para enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53819^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
