<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140638</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Skepticism, theology and science: the case of earth´s motion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Omnipotentia Dei absoluta thesis (any non-contradictory state of fact is possible) was used by theologians as a skeptical argument against any scientific claim unwarranted by biblical exegesis. Mathematical astronomy was bound to build models of data based on physically sound hypothesis acceptable to theology. Fourteenth century theologian Nicolas Oresme weighted the arguments pro Earth and Heavens rotation. Being an expert in mathematics and natural philosophy, concluded the higher plausibility of Earth&#146;s rotation, but skeptical considerations declared those arguments insufficient and the opinion false for scriptural reasons. Seventeenth century setting was much different: Reform induced an increase of catholic fundamentalism, while Galileo&#146;s physical arguments in support of Copernicanism, together with his refutation of Ptolemaic cosmology due to Venus phases, turned the skeptical balance between both systems untenable. Roman theologians being this time ignoramuses in mathematics and physics, condemned Galileo and declared heliocentrism false, physically absurd, and formally heretic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solís Santos, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tesis de la omnipotencia divina, según la cual Dios puede hacer cualquier cosa que no entrañe contradicción, fue usada por los teólogos bajomedievales como argumento escéptico contra las pretensiones de conocimiento de los físicos. La astronomía, una ciencia matemática, se limitaba a construir modelos de datos respetando los supuestos aceptables por la física que a su vez se debían subordinar a la teología. En el siglo XIV, el teólogo Nicolás de Oresme comparó los argumentos a favor de la rotación terrestre y a favor del giro de los cielos. Siendo un experto matemático y filósofo natural, concluyó la mayor plausibilidad de la primera hipótesis, aunque el escepticismo teológico lo llevó a considerar esas razones insuficientes y a declarar su falsedad por motivos bíblicos. La situación cambió en el siglo XVII. En primer lugar, la Reforma indujo entre los católicos un mayor fundamentalismo; en segundo lugar, los argumentos físicos de Galileo a favor del movimiento terrestre y su refutación del esquema ptolemaico por las fases de Venus hacían insostenible la equidistancia escéptica respecto a ambas posiciones; en tercer lugar, la falta de competencia científica de los actores eclesiásticos llevó a condenar a Galileo y declarar el heliocentrismo falso y formalmente herético (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;67(1): [p84], ene.-jun. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escepticismo, teología y ciencia: el caso del movimiento terrestre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12489^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51648^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36373^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11257^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1264^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12492</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
