<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94789</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disease caused by Triplet expansion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Today we know of a group of mutations caused by the expansion of nucleotide triplets, which are very unstable in meiosis and mitosis. Four types of triplets have the capacity for pathogenic expansion in human beings (CGG/ GCC, CAG/GTC, CTG/GAC and GAA/CTT) and maybe located both in coding sequences (bulbospinal muscular atrophy, Huntington&#146;s disease and certain spinocerebellar ataxias) and non-coding sequences (fragile X syndrome, Friedreich&#146;s ataxia, myotonic dystrophy). Trinucleotide expansion may lead to gains or losses in gene functioning and seems to be associated to a  variety of factors, some of which are directly related with the expansive process (cis-acting) and others whose interaction with the triplets helps to make them increasingly more unstable (trans-acting). Medium-sized expansions (pre-mutations), although clinically silent, do show a marked tendency to expand into complete mutations during the transition along the germinal line. The models that have been proposed to explain triplet expansion involve gene recombination and replication processes; however, they have not fully succeeded in explaining the phenomena related to mutation or phenotypic expression in these diseases. Development. This work examines the most recent concepts related to the dynamic mutation processes that give rise to human diseases; it also reviews the most important clinico-biological aspects observed in those diseases. Conclusions. Dynamic mutation processes represent a new concept in the molecular biology of gene mutations. An ever increasing number of pathologies are caused by this type of DNA alterations, which, as a whole, display very interesting clinico-biological characteristics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barros Núñez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales Reynoso, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Hernández, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. Actualmente se conoce un grupo de mutaciones por la expansión de tripletes de nucleótidos, los cuales resultan muy inestables en meiosis y mitosis. Cuatro tipos de tripletes tienen capacidad de expansión patogénica en seres humanos (CGG/GCC, CAG/GTC, CTG/GAC y GAA/CTT) y pueden localizarse tanto en secuencias codificadoras (atrofia muscular bulboespinal, enfermedad de Huntington y algunas ataxias espinocerebelosas) como no codificadoras (síndrome X frágil, ataxia de Friedreich, distrofia miotónica). La expansión trinucleótida puede producir ganancia o pérdida de la función génica y parece asociarse a una variedad de factores, algunos directamente relacionados con el proceso expansivo (cis-actuantes) y otros cuya  interacción con los tripletes contribuye a su inestabilidad (trans-actuantes). Las expansiones de tamaño intermedio (premutaciones), aunque clínicamente silentes, muestran una marcada tendencia a expandirse a mutaciones completas durante la transición por línea germinal. Los modelos propuestos para explicar la expansión de tripletes involucran los procesos de replicación y recombinación  génica; sin embargo, no han logrado explicar por completo los fenómenos relacionados con la mutación o la expresión fenotípica en estas enfermedades. Desarrollo. Este trabajo examina los conceptos más recientes en relación a los procesos de mutación dinámica causantes de enfermedades humanas y revisa los más importantes aspectos clínicobiológicos observados en éstas. Conclusiones. Los procesos de mutación dinámica representan un nuevo concepto en la biología molecular de las mutaciones génicas. Un número continuamente creciente de patologías son causadas por este tipo de alteraciones en el ADN,  las cuales muestran, en conjunto, características clinicobiológicas muy interesantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(2): 79-87, jul. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94789</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades causadas por expansión de tripletes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34243^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22469^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33609^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30920^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22880</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38373^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30289^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
