<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95969</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of a Humanisation Project in Perinatal Care in Andalusia (PHAPA) in a maternity care area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to analyze the impact of a new manual on midwifery-labor and delivery care based on maternity emergency admissions at the Regional Carlos Haya Hospital in Malaga, which is part of the Humanization Project Development in Perinatal Care in Andalusia (PHAP) through the assessment of admissions, length of stay, average stay and average weight (complexity of the cases attended to by Obstetrics). Material and method: interventional quasi-experimental &#147;before-after&#148;study (period I: before the implementation of the PHAPA; and periodII: period of implementation of the PHAPA) on pregnant women beyond their 37 week of pregnancy that were discharged before they had delivered. Intervention: implementation of an admissions manual of low risk pregnant women. Study variables: number of admissions with threatened premature labour or false labour, stay in days, mean stay, and mean weight. The information was gathered from the clinical documentation department of the hospital that uses the CIE 9 Clinical Modification and Minimum Basic Data Set.Results: 507 pregnant women met the selection criteria for the study periods, 305 in period I and 202 in period II. Hospital admissions decreased by 33% in period II. A savings of 137 in consumed bed-stays was realised. The change between period I and period II went from 4.07 days to 3.74 days in mean stay and from 0.69 to 0.71 in mean weight. Conclusion: the new manual of maternity emergency admissions at the Regional Carlos Haya Hospital in Málaga, included in the development of the PHAPA, has meant a decrease in the number of short stay admissions, a savings in consumed bed-stays and an increase in the mean weight of the department due to the increased complexity of the cases treated. A subjective improvement of the quality of the care delivered during labour and delivery was achieved as the expectations and needs of labouring women were met to the extent possible (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lazarraga Caffarena, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agulló Velasco, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Rodríguez, Trinidad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Gálvez, Isabel Mª de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: analizar el impacto de un nuevo manual en la atención al parto centrado en los ingresos en urgencias de maternidad del Hospital Regional Carlos Haya de Málaga, que está recogido en el desarrollo del Proyecto de Humanización en la Atención Perinatal en Andalucía (PHAPA), mediante la valoración de los ingresos, los días de estancia, la estancia media y el peso medio (complejidad atendida del servicio de Obstetricia).Material y método: estudio de intervención cuasi experimental antes después(periodo I: antes de la implantación del PHAPA; y periodo II: periodo de implantación del PHAPA) sobre gestantes de 37 semanas o más que eran dadas de alta hospitalaria sin parir. Intervención: implantación de un manual de ingresos y egresos de gestantes de bajo riesgo. Variables de estudio: número de ingresos de amenaza de parto prematuro o falso trabajo de parto, estancia en días, estancia media y peso medio.La información fue recogida del servicio de documentación clínica del hospital que hace uso de la CIE 9 Modificación Clínica y del Conjunto Mínimo Básico de Datos. Resultados: 507 gestantes cumplieron los criterios seleccionados para los periodos de estudio, 305 en el periodo I y 202 en el periodo II. Durante el periodo II descendieron los ingresos hospitalarios en un 33%. Se produjo un ahorro en estancia consumida de 137 días. El cambio entre el periodo(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(9): 8-12, nov. 2011. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del Proyecto de Humanizaciónen la Atención Perinatal en Andalucía(PHAPA) en un área maternal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6927^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
