<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76423</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antibiotic prophylaxis in otolaryngologic surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the beginning of the 80s, numerous clinical trials have shown a significant reduction in the incidence of infections in clean-contaminated upper respiratory tract surgery, due to perioperative use of antibiotics; however, there is no consensus about the best antibiotic protocol. Moreover, there are no universally accepted guidelines about flap reconstructive procedures. In otological and rhinological surgery, tonsillectomy, cochlear implant and laryngo-pharyngeal laser surgery, the use of antibiotics frequently depends on institutional or personal preferences rather than the evidence available. We reviewed clinical trials on different otorhinolaryngological procedures, assessing choice of antibiotic, length of treatment and administration route. There are no clinical trials for laryngo-pharyngeal laser surgery. Nor are there clinical trials on implant cochlear surgery or neurosurgical clean-contaminated procedures, but in these circumstances, antibiotic prophylaxis is recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, Juan P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Juan P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Obeso, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde principios de los años ochenta, numerosos ensayos clínicos han demostrado una reducción significativa en la incidencia de infección en la cirugía limpia-contaminada de la vía aerodigestiva superior debido al uso de antibióticos; sin embargo, no hay consenso sobre las pautas idóneas. Tampoco existe una pauta universalmente aceptada en la reconstrucción con colgajos. En la cirugía otológica, la rinológica, la amigdalectomía, la implantación coclear y la cirugía láser laringofaríngea, el uso de antibióticos perioperatorios depende frecuentemente de preferencias personales e institucionales, y no de la evidencia existente. Revisamos de forma crítica los ensayos clínicos disponibles sobre diversas técnicas quirúrgicas otorrinolaringológicas, evaluando distintos antibióticos, duración del tratamiento o vía de administración. No existen ensayos clínicos sobre la cirugía láser laringofaríngea. Tampoco hay ensayos clínicos sobre implantación coclear y los procedimientos neuroquirúrgicos limpios-contaminados, si bien en estos supuestos se recomienda la profilaxis antibiótica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;61(1): 54-68, ene.-feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76423</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Profilaxis antibiótica en cirugía otorrinolaringológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13899^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
