<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149988</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Financing problems of the descentraliced health expenditure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents an analysis of the financing problems of the descentraliced healths expenditure. Firstly, we introduce some general considerations about transfers of health to the Spanish Autonomous Communities. In second place, we review the sanitary financing agreement for 1998-2001 recently subscribed in the Fiscal and Financial Policy Council and the guarantee mechanisms that will assure the achievement of the adequacy and equity objectives. Finally, we consider some important results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantarero Prieto, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo presenta un análisis de los problemas en la financiación autonómica de la sanidad. En primer lugar, se realizan algunas consideraciones generales sobre las transferencias sanitarias a las Comunidades Autónomas españolas. En segundo lugar, se pasa revista al acuerdo de financiación sanitaria para el cuatrienio 1998-2001 recientemente suscrito en el Consejo de Política Fiscal y Financiera y a los mecanismos de garantía que permitan el logro de los objetivos de la suficiencia y la equidad. Por último, se sugieren algunos resultados importantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(supl.2): 111-113, 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La nueva financiación autonómica de la Sanidad: evaluación de la suficiencia y la equidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16763</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28841^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33941</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55153</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
