<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59312</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension: a Voyage Around the Year 2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There have been spectacular developments in pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH), both in its treatmentand knowledge of its pathogenesis. Several studies have been published throughout 2008 that havecontributed to improve these two aspects a little. As regards the pathogenesis, mutations in BMPR2continue gaining points as fundamental factors in the development of the disease. It has been shown thatpatients who carry any of them have a more rapid and severe clinical course. There is a relationshipbetween the BMPR2 pathway and inflammation of the pulmonary vascular tree. A new anti-endothelindrug, ambrisentan, has also appeared on the scene this year. With an efficacy comparable to other drugs ofits group, the secondary effects appear to be a lot less. An important work has been the demonstration ofan improvement in several parameters in functional class II in patients with PAH with bosentan. Resultsusing new combinations, such as sildenafil and epoprostenol, have also been presented. A common type ofPAH is that which seems to be associated with thromboembolic disease. Treatment with sildenafil and insome selected cases, percutaneous angioplasty, has obtained favourable responses. Finally, in 2008, twonew consensus documents have emerged, one Spanish and the other British, which in the light of currentknowledge, give a clearer insight into the management of this serious disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baloira, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipertensión arterial pulmonar (HAP) ha tenido un espectacular desarrollo, tanto en la terapéutica comoen el conocimiento de su patogenia. Durante el año 2008 se han publicado algunos trabajos que ha contribuidoa mejorar un poco más estos dos aspectos. En lo que se refiere a la patogenia, las mutaciones enBMPR2 siguen ganando puntos como actores fundamentales en el desarrollo de la enfermedad. Se ha podidocomprobar que los pacientes que portan alguna de ellas tienen un curso clínico más rápido y grave.Existe una relación entre la vía de BMPR2 y la inflamación de árbol vascular pulmonar. En este año tambiénha aparecido en escena un nuevo fármaco antiendotelina: ambrisentán. Con una eficacia comparable con lade otros fármacos de su grupo, los efectos secundarios parecen ser bastante menores. Un trabajo importanteha sido la demostración de una mejoría en diversos parámetros de pacientes con HAP en clase funcionalII con bosentán. También se han presentado resultados de algunas nuevas combinaciones, como sildenafiloy epoprostenol. Un tipo frecuente de HAP es el que aparece asociado a enfermedad tromboembólica. Tantoel tratamiento con sildenafilo como, en algunos casos seleccionados, la angioplastia percutánea obtienenrespuestas favorables. Por último, en 2008 han visto la luz dos nuevos documentos de consenso, uno españoly otro británico que, sobre la base de los conocimientos actuales, clarifican un poco más el manejo deesta grave enfermedad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;45(supl.1): 43-48, feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59312</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertensión arterial pulmonar: un recorrido por el año 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28921^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
