<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163087</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Muscle function of the pelvic floor in healthy, puerperal women with pelvic floor dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To understand the function of the pelvic floor muscles (PFM) at different ages in healthy women and in puerperal women with pelvic floor dysfunctions (PFD) and to ascertain whether there are differences among them. Material and methods: A descriptive cross-sectional study was conducted between June 2014 and September 2016 and included 177 women, 70 of whom had no symptoms of PFD, 53 primiparous mothers in late postpartum and 54 with PFD. The function of the PFM was measured through vaginal palpation (quality of the contraction); manometry (force); dynamometer (tone, strength, and response to stretching), and surface electromyography (neuromuscular activity and resistance). Results: The healthy women showed superior values for PFM tone, maximum strength, neuromuscular activity and resistance than the puerperal mothers and the women with PFD (P &lt; .01). The puerperal women and those with PFD showed similar functional PFM values (P &gt; .05). The muscle function of the healthy women did not vary significantly with age, except in the case of tone, which was lower in the women older than 46 years (P = .004). Conclusions: Age and births decrease the baseline tone of the PFM in healthy women. Therefore, lower strength, resistance and neuromuscular activity appear to be the main difference between the PFM of women with PFD and the PFM of healthy women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Brazález, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Pardiñas, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Lacomba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer la función de la musculatura del suelo pélvico (MSP) en distintas edades de la mujer sana, así como en mujeres puérperas y con disfunciones de suelo pélvico (DSP), y averiguar si existen diferencias entre ellas. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal realizado entre junio de 2014 y septiembre de 2016 que incluyó 177 mujeres: 70 sin sintomatología de DSP; 53 primíparas en el puerperio tardío, y 54 con DSP. La función de la MSP se midió mediante palpación vaginal (calidad de la contracción); manometría (fuerza); dinamometría (tono, fuerza y respuesta al estiramiento) y electromiografía de superficie (actividad neuromuscular y resistencia). Resultados: Las mujeres sanas mostraron valores superiores respecto al tono, la fuerza máxima, la actividad neuromuscular y la resistencia de la MSP que las puérperas y las mujeres con DSP (p &lt; 0,01). Las mujeres puérperas y con DSP mostraron valores funcionales de la MSP similares (p &gt; 0,05). La función muscular de las mujeres sanas no varió significativamente con la edad, excepto en el caso del tono, que fue menor en las mujeres mayores de 46 años (p = 0,004). Conclusiones: La edad y los partos disminuyen el tono basal de la MSP en mujeres sanas, por lo que una menor fuerza, resistencia y actividad neuromuscular parece ser la principal diferencia entre la MSP de mujeres con DSP y la MSP de mujeres sanas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;41(4): 249-257, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163087</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función muscular del suelo pélvico en mujeres sanas, puérperas y con disfunciones del suelo pélvico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31203^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54529^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9323^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
