<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120532</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional connectivity and complex networks in focal epilepsy. Pathophysiology and therapeutic implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The traditional surgical approach to treat drug-resistant focal epileptic patients is in the resection or disconnection of the epileptic focus. However, a significant minority of patients continue to experience seizures after surgery, which shows the incomplete level of knowledge that currently we have of this pathology. Aim. This paper introduces some concepts of functional connectivity and complex networks methodology with its application to the study of neurophysiological recordings from patients suffering from drug-resistant focal epilepsy. Development. In order to fully understand the new developments in the area of complex networks and its applications to the study of epilepsy, we will here review fundamental concepts in complex networks methodology, synchronization and functional connectivity. Some of the most recent published works dealing with focal epilepsy viewed under this new  perspective will be revised and commented. Conclusions. We think that a wider perspective in the study of epilepsy, such as the one reviewed in this work, will allow epileptologists to consider surgical alternatives in the usual treatment of focal epilepsy at those currently performed in most medical centers around the world. Combining the traditional knowledge with new insights provided by network theory will certainly fill many of the gaps we have today in the fragmented understanding of epilepsy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega Zelaya, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola, Rafael G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garnés, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Guillermo J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El modelo tradicional de cirugía de la epilepsia focal consiste en la localización y resección de la zona epileptógena. Sin embargo, una minoría significativa de pacientes epilépticos sigue teniendo crisis tras la resección, lo que muestra el nivel de conocimiento incompleto que actualmente se tiene sobre esta materia. Objetivo. Introducir algunos conceptos de conectividad funcional y redes complejas y su aplicación al estudio de registros neurofisiológicos de pacientes con epilepsia focal farmacorresistente, principalmente del lóbulo temporal. Desarrollo. Con el objeto de entender con plenitud los nuevos desarrollos en el área de redes complejas y sus aplicaciones  al estudio de la epilepsia, se revisarán los conceptos fundamentales de la metodología de redes complejas, sincronizacióny conectividad funcional. Asimismo, se revisarán algunos de los trabajos más recientes en los que se analizan registros  neurofisiológicos y resonancias funcionales de pacientes con epilepsia focal bajo esta nueva perspectiva. Conclusiones. Una visión más amplia en la perspectiva para el entendimiento de la epilepsia focal, como la tratada en este trabajo, permitirá también plantear nuevas alternativas al tratamiento quirúrgico de la epilepsia focal, tanto con el desarrollo de nuevos métodos no invasivos como con la mejora y optimización de algunos de los métodos invasivos ya existentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;58(9): 411-419, mayo 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conectividad funcional y redes complejas en el estudio de la epilepsia focal. Implicaciones fisiopatológicas y terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3360^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8207^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4912^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12572^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
