<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101612</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dephi consensus on the physical health of patients with schizophrenia: evaluation of the recommendations of the spanish societies of psychiatry and biological psychiatry by a panel of experts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Available data from scientific literature show that patients with schizophrenia have higher rates of physical comorbidity and excess mortality due to other physical pathologies. The growing interest to investigate and improve the health of these patients has led a group of Spanish experts to publish in 2008 a &#147;Consensus on physical health of patients with schizophrenia from the Spanish Societies of Psychiatry and Biological Psychiatry&#148; (2008Consensus). These recommendations imply a significant change to the present model of medical attention. Objective. To gauge the level of agreement of a group of expert psychiatrists on the clinical criteria and recommendations collected from the scientific literature and the 2008 Consensus on the physical health of patients with schizophrenia. Method. The process involved four phases: 1) Scientific Committee established to manage the study and to define the 66-item questionnaire; 2) Panel of 15 experts in psychiatry is established; 3) Submission of questionnaire to the Expert Panel in two consecutive rounds, with an intermediate processing and sharing of results; 4) Evaluation of results, discussion and conclusions between Scientific Committee and Expert Panel. Results. All items, as set by the Scientific Committee and aligned with the recommendations published in the2008 Consensus, achieved consensus on agreement from the Expert Panel, except 5 items, for which most of the answers were placed in the indeterminate position rate. Conclusions. The expert criteria shown in this study indicate a global agreement with regard to clinical criteria on the physical health of patients with schizophrenia, as well as with the present recommendations to improve the health of patients having, or at risk to have, other concomitant pathologies. The need to incorporate new intervention guidelines that facilitate a better control and improvement of the physical health of patients with schizophrenia must be disseminated in the psychiatric providers&#146; collectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero-Martínez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo-Arroyo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bobes-García, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz-Ruiz, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilaberte-Asín, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciudad-Herrera, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes con esquizofrenia presentan una mayor tasa de comorbilidad física y mayor incidencia de mortalidad por trastornos físicos que la población general. Producto del creciente interés por conocer y mejorar el estado de la salud física de los pacientes con esquizofrenia se publicó, en 2008, el &#147;Consenso sobre la salud física del paciente con esquizofrenia de las Sociedades Españolas de Psiquiatría y Psiquiatría Biológica&#148;. Sus recomendaciones suponen un cambio sustancial del modelo asistencial actual. Objetivo. Constatar el grado de acuerdo de un grupo de expertos españoles sobre una serie de criterios clínicos y recomendaciones sobre la salud física de los pacientes con esquizofrenia recogidas de la literatura científica y del Consenso publicado en 2008. Método. El proyecto se desarrolló en cuatro fases: 1) constitución de un Comité Científico, responsable de la dirección del proyecto y de la formulación de los 66 ítems de encuesta; 2) constitución de un panel de 15 psiquiatras expertos; 3) encuesta en dos rondas, con procesamiento intermedio de opiniones e informe a los panelistas; y 4) análisis de resultados y discusión de conclusiones en sesión presencial del Comité Científico y el panel de expertos. Resultados. Todos los ítems fueron consensuados por el Comité de Expertos de acuerdo con las propuestas del Comité Científico y en línea con las recomendaciones del Consenso publicado en 2008, a excepción de cinco ítems en los que no se alcanzó un nivel de acuerdo suficiente para el consenso entre los miembros del panel, debido a que la mayoría se decantó por posiciones de indeterminación. Conclusiones. Los expertos de este estudio alcanzan un acuerdo general sobre los criterios clínicos recogidos en la literatura sobre salud física de los pacientes con esquizofrenia, así como sobre las recomendaciones para la evaluación de la salud física de estos pacientes y para los procedimientos de diagnóstico y las intervenciones clínicas destinadas a controlar los factores de riesgo asociados, propuestos por la SEP-SEPB. Es importante mantener el proceso de concienciación del colectivo de psiquiatras clínicos acerca de la necesidad de implementar las recomendaciones incorporadas en guías como las aquí propuestas, que finalmente lleven al mejor control y el mejoramiento de la salud física del paciente con esquizofrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;40(3): 114-128, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso delphi sobre la salud física del paciente con esquizofrenia: valoración por un panel de expertos de las recomendaciones de las sociedades españolas de psiquiatría y de psiquiatría biológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32395^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32395^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32395^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32395^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
