<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045437</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Avascular necrosis of both hips and knees in a patient with ulcerative colitis treated for a long term with high-dose corticosteroids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Avascular necrosis represents the bone tissue death from vascularization failure, and it is mainly associated with the use of high-dose corticosteroids for a long time.  CLINICAL CASE. A 25 years old female patient treated with high-dose corticosteroids for 7 months for ulcerative colitis presents with both knees pain and limited hip and knee motility. In a plain X-ray and in nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) avascular necrosis was observed at these joints. Bone densitometry showed osteopenia at the femoral head and lumbar osteoporosis.  DISCUSSION. We present a striking case for its large involvement of the joints (both knees and hips) with simultaneous osteoporosis and osteopenia in a young patient treated with corticosteroids for ulcerative colitis. It is necessary to recommend the judicious use of glucocorticoids, prescribing the minimal necessary dose and for the least amount of time necessary to control the underlying disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camblor Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón Lesmes, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Peris, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuerda Compés, B de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Gimeno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal Casariego, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: La necrosis avascular representa la muerte del tejido óseo por fallo de su vascularización, y se asocia principalmente al uso de corticoides a dosis elevadas durante tiempo prolongado.  CASO CLÍNICO: Una paciente de 25 años tratada con glucocorticoides a altas dosis durante 7 meses por colitis ulcerosa presenta dolor en ambas rodillas y movilidad limitada de caderas y rodillas. En la radiografía simple y la resonancia nuclear magnética (RNM) se observó necrosis avascular en dichas articulaciones; la densitometría ósea demostró osteopenia en cabeza femoral y osteoporosis lumbar.  DISCUSIÓN: Presentamos un caso llamativo por la amplia afectación articular (ambas caderas y rodillas) con presencia simultánea de osteoporosis y osteopenia en una paciente joven tratada con corticoides por colitis ulcerosa. Es necesario recomendar el uso prudente de los glucocorticoides, prescribiendo la dosis mínima necesaria y durante el menor tiempo que sea posible para controlar la enfermedad de base (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(1): 109-112, ene.-feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045437</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necrosis avascular de ambas caderas y rodillas en una paciente con colitis ulcerosa tratada prolongadamente con corticoides a dosis altas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7894</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5376^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
