<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138318</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of kinesic and proxemic paraverbal communication in fitness instructors using time patterns (T-patterns)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze paraverbal communication and communication patterns in fitness instructors in four disciplines: body step, toning, aqua fitness, and indoor cycling. Using observational methodology, we filmed 12 workout sessions (3 for each discipline) led by twelve expert instructors (all women, with a mean age of 31±6.14 years). The sessions were observed using the SOCIN-fitness and SOPROX-fitness observation instruments and analyzed using the LINCE multiplatform sports analysis software. Descriptive results and time patterns (T-patterns) yielded by SPSS v.20.0 and THEME 5.0, respectively, revealed marked variability in kinesic and proxemic behaviors in all 4 disciplines, in addition to a predominance of gestures marked by the execution of the activities, with little interaction and participation with members of the class. Optimization of communication between fitness instructors and participants is key to improving motivation and acceptance of fitness programmes among the general populations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castañer, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hileno, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camerino, Oleguer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues,  José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es el análisis de la comunicación paraverbal y los perfiles comunicativos de los instructores de programas de fitness: step, tonificación, fitness acuático y cycling. Aplicamos la metodología observacional para grabar videográficamente doce instructoras expertas (n = 12 mujeres, edad de 31 ± 6.14 años), a razón de tres sesiones de cada uno de estos cuatro programas, que registramos con los instrumentos de observación SOCIN-fitness, SOPROX-fitness y codificado mediante el software LINCE. Los resultados descriptivos y de patrones temporales (T-patterns), obtenidos respectivamente mediante los programas SPSS v.20.0. y THEME 5.0., revelan una gran variabilidad en el comportamiento cinésico y proxémico de las instructoras de cada actividad, y también un predominio gestual condicionado por la ejecución con escasa riqueza interactiva y participativa hacia los usuarios. La optimización de los intercambios comunicativos de las instructoras es esencial para promover una mayor motivación y aceptación de los programas de fitness de la población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(1): 111-122, ene.-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El análisis de la comunicación paraverbal cinésica y proxémica de los instructores de fitness mediante patrones temporales (T-patterns)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50295^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9819</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
