<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145866</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Burnout in women: a comparative study between working and nonworking contexts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to study the incidence of burnout syndrome (emotional exhaustion, cynicism and professional competency) in a sample composed of women, and analyse the influence of their occupation (employees versus university students) in their level of burnout. The influence of the professional orientation of their degrees and the academic year on their level of burnout is aIso explored. The sample is composed by 283 women (N=214 university students and N=69 employees from different economic sectors). Results show that students manifest higher significant levels of emotional exhaustion and lower levels of professional competency than employees. Significant differences also appears for the students collective on the basis of the professional orientation of their degrees and the academic year. The limitations and implications of this study are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agust, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar la incidencia del síndrome de burnout (el agotamiento emocional, el cinismo y la competencia profesional) en una muestra de mujeres y, analizar cómo influye su ocupación (empleadas versus estudiantes universitarias) en el nivel de burnout que experimentan. En el colectivo de estudiantes también se explora la influencia de la orientación profesional y el curso académico en su nivel de burnout. La muestra principal se compone de 283 mujeres (N= 214 estudiantes universitarias y N= 69 empleadas en distintos sectores económicos). Los resultados indican que las estudiantes presentan, de forma significativa, mayor nivel de agotamiento emocional y menor nivel de competencia profesional que las empleadas. Además, aparecen diferencias significativas dentro del colectivo de estudiantes, en función de la orientación profesional de sus estudios y el curso académico en que se encuentran. También se discuten las limitaciones e implicaciones de los resultados obtenidos en el estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;7(1): 79-88, jun. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Burnout en mujeres: un estudio comparativo entre contextos de trabajo y no trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15330^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
