<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87174</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the novelties presented at the 26th Congress of the European Committee for Treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. The new insights presented at European Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ECTRIMS), held in the city of Gothenburg, Sweden, in October 2010, have been summarized at the third edition of Post-ECTRIMS meeting held in Madrid in November 2010. Encouraging findings from the 5-years follow up extension from PreCISe study confirm the benefit of early treatment with glatiramer acetate in patients with clinically isolated syndromes (CIS) against the conversion to clinically definitive multiple sclerosis and cerebral atrophy with an adequate safety and tolerability.  Regarding treatment decision with escalation or induction therapy, different strategies have been proposed depending on to the characteristics of the individual patient with CIS. Findings from several of the reported studies have revealed the favorable role of combined therapy on relapse rate but not on magnetic resonance parameters in patients with recurrentremittent multiple sclerosis. Novel therapies such as alemtuzumab, daclizumab ofatutumab or ocrelizumab have shown promising findings regarding efficacy. Nevertheless, safety findings for these emerging therapies have detected some  severe adverse events, the main ones being potentially fatal opportunistic infections such as progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) caused by JC virus, mainly linked to natalizumab treatment. In this regard, clinicians will face the assessment of he benefit-risk ratio when deciding on the adequate treatment for each patient in the clinical setting. In this regard, determination of antibodies to JC virus by a novel two-step enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) could  provide clinicians with a useful tool to stratify PML risk in patients. Regarding non pharmacologic therapies, behavioral intervention has emerged as an effective therapy in the treatment of depression in multiple sclerosis, showing additional benefits on fatigue, disability and adherence to treatment (AU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Cermeño, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca Lallana, José E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Delicias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Antigüedad, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coret Ferrer, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Virginia de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montalban, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova Estruch, Bonaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olascoaga, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Merino, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbizu Urdiain, Txomin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calles Hernández, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo González, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tintoré, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal García, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oreja Guevara, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comabellas, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Las novedades presentadas en el XXVI Congreso del Comité Europeo para el Tratamiento e Investigación en Esclerosis Múltiple (ECTRIMS), celebrado en octubre de 2010 en la ciudad sueca de Gotemburgo, han sido resumidas en la tercera edición de la reunión Post-ECTRIMS celebrada en Madrid en noviembre de 2010. Se han presentado los prometedores resultados de la extensión a cinco años del estudio PreCISe, que confirman la importancia del tratamiento temprano  con acetato de glatiramero en pacientes con síndrome clínicamente aislado (SCA) frente a la conversión a esclerosis múltiple (EM) clínicamente definida y la atrofia cerebral, con una seguridad y tolerabilidad adecuadas. Respecto a la decisión de tratamiento con terapia de escalado o inducción, se proponen diferentes estrategias, dependiendo de las características del SCA. Por otro lado, varios estudios han demostrado el papel favorable de la terapia combinada en pacientes con EM remitente-recurrente sobre la tasa de brotes, pero no sobre parámetros de resonancia magnética. Las nuevas terapias,  como alemtuzumab, daclizumab ofatumumab u ocrelizumab, han mostrado resultados esperanzadores de eficacia. No obstante, los resultados de seguridad han detectado varios efectos adversos graves, entre los que destacan las infecciones oportunistas, como la leucoencefalopatía multifocal progresiva causada por el virus JC, asociada principalmente al tratamiento con natalizumab. En este sentido, los clínicos deberán valorar el beneficio-riesgo de estas nuevas terapias al decidir el tratamiento adecuado para cada paciente en el ámbito de la práctica clínica. En este contexto, la detección de anticuerpos antivirus JC mediante un nuevo ELISA podría proporcionar a los clínicos una herramienta útil para estratificar  el riesgo de desarrollar leucoencefalopatía multifocal progresiva en los pacientes. En relación con las terapias no farmacológicas, la terapia conductual ha resultado eficaz en el tratamiento de la depresión en la EM, demostrando beneficios adicionales sobre la fatiga, la discapacidad y la adhesión a los tratamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;52(5): 289-299, mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87174</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las novedades presentadas en el XXVI Congreso del Comité Europeo para el Tratamiento e Investigación en Esclerosis Múltiple (ECTRIMS) (II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
