<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83984</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors related to non-prescription of tuberculin skin testing in a cohort of HIV-infected people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Tuberculin skin testing (TST) for tuberculosis (TB) is recommended for all patients with HIV infection because of the known relationship between these two conditions. In this report we analyze the incidence and variables associated with non-prescription of TST in a cohort of HIV-infected people. Patients and methods Longitudinal study conducted between 2000 and 2002 at 10 HIV hospital-based clinics. All HIV-infected patients who had not been regularly followed-up previously in dedicated clinics were identified. Data about TST and other variables related to TB were obtained from the clinical records. We calculated the percentage of patients who did not undergo TST and the associated factors, using odds ratios (ORs) and the 95% CI to investigate associations. A multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed. Results A  total of 1242 patients met the inclusion criteria. TST was not performed in 185 patients (17.6% of those eligible). The fact of being an intravenous drug abuser was associated with a higher probability of TST non-prescription (OR: 2.6, 95% CI 1.1¨C6.5), whereas being unemployed (OR: 0.6, 95% CI 0.3¨C1.0), having a CD4 cell count &gt;200 (CD4 200¨C499: OR 0.5, 95% CI 0.3¨C0.9. CD4¡Ý500: OR 0.3, 95% CI 0.2¨C0.6), and contact with persons with TB (OR 0.2, 95% CI 0.1¨C0.5) were associated with a lower probability. ConclusionsIn this study, the percentage of TST non-prescription was quite high. The results suggest that TST non-prescription in this population is related to the clinicians¡¯ expectations regarding the results of the test and the patients¡¯ adherence to treatment for latent TB infection(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trapiella, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labarga,  Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa,  Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iribarren,  Jose Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Telenti, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldamiz, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viciana, Pompeyo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, M. Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trastoy, Monica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaria, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa,  Asuncion</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinilla,  Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez,  Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camino,  Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno,  Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bleda,  M. Jose</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cepeda,  Concepcion</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portu,  Joseba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido,  Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Geijo, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diaz, Asuncion</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduccion Dada la asociacion entre tuberculosis (TB) e infeccion por VIH, la realizacion del Mantoux esta indicada en todo paciente infectado con VIH. Este articulo analiza la frecuencia de no realizacion de la prueba de la tuberculina y sus factores asociados en una cohorte de infectados con VIH. Pacientes y metodos Entre 2000-C2002 se identifico en 10 hospitales a todos los pacientes infectados con VIH y no seguidos previamente, de forma regular, en consultas especificas. Se recogio informacion de la historia clinica sobre realizacion del Mantoux y otras variables. Se calculo el porcentaje de no realizacion del Mantoux y los factores asociados mediante la utilizacion como medida de asociacion de la odds ratio (OR) y su intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95%. Para el analisis multivariante se ajusto un modelo de regresion logistica. Resultados Mil doscientos cuarenta y dos pacientes cumplieron criterios de inclusion y a 185 pacientes no se les realizo el Mantoux (el 17,6% de aquellos en los que estaba indicado). La probabilidad de no realizacion del Mantoux fue mayor en usuarios de drogas (OR: 2,6; IC del 95%: 1,1¨C6,5) y menor entre los desempleados (OR: 0,6; IC del 95%: 0,3¨C1,0), aquellos con mas de 200 CD4 (CD4 200¨C499: OR: 0,5; IC del 95%: 0,3¨C0,9; CD4 ¡Ý500: OR: 0,3; IC del 95%: 0,2¨C0,6) y los contactos con enfermos tuberculosos (OR: 0,2; IC del 95%: 0,1¨C0,5).ConclusionesEl porcentaje de no realizacion del Mantoux es bastante elevado. La no realizacion del Mantoux parece asociarse con las expectativas del medico, tanto sobre el resultado de la prueba como sobre la correcta cumplimentacion del tratamiento preventivo anti-TB por el paciente ( AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;28(4): 215-221, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83984</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con la no realizacion de la prueba de la tuberculina en una cohorte de pacientes VIH positivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24888^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22710^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
