<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155253</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High prevalence of cannabinoid hyperemesis syndrome in marijuana users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cannabinoid hyperemesis syndrome (CHS) is a recently described condition associated with chronic marijuana use. CHS is defined by the triad of chronic marijuana consumption cyclic bouts of nausea and vomiting, plus frequent hot showering. Its etiology, pathogenesis, and epidemiology remain obscure. We interviewed all patients over the age of 18 years attended between February and April 2014 in an outpatient marijuana rehabilitation center. A questionnaire was used to collect sociodemographic and clinical data as well as information related to a diagnosis of CHS. Of 22 patients who met the inclusion criteria, 4 (18.2%) reported symptoms suggestive of CHS; 2 (9.1%) had all symptoms, and 2 (9.1%) had some. CHS is common. We recommend asking about symptoms that might indicate this diagnosis given that CHS generates a high level of discomfort as well as diagnostic errors and many referrals to specialists (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bruguera, Pol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pelayo, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balcells-Oliveró, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de hiperémesis cannábica (SHC) es una triada consistente en uso crónico de cánnabis, náuseas y vómitos, y duchas de agua caliente de presentación cíclica asociada al consumo crónico de cánnabis. Es una patología descrita recientemente con una etiopatogenia y epidemiología desconocidas. Se entrevistó todos los pacientes mayores de 18 años atendidos desde febrero a abril de 2014 en una consulta ambulatoria para deshabituación del cánnabis. Se diseñó un cuestionario para recoger datos sociodemográficos, clínicos y criterios diagnósticos de SHC. De los 22 pacientes que cumplieron los criterios de inclusión, un 18,2% (n = 4) refirieron haber presentado síntomas sugestivos de SHC, de una forma parcial [9,1% (n = 2)] o completa [9,1% (n = 2)]. El SHC es una entidad frecuente, por lo que recomendamos preguntar por la presencia de clínica sugestiva dado que genera un el elevado grado de disconfort, errores diagnósticos y múltiples consultas a especialistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(4): 249-251, ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elevada prevalencia del síndrome de hiperémesis cannábica en pacientes consumidores de cánnabis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
