<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76474</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Being a good boss is not that easy. Influence of manager communication skills on the motivation, self-efficacy and satisfaction of working teams</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From an organization view, it is very interesting to find out how a manager can positively influence team efficiency. Given the importance of service industries in Spain, a study was planned on the variables likely to influence motivation, perceived self-efficacy and job satisfaction of employees working in teams in a number of jobs, with a special emphasis on the influence of manager&#146;s communication skills. The research sample consisted of 296 employees belonging to 37 different working teams. They were administered the Job Diagnostic Survey (Hackman and Oldman, 1974) and an ad hoc social abilities scale. Results proved what is shown in the literature concerning the relevance of manager communication skills and competences for employee motivation, satisfaction and self-efficacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Buades, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramis Palmer, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Pérez, Victoria A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manassero Mas, M. Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde el punto de vista de la organización resulta altamente interesante saber qué debe hacer un mando para influir positivamente en la eficacia de su equipo. Relacionado con ello, y dada la importancia del sector servicios en nuestro país, se planteó una investigación sobre las variables que intervienen en la motivación, en la percepción de auto eficacia y en la satisfacción laboral de los trabajadores/as con diferentes puestos de trabajo y que realizan su trabajo en equipo, prestando especial atención a la influencia del mando a partir de sus habilidades comunicativas. La muestra de estudio estaba formada por 296 trabajadores/as integrados/as en 37 equipos de trabajo, a quienes se aplicó el &#147;Job Diagnostic Survey&#148;(Hackman y Oldman, 1974) y una escala para evaluar las habilidades sociales diseñada ad hoc. Los resultados obtenidos corroboran lo descrito en la literatura en cuanto a la importancia de las habilidades y competencias comunicativas de los mandos y directivos sobre la motivación, satisfacción y auto eficacia de sus colabores/as (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);23(2): 161-181, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">No es fácil ser un buen jefe/a. Influencia de las habilidades comunicativas de la dirección sobre la motivación, la autoeficacia y la satisfacción de sus equipos de trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10751</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
