<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69207</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hereditary haemorrhagic telangiectasia (Rendu-Osler-Weber syndrome) is a disease characterized by systemic vascular malformations. Typical clinical manifestations are recurrent epistaxis and telangiectases of the skin and the mucous membranes. The syndrome is furthermore characterized by its hereditary aspect. The disease seems to be much more complicated than previously thought, mainly because of the accompanying vascular malformations in vital organs, like the liver, the kidney, the lung, the brain, and the eyes. The diagnosis and treatment of systemic vascular malformations requires interdisciplinary management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cerra Pohl, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfred Werner, Jochen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Josef Folz, Benedikt</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La telangiectasia hemorrágica hereditaria o enfermedad de Rendu-Weber-Osler es un síndrome de malformaciones vasculares sistémico. Esta patología, que se caracteriza por las hemorragias nasales, las telangiectasias de la piel y las mucosas y por su carácter hereditario, es mucho más compleja de lo que se creyó durante décadas, y así se puede encontrar manifestaciones clínicas muy importantes en el hígado, el riñón, el pulmón, el cerebro o en los ojos. El diagnóstico y el tratamiento de esta entidad clínica son un reto que hace imprescindible la colaboración de todas las disciplinas médicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;59(9): 463-468, nov. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69207</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14061^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14061^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5225^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19104^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
