<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73872</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The magnitude of the variation in glycemia: a new parameter for risk assessment in acute coronary syndrome?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The aim was to evaluate the relationship between the magnitude of the variation in the level of glycemia during hospitalization and in-hospital and long-term mortality and postdischarge endpoints in two groups of patients with acute coronary syndrome: those with and those without a previous diagnosis of diabetes. Methods. The study included 1210 patients admitted for acute coronary syndrome between May 2004 and July 2007. The study population was divided in two subgroups: patients with a previous diagnosis of diabetes (n=386) and nondiabetics (n=824). Each subgroup was further divided into four smaller groups according to the quartile of glycemia variation: diabetics (Q1: &lt;46 mg dl q2: 46-88 q3: 88-164 q4: 8805 164 and nondiabetics q1: &lt;14 mg dl q2: 14-30 q3: 30-60 q4: 8805 60 patients were followed up for an average of 18 months after the occurrence acute coronary syndrome results in diabetic there was no relationship between magnitude glycemia variation and in-hospital or postdischarge endpoints nondiabetics significant difference observed mortality morbidity but statistically clinical differences found during follow-up multivariate regression analysis showed that q4 versus q1 age 70 years previous antiplatelet angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor therapy independent predictors nondiabetic group conclusions hospitalization a strong predictor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Providência, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Evaluar la relación entre la magnitud de la variación de la glucemia durante la hospitalización y la mortalidad hospitalaria y a largo plazo y otras variables de valoración posteriores al alta, en dos poblaciones con síndrome coronario agudo: pacientes con o sin diagnóstico previo de diabetes. Métodos. Estudiamos a 1.210 pacientes ingresados por síndrome coronario agudo entre mayo de 2004 y julio de 2007. Dividimos la población en dos subgrupos: pacientes con un diagnóstico previo de diabetes (n = 386) y pacientes no diabéticos (n = 824). Cada una de estas subpoblaciones se dividió en cuatro grupos, según los cuartiles de variación de la glucemia: diabéticos (Q1 &lt; 46, Q2 46-88, Q3 88-164, Q4 &amp;#8805; 164 mg/dl) y no diabéticos (Q1 &lt; 14, Q2 14-30, Q3 30-60, Q4 &amp;#8805; 60 mg/dl). Se efectuó un seguimiento durante una media de 18 meses tras el síndrome coronario agudo. Resultados. En los pacientes diabéticos no hubo relación alguna entre la magnitud de variación de la glucemia y las variables de valoración intrahospitalarias y posteriores al alta. En los no diabéticos, no se observaron diferencias significativas en cuanto a la morbimortalidad hospitalaria, pero sí hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el seguimiento clínico. Tras un análisis de regresión múltiple, el cuartil Q4 frente al Q1, la edad &amp;#8805; 70 años y los antecedentes previos de tratamiento con antiagregantes plaquetarios o con inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de angiotensina fueron factores predictivos independientes para las variables de valoración posteriores al alta en el grupo no diabético. Conclusiones. En los pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo no diabéticos, la magnitud de variación de la glucemia durante la hospitalización es un factor predictivo independiente y potente de las variables de valoración posteriores al alta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(10): 1099-1108, oct. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Magnitud de la variación de la glucemia: ¿un nuevo instrumento para la evaluación del riesgo en el síndrome coronario agudo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
