<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056198</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">All the workers are entitled to an adaptation from    their workstation to their special derived conditions    of sensibilities or specific problems of health, arriving    to the workstation change when this is not possible.    The objective of this work, is to articulate a    protocol, with the activities to carry out for the Service    of Prevention of Labor Risks guided to the    attainment of that end, to carry out a study of all the    adaptations carried out in the period that goes from    January of 2001 to June of 2006 and worker's profile    that more adaptation applications present in our    hospital to settle down</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riesco García, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Herrera, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marroquí López-Clavero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Todos los trabajadores tienen derecho a una    adaptación de su puesto de trabajo a sus especiales    condiciones derivadas de sensibilidades o problemas    específicos de salud, llegando al cambio de    puesto de trabajo cuando esto no sea posible. El    objetivo de este trabajo, es articular un protocolo,    con las actividades a realizar por el Servicio de    Prevención de Riesgos Laborales encaminadas a    la consecución de ese fin, realizar un estudio de    todas las adecuaciones realizadas en el periodo    que va desde enero de 2001 a junio de 2006 y establecer    el perfil de trabajador que más solicitudes    de adecuación presenta en nuestro hospital</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;53(206): 1-7, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056198</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de puesto de trabajo en el ámbito sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20201^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
