<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165202</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Apical periodontitis and oral status in patients with different systemic conditions and smoking habits in Portuguese population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of apical periodontitis (AP), endodontic treatment (ET), and oral status in patients with different systemic conditions and smoking habits. Methods: Panoramic radiographs and clinical processes of 199 patients from their first visit to the clinic of the Faculty of Dentistry of the University of Porto were assessed. The number and presence of AP and ET, the oral status (number of missing teeth, caries, and roots), and the presence of diabetes mellitus (DM), cardiovascular diseases (CVD), allergies, and smoking habits were registered. Teeth were assessed according to Ørstavik&#146;s periapical index. Data were analyzed using inferential statistics, based on a significance level of 5%. Results: The prevalence of AP and ET per patient was 44.2% (95% CI, 37.3%-51.4%) and 47.2% (95% CI, 40.2%-54.4%), respectively. An AP &amp;#8805; 3 was associated with smokers (p = 0.025). The number of missing teeth increased with age (r = 0.723; p = 0.005) and was higher in patients with DM (p = 0.000). A higher number of missing teeth, caries, and roots was detected in patients with AP (p = 0.002, p = 0.000, p = 0.000, respectively) and patients with CVD (p = 0,000, p = 0,001, p = 0.040, respectively). Conclusions: AP and ET were highly prevalent in the studied population, regardless of the patient&#146;s systemic condition and smoking habit. A higher prevalence of missing teeth, caries, and roots was associated with certain systemic conditions, thus suggesting a higher susceptibility of these patients to develop primary endodontic disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lacet, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, Inês</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pina-Vaz, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Braga, Ana Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de periodontitis apical (PA), tratamiento endodóncico (TE) y estado de salud oral en individuos con diferentes condiciones sistémicas y hábitos de tabaquismo. Métodos: se evaluaron las radiografías panorámicas y procesos clínicos de la primera consulta de 199 pacientes en la Facultad de Medicina Dentaria de la Universidad de Porto. Se registraron el número y presencia de PA y TE, el estado de salud oral (número de dientes ausentes, caries y raíces) y la presencia de diabetes mellitus (DM), enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV), alergias y hábitos de tabaquismo en cada individuo. Los dientes fueron evaluados de acuerdo con el Índice Periapical de Ørstavik. Los datos fueron analizados por medio de estadística inferencial, considerando un nivel de significancia de 5%. Resultados: La prevalencia de PA y TE por individuo fue de 44,2% (IC 95%, 37,3%-51,4%) y 47,2% (IC 95%, 40,2%-54,4%), respectivamente. Se verificó una asociación entre el número de PA (&amp;#8805;3) e individuos fumadores (p = 0,025). Se detectó que el número de dientes ausentes aumentaba con la edad (r = 0,723; p &lt; 0,005) y era mayor en individuos diabéticos (p = 0,000). Un mayor número de dientes perdidos, caries y raíces fue detectado en los individuos con AP (p = 0,02, p = 0,000, p = 0,000, respectivamente) y con ECV (p = 0,000, p = 0,001, p = 0,040, respectivamente). Conclusiones: La PA y el TE eran altamente prevalentes en la populación estudiada, independientemente de la condición sistémica o hábitos de tabaquismo del paciente. Se verificó que una mayor prevalencia del número de dientes ausentes, caries y raíces estaba asociada a ciertas condiciones sistémicas, lo que sugiere una mayor susceptibilidad de estos individuos a desarrollar lesión endodóncica primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);35(1): 10-22, ene.-mar. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Periodontitis apical y estado de salud oral en individuos con diferentes condiciones sistémicas y hábitos de tabaquismo en una población portuguesa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29434^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
