<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106423</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical students' preferences on specialty selection in Buenos Aires University</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Factors associated with medical students' specialty choice are work market opportunities, expected income, prestige, length of training and controllable life style possibility. However, cultural influence may modify the weight of these variables at time of choosing a specialty. Aim. To analyze the factors influencing on medical students' specialty preferences. Subjects and methods. From March to May of 2010, 125 medical students' from 5th and 6th year were surveyed. Information was collected by an anonymous questionnaire about factors influencing on a future specialty choice. Results. Opinions about which specialties were regarded as better remunerate, has most prestige, a controllable life style, need more length of training and/or has a good job market were obtained. Pediatrics was the most selected but it was considered one with the worst payment, with less length of training, moderate prestige, although an adequate job market. Surgery was the second choice and was regarded as the one with most prestige and best remuneration. On the other hand, internal medicine was considered to need more length of training, with better work opportunities, but worse remuneration. Internal medicine as well as surgery, is regarded as having the less controllable life style, being pediatrics on third place. Conclusion. The characteristics of income, prestige, life style, length of training and job market opportunities, in general seem to not significantly relate on specialty selection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poveda-Camargo, Ricardo L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pittaluga, Roberto D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribalzaga, Eduardo B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferraina, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borracci, Raúl A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los factores que influyen en la elección de una especialidad son la demanda laboral, la remuneración, el prestigio, el tiempo de formación y la posibilidad de tener un estilo de vida 'controlable'. Sin embargo, la influencia de la cultura podría modificar el peso de estas variables a la hora de elegir una especialidad. Objetivo. Analizar los factores que influían sobre la elección de la especialidad médica por parte de los estudiantes. Sujetos y métodos. Entre marzo y mayo de 2010 se encuestaron 125 estudiantes que cursaban quinto año o el internado. Por medio de una encuesta anónima se recogió información sobre los factores que podrían influir en la elección futura de la especialidad. Resultados. La pediatría fue la especialidad más elegida, pero se la consideró entre las menos lucrativas, con más tiempo de formación y prestigio moderado, aunque con una adecuada demanda laboral. La cirugía fue la segunda más elegida y considerada como la de mayor prestigio y mejor remunerada. La clínica médica requeriría más tiempo de formación, con más oportunidades laborales, pero peor remuneradas. Tanto la clínica médica como la cirugía se eligieron como las de estilo de vida menos 'controlable', hallándose en tercer lugar la pediatría. Conclusión. Las características de remuneración, prestigio, estilo de vida, tiempo de formación y demanda laboral, en general, parecen no haber influido significativamente en la elección de la especialidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);15(3): 155-160, sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106423</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Preferencias de los estudiantes de medicina de la Universidad de Buenos Aires en la elección de la especialidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4572^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
