<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142239</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anthropometric characterization, quality and lifestyles of the chilean higher octogenarian old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: in Chile there has been an increase in the elderly population (AM). There is an interest in the group aged in 80 and older, because it has been described that they have different characteristics in relation to nutritional status, habits and quality of life. Objective: to describe the characteristics of autonomous -AM of 80 years and over considering different aspects such as anthropometry, styles and quality of life. Methods: cross-sectional study, 271 AM of both genders, anthropometry was assessed by body mass index (BMI), two criteria for nutritional diagnosis were considered:, one from the Ministry of Health of Chile (MINSAL) and the other from the World Health Organization (WHO). Subsequently surveys of food frequency , Pittsburgh Sleep, sleepiness and quality of life perception were applied. Results: the mean BMI was similar in both sexes (p = 0.06). However the intake of energy, macronutrients and micronutrients was higher in men (p&lt; 0.01 ). Moreover an excessive daytime sleepiness and moderate quality of life in the AM were perceived in the studied population Conclusion: there is a significant prevalence of overweight in this age group, independently of criteria used. Although there are still some critical micronutrient deficiencies for this emerging age group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vásquez Leiva, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Agüero, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: en Chile ha habido un incremento de la población de adultos mayores (AM). Existe interés por el grupo de 80 años y más, debido a que se ha descrito que presentan características diferentes en relación al estado nutricional, hábitos y calidad de vida. Objetivo: describir las características de los adultos mayores autónomos de 80 años y más desde diferentes aspectos, como son la antropometría y el estilo y calidad de vida. Metodología: estudio de corte transversal en 271 AM autónomos de ambos sexos. El estado nutricional se evaluó mediante índice de masa corporal (IMC) y se utilizaron dos criterios para el diagnóstico nutricional: el del Ministerio de Salud de Chile (MINSAL) y el internacional (OMS). Posteriormente se aplicaron las encuestas de tendencia de consumo, sueño de Pittsburg, somnolencia y percepción de calidad de vida. Resultados: el IMC promedio fue similar en ambos sexos (p=0,06), sin embargo la ingesta alimentaria presentó diferencias para energía, macronutrientes y micronutrientes (p &lt; 0,01). Por otra parte no se detectaron diferencias en horas de sueño, somnolencia y percepción de calidad de vida en los AM estudiados. Conclusión: existe una prevalencia importante de exceso de peso en este grupo, independientemente del referente que se utilice, y aún persisten deficiencias de algunos micronutrientes esenciales para este grupo etario emergente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(6): 2554-2560, jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización antropométrica, calidad y estilos de vida del anciano chileno octogenario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50320</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
