<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056035</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of atorvastatin on vascular expression of PPAR in dyslipidemic rabbits</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The family of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors (PPARs) displays anti-inflammatory and anti-oxidant effects, as well as some effects that act on lipid and glucose metabolism. Statins show certain effects similar to those of PPARs, and consequently it has been suggested that these drugs could exert their anti-atherogenic effects by means of PPAR modulation. Aim. To evaluate the effect of dyslipidemia and atorvastatin treatment on vascular expression of PPARa, b/d and g, endothelial function, and atherosclerotic lesions. Material and method. Male New Zealand rabbits were fed a 1% cholesterol-enriched diet with or without atorvastatin (1 mg/kg/day) for 10 weeks. A group of animals fed a standard diet was used as a control. At the end of the treatment, responses to acetylcholine (10­9-10­5 mol/l) and sodium nitroprusside were evaluated (10­10-10­6 mol/l). Morphometric analysis of the aorta was performed, as well as real time RT-PCT to measure vascular expression of PPARa, b/d and g. Results. Animals fed a cholesterol-enriched diet had higher levels of total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein (LDL)-cholesterol and triglycerides than controls. Dyslipidemia was associated with intimal thickening and reductions in acetylcholine relaxation and PPARa and g vascular expression. Atorvastatin treatment normalized triglyceride levels and reduced those of total cholesterol and LDL-cholesterol but was not able to normalize them. This drug also prevented reductions in acetylcholine relaxation and PPAR expression and reduced atherosclerotic lesion size. Neither dyslipidemia nor atorvastatin treatment modified PPARb/d expression. Conclusions. These data suggest that dyslipidemia exerts varying effects on aortic PPAR expression, reducing PPARa and g while not modifying PPARb/d. The increased PPARa and g expression observed with atorvastatin administration could mediate the anti-atherogenic effects exerted by this statin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cachofeiro, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragoncillo, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miana, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Rosa, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Natalia de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahera, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La familia de los receptores activados por proliferadores de peroxisomas (PPAR) presenta efectos antiinflamatorios, antioxidantes así como efectos sobre el metabolismo lipídico y glucídico. Las estatinas presentan ciertos efectos parecidos a los PPAR, por lo que se ha sugerido que parte de sus acciones podrían estar mediadas por los PPAR. Objetivo. Evaluar el efecto de la dislipemia y del tratamiento con atorvastatina sobre la expresión vascular de los PPARa, b/d y g, la función endotelial y la lesión aterosclerótica. Material y método. Se utilizaron conejos macho New Zealand alimentados con una dieta con un 1% de colesterol con o sin tratamiento con atorvastatina (1 mg/kg/día) durante 10 semanas. Un grupo de animales alimentados con una dieta estándar se utilizó como un grupo control. Se evaluó la respuesta a la acetilcolina (10­9-10­5 mol/l) y al nitroprusiato sódico (10­10-10­6 mol/l) en la aorta. Se realizó el análisis morfométrico de la aorta, así como la expresión vascular de los PPARa, b/d y g por RT-PCR a tiempo real. Resultados. Los animales alimentados con una dieta con un 1% de colesterol presentaron concentraciones de colesterol total, colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) y triglicéridos superiores a los de los conejos controles. La dislipemia se asoció con un engrosamiento de la íntima, una reducción de la relajación a la acetilcolina y una reducción de la expresión vascular de los PPARa y g. El tratamiento con atorvastatina normalizó las concentraciones de triglicéridos y redujo las de colesterol total y cLDL, aunque no fue capaz de normalizarlas. Asimismo, redujo el tamaño de la lesión aterosclerótica, y previno la reducción de la relajación a la acetilcolina y de la expresión de los PPAR. Ni la dislipemia ni el tratamiento con atorvastatina fueron capaces de modificar la expresión de los PPARb/d. Conclusiones. Estos datos sugieren que la dislipemia tiene un efecto diferencial sobre la expresión aórtica de los distintos PPAR, ya que reduce los PPARa y g y no altera los PPARb/d. El aumento de la expresión de los PPARa y g observado con el tratamiento con atorvastatina podría participar en los efectos antiaterogénicos ejercidos por ella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);19(4): 166-173, jul. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la atorvastatina sobre la expresión vascular de los PPAR en conejos dislipémicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22891^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33819</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
