<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91714</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital heart disease of neonatal detection in a health carea rea: a two decade long experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Congenital heart defects frequency have grown in the last years, mainly because of minor defects. Objectives. To establish the incidence of congenital heart defects in a regional hospital. To compare demographic and clinical data with another sample collected at the beginning of the 90´s. Materials and methods. Observational, descriptive and retrospective study of neonates with congenital heart defects form 2003 to 2007. Comparison with data from another sample collected in our hospital from 1991 to 1995. Results. We included 192 cases (17.0/1,000 newborns). The main cause of admission was  clinical suspect of a congenital heart defect, followed by preterm babies. Fifteen newborns needed to be transferred to a reference hospital for surgery. The more common congenital heart diseases were: septal defects (69,93%), great arteries defects (11,5%). In the comparative study we have noticed a significant rise in the incidence of congenital heart defects, the use echocardiography, and decreased number of transfers (form 28 to 15) and mortality (from 11 to 6). Conclusions. The incidence of congenital heart defects has risen comparing to the study carried our form 1991 to 1995, mainly due to minor septald effects, with a usually benign prognosis and trend to spontaneous closure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo de la Vega, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán Poladura, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Redondo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinos Norniella, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández González, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Castañón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La incidencia de cardiopatías congénitas ha aumentado en los últimos años, a expensas de las formas más leves. Objetivos. Determinar la incidencia de cardiopatías congénitas de diagnóstico neonatal en un área sanitaria. Comparar los datos demográficos y clínicos con una muestra similar obtenida a principios de los años 90. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional, descriptivo y retrospectivo, de los menores de un mes diagnosticados de cardiopatía congénita entre 2003-2007. Análisis comparativo con una muestra similar recogida en nuestro centro entre 1991-1995. Resultados. Se incluyeron 192 pacientes (17,9 casos/1000 recién nacidos vivos). El motivo de ingreso principal ha sido la sospecha clínica de cardiopatía, seguido de prematuridad. Quince niños precisaron traslado para tratamiento quirúrgico. Los defectos hallados más frecuentes son los de tabiques cardíacos (69,3%) y grandes arterias 811,5%). En el estudio comparativo por quinquenios se observa un  aumento significativo de la incidencia de cardiopatías y del uso de la ecocardiografía (de 91% a 98,4%), con una disminución de los traslados (de 28 a 15) y de los fallecimientos (de 11 a 6). Conclusiones. La incidencia de cardiopatías congénitas ha aumentado en nuestra área sanitaria, a expensas fundamentalmente de defectos septales leves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;66(3): 175-180, mayo-jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cardiopatías congénitas de detección neonatal en un área sanitaria: experiencia de dos décadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6495^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14580^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
