<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050615</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A sensate lateral sural artery muscle perforator flap</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The calf region is a potential source for relatively thin cutaneous flaps, even in obese individuals. This can be an especially valuable option if the defect requires that the patient remain in a prone position. Whereas gastrocnemius musculocutaneous flaps have long been recognized to be reliable, with the advent of the muscle perforator flap concept, now instead a medial sural artery perforator [MSAP] or lateral sural artery perforator [LSAP] flap can be selected with preservation of function of the excluded muscle. Although the MSAP flap has been most commonly used, if an appropriate major musculocutaneous perforator of the lateral gastrocnemius muscle exists, a LSAP flap can be used. The latter has the advantage of being a sensate flap by inclusion of the lateral sural cutaneous nerve (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hallock, G. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La región de la pantorrilla es un potencial fuente de colgajos cutáneos relativamente finos, incluso en personas obesas. Este colgajo es una opción a tener en cuenta si el procedimiento reconstructivo requiere que el paciente permanezca en posición prona. Los colgajos musculo cutáneos de gemelo han sido considerados desde hace tiempo fiables, y ahora, con los avances en colgajos de perforantes, es posible elegir elevar un colgajo de perforantes de la arteria suralmedial (PSM) o bien de la arteria sural lateral (PSL)respetando la función del músculo que en estos casos queda excluido del colgajo. Aunque el colgajo PSM ha sido el más ampliamente usado, si se demuestra la existencia de una perforante musculo cutánea del músculo gastrocnemio lateral, también puede usarse el colgajo PSL. Este último tiene la ventaja de ser un colgajo sensitivo si se incluye el nervio cutáneo sural lateral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;32(4): 293-297, oct.-dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajo sensible basado en perforantes de la arteria sural lateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11592^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11592^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8044^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8044^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
