<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046440</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early development and learning conditions: the role of the executive functions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. From the neuroconstructivist approach, cognitive development is understood and studied as a process ofsuccessive rearrangement, as are its mechanisms of change and its differential results. The early years of life are essential inbeing able to explain the differential cognitive, emotional and social competencies. Changes in the executive functions play acrucial role in this process. Understanding it calls for interdisciplinary research that relates neuroanatomical data about thebrain with functional and psychological data. Aims. To further our knowledge in a number of different disciplines about earlyexecutive functioning in infants with differential courses of development (typical infants, infants with Down syndrome, infantsborn with risk factors). We suggest the existence of an early differential gradient of executive functioning. Subjects and methods.A comparative and longitudinal study was conducted into the activity of typical infants (n = 10), infants with a risk factor (n = 6infants with congenital hypothyroidism; n = 6 infants born underweight) and infants with Down syndrome (n = 6), using astimulating material, at 1.3 years and again 9 months later. Data was analysed both qualitatively and quantitatively. Results. Thetwo groups that were studied showed different patterns of early executive functioning, and the biggest difference was observedbetween typical infants and infants with Down syndrome. The infants with risk factors were located on a gradient between thesetwo, although closer to the former but with certain differences. It is also noted how the executive functions develop over the agesthat were studied. Conclusion. These differences in executive functioning provide us with guidelines on interventions aimed atharmonising early cognitive development</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sastre-Riba, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Desde el neuroconstructivismo, el desarrollocognitivo se entiende y estudia como proceso de reorganizaciónsucesiva, al igual que sus mecanismos de cambio y sus resultadosdiferenciales. Los primeros años de vida son esenciales paraexplicar las competencias cognitivas, emocionales y sociales diferenciales.En este proceso, los cambios en las funciones ejecutivascumplen un papel esencial. Captarlos reclama una investigacióninterdisciplinar que relacione los datos neuroanatómicos cerebralescon datos funcionales y psicológicos. Objetivo. Conocer interdisciplinarmenteel funcionamiento ejecutivo temprano en bebéscon cursos diferenciales de desarrollo (bebés típicos, bebés consíndrome de Down, bebés con factores de riesgo al nacer). Postulamosla existencia de un gradiente diferencial temprano de funcionamientoejecutivo. Sujetos y métodos. Se estudia, comparativay longitudinalmente, la actividad de bebés típicos (n = 10),bebés con factores de riesgo (n = 6 bebés con hipotiroidismo congénito;n = 6 bebés con bajo peso al nacer) y bebés con síndromede Down (n = 6), con un material de estímulo, a los 1,3 años y 9meses después. Se realiza un doble análisis de datos cualitativo ycuantitativo. Resultados. Se obtienen diferentes patrones de funcionamientoejecutivo temprano entre los grupos estudiados; lamayor diferencia se observa entre los bebés típicos y los bebés consíndrome de Down; los bebés con factores de riesgo ocupan ungradiente entre ambos, más cercano a los primeros, pero con ciertasdiferencias. Se evidencia también el desarrollo de las funcionesejecutivas a lo largo de las edades estudiadas. Conclusión.Estas diferencias de funcionamiento ejecutivo proporcionan pautasde intervención para la armonización del desarrollo cognitivotemprano</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(supl.2): s143-s151, feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condiciones tempranas del desarrollo y el aprendizaje: el papel de las funciones ejecutivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
