<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60727</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: a) to identify differences in the perception of patient painand suffering between patients and caregivers; b) to describe the strategiesused to alleviate patient suffering; and c) to determine the relationshipbetween the strategies used by caregivers and patient suffering levels.Materials and methods: the sample was conformed by patients withcancer (CP) and non-cancer pain (NCP) who attended pain and palliativecare services, and by their caregivers. Semi-structured interviews werecarried out with patients and caregivers. Descriptive analyses were performedfor socio-demographic and clinical data, and support strategiesreceived by patients and delivered by caregivers in each group, as well as acomparative analysis between pain and suffering levels as indicated bypatients and caregivers, and the strategies used by caregivers versuspatient suffering.Results: the sample was composed of 148 patients and 131 caregivers.A high correlation between patient and caregiver perception of pain andsuffering was found both for CP and NCP groups. The most commonstrategies used were mixed, followed by the affective and instrumentaltypes. Caregivers in the CP group used more affective strategies, and thosein the NCP group used all types of strategies. There was no relationbetween strategy used and patient suffering extent.Conclusions: the concordance in patient and caregiver perceptionsmay be due to a strong relationship between them, given the high familiarityand the type of relations encountered in Latin-American societies,which can affect in a positive way the relief of suffering. Caregivers canplay an important role by facilitating treatments offered by health teams.Patients with pain, either with cancer or other pain conditions, are at riskof experiencing suffering. This can be perceived in a higher or lesserdegree by the patient&#146;s caregiver, who may influence strategies used toalleviate their suffering (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, C. Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torné, G. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez Ángel, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Krikorian Daveloza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Avellaneda, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Gómez, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Pinedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, B. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: a) Identificar diferencias entre pacientes y cuidadores respectoa la percepción de dolor y sufrimiento en el paciente; b) describir lasestrategias de cuidado útiles en el alivio del sufrimiento; y c) determinar larelación entre estrategias de cuidado y sufrimiento.Material y métodos: la población estuvo conformada por pacientes,con dolor oncológico (DO) y no oncológico (DNO) que consultaron a serviciosde alivio del dolor y cuidados paliativos y sus cuidadores principales.Se realizaron entrevistas semi-estructuradas a pacientes y cuidadores porseparado. Se obtuvieron estadísticos descriptivos para los datos sociodemográficos,clínicos y las estrategias de cuidado recibidas por el paciente ybrindadas por el cuidador de cada grupo y se realizaron análisis comparativosentre los niveles de dolor y sufrimiento indicado por pacientes y cuidadores,y las estrategias de cuidado empleadas por el cuidador y el nivelde sufrimiento del paciente utilizando estadísticos de chi-cuadrado.Resultados: muestra final conformada por 148 pacientes y 131 cuidadoresprincipales. Se encontró una alta concordancia en las medidas desufrimiento y dolor percibidos entre pacientes y cuidadores, tanto en elgrupo DO como en el grupo DNO. Las estrategias de cuidado más empleadasfueron de tipo mixto, seguido de afectivas y por último instrumentales.Los cuidadores de pacientes DO tienden a usar más estrategias afectivas,mientras que los de DNO usan todo tipo de estrategias. No huborelación entre la estrategia de cuidado empleada y un menor sufrimientoen el paciente (...) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;15(5): 279-286, nov.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sufrimiento, dolor y estrategias de cuidado: percepción de pacientes y cuidadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
