<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133752</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Description of disease type 1 diabetes mellitus associated autoimmune disease in a health area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To describe the onset of autoimmune disease and monitoring associated with type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) in a sample of patients under 19 years, and to explain the importance of the onset and monitoring screening of T1DM in this health area. Patients and methods: An observational descriptive study was conducted on patients under 19 years-old with onset of type 1 diabetes mellitus in the health district of West Valladolid (Spain) during the period from 2001 to 2011. The results of the diagnostic tests for diseases associated with T1DM (autoimmune polyendocrine syndromes, Addison's disease, pernicious anemia, vitiligo, thyroid disease, celiac disease) were recorded). Results: Antithyroid antibodies were performed (peroxidase antibodies, anti-TPO) in 85.9% of patients (67 cases), being positive in 23.9% (16 cases) at onset and during follow-up. The most common thyroid disease was chronic lymphocytic thyroiditis. Screening for celiac disease was performed in 75.6% (59 cases) of patients, being positive in 3.4% of patients at onset, and 1.7% (1 case) in the follow-up. None of the patients in our population sample presented with autoimmune polyendocrine syndromes, Addison's disease, pernicious anemia, or vitiligo. Conclusions: The results suggest that it may be worthwhile screening for autoimmune diseases associated with T1DM, both at the time of diagnosis of disease and periodically during the follow-up of T1DM. Perhaps, with current international recommendations and medical consensus, screening for autoimmune diseases associated with T1DM could become routine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar-Galán, Rafael del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando-Mayor, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno-Malfaz, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luis-Román, Daniel de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar-Guerra, Pablo del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Sagrado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Describir la patología autoinmune al inicio y en el seguimiento asociadas a la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 (DM1), así como exponer la importancia del cribado al comienzo y en el seguimiento de la DM1 en nuestro entorno de trabajo. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo transversal del periodo 2001-2011 de pacientes con inicio de DM1 menores de 19 años, correspondientes al Área de Salud Oeste de Valladolid. A todos los pacientes de nuestra muestra durante el período estudiado se realizaron estudios para las enfermedades comórbiles de la DM1 (síndromes autoinmunes poliendocrinos, enfermedad de Addison, anemia perniciosa, vitíligo, enfermedad tiroidea, enfermedad celíaca). Resultados: Se realizaron anticuerpos antitiroideos al ingreso (anticuerpos antiperoxidasa, anti-TPO) en el 85,9% de los pacientes (67 casos), siendo positivos en el 23,9% (16 casos) tanto al inicio como en el seguimiento. La patología tiroidea más común fue la tiroiditis linfocitaria crónica. Se realizó al inicio de la DM1 el cribado de la enfermedad celíaca en el 75,6% (59 casos) de los pacientes, siendo positivos el 3,4% de los pacientes (2 casos), y el 1,7% (un caso) en el seguimiento. Ningún paciente de nuestra población presentó síndromes autoinmunes poliendocrinos, enfermedad de Addison, anemia perniciosa, ni vitíligo. Conclusiones: Quizá con las recomendaciones internacionales actuales y el consenso médico se pueda realizar el cribado rutinario de las enfermedades autoinmunes comórbiles con DM1 de manera estandarizada. Es conveniente realizar el cribado de enfermedades autoinmunes relacionadas con la DM1, tanto en el momento del diagnóstico de la enfermedad como periódicamente en el seguimiento posterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;31(1): 30-35, ene.-feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de las enfermedades autoinmunes acompañantes de la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 en un área sanitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d767^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d767^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
