<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154949</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ductal carcinoma in situ: analysis of cases and assessment of recurrences in our center from 1999-2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse recurrences in patients diagnosed, treated and followed up in our centre for ductal carcinoma in situ and to identify the variables associated with an increased risk of their development. Patients and methods. We performed a retrospective study of cases of ductal carcinoma in situ diagnosed and treated in our hospital from January 1999 to January 2012. We excluded cases with coexistence of an infiltrating component, a history of neoplasia, and/or prior radiation to the affected breast. The variables analysed were patient age, tumour size, nuclear grade, surgical margin status, type of surgery, and adjuvant therapy (radiation and hormone therapy). Results. We studied 162 cases of ductal carcinoma in situ occurring between 1999 and 2012. Of these, 117 cases (72.2%) were treated with conservative surgery and 45 (27.7%) by mastectomy. In that period, we found 16 recurrences (9.9%). We found no statistically significant difference in the recurrence rate according to tumour size, surgical distance from the margin, histological grade, or patient age. In the subgroup of patients treated with lumpectomy, disease-free survival was higher in patients receiving radiation therapy and hormone therapy as a complementary treatment than in those who received only one or no treatment at all (P=.001). Conclusion. In the subgroup of patients with ductal carcinoma in situ treated with lumpectomy, the recurrence risk was 19 times higher in patients who received no adjuvant treatment than in those treated with lumpectomy, radiation and hormone therapy (P=.001) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cusidó, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fábregas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tresserra, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ara, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baulies, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las recidivas de las pacientes diagnosticadas, tratadas y seguidas en nuestro centro por carcinoma ductal in situ de mama, y establecer qué variables se asocian a un mayor riesgo de desarrollarlas. Pacientes y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de los casos de carcinoma ductal in situ diagnosticados y tratados en nuestro centro desde enero de 1999 hasta enero de 2012. Se excluyeron los casos en que coexistía componente infiltrante y aquellos con antecedente de neoplasia y/o radioterapia previa en la mama afecta. Las variables que se analizaron fueron: la edad de la paciente, el tamaño tumoral, el grado nuclear, el estado de los márgenes quirúrgicos, el tipo de cirugía y el tratamiento complementario (radioterapia y hormonoterapia). Resultados. Se estudiaron 162 casos de carcinomas in situ en el periodo 1999-2012. De estos, 117 (72,2%) fueron tratados con cirugía conservadora y 45 (27,7%) mediante mastectomía. Se produjeron 16 recidivas (9,9%) en el periodo estudiado. No se encuentran diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la tasa de recidivas en función del tamaño tumoral, la distancia quirúrgica al margen, el grado histológico ni la edad de la paciente. En el subgrupo de pacientes tratadas con tumorectomía, la supervivencia libre de enfermedad fue mayor en las que recibieron de forma complementaria radioterapia y hormonoterapia que en aquellas que solo recibieron uno o ninguno de los tratamientos (p=0,001). Conclusión. En el subgrupo de pacientes con carcinoma in situ tratadas con tumorectomía el riesgo de recidiva es 19 veces superior en los casos que no recibieron ningún tratamiento complementario que en aquellos tratados con tumorectomía, radioterapia y hormonoterapia (p=0,001) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);29(3): 106-112, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154949</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma in situ de mama: análisis de los casos y evaluación de las recidivas en nuestro centro, 1999-2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6885^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
