<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051077</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a structured summary of the document &#147;Consensus on international adoption.Guidelines for paediatricians and other health professionals&#148; published on November2005. The summary presented tries to be a representative sample of the whole original documentand to reflect its contents and proposals with fidelity. International adoption hasincreased in an extraordinary way in our country. Between 1997 and 2004, 24042 childrenfrom 49 countries have arrived. Children adopted abroad have an increased risk of presentingwith health problems. The journey and stay abroad implies additional risks. We describethe contents of the preadoptive medical visit and recommendations for making acomplete evaluation after the arrival of the child from his/her country of origin to the newfamily. We also stress the need of undertaking a long follow up</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lirio Casado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Merino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Lozano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López-Hortelano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliván Gonzalvo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fumadó Pérez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranzábal Agudo, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un resumen estructurado del documento &#147;Consenso en adopción internacional.Guía para pediatras y otros profesionales sanitarios&#148; publicado en noviembre de 2005. Elresumen presentado trata de ser una muestra representativa del conjunto del documentooriginal y reflejar con fidelidad su contenido y propósitos.La adopción internacional ha aumentado en nuestro entorno de forma extraordinaria.En el período de tiempo de 1997 a 2004 han llegado a nuestro país 24.042 niños procedentesde 49 países. Los niños adoptados en el extranjero tienen mayor riesgo de presentar problemasde salud. El viaje y la estancia en el extranjero implican riesgos adicionales. Se describenel contenido de la consulta preadoptiva y las recomendaciones para llevar a cabo una evaluacióncompleta tras la llegada del niño desde su lugar de origen a su nueva familia. También sedestaca la necesidad de hacer un seguimiento longitudinal a largo plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(supl.6): 41-53, jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051077</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">&#147;Consenso en adopción internacional. Guía para pediatras y otros profesionales sanitarios&#148;. Resumen estructurado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
