<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61454</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical disorders and pregnancy. Gastrointestinal, neurological, cardiovascular and dermatological disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A pregnant woman can present medical pathologiessimilar to a woman who is not pregnant. However, theclinical features of some pathologies and the diagnosticor therapeutic process might be altered due to changesproduced by pregnancy and the presence of the foetus.In some cases this can limit the diagnostic methods orthe therapies to be applied. This article sets out thedigestive and cardiovascular pathologies, pathologiesof the nervous system and dermatoses of greatest relevancedue to their frequency or severity, which mightbe encountered in an emergency consultation. It alsooffers a practical approach for the initial handling andthe prognosis for the mother and the foetus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Larrañaga, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roche, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rodríguez, A. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la mujer embarazada se pueden presentar patologíasmédicas similares a la no gestante, si bien el cuadroclínico de algunas patologías así como el procesodiagnóstico o terapéutico puede estar alterado por loscambios que el embarazo produce en ella, así como porla presencia del feto, que en algunos casos puede limitarlos métodos diagnósticos o las terapias a aplicar. Eneste trabajo se exponen las patologías digestivas, cardiovasculares,del sistema nervioso y dermatosis másrelevantes por su frecuencia o por su gravedad, quepueden presentarse en una consulta de urgencias, conun enfoque práctico sobre el manejo inicial y sobre elpronóstico para la madre y el feto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(supl.1): 135-157, ene.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61454</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología médica y embarazo. Trastornos gastrointestinales, neurológicos, cardiovasculares y dermatológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7119^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
