<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131154</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on the treatment of osteoporosis: management from a unit of pain (I)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteoporosis (OP) is defined as a skeletal disorder characterized by decreased bone strength, which predisposes to an increase in fracture risk. In Europe produced 2.7 million fragility fractures in both men and women with a direct cost of 36 billion euros. These fractures are associated with increased morbidity and mortality. The risk of osteoporotic fracture is determined by the presence of one or more risk factors and decreased bone mineral density (BMD) assessed by Dual Energy technique absortiometry X-ray (DEXA) densitometry. The indication for treatment is made based on the absolute risk of fragility fracture. In patients with a low risk of fracture are sufficient hygienic measures, preventing falls and maintaining an adequate intake of calcium and vitamin D. In patients with a moderate risk should be individualized drug treatment need and initiate treatment in those at high risk of fracture. The most commonly used drugs are bisphosphonates, inhibitors of bone resorption, also used as hormone teriparatide, osteoanabolic drug and monoclonal antibodies such as denosumab (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Callejo Orcasitas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Álvarez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Mollinedo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Garcés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arizaga Maguregui, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteoporosis (OP) se define como una enfermedad esquelética caracterizada por una resistencia ósea disminuida que predispone a un aumento en el riesgo de fracturas. En Europa se producen 2,7 millones de fracturas por fragilidad, tanto en hombres como mujeres, con un coste directo de 36 billones de euros. Estas fracturas se asocian con un incremento en la morbilidad y mortalidad. El riesgo de fractura osteoporótica viene determinado por la presencia de uno o más factores de riesgo y el descenso de la densidad mineral ósea (DMO) valorado mediante la técnica Dual Energy X-ray absortiometry (DEXA), densitometría. La indicación de tratamiento se realiza en función del riesgo absoluto de fractura por fragilidad. En los pacientes con un bajo riesgo de fractura son suficientes las medidas higiénicas, prevención de caídas y mantener una ingesta adecuada de calcio y vitamina D. En los pacientes con un riesgo moderado se debe individualizar la necesidad de tratamiento farmacológico e iniciar el tratamiento en aquellos con alto riesgo de fractura. Los fármacos más utilizados son los bifosfonatos, inhibidores de la reabsorción ósea, también se utilizan fármacos osteoanabólicos como la hormona teriparatida y anticuerpos monoclonales como el denosumab (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;21(6): 328-337, nov.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131154</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en el tratamiento de la osteoporosis. Manejo desde una unidad del dolor (1.ª parte)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54517^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52863^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52863^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22372^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1887^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1887^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
