<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125825</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical intrastromal keratopigmentation using tattoo ink</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 31-year-old woman who had undergone surgery for a congenital cataract as a newborn developed bilateral malignant glaucoma, which was refractory to medical-surgical treatment. The patient currently has terminal glaucoma and severe band keratopathy. For aesthetic purposes, we performed intrastromal keratopigmentation surgery using ink for skin tattoos supplied in sterile single-dose vessels. No secondary effects or complications were observed. Discussion: Keratopigmentation or corneal tattooing can now be used as a last resort in patients who are unable to tolerate cosmetic contact or intraocular lenses, or in whom corneal transplant is contraindicated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gessa-Sorroche, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ángeles-Figueroa, R. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Hermosilla, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 31 años intervenida de cataratas congénitas siendo aún lactante, que desarrolla posteriormente un glaucoma maligno bilateral refractario a tratamiento médico-quirúrgico, hasta alcanzar el estado actual terminal con queratopatía en banda severa. Por este motivo, se realiza con fines estéticos una queratopigmentación quirúrgica intraestromal con la novedad de emplear envases monodosis estériles de tinta para tatuaje cutáneo, sin hallarse efectos secundarios ni otras complicaciones. Discusión: La queratopigmentación o tatuaje corneal constituye actualmente el último recurso en pacientes que no toleran las lentes cosméticas o intraoculares y en los que el trasplante corneal está contraindicado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(7): 286-289, jul. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Queratopigmentación quirúrgica intraestromal con tinta para tatuaje cutáneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4457^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14032^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3334^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
