<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60795</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Upper gastrointestinal bleeding secondary to a jejunal stromal tumor in a patient with neurofibromatosis type 1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) is a multisystemic disease with an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance, complete penetrance and variable expressivity. This disease affects one in every 3,000 individuals and one out of every 200 patients with mental retardation. Gastrointestinal bleeding secondary to gastrointestinal mesenchymal tumors is one of the many complications associated with NF1. We report the case of a patient with NF1 admitted to hospital for severe gastrointestinal hemorrhage secondary to a jejunal gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) with favorable outcome after surgical removal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clemente Ricote, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalina Rodríguez, María Vega</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bachiller, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Rodríguez, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neurofibromatosis tipo 1 (NF1) es una enfermedad multisistémica de herencia autosómica dominante, con penetrancia completa y expresividad variable. Afecta a uno de cada 3.000 individuos y se presenta en uno de cada 200 pacientes con retraso mental. Dentro de las múltiples complicaciones que asocia se encuentra la hemorragia digestiva secundaria a tumores mesenquimales gastrointestinales. Presentamos el caso de un paciente con NF1, ingresado por una hemorragia digestiva grave secundaria a un tumor yeyunal del estroma gastrointestinal (GIST), que presentó una buena evolución tras su exéresis quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;32(4): 287-290, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia digestiva alta, secundaria a un tumor estromal yeyunal, en un paciente con neurofibromatosis tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
