<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67688</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multicystic dysplasia is the most common type of renal cystic disease, and it is one of the most common causes of an abdominal mass in infants. The contralateral system is also frequently abnormal. The most commonly associated anomalies are contralateral ureteropelvic junction obstruction and contralateral vesicoureteral reflux. In a few cases, multicystic dysplasia involves a horseshoe kidney or one pole of a duplex kidney. We present a female patient diagnosed with this condition at 9 years old, when she was being studied due to recurrent abdominal pain. The renal function was normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Alacio, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roper, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Nieto, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luis Yanes, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia renal multiquística es la variedad más frecuente de enfermedad quística renal y una de las causas más comunes de masa abdominal en recién nacidos y lactantes. Las anomalías contralaterales que se asocian con más frecuencia son la estenosis de la unión pieloureteral y el reflujo vesicoureteral. En muy pocos casos, la displasia renal multiquística está presente en uno de los segmentos de un riñón "en herradura" o en uno de los polos, en el caso de un doble sistema. Presentamos el caso de una paciente portadora de esta asociación de malformaciones diagnosticada a los 9 años de edad al ser estudiada por tener dolor abdominal recurrente. La función renal fue normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);69(4): 355-357, oct. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67688</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d50494^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10171</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5801^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
