<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108470</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Allergic Contact Dermatitis to Fragrances: Part 2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Allergic contact dermatitis due to fragrances usually manifests as subacute or chronic dermatitis because fragrances are found in a wide range of products to which patients are repeatedly exposed. The typical patient is a middle-aged woman with dermatitis on her hands and face, although other sites may be affected depending on the allergen and the product in which it is found. The standard patch test series of the Spanish Contact Dermatitis and Skin Allergy Research Group (GEIDAC) contains 4 fragrance markers: balsam of Peru, fragrance mix I, fragrance mix II, and lyral. Testing with a specific fragrance series is recommended in patients with a positive result to any of these 4 markers. The use of a specific fragrance series and new legislation obliging manufacturers to specify the fragrances used in their products, will help to improve the management of allergic contact dermatitis due to fragrances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silvestre, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dermatitis de contacto alérgica por fragancias suele presentarse clínicamente como un eczema subagudo o crónico debido a la ubicuidad de este alérgeno en los productos de uso cotidiano y el contacto repetido. El paciente típico es una mujer de edad media con afectación de las manos y la cara, aunque la localización de las lesiones variará dependiendo del alérgeno y del producto causante. Dentro de la batería estándar del Grupo Español en Investigación de Dermatitis de Contacto y Alergia Cutánea (GEIDAC) están incluidos 4 marcadores de fragancias: el bálsamo del Perú, la mezcla de fragancias I, la mezcla de fragancias II y el lyral. En caso de que alguno de estos marcadores sea positivo está indicada la utilización de una serie de fragancias específicas para el diagnóstico. Esto, unido a la nueva legislación que obliga a la industria a notificar qué ingredientes y fragancias utiliza en sus productos, nos ayudará a la resolución de la dermatitis de pacientes alérgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;104(1): 29-37, ene. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatitis de contacto alérgica por fragancias. Parte II</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10668^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
