<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162155</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivation Questionnaire to Adopt a Healthy Lifestyle: Adaptation of the Treatment Self-Regulation Questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to develop a Motivation Questionnaire to Adopt a Healthy Lifestyle (CM-EVS) for adolescents, an adaptation of the Treatment Self-Regulation Questionnaire (TSRQ) to the Spanish context. Two independent studies were carried out, in 858 and 344 post-compulsory secondary education students (aged from 16 to 21) participated, respectively. The factorial structure of the instrument was tested in the first study. Results showed unsuitable fit indices because of item ten. After a new wording of this item, results gave support to a four-subscale structure (self-determined motivation, introjected regulation, external regulation, and amotivation). There was invariance across sex and physical exercise. Except for introjected regulation, internal consistence (Cronbach's alpha and composite reliability) of the rest of subscales was acceptable (&gt; .70). Results showed evidence of reliability and validity of the TSRQ in order to measure motivation to adopt a healthy lifestyle in Spanish adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sicilia, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lirola, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferriz, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue desarrollar el «Cuestionario de la motivación para adoptar un estilo de vida saludable» (CM-EVS) para adolescentes, una adaptación española del «Treatment Self-Regulation Questionnaire» (TSRQ). Se realizaron dos estudios independientes, en los que participaron 858 y 344 estudiantes de educación secundaria postobligatoria, de entre 16 y 21 años, respectivamente. En el primer estudio se evaluó la estructura factorial del cuestionario, mostrando los resultados un ajuste inadecuado e identificando el ítem 10 como problemático. En el segundo estudio se modificó la redacción del ítem y se comprobó de nuevo el modelo. Los resultados apoyaron una estructura de cuatro subescalas: Motivación autodeterminada, Regulación introyectada, Regulación externa y Desmotivación. La estructura factorial se reveló invariante respecto al sexo y la práctica de actividad física. La fiabilidad de las diferentes subescalas fue aceptable (&gt; 0,70), excepto para el factor Regulación introyectada. Los resultados muestran la fiabilidad y validez del TSRQ para evaluar la motivación para un adoptar un estilo de vida saludable en los adolescentes españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;25(1): 79-97, 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">«Cuestionario de la motivación para adoptar un estilo de vida saludable»: Adaptación del Treatment Self-Regulation Questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
