<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166790</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical pharmacology of ranolazine, a novel compound for treating chronic stable angina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ranolazine is a piperazine derivative that has a novel mechanism of action and which has been approved as add-on therapy for patients with chronic stable angina. Myocardial ischemia increases the late inward sodium ion (Na+ ) current in cardiac cells (INaL) and raises the intracellular sodium concentration (Na+ i ), which in turn activates the reverse mode of the sodium-calcium (Na+ - Ca2+) exchanger and increases the intracellular calcium concentration (Ca2+ i ). This increase in Na+ i and Ca2+ i leads to mechanical dysfunction (i.e. diastolic pressure increases, and contractility and myocardial oxygen supply decrease), electrical dysfunction (i.e. the induction of arrhythmias) and mitochondrial dysfunction (i.e. myocardial oxygen demand increases and the rate of ATP formation decreases). Ranolazine selectively inhibits the increase in INaL, reduces intracellular Na+ accumulation and the subsequent Ca2+ accumulation induced by Na+ , and decreases mechanical, electrical and metabolic dysfunction in the ischemic or failing myocardium. Controlled clinical trials have shown that ranolazine has both antianginal and anti-ischemic effects in patients with chronic stable angina, and an antiarrhythmic effect in patients with acute coronary syndrome. Moreover, ranolazine reduces the glycosylated hemoglobin level in diabetic patients with coronary heart disease and improves ventricular function in patients with ischemic heart disease or chronic heart failure. Ranolazine is well tolerated, with the most common adverse effects being nausea, dizziness, asthenia and constipation. For these reasons, ranolazine is a safe and effective option for patients with chronic stable angina whose symptoms are not under control or who can not tolerate conventional anti-anginal drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dolz, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barana, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamargo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorós, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delpón, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ranolazina es un derivado piperazínico con un nuevo mecanismo de acción que ha sido aprobado para su uso en combinación en pacientes con angina crónica estable. La isquemia miocárdica aumenta la corriente tardía de entrada de Na+ en las células cardiacas (INaL) e incrementa la concentración de sodio intracelular ([Na+ ] i ), lo que, a su vez, activa el modo inverso del intercambiador Na+ -Ca2+ y aumenta la concentración de calcio intracelular ([Ca2+] i ). Este aumento en Na+ i y Ca2+ i conduce a una disfunción mecánica (aumenta la presión diastólica y reduce la contractilidad y el aporte coronario de O2 ), eléctrica (produce arritmias) y mitocondrial (aumenta las demandas miocárdicas de O2 y reducción de la formación de adenosintrifosfato). La ranolazina inhibe selectivamente la INaL, reduce la acumulación intracelular de Na+ y la posterior de Ca2+ inducido por el Na+ , así como las anomalías mecánicas, eléctricas y metabólicas en el miocardio isquémico o insuficiente. En ensayos clínicos controlados realizados en pacientes con angina crónica estable, la ranolazina ejerce acciones antianginosas y antiisquémicas y, en pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo, ejerce acciones antiarrítmicas. Además, reduce la glucohemoglobina en pacientes coronarios diabéticos y mejora la función ventricular en pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica o insuficiencia cardiaca crónica. La ranolazina es un fármaco bien tolerado cuyos efectos adversos más comunes son náuseas, mareos, astenia y estreñimiento. Por todo lo anterior, la ranolazina representa una alternativa segura y eficaz en pacientes con angina crónica estable con síntomas no controlados o que no toleran los fármacos antianginosos convencionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.B): 41b-54b, 2010. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166790</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Farmacología clínica de la ranolazina, un nuevo fármaco en el tratamiento de la angina crónica estable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55872^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19558^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
