<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89159</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of a mattress designed with normactive technology: influence on the quality of sleep</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to assess wheter an improvement in the quality of sleep in occupational-aged adults could be achieved through the indroduction of a mattress designed using Normactive technology. The study population was constituted by 79 subjects (42 males; 37 females) aged 30 to 69 years. The study was conducted in the subjects´own bedrooms. The of sleep was first analysed with the subjects sleeping in their own mattresses, and the sults were then compared with the sleep quality data reported after sleeping on the new mattress for 15 days. The measurement instruments were subjective quality of sleep questionnaires in which lower scores relect good quality of sleep and higher scores a poorer sleep quality. The analysis of the questionnaires answers showed a marked decrease in the mean score for all questions and items. this decrease was statiscally significant for all parameters studied, although the observed difference was greater for the items "drowsiness on awaking", "mornig tiredness" and "uneasy sleep/movements while sleeping". these differences were unrelated to factors such as age, gender or "own" mattress composition (springs or latex". At the end of the study, a survey was carried out regarding satisfaciton with the new mattress as compared to the previous one, in which the majority of the surveyed population considered the new one to be more comfotable, to have a better design, and to cause the subject to feel better in the morning (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuartero Ríos, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacruz Casaucau, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Usieto Aguelo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valiño Colás, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Lorente, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo nos propusimos el objetivo de investigar si se producía na mejoría en la calidad del sueño en adultos en edad labora introducieondo un colchón diseñado con tecología Normative. La muestra estuvo constitutida por 79 sujetos (42 varones y 37 mujeres), de entre 30 y 60 años. El estudio se llevó a cabo en el dormitoros de los sujetos. En primer lugar se analizó la calidad de sueño mientras dormían en sus propias camas. para después comparar los resultados con la calidad del sueño infomrada tras dormir en e nuevo colchón durante 15 días. Como instrumento de medida se utlizaron cuestionarios de calidad subjetiva del sueño (donde puntuaciones bajas se relacionana con sueño de buena calidad y puntuaciones altas con sueño de mala calidad). Al analizar los cuestionarios se observa que hay un importante descenso en la puntuación media en todas las preguntas. La reducción es tadísticamente significativa en todos los parámetros, aunque la difernecia que se observa es mayor en las preguntas de sommolenica al despertar, cansancio físico por la mañana y movimientos durante la noche. Estas diferencias se mantienen más allá de características como la edad, el sexo o el interor del colchón propio (muelles o látex). Al finalizar el estudio se realizó una encuesta sobra la satisfacción con el nuevo colchón, en la que la mayoría consideró que es más cómodo, tiene mejor diseño y que se siente mejor al despertarse que con su colchón anterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;16(1): 14-20, feb. 2007. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia en la calidad del sueño mediante la utilización de un colchón diseñado con tecnología normactive</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1532^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
