<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73353</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypoglycemias in type 1 and 2 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypoglycemia and fear to suffer them are limiting factors, both inpatients with type 1 diabetes as well as type 2 diabetes, to achieveand maintain an adequate glycemic control to avoid appearance/progression of chronic complications. Frequency of hypoglycemicepisodes mostly depends on type of diabetes, employed treatmentand individual risk factors. Episodes may be minor, asymptomatic, orsevere even with loss of consciousness. Hypoglycemia may haveimportant clinical outcomes due to an increase in morbidity and mortalityand a reduction in quality of life. This situation is feared eitherby patients or their relatives. Economic implications of severe episodes,both as direct hospital costs as well as indirect costs due toinability to work, are considerable. Therefore, hypoglycemia is thebasic limiting factor to achieve glycemic control goals in patients withdiabetes mellitus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barquiel Alcalá, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisbona Catalán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Vaquero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puma Duque, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las hipoglucemias y el temor a presentarlas son factores limitantes,tanto en los pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1 como tipo 2,para alcanzar y mantener un adecuado control glucémico y evitar laaparición/progresión de las complicaciones crónicas. La frecuenciade episodios hipoglucémicos depende del tipo de diabetes, del tratamientoempleado y de factores de riesgo individuales. Los episodiospueden ser leves, asintomáticos, o graves, incluso con pérdidade conciencia. Las hipoglucemias tienen consecuencias clínicasnotables en cuanto al incremento de la morbimortalidad y la reducciónde la calidad de vida. Se trata de una situación muy temida porlos pacientes y sus familiares. Las implicaciones económicas de losepisodios graves son considerables, tanto en los costes hospitalariosdirectos como en los indirectos derivados de la incapacidadpara trabajar. Así pues, la hipoglucemia es el factor limitante básicopara lograr los objetivos glucémicos en los pacientes con diabetesmellitus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(4): 269-279, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipoglucemias leves y graves en la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 y 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22478^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
