<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62002</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transport, environment and health. 2008 SESPAS Report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Motor road transport has increased exponentially in the lastfew years. To a large extent, mobility is an essential elementin the organization of society, but, until recently, the implicationsof chosen forms of transport for health and the environmenthave not been considered.In this chapter we review the negative impact of current formsof transport on health in terms of traffic injuries, climate change,atmospheric contamination, noise, and interference withdaily activities and exercise, such as impediments to walkingor cycling. Some possible interventions related to the instrumentsavailable in public health and other fields are proposed.Issues deserving further research are highlighted.Some examples in Spain and other countries are described.Recommendations are made on the need to reduce the useof private cars and to develop segmented routes and areasof quiet traffic connected in the cities and among nearby townsto promote walking are cycling. One major goal in currentpublic policies should be to develop and maintain a publictransport system that is safe, cheap and faster and less pollutingthan private transport. These interventions would helpto achieve a change in current modes of transport and wouldlead to a healthier population and a more sustainable environment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peiró, Rosanna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester, Ferr</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El transporte a motor se ha incrementado de manera exponencialen los últimos años. La organización de la sociedadrequiere en gran medida la movilidad como un elemento esencial,pero, hasta hace poco tiempo, no se habían consideradolas implicaciones para la salud y el medio ambiente de lasformas de desplazamiento elegidas. En este capítulo se revisael impacto negativo en salud que el tipo de transporte actualtiene en términos de lesiones de tráfico, el cambio climático,la contaminación atmosférica, el ruido, y las interferenciaspara las actividades cotidianas y la actividad física, como ladificultad para andar o ir en bicicleta. Se proponen algunas intervencionesposibles relacionadas con los instrumentos disponiblesen salud pública y otras áreas, y se destacan aspectosdonde se necesita más investigación. Se describen algunosejemplos en España y en otros países. Se hacen recomendacionesacerca de la necesidad de reducir el uso del cocheprivado, desarrollar vías segmentadas y espacios de tráfico tranquiloconectados en las ciudades y entre pueblos cercanos parapromocionar el desplazamiento andando o en bicicleta. Se planteaque el desarrollo y el mantenimiento de un sistema de transportepúblico que sea más rápido, seguro, barato y menos contaminanteque el transporte privado debería ser una metaimportante en las políticas públicas actuales. Estas accionesayudarán a conseguir un cambio en los modos de transportede la sociedad y, consecuentemente, una población más sanay un ambiente más sostenible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;22(supl.1): 53-64, abr. 2008. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62002</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transporte, medio ambiente y salud. Informe SESPAS 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d400^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d400^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9810^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9808^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9810^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9808^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31494</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
