<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057116</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Course and cares of intestinal transplant in immediate post-operative period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Describe the course and immediate post-operative care in patients with intestinal transplant. Material and methods. Descriptive, prospective study conducted in the Polyvalent Intensive Care Unit of a tertiary hospital for one year. Variables analyzed during the first 48 hours of the post-operative period: vital signs, O2 saturation, weaning time, diuresis, glycemia, catheters, drains, ileostomy, gastrostomy, TISS, NEMS, nursing cares, APACHE II and SAPS II on admission. Statistical analysis with SPSS 11.0. Results. Four patients, 50% women, mean age 42 ± 8 years. Reason for intestinal transplant: 75% familial adenomatous polyposis with desmoid tumor and 25% mesenteric artery obstruction. They were administered alemtuzumab and tacrolimus. All the patients were carrier of central and arterial venous catheters, and Jackson Pratt abdominal drains (50% two, 50% three). Intubation time (median) 15 hours. APACHE II 10 ± 6 y SAPS II 16 ± 4. Means on first and second day of: systolic/diastolic blood pressure 132 ± 23/73 ± 11; 130 ± 25/74 ± 13 mmHg; glycemia 136 ± 26/119 ± 25 mg/dl; diuresis 95 ± 34/125 ± 30 cc/hour; TISS28 49 ± 4/38 ± 11 and NEMS 27 ± 0/25 ± 10, respectively. One re-operation due to hemorrhagic shock. Median study in Intensive Care Unit of 4 days. Conclusions. 1) They are hemodynamically stable patients with short weaning. They do not have many catheters, functioning ileostomy since the first day and TISS28 and NEMS in the middle of the range. 2) The most specific cares of the intestinal transplant are: surgical wound, drains, ileostomy, gastrostomy. 3) The need for intense immunosuppression implies strict isolation and nursing:patient ratio of 1:1</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Frade Mera, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jacue Izquierdo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo González, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontan Vinagre, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir la evolución y cuidados del postoperatorio inmediato en pacientes con trasplante intestinal. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo prospectivo realizado en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Polivalente de un hospital terciario durante un año. Variables analizadas durante las primeras 48 horas del postoperatorio: constantes vitales, saturación O2, tiempo de destete, diuresis, glucemia, catéteres, drenajes, ileostomía, gastrostomía, TISS, NEMS, cuidados de enfermería, APACHE II y SAPS II al ingreso. Análisis estadístico con SPSS 11.0. Resultados. Cuatro pacientes. Mujeres 50%, edad media 42 ± 8 años. Motivo trasplante intestinal: 75% poliposis adenomatosa familiar con tumor desmoides y 25% obstrucción arteria mesentérica. Recibieron alemtuzumab y tacrólimus. Todos los pacientes eran portadores de catéter venoso central, arterial y drenajes abdominales Jackson Pratt (50% dos, 50% tres). Tiempo intubación (mediana) 15 horas. APACHE II 10 ± 6 y SAPS II 16 ± 4. Medias primer y segundo día de: tensión arterial sistólica/diastólica 132 ± 23/73 ± 11; 130 ± 25/74 ± 13 mmHg; glucemia 136 ± 26/119 ± 25 mg/dl; diuresis 95 ± 34/125 ± 30 cc/hora; TISS28 49 ± 4/38 ± 11 y NEMS 27 ± 0/25 ± 10, respectivamente. Una reintervención por shock hemorrágico. Mediana de estancia en Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos 4 días. Conclusiones. 1) Son pacientes hemodinámicamente estables; con destete corto; no portan muchos catéteres; ileostomía funcionante desde el primer día y con TISS28 y NEMS en la media del rango. 2) Los cuidados más específicos del trasplante intestinal son: herida quirúrgica, drenajes, ileostomía, gastrostomía. 3) La necesidad de intensa inmunosupresión implica aislamiento estricto y una ratio de enfermería:paciente 1:1</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;18(2): 61-69, abr.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución y cuidados del trasplante intestinal en el postoperatorio inmediato</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7585^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
