<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112019</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Today´s dilemas concerning psychic splitting. Toward a third topic?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author takes up the Freudian concept of splitting and the use of this concept by Kleinian authors; he then discusses A. Green´s interesting proposal regarding the urgent need to re-interpret Freud´s works in the light of the discoveries of Winnicottt and other important post-Freudian authors. He goes on to discuss controversies on the concept of &lt;enactment&gt; or &lt;passage into act&gt; in psychoanalytic practices as well as some developments interesting for psychoanalysis in the modern neurosciences (R. W. Sperry, Michael Gazzaniga, Eric Kandel, Antonio Damasio, etc). He then introduces the proposal of a new and more modern model of functioning of the psychic apparatus. He finds support for his proposal in his psychoanalytic and psychotherapeutic practice, illustrating with some clinical vignettes for the purpose of improving understanding of the structure and dynamis of psychic splitting in some severe psychopathologies. He underssoma and the other, characterized by splitting, introduced in the second Freutence of at least two important modes of mental functioning: the repressed and splitting. He agrees with other authors that it would be given the term: &lt;the third topic&gt;. It is therefore a question of advancing proposals in relation to the question: &lt;How to represent two or more different modes of psychic functioning within the same topic?&gt; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Martín, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor, partiendo primero del concepto de escisión freudiano y de la utilización de dicho concepto por los autores kleinianos, recalando después en la interesante propuesta de A. Green sobre la urgente necesidad de reinterpretar la obra freudiana a la luz de los descubrimientos de Winnicott y otros importantes autores postfreudianos, teniendo en cuenta, a continuación, las controversias sobre el concepto de &lt;enactment&gt; (pasaje al acto) en la práctica psicoanalítica, así como algunos interesantes desarrollos para el psicoanálisis de las modernas neurociencias (R. W. Sperry, Michael ÇGazzaniga, Eric Kandel, Antonio Damasio, etc.)  y apoyándose, finalmente, en su práctica psicoanalítica y psicoterapéutica (exponiendo, a modo de ejemplo, algunas viñetas clínicas), introduce, siempre con el fin de poder comprender mejor la estructura y dinámica de la escisión psíquica en algunas graves psicopatologías, la propuesta de un nuevo y más actual modelo de funcionamiento del aparato psíquico, entendido como la construcción del psiquismo entre el soma y el otro, caracterizado por la introducción en la segunda tópica freudiana de la escisión como mecanismo universal y estructurante, que permite la coexistencia de, al menos, dos importantes modos de funcionamiento mental: el de denominar: la tercera tópica. Se trata, pues, de plantear propuestas a la cuestión de: ¿Cómo representar dos o más funcionamientos psíquicos diferentes en el interior de una misma tópica? (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(64): 69-132, dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112019</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dilemas actuales acerca de la escisión psíquica ¿Hacia una tercera tópica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
