<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85351</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychotherapy of Psychosis: From the Subject at Risk to the Chronic Patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors review the psychotherapy interventions used most in psychotic patients, stressing, firstly, those conducted in the early phases of the disease, the most classical interventions during periods of stability, and, finally interventions related with psychosocial rehabilitation of the psychotic patient. Within the early phases of the disease, a  distinction is made between high-risk subjects and those who have already had a first psychotic episode. The efficacy and the current intervention model in each of the most conventional psychotherapies: dynamic, cognitive-behavioral, family, and group therapies, are described. Special emphasis is placed on adaptation to the patient&#146;s needs in each intervention  model. Finally, the psychosocial interventions that have demonstrated their efficacy are indicated, that is to say, assertive community therapy, social skills training and supported employment programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>gonz´lez Moliner, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cabeza, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraile Fraile, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Avezuela, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve Díaz, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los autores revisan las intervenciones psicoterapéuticas más utilizadas en pacientes psicóticos, describiendo por un lado aquellas intervenciones realizadas durante las fases tempranas de la enfermedad, las intervenciones psicoterapéuticas clásicas durante los periodos de estabilidad del paciente y finalmente aquellas relacionadas con la rehabilitación psicosocial del enfermo psicótico. Durante las fases tempranas se diferencia entre tratamientos  psicoterapéuticos en pacientes de alto riesgo y los que ya padecen una psicosis franca. Se describe la eficacia y la forma de intervención actual de cada uno de los cuatro modelos psicoterapéuticos más convencionales: dinámico, cognitivo-conductual, familiar y grupal. Se hace un especial énfasis en la necesidad de intervenciones integradoras y orientadas a las necesidades de cada paciente. Por último, se describen las intervenciones psicosociales  que han demostrado su eficacia, a saber: tratamiento comunitario asertivo, entrenamiento en habilidades sociales y programas de apoyo al empleo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;21(3): 285-297, nov. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicoterapia de la Psicosis: De la Persona en Riesgo al Paciente Crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
