<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105941</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To evaluate the ef&amp;#64257;cacy and safety of an update to an anti-emetic protocol in chemotherapy for gynecological tumours. Method: Prospective observational study performed over 12 months in a general hospital with400 beds. We evaluated the ef&amp;#64257;cacy of the old anti-emetic protocol, a new protocol was implemented, and its ef&amp;#64257;cacy was determined. We included patients with gynaecological tumours that sought treatment at the Day Hospital. After each chemotherapy cycle, patients &amp;#64257;lled out a survey that registered the number and severity of episodes of nausea/vomiting and other adverse effects. The ef&amp;#64257;cacy of treatment was measured as complete response (no nausea orvomit) in the acute phase (&amp;#64257;rst 24 h after chemotherapy) and late phase (2-5 days after chemotherapy). We also evaluated whether age, the type of protocol, and the emetogenous power of the different treatment schemes could in&amp;#64258;uence patient response. Results: We analysed 102 chemotherapy cycles under the old protocol (52 patients) and293 cycles under the new protocol (98 patients). We observed signi&amp;#64257;cant differences in completeresponse rates in the late phase between old and new protocols (36.27% vs 67.38%, P&lt;.0001).The probability of obtaining a complete response using the new protocol was twice as high as with the old protocol in acute emesis (OR = 1.85, 95% CI: 1.05-3.24, P=.03) and four times higherin late emesis (OR = 4.27, 95% CI: 2.59-7.02, P&lt;.0001).Conclusions: A greater percentage of complete responses to late emesis was obtained using the new protocol. Age and the low emetogenous power of the treatment schemes were predictive factors for complete response in acute emesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan Arroyo, A. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Ibáñez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urrutia Losada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Torre Querejazu, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarra García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios Zabalza, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de una actualización de un protocolo antiemético de quimioterapia en tumores ginecológicos. Método Estudio prospectivo, observacional, realizado durante 12 meses en un hospital general de 400 camas. Se evaluó la eficacia del protocolo antiemético antiguo, se implantó el protocolo nuevo, y se midió su eficacia. Se incluyeron pacientes con tumores ginecológicos que acudían al hospital de día. Tras cada ciclo de quimioterapia, en una encuesta, registraban el número y severidad de náuseas/vómitos y otros efectos adversos. Se midió la eficacia como respuesta completa (sin náuseas y sin vómitos) en la fase aguda (primeras 24h posquimioterapia) y en retardada (día 2-5 posquimioterapia). Se evaluó si la edad, el tipo de protocolo y el poder emetógeno de los esquemas podían influir en la respuesta. Resultados Se analizaron 102 ciclos de quimioterapia con el protocolo antiguo (52 pacientes) y 293 ciclos (98 pacientes) con el protocolo nuevo. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en la respuesta completa en la fase retardada con el protocolo nuevo (67,38 vs 36,27%), p &lt; 0,0001. La probabilidad de obtener respuesta completa con el protocolo nuevo era dos veces mayor que con el antiguo en emesis aguda (OR=1,85; IC 95% = 1,05-3,24; p=0,03) y cuatro veces mayor en emesis retardada (OR=4,27; IC 95% = 2,59-7,02; p&lt;0,0001). Conclusiones Con el nuevo protocolo se consiguió un mayor porcentaje de respuesta completa en la emesis retardada. La edad y el bajo poder emetógeno de los esquemas fueron factores predictivos de respuesta completa en la emesis aguda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;36(4): 220-228, jul. -ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105941</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de eficacia y seguridad de dos protocolos antieméticos en quimioterapia ginecológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d939^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5969^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9517^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
