<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113205</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment results in a case of Asperger disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reports on the treatment of an 8-year-old boy who fulfilled the DSM-IV-TR diagnostic criteria for Asperger disorder (APA, 2000). The boy had poor concentration, disobedience and social skills deficits along with problem behaviors. Training in social skills was used together with a multiple-setting intervention for other contexts (parent training and teacher&#146;s cooperation in the school context). The boy&#146;s parents used a token economy in the family context and were advised to carry out home-based activities intended to facilitate generalization. After treatment he achieved the planned objectives. His improvements were observed by his teacher and parents and were reflected in test results (&#147;Multifactorial Childhood Adaption Evaluation Test&#148; and &#147;Assertive Behavior Scale for Children&#148;). In addition, there was generalization to other behaviors that were not directly treated, as shown by the disappearance of aggressive behaviors. Therefore, this behavioral intervention demonstrated its effectiveness</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vives Montero, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ascanio-Velasco, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se expone un estudio de caso de un niño de 8 años que cumplía los criterios diagnósticos del DSM-IV-TR (APA, 2000) para el trastorno de Asperger. Presentaba problemas de concentración, falta de obediencia y déficit en habilidades sociales, así como algunas conductas problema. Se aplicó un tratamiento en habilidades sociales con el niño y también una intervención extensiva a otros contextos (entrenamiento a padres y colaboración de la profesora en el contexto escolar). Los padres aplicaron una economía de fichas en el contexto familiar y se les encomendó algunas actividades para la casa dirigidas a facilitar la generalización. Después del tratamiento se comprobó que se habían alcanzado los objetivos planteados. Las mejorías fueron detectadas por la profesora, los padres y se reflejó en los resultados de las pruebas empleadas (el &#147;Test evaluativo multifactorial de adaptación infantil&#148; y la &#147;Escala de comportamiento asertivo para niños&#148;). Adicionalmente, se produjo la generalización a otras conductas no tratadas directamente, como la eliminación de las conductas agresivas. Por tanto, se demuestra la eficacia de esta intervención conductual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;20(2): 401-419, mayo-ago. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113205</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del tratamiento en un caso con trastorno de Asperger</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
