<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047445</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Middle latency auditory evoked potentials in critical care children: preliminary study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Middle latency auditory evoked potentials (MLAEP) reflect changes in electroencephalogram waves after an auditory signal and represent the earliest cortical response to acoustic stimulus. They are therefore used to measure variations in the level of consciousness. MLEAP have been used to measure the depth of anesthesia during surgical procedures, but experience in critical care patients is very limited.         Objective: To analyze the utility of MLAEP for monitoring the level of sedation in critically ill children.         Methods: Level of consciousness was monitored through MLAEP by placing special headphones and three sensors situated in the frontal and preauricular regions. Simultaneously, the level of sedation was measured using the COMFORT scale and the Bispectral Index (BIS) in distinct clinical situations.         Results: We studied six critically ill children in whom MLAEP helped us to evaluate the level of consciousness: light sedation, natural sleep, deep sedation, sedation in a paralyzed child, and brain death. MLAEP showed a good correlation with the COMFORT scale and BIS in light and deep sedation and were effective in the early detection of brain death in one patient. In the paralyzed patient, MLAEP was able to detect undersedation. In one patient, a pacemaker interfered with the MLAEP signal.         Conclusions: MLAEP can be useful in evaluating the level of consciousness and sedation in critically ill children. Further studies with larger samples are required to analyze the limitations and reproducibility of this type of monitoring in children of different ages</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lamas Ferreiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrego Domínguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáncho Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mencía Bartolomé, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Herce Cid, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Los potenciales evocados auditivos (PEA) recogen los cambios en las ondas auditivas cerebrales frente a un estímulo sonoro y estiman el grado de actividad eléctrica erebral. Los potenciales de latencia media o respuesta cortical temprana se correlacionan con las variaciones del estado de conciencia. Los PEA se han utilizado para valorar la hipnosis durante la cirugía, pero existe poca experiencia en el paciente crítico.         Objetivo: Analizar la utilidad de la monitorización con PEA de latencia media en niños críticamente enfermos.         Métodos: Se monitorizó el estado de conciencia mediante los PEA colocando unos auriculares de emisión de sonidos y 3 sensores en región frontal y preauricular. Simultáneamente se recogió la puntuación de la escala clínicas de sedación COMFORT y el Índice Biespectral (BIS), analizándose la puntuación de los PEA y su relación con los otros parámetros de sedación en niños en distintas situaciones clínicas.         Resultados: Se estudiaron 6 niños críticamente enfermos en los que los PEA ayudaron a valorar el estado de conciencia: sedación superficial, sueño espontáneo, sedación profunda, sedación en el paciente relajado y muerte cerebral. Los PEA mostraron una buena correlación con las escalas clínicas y el BIS en los casos de sedación superficial y profunda, y diagnosticaron precozmente un paciente con muerte cerebral. En un paciente relajado los PEA permitieron detectar la infrasedación. En un caso se observó que el marcapasos cardíaco producía interferencias en la medición de los potenciales evocados.         Conclusión: Los PEA pueden ser útiles en la valoración del estado de conciencia y sedación de los niños críticamente enfermos. Son necesarios estudios amplios que analicen su fiabilidad y limitaciones en las diferentes edades</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(4): 354-359, abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047445</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Potenciales evocados auditivos de latencia media en el niño críticamente enfermo: estudio preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5169</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14873^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29638</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
