<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165902</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Heart Transplantation Registry (Adults). The 25th Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Heart Failure and Heart Transplantation (1984-2013)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes the characteristics and outcomes of heart transplantations in patients aged 16 years or more in Spain from May 1984, when the technique was first used in the country. It contains a descriptive analysis of the characteristics of recipients, donors and surgical procedures and of the outcomes of all heart transplantations performed up to December 31, 2013. In 2013, 219 procedures were carried out in patients aged 16 years or more at the time of transplantation. These patients form part of the historical series of 6632 procedures carried out in this age group. In recent years, there has been progressive worsening of the clinical characteristics of recipients (i.e. 32% were aged over 60 years, 23% had severe renal failure, 19% were insulindependent diabetics, 27% had undergone cardiac surgery and 15% were on mechanical ventilation), donors (i.e. 45% were aged over 45 years and 25% had a recipient-donor weight mismatch &gt;20%), and surgical procedures (i.e. 28% involved an ischemia time &gt;4 hours and 37% were urgent). The survival rate at 1, 5, 10, and 15 years was 77%, 65%, 53%, and 37%, respectively. These figures have remained stable since 1995. Over the last few years there has been a slow decline in the number of heart transplantations performed in Spain. However, despite a clear deterioration in the clinical characteristics of recipients, donors and surgical procedures, mortality has remained comparable with that observed in neighboring countries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Vílchez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Bueno, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenar Bonet, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Leiro, María G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo presenta las características y resultados del trasplante cardiaco realizado en pacientes de 16 o más años desde que empezó su actividad en España en mayo de 1984. Se realiza un análisis descriptivo de las características de receptores, donantes, procedimiento quirúrgico y resultados de los trasplantes cardiacos realizados en España hasta el 31 de diciembre de 2013. Durante 2013 se han realizado 219 procedimientos en pacientes de 16 o más años de edad en el momento del trasplante, con lo que la serie histórica consta de 6.632 trasplantes en pacientes de esas edades. En los últimos años, se observa un empeoramiento del perfil clínico tanto de los receptores (el 32% mayores de 60 años, el 23% con insuficiencia renal grave, el 19% con diabetes mellitus insulinodependiente, el 27% con cirugía cardiaca previa, el 15% con ventilación mecánica) como de los donantes (el 45% mayores de 45 años, el 25% con discordancia de peso &gt; 20%) y el procedimiento (el 28% con tiempo de isquemia &gt; 4 h y el 37% procedimientos urgentes). La supervivencia a 1, 5, 10 y 15 años es del 77, el 65, el 53 y el 37% respectivamente. Estas cifras permanecen estables desde 1995. La actividad de trasplante cardiaco en España muestra un lento declive en los últimos años. A pesar del claro empeoramiento en las características de donantes, receptores y tiempos quirúrgicos, se mantienen unos resultados en mortalidad comparables a los de nuestro entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);15(supl.B): 31b-42b, 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Trasplante Cardiaco (Adultos). XXV Informe Oficial de la Sección de Insuficiencia Cardiaca y Trasplante Cardiaco de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (1984-2013)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14408^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55779^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
