<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129686</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intestinal microbiota and intense physical activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gastrointestinal (GI) complaints are common among athletes (30% to 70%). Both the intensity of sport and the type of sporting activity have been shown to be contributing factors in the development of GI symptoms. Three important factors have been postulated as contributing to the pathophysiology of GI complaints in athletes: mechanical forces, altered GI blood flow, and neuroendocrine changes. As a result of those factors, gastroesophageal reflux disease, nausea, vomiting, peptic ulcers or exercise-related transient abdominal pain may develop. The current state of knowledge suggests that the alterations in the immune system are dependent on parameters inherent to exercise and that in order to have all these alterations occurring, some cell signaling cascades are activated, giving rise to a complex process that culminated in the activation of transcription factors, translation of mRNA, protein synthesis and cell proliferation. Hundreds of studies have now been conducted that confirm both acute and chronic effects of exercise on the immune system, yet there are still very few studies that have been able to show a direct link between exercise-induced immune depression and increased incidence of confirmed illness in athletes. Gut microbiota interacts with both innate and adaptive immune system, playing a pivotal role in maintenance and disruption of gut immune quiescence. A cross talk between the mucosal immune system and endogenous micro-flora favours a mutual growth, survival and inflammatory control of the intestinal ecosystem. Based on these evidences, probiotics, some amino acids such as glutamine, arginine and leucine and certain phytochemicals can be used as an ecological and preventive therapy. This review was an attempt to lay down the foundations of what is already known from literature in order to help develop personalized nutrition for better management of gastrointestinal disorders in athletes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villegas García, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos gastrointestinales son bastante comunes entre los deportistas (30% a 70%). En este sentido, tanto la intensidad como el tipo de actividad deportiva han demostrado ser factores que contribuyen a estos problemas (acciones mecánicas, modificaciones del flujo sanguíneo gastrointestinal, y cambios neuroendocrinos). Como resultado de estos factores, pueden producirse molestias por reflujo gastroesofágico, náuseas, vómitos, úlcera péptica, o dolor abdominal transitorio relacionado con el ejercicio. A la luz de los conocimientos actuales, parece que las deficiencias inmunitarias que aparecen en deportistas, se deben a parámetros inherentes al propio ejercicio físico que genera toda una sucesión de cascadas de señalizadores celulares que culminan en la activación de factores de transcripción, traducción de ARNm, síntesis de proteínas y proliferación celular. Numerosos estudios confirman los efectos agudos y crónicos del ejercicio sobre el sistema inmunológico, pero todavía hay muy pocos estudios que hayan sido capaces de demostrar una relación directa entre la depresión inmunitaria inducida por el ejercicio y el aumento de la incidencia de patologías infecciosas en deportistas. La microbiota interactúa con el sistema inmune innato y adquirido jugando un papel fundamental en el mantenimiento de un estado inmunitario adecuado. La interacción con las bacterias de la microflora endógena favorece un crecimiento mutuo y la supervivencia y control de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal. En base a estas evidencias, los probióticos, algunos aminoácidos como la glutamina, arginina y leucina y determinados fitoquímicos se pueden usar como una terapia ecológica preventiva. Esta revisión es un intento de establecer las bases fisiopatológicas de estos desórdenes con el fi n de contribuir al desarrollo de la nutrición personalizada que permita un óptimo tratamiento de los trastornos gastrointestinales en deportistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;31(162): 268-272, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microbiota intestinal y actividad física intensa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7585^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55394^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
