<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153963</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish consensus on the risks and detection of antipsychotic drug-related hyperprolactinaemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Iatrogenic hyperprolactinaemia (IHPRL) has been more frequently related to some antipsychotic drugs that provoke an intense blockade of dopamine D2 receptors. There is a wide variation in clinical practice, and perhaps some more awareness between clinicians is needed. Due to the high frequency of chronic treatment in severe mental patients, careful attention is recommended on the physical risk. IHPRL symptoms could be underestimated without routine examination. Methodology. An intense scientific literature search was performed in order to draw up a multidisciplinary consensus, including different specialists of psychiatry, endocrinology, oncology and internal medicine, and looking for a consensus about clinical risk and detection of IHPRL following evidence-based medicine criteria levels (EBM I- IV). Results. Short-term symptoms include amenorrhea, galactorrhoea, and sexual dysfunction with decrease of libido and erectile difficulties related to hypogonadism. Medium and long-term symptoms related to oestrogens are observed, including a decrease bone mass density, hypogonadism, early menopause, some types of cancer risk increase (breast and endometrial), cardiovascular risk increase, immune system disorders, lipids, and cognitive dysfunction. Prolactin level, gonadal hormones and vitamin D should be checked in all patients receiving antipsychotics at baseline although early symptoms (amenorrhea-galactorrhoea) may not be observed due to the risk of underestimating other delayed symptoms that may appear in the medium term. Routine examination of sexual dysfunction is recommended due to possible poor patient tolerance and low compliance. Special care is required in children and adolescents, as well as patients with PRL levels &gt;50 ng/ml (moderate hyperprolactinaemia). A possible prolactinoma should be investigated in patients with PRL levels &gt;150 ng/ml, with special attention to patients with breast/endometrial cancer history. Densitometry should be prescribed for males &gt;50 years old, amenorrhea &gt; 6 months, or early menopause to avoid fracture risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mories, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arango, Celso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Escudero, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo, Ángel L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral van Son, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino, Javier del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pinto, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rizo, Clemente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo-Facorro, Benedicto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieta, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pachiarotti, Isabella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Ana I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral Cleries, Fermin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Carrasco, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hiperprolactinemia iatrogénica (HPRLi) se ha descrito con más frecuencia con algunos antipsicóticos, dependiendo de su capacidad de bloqueo de los receptores de dopamina D2. Existe gran heterogeneidad de la práctica clínica y posiblemente falta de concienciación sobre este problema entre los médicos. Dada la elevada frecuencia con la que los pacientes con enfermedad mental grave reciben antipsicóticos de forma prolongada, se precisa vigilar posibles riesgos en su salud física. La HPRLi y sus síntomas pueden pasar desapercibidos si no se investigan rutinariamente. Metodología. Se realiza una revisión profunda de la literatura para elaborar un consenso multidisciplinario con psiquiatras junto a otros especialistas (de Endocrinología, Medicina Interna y Oncología) con el fin de consensuar los riesgos clínicos y los métodos de detección más adecuados de la HPRLi de acuerdo con los distintos niveles de evidencia científica (I-IV). Resultados. Los síntomas a corto plazo incluyen amenorrea, galactorrea y disfunción sexual (descenso del deseo y disfunción eréctil por hipogonadismo secundario). A medio-largo plazo y relacionado con la disminución de estrógenos, se pueden inducir baja masa ósea (osteopenia y osteoporosis), hipogonadismo, menopausia precoz, incremento del riesgo de algunos tipos de cáncer (mama y endometrio), aumento del riesgo cardiovascular, alteraciones en la inmunidad, dislipidemia y disfunción cognitiva, entre otros. La petición de niveles de PRL debería realizarse al inicio del tratamiento en todos los pacientes que reciben antipsicóticos, aunque no se observen síntomas precoces (amenorrea, galactorrea) por el riesgo de subestimar otros síntomas que pueden aparecen a medio plazo. Se aconseja determinar también niveles de FSL, LH, testosterona y vitamina D. Se recomienda explorar rutinariamente la función sexual, ya que puede ser un síntoma mal tolerado que podría conducir al abandono del tratamiento. Se propone un especial cuidado en niños y adolescentes, así como en pacientes con PRL &gt; 50 ng/ml (intensidad moderada), revisando periódicamente si existe hipogonadismo o disfunción sexual. En los pacientes con PRL &gt; 150 ng/ml debe descartarse siempre un prolactinoma radiológicamente y se debe prestar especial atención a posibles antecedentes de cáncer de mama o endometrio. Se aconseja realizar densitometrías en varones &gt;50 años y en mujeres con amenorrea &gt; 6 meses o menopausia precoz para detectar osteoporosis y evitar riesgo de fracturas por fragilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);9(3): 158-173, jul.-sept. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153963</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso español sobre los riesgos y detección de la hiperprolactinemia iatrogénica por antipsicóticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20186^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30566^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20186^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11821^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20186^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
