<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112938</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Questionnaires for measuring fatigue and its impact on health perception in inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: fatigue impacts perceived health, but its importance in inflammatory bowel disease is not known. Objectives: to define the applicability of the fatigue measurement questionnaires and analyze it in patients with Crohn&#146;s disease and ulcerative colitis. Material and methods: in a first phase, the psychometric properties of 3 fatigue measurement questionnaires were determined in 99 patients: Daily Fatigue Impact Scale, Fatigue Severity Scale, and Modified Fatigue Impact Scale. In a second phase, fatigue status and its relationship to disease and quality of life was determined in 127 patients and 69 healthy controls. Results: the first part of the study showed the applicability of the questionnaires listed in inflammatory bowel disease, the Daily Fatigue Impact Scale (DFIS) having the best correlation with the quality of life and clinical activity. In the second phase, significantly higher levels of fatigue were observed in active disease than in disease in remission and healthy controls (p &lt; 0,05). The severity of fatigue was significantly correlated with quality of life (r = -0.66 and -0.72 between IBDQ-9 and DFIS and in Crohn&#146;s disease and ulcerative colitis, respectively) and with disease activity (r = 0.25 and Crohn&#146;s disease and ulcerative colitis, respectively, p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: in inflammatory bowel disease, fatigue measurement questionnaires have good properties and show that fatigue is an important manifestation of the disease, which has a significant impact on quality of life of patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peláez, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Cejas, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borruel, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrejón, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casellas, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la fatiga repercute en la salud percibida, pero se desconoce su relevancia en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal. Objetivos: definir la aplicabilidad de cuestionarios de medida de fatiga y analizarla en pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn y colitis ulcerosa. Material y métodos: en una primera fase, en 99 pacientes se determinaron las propiedades psicométricas de 3 cuestionarios de medida de fatiga: Escala del Impacto Diario de Fatiga, Escala de Gravedad de la Fatiga y Escala Modificada del Impacto de Fatiga. En una segunda fase, se determinó el estado de fatiga y su relación con la enfermedad y la calidad de vida en 127 pacientes y 69 controles sanos. Resultados: la primera parte del estudio, demostró la aplicabilidad de los cuestionarios citados en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal, siendo la Escala del Impacto Diario de Fatiga (EIDF) el de mejor correlación con la calidad de vida y la actividad clínica. En la segunda fase, se objetivaron unos niveles significativamente superiores de fatiga en la enfermedad activa que en la enfermedad en remisión y los controles sanos (p &lt; 0,05). La intensidad de la fatiga se correlacionó de forma significativa con la calidad de vida (r = -0,66 y -0,72 entre el IBDQ- 9 y EIDF en enfermedad de Crohn y colitis ulcerosa respectivamente) y con la actividad de la enfermedad (r = 0,25 y 0,33 en la enfermedad de Crohn y colitis ulcerosa respectivamente, p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal los cuestionarios de medida de fatiga tienen propiedades adecuadas y demuestran que la fatiga es una manifestación importante de la enfermedad, que repercute de forma significativa en la calidad de vida de los pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(3): 144-153, mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionarios de medida e impacto de la fatiga en la percepción de salud en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
