<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128828</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in Uro-oncology «OncoForum»: The Best of 2013</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To present the new findings in oncologic urology with impact on clinical practice which were displayed at 2013 major annual meetings (EAU, ESTRO, AUA, ASCO and ASTRO). Methods: The abstracts on prostate kidney, bladder and upper tract urothelial cancer with the highest scores by the OncoForum committee, presented in 1013 Congresses are included in this paper. Results: The following messages were considered as important by the Onco Urology Forum committee. In renal tumors T1a, comorbidities should be evaluated by its impact on overall and specific cancer survival, especially in men over 65. In metastatic renal tumors, the benefit of Everolimus vs. Sunitinib has not been demonstrated. Patients with non-muscle invasive bladder cancer of high risk, with three or more risk factors, should be considered for radical cystectomy. The ERSPC study&#146; data demonstrate the benefit of the systematic screening in prostate cancer. In metastatic disease, the results of the Ra-223 and enzalutamide studies show benefit in pain control and overall survival in metastatic disease. Conclusions: Localized renal and non-muscle invasive bladder of high-risk tumors, should be assessed according to comorbidities or oncologic risk factors, to determinate the adequate treatment options. New data from metastatic prostate cancer clinical trials have shown promising results in the control of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cózar-Olmo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Veiga, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos-Revilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz-Asensio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Exponer los nuevos hallazgos en urología oncológica con impacto en la práctica clínica presentados en las principales reuniones anuales durante 2013 (EAU, ESTRO, AUA, ASCO y ASTRO). Métodos: Se revisan los resúmenes sobre cáncer de próstata, renal, de vejiga y los tumores del tracto urinario presentados en los congresos del año 2013 que recibieron mayor valoración por parte del comité de Onco Forum. Resultados: El comité consideró importantes los siguientes mensajes. Las comorbilidades han de ser evaluadas por su impacto en la supervivencia global y cáncer específica en tumores renales T1a, especialmente en varones de más de 65 años. Everolimus no ha demostrado beneficio en tumores renales metastásicos frente a sunitinib. Los pacientes con cáncer de vejiga superficiales de alto riesgo, con 3 o más factores de riesgo, deben ser considerados para cistectomía radical. Los datos del ERSPC siguen demostrando el beneficio del despistaje sistemático. Los resultados de los estudios Ra-223 y enzalutamida demuestran beneficio en el control del dolor y la supervivencia global en la enfermedad metastásica. Conclusiones. Los tumores renales localizados y de vejiga superficiales de alto riesgo han de ser evaluados en relación con factores de riesgo por comorbilidades u oncológicos del tumor, para definir opciones de tratamiento adecuadas. Los nuevos datos de los ensayos clínicos en cáncer de próstata metastásico demuestran la eficacia en el control de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;38(8): 491-498, oct. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128828</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en uro-oncología «OncoForum»: lo mejor de 2013</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
