<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74731</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of neuropathic pain in patients with cancer not associated with prior oncologic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the prevalence of neuropathic and mixed pain in the population treated in the Oncology Service of the catchment area (Cadiz-San Fernando) of the Puerta del Mar University Hospital. Patients with cancer reporting pain and who had not received prior oncological treatment that could have caused the pain were included. We also aimed to determine the demographic, clinical and psychiatric comorbidities associated with the presence of neuropathic and mixed pain in these patients. Material and methods: Design: Observational, cross-sectional study. Setting: Catchment area of the Puerta del Mar University Hospital (Cadiz-S. Fernando), which attends a population of 242,723 people. Study subjects: Patients diagnosed with cancer who reported pain and who had not received prior oncological treatment that could potentially have caused the pain attended in the Outpatient Oncology Department of the Puerta del Mar University Hospital. Data collection: The following scales were used: the validated Spanish version of the Leeds Assessment of Neuropathic Symptoms and Signs (LANSS) scale for the diagnosis of neuropathic pain, the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) and the Brief Pain Inventory Short Form (BPI-SF). A questionnaire was employed to collect sociodemographic and clinical variables. Analysis: The prevalence of neuropathic and mixed pain (± 95% CI) was calculated in the population attending the Outpatient Oncology Department of the Puerta del Mar University Hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Failde, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pernia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Hernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer la prevalencia de dolor neuropático y mixto de la población enferma de cáncer tratada en la consulta de oncología procedente de la zona de cobertura (Cádiz-San Fernando) del Hospital Universitario Puerta del Mar (HUPM), que refiere dolor, y que no ha recibido tratamiento oncológico previo potencialmente causante. Conocer las variables demográficas, clínicas y de comorbilidad psíquica asociadas a la presencia de dolor neuropático y mixto de estos pacientes. Material y métodos: Diseño: estudio observacional, transversal. Ámbito del estudio: zona de cobertura del HUPM (Cádiz-San Fernando) que cubre a una población de 242.723 personas. Sujetos de estudio: pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer, con dolor y que no han recibido tratamiento oncológico previo potencialmente causante, atendidos en la Consulta Externa de Oncología del HUPM. Recogida de la información: escala LANSS de diagnóstico de dolor neuropático, versión validada española; escala HADS de depresión y ansiedad; cuestionario breve del dolor (edición corta BPI-SF); cuestionario para recogida de variables sociodemográficas y clínicas. Análisis: cálculo de la prevalencia de dolor neuropático y mixto (± intervalo de confianza del 95%) en la población que atiende la consulta externa de oncología del HUPM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;16(7): 386-398, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74731</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de dolor neuropático en pacientes con cáncer sin relación con el tratamiento oncológico previo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
