<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101024</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implication of psychosocial competencies, behavioural problems and personality variables in the prediction of social interaction anxiety in adolescents: Sex and age differences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present it is assumed that there are several factors involved in social interaction anxiety. This study seeks to determine whether certain psychological variable have an influence on normal adolescent social anxiety, and if the role of these differ according to sex and age. A sample of 961 (412 males and 549 females) Spanish adolescents (M=15.63; SD=1.32) was assessed using the YSR/11-18, MMPI-A and SIAS. Results indicate that significant sex and age differences were found in social anxiety. Most of the correlations found between social interaction anxiety and the variables assessed by YSR/11-18 and MMPI-A were found to be significant, although low in both sexes and both age groups. Variables included in the regression models for men and women explained 33,50% and 40,40% of the variance in social interaction anxiety, respectively; those included in the models of eldest and youngest adolescents were able to explain the 24,60% and 41,50% of the variance in social interaction anxiety. We discuss these sex and age differences in order to explain the nature of anxiety experienced in interpersonal situations according to the existing theoretical proposals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubeidat, Ihab</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad se asume que existen varios factores implicados en la ansiedad ante la interacción social. En este estudio se pretende determinar en qué medida ciertas variables psicológicas influyen en la ansiedad social de adolescentes normales y si el papel de las mismas difiere en función del sexo y de la edad. Una muestra de 961 (412 varones y 549 mujeres) adolescentes españoles (M=15,63; DT=1,32) fue evaluada mediante el YSR/11-18, el MMPI_A y la SIAS. Los resultados indican que se ha encontrado una diferencia significativa en la ansiedad social respecto al sexo y curso escolar. La mayoría de las correlaciones encontradas entre la ansiedad ante la interacción social y las variables evaluadas por el YSR/11-18 y MMPI-A fueron significativas, aunque bajas, en ambos sexos y en los dos grupos de edad. Las variables incluidas en los modelos de regresión de los hombres y mujeres explicaron el 33,50% y el 40.40% de la ansiedad ante la interacción social, respectivamente; las incluidas en los modelos de adolescentes de menor y mayor edad lograron explicar el 24,60% y el 41,50% de dicha ansiedad. Se discuten estas diferencias de sexo y edad a la hora de explicar la naturaleza de la ansiedad experimentada en situaciones interpersonales de acuerdo a las propuestas teóricas existentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;15(2/3): 231-247, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101024</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicación de competencias psicosociales, problemas de conducta y variables de personalidad en la predicción de la ansiedad social ante la interacción social en adolescentes: diferencias de sexo y edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
