<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110875</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of sleep in patients hospitalized in an Intensive Care Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Trouble sleeping is common in the elderly population and is attributed to changes that aging brings in the sleep architecture and circadian rhythm. The prevalence of insomnia shows a marked increase with advancing age, in a proportion of 14 to 32% among those over 65 years. If we add these physiological changes of sleep with those found in patients admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU), the problem worsens. The prevalence of these disorders in these units is from 22 - 61%. Sleep deprivation may contribute to worsening of the patients. The main objective is to describe the quality of sleep of patients admitted to the Coronary ICU of the Hospital Miguel Servet and the environmental factors that contribute to these disorders. Material and methods A total of 75 conscious and oriented patients in the Coronary ICU Hospital Miguel Servet were included. Data was collected between February 17 and April 30, 2011. The subjects were asked to state if they had slept well by means of a survey and to score the environmental factors that may have bothered them. Results and discussion Most patients said they had slept well (66.7%). Noise was the environmental factor that bothered them most. In analyzing the different noises, patients identified hearing people talking as being the most annoying. Conclusion Changes must be implemented in the unit that would favor restful sleep (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sanz, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La dificultad para dormir es común en la población anciana y se atribuye a cambios que la edad produce en la arquitectura del sueño y en el ritmo circadiano. La prevalencia de insomnio muestra un notable incremento a medida que avanza la edad a una proporción del 14 al 32% entre los mayores de 65 años. Si sumamos estos cambios fisiológicos del sueño con encontrarse ingresado en una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) el problema se agrava. La prevalencia de estos trastornos en estas unidades está entre el 22-61%. La deprivación del sueño puede contribuir al empeoramiento de los pacientes. El objetivo principal es describir la calidad del sueño de los pacientes ingresados en la Unidad Coronaria de Cuidados Intensivos dl Hospital Miguel Servet y los factores ambientales que contribuyen a estos trastornos. Material y métodos Se incluyeron 75 pacientes conscientes y orientados de la Unidad Coronaria de Cuidados Intensivos del Hospital Miguel Servet. La recogida de datos se realizó entre el 17 de febrero y el 30 de abril de 2011. Se les pidió que valorasen mediante la realización de una encuesta si habían dormido bien y que puntuasen los factores ambientales que les pudieran haber molestado. Resultados y discusión La mayoría de los pacientes dijo haber dormido bien (66,7%). El factor ambiental que más les molestó fue el ruido. Al analizar los distintos ruidos, los pacientes identificaron escuchar gente hablando como el más molesto. Conclusión Es necesario implementar cambios en la unidad que favorezcan un sueño reparador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;24(1): 3-11, ene.-Mar. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad del sueño de los pacientes ingresados en una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12566</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
