<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79228</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occupationa back injury risks for sanitary personnel in hemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study is based on Spanish Law 31/1995 regarding the Prevention of Risks in the Workplace, on the specialty of ergonomics and psycho-sociology, as well as on the official royal decrees which have been annexed to this law. Ergonomics is a multidisciplinary technology which gathers together and organizes knowledge in order to apply that knowledge to means, designs and working places having as an objective to optimize the efficiency of the system, and the comfort, safety and satisfaction of workers. It searches for the adequateness of men to their work. Its prime objective is to improve those conditions, while its final goal consists in harmonizing an individual&#146;s physical and psychological capacities.  The number of patients who need this treatment while undergoing hemodialysis increases every year; therefore, these units should be progressively adapted to this demand. Be it due to the time required to carry out an adequate working environment, of to adapt personnel to this new situation, workers&#146; needs always wind up in second place(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mena Mayayo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eva Cerdán Urrutia, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio se basa en la Ley 31/1995 de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales, en la especialidad de ergonomía y psicosociología, así como los reales decretos que se han ido anexionando a la misma. La ergonomía es una tecnología pluridisciplinar que reúne y organiza conocimientos para aplicarlos a medios, diseños y lugares de trabajo, con el fin de optimizar la eficacia del sistema, comodidad, seguridad y satisfacción de los trabajadores. Busca la adecuación del hombre al trabajo. Su objetivo prioritario es mejorar las condiciones del mismo, mientras que el objetivo final consiste en armonizar las capacidades físicas y psicológicas del individuo. El número de pacientes que necesitan este tratamiento en hemodiálisis aumenta cada año, por lo que estas unidades se deben adaptar progresivamente a esta demanda. Ya sea por el tiempo que se requiere para realizar una buena adecuación del entorno, como del personal a la nueva situación, las necesidades de los trabajadores quedan en un segundo plano(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(3): 188-193, mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgos dorsolumbares del personal sanitario en unidades de hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
