<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98875</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrical impedance tomography in acute lung injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Electrical impedance tomography has been described as a new method of monitoring critically ill patients on mechanical ventilation. It has recently gained special interest because of its applicability for monitoring ventilation and pulmonary perfusion. Its bedside and continuous implementation, and the fact that it is a non-ionizing and non-invasive technique, makes it an extremely attractive measurement tool. Likewise, given its ability to assess the regional characteristics of lung structure, it could be considered an ideal monitoring tool in the heterogeneous lung with acute lung injury This review explains the physical concept of bioimpedance and its clinical application, and summarizes the scientific evidence published to date with regard to the implementation of electrical impedance tomography as a method for monitoring ventilation and perfusion, mainly in the patient with acute lung injury, and other possible applications of the technique in the critically ill patient. The review also summarizes the limitations of the technique and its potential areas of future development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masclans, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riu, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casan, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tomografía de impedancia eléctrica se ha descrito como un nuevo método de monitorización en el paciente crítico en ventilación mecánica. Recientemente ha cobrado especial interés, debido a su aplicabilidad para la monitorización de la ventilación y la perfusión pulmonar. Su implementación continua a pie de cama y el ser una técnica no ionizante y no invasiva son propiedades particulares que la convierten en un recurso extremadamente atractivo. Asimismo, por su capacidad de evaluar las características regionales de la estructura pulmonar, podría constituir una herramienta de monitorización ideal en el heterogéneo pulmón con lesión pulmonar aguda. En el presente artículo de revisión, se explica el concepto físico de la bioimpedancia y su aplicación clínica y se resume la evidencia científica publicada hasta la fecha en lo referido a la utilización de la tomografía de impedancia eléctrica como método de monitorización de la ventilación y de la perfusión, fundamentalmente en el enfermo con lesión pulmonar aguda, así como otras aplicaciones posibles de la técnica en el enfermo crítico. Asimismo, se resumen las limitaciones de la técnica y sus potenciales áreas de desarrollo en el futuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(8): 509-517, nov. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tomografía de impedancia eléctrica en la lesión pulmonar aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53086^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
