<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80224</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing Case Management of caregiver emotional heatlh at hospital setting and it´s influence on caregivers decission to take care at home</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: a) To determine the influence of the interventions ofNurse Case-Manager (NCM) at Hospital on &#147;CaregiverRole Strain&#148; and on the decision to take care of the patientat home. b) To quantify saving hospital stays and economiccost. Methodology: A retrospective observational study oncaregivers with &#147;Role Strain&#148; managed by the NCM betweenApril and September 2008. We analysed effectiveness ofinterventions by measuring the score at admission and atdischarge on Nursing Outcome (NOC) &#147;Caregiver emotionalhealth&#148; . Saving hospital stays and economic cost havebeen calculated using the formula: Total number of patientswith income / early Hospital discharge x Averagedaily cost. Results: 64 patients had the diagnosis. In all cases,NOC &#147;Caregiver emotional health&#148; was activated. Interventionswere effective in improving the NOC from2.41 on admission to 3.81 at discharge (p &lt;0.0001). 31 ofthese patients, who were planned to be transfered to a medium-stay hospital, have been discharged home after interventionby the NCM. There are differences in the scores atdischarge from the NOC (&gt; or &lt;4) in this group comparedwith the group that continues normal course (p&gt; 0006).The interventions of the 2 NCM have saved a total of 798days of stay valued at &#128; 360,270 in 6 months. Conclusions:The interventions of the NCM improve the emotionalhealth of caregivers, and succeed in improving the readinessof the caregiver to take care of the patient at home,which has direct impact on the average length of stay andassociated cost (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Laguna-Parras, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa-García, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Lendínez,  Alfonso J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Torres, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gila-Selas, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, Francisco Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: a) Determinar la influencia de las intervencionesde las Enfermas Gestoras de Casos (EGC)sobre el cansancio en el rol de cuidador y en la decisiónde éstos de asumir la atención del paciente en sudomicilio. b) Cuantificar el ahorro de estancias y decostes. Metodología: Estudio observacional restrospectivosobre pacientes con cansancio en el rol delcuidador gestionados por las EGC entre abril y septiembrede 2008. Se analiza la efectividad de las intervencionesmidiendo la puntuación al ingreso y al altadel CRE Salud Emocional del Cuidador Principal. Elahorro de estancias y costes se ha calculado mediantela fórmula: total de pacientes con ingreso/alta precozconseguida x estancia media x coste diario. Resultados:Sesenta y cuatro pacientes presentaban el diagnóstico.En todos los casos se activó el criterio de saludemocional. Las intervenciones fueron efectivasmejorando el CRE de 2,41 al ingreso a 3,81 al alta (p&lt; 0,0001). Treinta y uno de estos pacientes que teníanprevisto el traslado al hospital media estancia han sidodados de alta a domicilio tras su intervención. Existendiferencias en la puntuación al alta del CRE (&gt; ó &lt; 4)en este grupo comparado con el que continúa cursonormal (p &gt; 0,006). La intervención de las EGC haahorrado un total de 798 días de estancia tasados en360.270 euros en 6 meses. Conclusiones: Las intervencionesde las EGC mejoran la salud emocional delas cuidadoras, sitúa a la cuidadora en disposición de (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);20(4): 152-158, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de las Enfermeras Gestoras de Casos hospitalarias sobre la preparación de las cuidadoras para asumir el cuidado domiciliario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
