<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65766</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. C-reactive protein (CRP) is an inflammatory and powerful marker of future vascular events. Recently, it has been proposed as a mediator molecule of atherosclerotic disease due to its multiple proatherogenic effects and its presence in atherosclerotic plaques. Material and methods. CRP expression was analyzed by real time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in advanced carotid plaques. Furthermore, protein expression was analyzed by immunohistochemistry in carotid atherosclerotic lesions obtained by endarterectomy and in carotid samples in different phases of progression. Results. Analysis by real time PCR showed significantly higher levels of CRP in ulcerated non-complicated lesions as compared to complicated ulcerated lesions (p = 0.001) or fibrous lesions (p = 0.01). An immunohistochemistry assay for CRP showed that in advanced lesions, mainly infiltrated inflammatory cells and new vessels were stained. In contrast, no CRP staining was observed in early lesions and carotid artery controls. Conclusion. CRP expression in carotid atherosclerotic lesions is induced in moderated and advanced stages of plaque progression, suggesting a possible role of this molecule in inflammation and neovascularization and triggering atherothrombotic complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvajal, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Font, Maria Ángels</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iborra, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oriol Juan-Babot, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Krupinskia, Jerzy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Turu, MArta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Slevin, Mark</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badimón, Lina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La proteína C-reactiva (PCR) es un marcador de inflamación y de pronóstico de la enfermedad cardiovascular. Además, esta proteína parece realizar funciones mediadoras de esta enfermedad, dado sus múltiples efectos proaterogénicos y su presencia en las lesiones ateroscleróticas. Material y métodos. En este estudio, se analizó la expresión de la PCR, mediante la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa a tiempo real, en las lesiones avanzadas de carótida obtenidas mediante endarterectomía. Además, mediante inmunohistoquímica, se analizó la expresión de esta proteína en estas lesiones ateroscleróticas avanzadas y en muestras de arteria carótida que se encontraban en diferentes estadios de progresión. Resultados. Los valores de ácido ribonucleico mensajero de PCR fueron significativamente más elevados en las lesiones ulceradas no complicadas, comparado con las lesiones ulceradas complicadas (p = 0,001) y fibrosas (p = 0,01). Mediante inmuno-histoquímica, se observó marcaje para PCR en las lesiones más avanzadas, principalmente en las células inflamatorias infiltradas y en vasos de nueva formación. En cambio, en lesiones más tempranas y en las arterias carótidas sanas no se encontró tinción para la PCR. Conclusión. La expresión de la PCR en las lesiones ateroscleróticas de carótida se induce en estadios medios y avanzados de la progresión, y puede estar implicada en la inflamación y la neovascularización que aparece en estos estadios, lo que conlleva riesgo de complicaciones hemorrágicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);20(3): 95-101, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65766</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d30132^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22275^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3963^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2381^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
