<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108558</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9572</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prolonged-release melatonin (ciRcadiN): a new MT receptor agonist for the treatment of insomnia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Circadin® 2 mg is a prolonged-release tablet formulation of melatonin which circumvents the fast clearance of the hormone by releasing it into the gastrointestinal tract over an extended period of time, providing a melatonin profile in the blood that is more closely matched to the normal physiological release profile. It represents new treatment paradigm, indicated as monotherapy for the short-term treatment of primary insomnia characterised by poor quality of sleep in patients aged 55 years and older. In an extensive clinical development programme, Circadin® significantly improved the quality of sleep and morning alertness, and significantly reduced the time taken to get to sleep. Circadin® has an excellent safety/tolerability profile not causing &#147;hangover&#148; effects or impairing memory and psychomotor skills. Circadin® has been shown to significantly improve quality of life in the target patient population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Susana Gómez-Lus Centelles, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Circadin® 2 mg es una formulación de melatonina de liberación prolongada en comprimidos que evita el aclaramiento rápido de la hormona, liberándola en el tracto gastrointestinal durante un periodo de tiempo prolongado, lo que da lugar a un perfil plasmático de melatonina similar al producido por la liberación fisiológica normal. Esta opción representa un nuevo tratamiento paradigmático, indicado en monoterapia para el tratamiento a corto plazo del insomnio primario, caracterizado por un sueño de mala calidad en pacientes mayores de 55 años. En un amplio programa de desarrollo clínico, Circadin® mejoró significativamente la calidad del sueño y la alerta matutina y redujo significativamente el tiempo necesario para dormirse. Circadin® presenta un buen perfil de tolerabilidad, sin efectos de &#147;resaca&#148; o deterioro en la memoria y capacidades psicomotoras. Globalmente Circadin® mejora significativamente la calidad del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Vigilia sueño;21(1): 38-48, ene.-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108558</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Melatonina de liberación prolongada (ciRcadiN®): Un nuevo agonista de los receptores MT en el tratamiento del insomnio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
