<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161667</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability and validity of the modified Allen test: a systematic review and metanalysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective was to evaluate the reliability and validity of the modified Allen test in screening for collateral circulation deficits in the palm and for predicting distal hand ischemia. We performed a systematic review of the literature indexed in 6 databases. We developed a search strategy to locate studies comparing the Allen test to Doppler ultrasound to detect circulation deficits in the hand, studies assessing the incidence of ischemic events on arterial puncture after an abnormal Allen test result, and studies of Allen test interobserver agreement. Fourteen articles met the inclusion criteria. Nine assessed the validity of the test as a screening tool for detecting collateral circulation deficits. From data published in 3 studies that had followed comparable designs we calculated a sensitivity of 77% and specificity of 93% for the Allen test. Four studies that assessed the ability of the test to predict ischemia did not predict any ischemic hand events following arterial puncture in patients with abnormal Allen test results. A single study assessing the test&#146;s reliability reported an interobserver agreement rate of 71.5%. This systematic review and metanalysis allows to conclude that the Allen test does not have sufficient diagnostic validity to serve as a screening tool for collateral circulation deficits in the hand. Nor is it a good predictor of hand ischemia after arterial puncture. Moreover, its reliability is limited. There is insufficient evidence to support its systematic use before arterial puncture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros Peña, Sendoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeu Bordas, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta revisión se centra en evaluar la validez y fiabilidad del test modificado de Allen como prueba de cribado para déficits en la circulación colateral palmar y como predictor de isquemia distal de la mano. Para ello, se realizó una revisión sistemática de la literatura a través de 6 bases de datos. Se elaboraron protocolos de búsqueda para localizar estudios que comparasen el test de Allen con la ecografía Doppler para detectar déficits de la circulación colateral de la mano; que evaluasen la incidencia de eventos isquémicos cuando la arterioclisis se realizaba ante un test de Allen anormal y que estudiasen la concordancia interobservador del test. En total, 14 artículos cumplieron los criterios de búsqueda. Nueve estudios evaluaron la validez del test como prueba de cribado para déficits de circulación colateral. En base a 3 estudios de metodología análoga, se calculó una sensibilidad y especificidad del test del 77% y 93%, respectivamente. Cuatro estudios que valoraban la capacidad del test para predecir isquemia no objetivaron ningún evento isquémico de la mano tras arterioclisis cuando el test de Allen era anormal. Un único estudio evaluó la fiabilidad del test, determinando una concordancia interobservador del 71,5%. Esta revisión sistemática y metanálisis permite concluir que el test de Allen no presenta una adecuada validez diagnóstica como prueba de cribado de déficits de la circulación colateral de la mano, ni resulta un buen predictor de isquemia de la mano tras una punción arterial. Además, presenta una limitada fiabilidad, por lo que no existen evidencias que sustenten su realización sistemática previa a una punción arterial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);29(2): 126-135, abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez y fiabilidad del test modificado de Allen: una revisión sistemática y metanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3128^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6378^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
