<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039031</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Goals in the reduction of automatic prejudice: experiencing the discrepancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From a social cognition approach, it has been shown that, by default, stereotypes and prejudices are activated in automatic ways. At the same time, there is trend aimed at discovering the conditions under which automatic influences can be controlled. Within this field, the effectiveness of a strategy for the reduction of automatic prejudice was evaluated in the current study. The intervention was aimed at causing participants to experience a failure when a goal was to be achieved. Different discrepancy theories predict that the perceiver will try to compensate for the failure in this situation. Results obtained from data collected with the Implicit Association Test show that the spontaneous in-group favouritism can be reduced through the use of such a strategy, suggesting that the experience of discrepancies fosters affective compensation. The discussion underlines the contribution of results to theoretical development in the field of automaticity and control</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Castillo, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde el enfoque de la cognición social se ha puesto de relieve que, por defecto, los estereotipos y los prejuicios se activan automáticamente, al tiempo que han proliferado los intentos por controlar las influencias automáticas no deseadas. En este marco, el presente estudio fue diseñado para evaluar la efectividad de un procedimiento de reducción automática del prejuicio, basado en la evocación de la experimentación de un fracaso en el logro de una meta. Distintas teorías de la discrepancia predicen que el preceptor llevará a cabo esfuerzos compensatorios en este tipo de situación. Los resultados evidencian, a partir de los datos recogidos con el Test de Asociación Implícita, que la estrategia aplicada produjo una reducción significativa del favoritismo endogrupal automático, sugiriendo la operatividad de algún tipo de compensación afectiva. En la discusión se subraya la contribución de este resultado al desarrollo teórico de la investigación sobre automaticidad y control</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);17(1): 71-75, feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las metas en la reducción del prejuicio automático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13628</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
