<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86259</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An unusual case of hemoptysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hemoptysis is the expulsion of blood from subglottic airway. It is important to confirm it and make a differential diagnosis of gastrointestinal bleeding, assessment of severity, perform a detailed history and physical examination and the additional tests needed to reach a diagnosis. Chronic bronchitis, bronchiectasis and neoplasms are responsible for 70% of these cases, and despite a thorough evaluation, it is not possible to reach an etiological diagnosis in up to 30% of patients. In the case we present it was caused by a typical carcinoid tumor, a tumor of lower incidence among lung tumors. At the time of diagnosis there were liver metastases, causing a carcinoid syndrome. Carcinoid tumors are slow-growing and of neuroendocrine origin. These tumors represent a diagnostic challenge as they are often innocuous on presentation. The preferred treatment is surgery, and in cases of carcinoid disease spread, it requires a multidisciplinary approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñero López, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejeda Borrallo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemoptisis es la expulsión de sangre procedente de las vías respiratorias subglóticas. Es importante: la confirmación y el diagnóstico diferencial con el sangrado del aparato digestivo, la valoración de la gravedad, realizar una anamnesis y exploración física detallada, y las pruebas complementarias necesarias para llegar a un diagnóstico. La bronquitis crónica, las bronquiectasias y las neoplasias son responsables del 70% de los casos de esta, y a pesar de una exhaustiva evaluación, hasta en un 30% de los pacientes no es posible llegar a un diagnóstico etiológico. El caso que exponemos es producido por un tumor carcinoide típico, tumor de baja incidencia dentro de los tumores pulmonares. En el momento del diagnóstico se observan metástasis hepáticas que causan un síndrome carcinoide. Los tumores carcinoides son de lento crecimiento, de origen neuroendocrino. Estos tumores representan un reto diagnóstico porque a menudo son inocuos en el momento de la presentación. El tratamiento de elección es la cirugía y en casos de diseminación de la enfermedad carcinoide es necesario un enfoque multidisciplinar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(3): 148-152, mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86259</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un caso atípico de hemoptisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2319^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2319^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2319^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
