<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-7995</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epistaxis: prospective study on hospital emergency care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We prospectively studied 279 patients with epistaxis referred to ENT specialist from emergency room in our hospital in one year. Masculine sex (62%), medium or old ages (median 56 year), and associated diseases (HBP 22.9%, anticoagulants or antiplatelet drugs 11.1%), were the most common. Predominant local etiologic factors were trauma (12.9%) and inflammation (14%). Epistaxis had been essential in 36.9%. The most frequent location in all ages was the anterior one, especially located in the Kiesselbach's area, although the incidence of the posterior epistaxis increases in characteristic way from fourth decade, affecting more to men. Most of epistaxis (&gt; 99%) were treated successfully by conservative approach and only two patients required surgical or interventional therapy. Patients between 30-59 year and the posterior epistaxis was the most refractory to the treatment. Hospitalized patients were older than ambulatory ones and had more associated diseases. Their average hospital stay was 9.2 days (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Realizamos un estudio prospectivo sobre los 279 pacientes con epistaxis referidos al ORL por el servicio de urgencias de nuestro hospital a lo largo de un año. Nuestros pacientes han sido preferentemente varones (62 por ciento), de edad media o avanzada (mediana 56 años), y aquejados de otras enfermedades (HTA 22,9 por ciento, Tto. antiagregante/anticoagulante 11, 1 por ciento). Los factores etiológicos locales predominantes han sido los traumatismos (12,9 por ciento) y las inflamaciones (14 por ciento). Las epistaxis esenciales han supuesto un 36,9 por ciento de nuestra serie. La localización más frecuente en todas las edades fue la anterior, en su mayor parte localizada en el área de Kiesselbach, aunque a partir de la 4ª década la incidencia de las posteriores aumentó deforma característica, afectando más a los varones. La mayoría de la epistaxis (&gt; 99 por ciento) han sido manejadas exclusivamente de manera conservadora y sólo en dos pacientes ha sido necesario tratamiento quirúrgico o intervencionista. El mayor índice de resangrado se presentó en las epistaxis de localización posterior y en los pacientes entre los 30 y los 59 años. Los pacientes que necesitaron ingreso hospitalario tuvieron más edad que los ambulatorios y padecían más enfermedades. Su estancia media hospitalaria fue de 9,2 días (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;51(8): 697-702, nov. 2000. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epistaxis: estudio prospectivo sobre la atención urgente a nivel hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vaamonde Lago, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartual Magro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labella Caballero, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez Beltrán, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lechuga García, MR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frade González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Varela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-7995</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28002^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
