<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92583</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic Treatment of Persistent Alveolar-Pleural Air Leaks with a Unidirectional Endobronchial Valve</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Persistent air leaks due to alveolopleural fistula are not an uncommon complication of pneumothorax,particularly secondary ones. Unidirectional flow endobronchial valves designed for lung volumereduction are the latest incorporation to the therapeutic armamentarium.We present the case of a patient with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) with persistentpneumothorax in spite of treatment with three pleurodesis which was able to be resolved with theplacement of two IBVTM valves(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosell, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorca, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Lisbona, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Obiols, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fuga aérea persistente por fístula alveolopleural no es una complicación infrecuente del neumotórax,sobretodo de los secundarios. Las válvulas endobronquiales de flujo unidireccional diseñadas para lareducción del volumen pulmonar son la última incorporación en el arsenal terapéutico.Se presenta el caso de un paciente con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC), con unneumotórax persistente a pesar del tratamiento con tres pleurodesis, y que pudo resolverse con laimplantación de dos válvulas tipo IBV(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(7): 371-373, jul. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endoscópico de la fuga aérea persistente alveolo-pleural con una válvula endobronquial unidireccional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29107^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29107^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32076</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
