<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158665</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary care nurses&#146; difficulties in advance care planning processes: a qualitative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To know the primary care nurses&#146; difficulties to promote advance care planning process with patients in the end of life. Design. Phenomenological qualitative methodology. Location. Health Management Area North of Jaén. Participants. Primary care nurses. Method. Purposive sampling. Fourteen in-depth interviews were conducted until the speeches saturation. Content analysis in four steps: transcription, coding, obtaining results and conclusions verification. Supported whit the software Nvivo 8. Triangulation of results between researchers. Results. Professionals&#146; difficulties: Lack of knowledge about the topic, lack of communication skills, lack of experience and presence of negative emotions. In the health institution lack of time and interference with other professionals is a barrier. Also the patient's attitude and the family are identified as an obstacle because few people speak about the end of life. Finally, our society prevents open discussion about issues related to death. Conclusions. Professional learning about advanced care planning, training in communication skills and emotional education are necessary. Health managers should consider the fact that early interventions for planning health decisions require training, time and continued attention. If a cultural change does not happen, an evasive way to face the end of life will persist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio-Cantalejo, Inés M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granero-Moya, Nani</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frías-Osuna, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Morcillo, Antonio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer las dificultades que encuentran las enfermeras de atención primaria para promover procesos de planificación anticipada de las decisiones con personas en el final de la vida. Diseño. Estudio cualitativo fenomenológico. Emplazamiento. Área de Gestión Sanitaria Norte de Jaén. Participantes. Enfermeras de atención primaria. Método. Muestreo intencional. Realización de 14 entrevistas en profundidad hasta la saturación de los discursos. Análisis de contenido en 4 etapas: transcripción de datos, codificación, obtención de resultados y verificación de conclusiones. Uso de N-Vivo como apoyo al análisis. Triangulación de resultados entre investigadores. Resultados. Dificultades referidas a los profesionales: falta de conocimiento sobre el tema, falta de habilidades de comunicación o de experiencia y presencia de emociones negativas. En la institución sanitaria, la falta de tiempo y las interferencias con otros profesionales suponen una barrera. También la actitud del propio paciente o su familia es vista como una traba ya que pocos hablan sobre el final de la vida. Finalmente, nuestra sociedad evita las conversaciones abiertas sobre temas relacionados con la muerte. Conclusiones. Es necesario el aprendizaje de los profesionales sobre planificación anticipada de decisiones, su entrenamiento en habilidades comunicativas y su educación afectiva. Los gestores sanitarios han de tener en cuenta el hecho de que las intervenciones para planificar anticipadamente decisiones sanitarias precisan formación, tiempo y atención continuada. En tanto no acontezca un cambio cultural, persistirá un modelo evasivo para afrontar el final de la vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(10): 649-656, dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dificultades de las enfermeras de atención primaria en los procesos de planificación anticipada de las decisiones: un estudio cualitativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37745^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29199</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37745^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
